<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="heidelberg_prose_glosses_contextual">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Heidelberg" [prose]</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses" subtype="contextual">
                <note xml:id="BEAUTIFULPATHS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Most beautiful are the paths which scale the face of the hill which is crowned by the 
                    <placeName type="building" corresp="#HEIDELBERGCASTLE">castle of Heidelberg</placeName>&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title>; 
                    <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi><persName corresp="#FMT">Frances Trollope</persName> (<date notBefore="1769" notAfter="1863">1779&#x2013;1863</date>), 
                    traveling in the same year as did the Ruskins, explained that "there are two approaches to the castle; one, by a fair smooth path, sheltered by noble trees, 
                    and gradually leading above the tops of those which grow on the hill-side, till at length the level space behind the castle and in front of the great gateway is reached; 
                    the other is by a steep flight of steps into the very heart of the fortress, through a vast, subterranean, vaulted hall. . . . Take which route you will, 
                    there is no danger of the highest-wrought expectations being disappointed. By the first, you will wind round the base of towers, which look as if a giant architect 
                    had reared them for a giant prince . . .  and both lead to a terrace, from whence a view is seen, so much beyond what the power of words can paint, 
                    that all the most faithful traveller can say, to any purpose, on the subject is, 'Go, all, with as little delay as possible, and look at it.' . . . 
                    On reaching the esplanade, before the chief entrance, you have no very extended view; for the lofty summit of the Geissberg is on one side, 
                    and the wide-spreading castle on the other; but, on passing under this portal, and crossing the court-yard, you reach another archway, 
                    which leads to the grand north terrace, acknowledged to be one of the finest points of view in Europe" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#TROLLOPEBELGIUM">Trollope, <hi rend="italic">Belgium and Western Germany in 1833</hi></ref>, 1:262-63).</p></note>

                <note xml:id="BRAKE" resp="#DCH"><p>&#x201C;brake&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title>; 
                    <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;bracken.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="EMBOUCHURE" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;embouchure&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi>"The mouth of a river or creek. 
                    Also <hi rend="italic">transf</hi>.," as Ruskin is using the word here, "the opening out of a valley into a plain" 
                    (&#x201C;embouchure, 1.&#x201D; <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>, accessed <date when="2015-01-16">16 January 2015</date>).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="DESOLATE" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;The <placeName type="building" corresp="#HEIDELBERGCASTLE">castle of Heidelberg</placeName> is exceeding desolate. 
                    Armies have razed its foundations, the thunder hath riven its towers and there is no sound in its courts, and the wind is still in the open galleries&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi>In 
                    his <date when="1836">1836</date> guidebook to the <geogName corresp="#CONTINENT">Continent</geogName>, <persName corresp="#JM">John Murray</persName> 
                    introduces his account of Heidelberg with the reminder that "[f]ew cities in Europe have experienced to a greater extent, or more frequently, the horrors of war, 
                    than the ill-starred Heidelberg. Previous to the Thirty Years' War, it displayed in its buildings all the splendour arising from nourishing commerce 
                    and the residence of the Court of the Electors Palatine of the Rhine. It has been five times bombarded, twice laid in ashes, 
                    and thrice taken by assault and delivered over to pillage." Of the castle in particular, Murray wonders at the "architectural magnificence which it still displays, 
                    after having been three times burnt, and having ten times experienced the horrors of war. Its final destruction was owing to its having been struck by lightning 
                    in 1764: and since the total conflagration which ensued, it has never been restored or tenanted. It is at present only, a collection of red stone walls, 
                    and has remained roofless for nearly a century" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKCONTINENT1836"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers on the Continent</hi></ref>, 430, 432).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="TURENNE" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;When <persName corresp="#TURENNE">Marshall Turenne</persName> attacked the castle in question&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi>The larger context lay in the 
                    wars waged by Louis XIV (1638-1715) to secure borders and achieve glory in the aftermath of the declining Hapsburg empire, divided between the Spanish and German lines. 
                    One border was threatened by the Spanish Netherlands; to guard against its southward flowing rivers, France maintained a series of fortresses. 
                    Another border was the Rhine and Moselle valleys. While French control over Alsace remained as a legacy of the Thirty Years' War, 
                    and the diplomacy of Louis's boyhood minister, Cardinal Mazarin (1602-61), made an alliance with neutral German states that countered the rival Hapsburg influence 
                    of the Holy Roman Emperor, Leopold I (1640-1705), Louis abandoned Mazarin's diplomacy and sought to secure this border militarily 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LYNNWARSOFLOUISXIV">Lynn, <hi rend="italic">The Wars of Louis XIV</hi></ref>, 1-16).</p>
                    
                    <p>The second of Louis's wars for glory, the Dutch War (1672-78), formed the context of the actions by Henri de la Tour d'Auvergne, Vicomte Turenne, the marshall of France (1611-75), 
                    to whom Ruskin refers. In a prior conflict, the War of Devolution (1667-68), Louis laid claim to parts of the Spanish Netherlands on the grounds that these holdings "devolved" 
                    on his Spanish queen. To the north, although the Dutch Republic had been warring with the English navy, the Republic, alarmed by Louis's aggression, 
                    signed a Triple Alliance with Britain and Sweden. Louis regarded the alliance as a betrayal by a longtime ally against Spain, which he avenged by launching the Dutch War, 
                    meantime undermining the alliance with a secret treaty with the king of England, Charles II (1630-85). English troops including the young 
                    John Churchill, the future duke of Marlborough (1650-1722), joined the French assault on the Dutch, 
                    with Churchill distinguishing himself in the successful breach of the Dutch fortress of Maastricht. 
                    In 1674, the English Parliament finally forced Charles II to make peace with the Dutch Republic, motivated both by mercantile interests and by sympathy for Protestant Holland. 
                    Some English troops under Churchill's command of remained with the French, however, and they joined with the army led by Turenne, 
                    which was stationed in Alsace and the Palatinate
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LYNNWARSOFLOUISXIV">Lynn, <hi rend="italic">The Wars of Louis XIV</hi></ref>, 105-22).</p>
                    
                    <p>Louis's attention turned to the German theater in order to protect Alsace while, if possible, capturing Franche-Comt&#x00E9; to the south, 
                    along the Savoyard and Swiss border, which he also treated as a Spanish Hapsburg inheritance owing to him. As Leopold I, in alliance with the Dutch, 
                    turned Imperial forces against Louis, the formerly neutral and Protestant Palatinate grew more hostile to France than they had resented domination by the Empire, 
                    owing to Turenne's occupation. In June 1674, Turenne led a battle against Imperial forces up to the gates of Heidelberg, the seat of the Elector of the Palatinate; 
                    and in the subsequent summer months he laid waste to the Neckar valley overlooked by Heidelberg Castle, supplying his troops and burning villages that refused to cooperate 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LYNNWARSOFLOUISXIV">Lynn, <hi rend="italic">The Wars of Louis XIV</hi></ref>, 122-35).</p>
                    
                    <p>At the onset of the Nine Years' War (1688-97), the suffering of the Palatinate again became a symbol of the perceived ruthlessness of the French. 
                    In the year that Louis's old enemy, William of Orange and Stadtholder of the Dutch Republic, took the place of his father in law, James II, 
                    as king of England, Louis took defensive measures against the Dutch-Imperial alliance by adopting a scorched-earth campaign in the Palatinate so that an enemy army 
                    would be unable to support itself in the region. While the brutal destruction was not unique in Louis's wars, 
                    it was "the devastation of the Palatinate that burned itself into the European conscience," 
                    according to a modern historian, to become "one of the influences that inspired Europeans to try to make the conduct of war more restrained and humane in the eighteenth century 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LYNNWARSOFLOUISXIV">Lynn, <hi rend="italic">The Wars of Louis XIV</hi></ref>, 199, and see 191-99).</p>
                    
                    <p>As an example of English feeling about what the desolation of the Palatinate and Heidelberg Castle represented, here is <persName corresp="#JM">John Murray</persName>'s 
                    guidebook description from 1836 of the repeated attacks on the castle: 
                    "In 1674, the Elector, Charles Louis [1617-80], incurred the displeasure of Louis XIV; and a French army, under Turenne, was in consequence let loose 
                    upon the Palatinate, carrying slaughter and desolation before them. The Elector beheld with distress, from the castle in which he had shut himself up, 
                    the inroads of foreign troops, and flame and smoke rising up along the plain from burning towns and villages. Unable to oppose the French with equal force 
                    at the head of an army, but anxious to avenge the wrongs of his country, he resolved, in a spirit which some may deem Quixotic, others chivalrous, 
                    to endeavour to end the contest with his own sword; and accordingly he sent a cartel to Marshal Turenne, challenging him to single combat. 
                    The French general returned a civil answer, hut did not accept it. The ambition of Louis XIV led him, on the death of the Elector, to lay claim to the Palatinate 
                    on behalf of [his younger brother,] the Duke of Orleans [1640-1701, whose second marriage was to the daughter of Elector Charles Louis], 
                    and another French army, more wicked than the first, was marched across the Rhine. 
                    Heidelberg was taken and burnt, 1688 [the onset of the Nine Years' War], by [Compte de] Melac [1630-1704], a general whose brutality and cruelty surpassed that 
                    of [the Count of] Tilly [1559-1632, known for the sacking and massacre of the Protestant German city of Magdeburg in 1631, during the Thirty Years' War]. 
                    But it was at the following siege under [the Marquis de] Chamilly [1636-1715], in 1693, that it was reserved for the French to display the most merciless tyranny, 
                    and practise excesses worthy of fiends rather than men, upon the town and its inhabitants, paralleled only in the French Revolution, 
                    and which will ever render the name of Frenchman odious in the Palatinate. The castle was betrayed through the cowardice or treachery of the governor, 
                    with the garrison, and many of the townspeople who had fled to it for refuge. The cruelty of the treatment they met with was, in this instance, 
                    heightened by religious intolerance, and no mercy was shown to the Protestants. On this occasion the castle was entirely destroyed" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKCONTINENT1836"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers on the Continent</hi></ref>, 430).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CELEBRATEDBUTT" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;And the celebrated butt sounds mournfully hollow&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi>The giant Heidelberg Tun, 
                    "the largest wine cask in the world, being capable of holding 800 hogsheads, 283,200 bottles, which is less, after all, than the dimensions of the porter vat 
                    of a London brewer. In former days, when the Tun was filled with the produce of the vintage, it was usual to dance on the platform on the top. 
                    It has, however, remained empty since 1769, more than half a century" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKCONTINENT1836"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers on the Continent</hi></ref>, 432-33).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="VINUM" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;vinum&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi>wine (Lat.).</p></note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>