<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Early Ruskin Manuscripts Home Page Introduction</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-21">October 21, 2010</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department
                        of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Early Ruskin Manuscripts</hi> is an archive of the youthful
                    writing of John Ruskin (1819&#x2013;1900). Among the most multifaceted thinkers
                    of the nineteenth century, Ruskin developed an approach to art criticism that
                    probed the social, religious, political, and economic implications of
                    appreciating beauty in the arts and the natural world. <hi rend="italic"
                        >ERM</hi> contains the records of his education leading to that career, a
                    body of work distinguished not only by its extraordinary quality and precocity
                    but also by its variety and scope. The archive therefore presents a resource for
                    students of Ruskin's development and of early Victorian culture and education
                    generally.</p>
                <p>In scope, the archive ranges from poetry and fiction to critical essays on the
                    arts; from travelogues and topographical poetry and prose to sermons and
                    religious verse; from mineralogy and geology to mathematics. Starting in 1826,
                    the archive&#x02BC;s earliest documents reveal the Ruskin family&#x02BC;s
                    engagement with late-Enlightenment pedagogy for young children; extending to
                    1842, later documents open up the experiences of an early Victorian Oxonian and
                    the professionalization of a rising author.</p>
                <p>Once the task of organizing, annotating, and exhibiting this mass of material is
                    well underway, the archive also aims to facilitate study of how Ruskin became
                    seemingly the most proto-<hi rend="italic">hypertextual</hi> of Victorian
                    writers. Late in his career, Ruskin experimented with writing and publication
                    that anticipate modes later made possible by digital platforms. Straining the
                    publication resources of his day, he invented an unbounded and hypertextual, if
                    perhaps not quite nonlinear, series of monthly letters called <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fors Clavigera</hi>. It is a valuable question how far Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    innovations were grounded, for example, in a social-network methods of education
                    promoted by the Edgeworths, or in a Romantic-era alertness to the interrelation
                    of arts and disciplines.</p>
                <p>In such questions and in the ongoing digitization of Ruskin&#x02BC;s works, <hi
                        rend="italic">ERM</hi> joins other digital editions such as the <ref
                        target="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/depts/ruskinlib/eSoV/index.html"><hi
                            rend="italic">Ruskin&#x02BC;s Venetian Notebooks</hi></ref>, and <ref
                        target="http://ruskin.ashmus.ox.ac.uk/main.php"><hi rend="italic">The
                            Elements of Drawing</hi></ref>. <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> most directly
                    complements the Lancaster University's <ref
                        target="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/depts/ruskinlib/Pages/welcome.html"
                        >Electronic Edition of <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters</hi> I</ref>, in
                    the sense that the present archive can be viewed as editing the works leading up
                    to that 1843 work, which established Ruskin&#x02BC;s reputation as a popular art
                    critic.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> is not the first edition of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early
                    writing, but, when complete, it will be the most comprehensive. Approximately a
                    third of its materials has never before been available in edited form, and a
                    large portion of the remainder has been available only in the problematically
                    edited form of late-nineteenth- and early-twentieth-century editions. The
                    archive also encourages awareness of the editorial, scholarly, and biographical
                    tradition in which it stands, inviting critical assessment of a tradition of
                    reflection on Ruskin&#x02BC;s youth and education.</p>
                <p>That tradition started in 1850, with the private publication of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Poems</hi> by &#x201C;J.R.,&#x201D; collected by Ruskin&#x02BC;s father,
                        <persName>John James Ruskin</persName>, and by Ruskin&#x02BC;s editor and
                    his father&#x02BC;s friend, <persName>W. H. Harrison</persName>. A contribution
                    by Ruskin himself awaited his autobiographical reflections in the 1880s, when he
                    proposed to print selected early poetry and prose as a
                    &#x201C;supplement&#x201D; to his autobiography, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Praeterita</hi>. This hypertextual link to the early writing was soon
                    realized, however, by Ruskin&#x02BC;s secretary, <persName>W. G.
                        Collingwood</persName>, and his publisher, <persName>George
                    Allen</persName>. They produced a series of editions of poetry and prose,
                    starting with the 1891 <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>, which Collingwood edited
                    with exemplary scholarship by the standards of the time. Transcripts of his
                    edited versions of poems are included in the archive.</p>
                <p>A complementary volume of early prose edited by Collingwood was planned but never
                    executed. Instead, Allen was responsible for a small, somewhat haphazard
                    miscellany of volumes of early prose writing, perhaps meant more to ply the
                    heated trade for fine editions of fugitive writing by &#x201C;modern
                    writers&#x201D; than to serve scholarship. These editions along with the 1891
                        <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> were absorbed into and editorially expanded in
                    the first two volumes of the 1903&#x2013;12 <hi rend="italic">Library
                        Edition</hi>, edited by <persName>E. T. Cook</persName> and
                        <persName>Alexander Wedderburn</persName>.</p>
                <p>Thus, the transmission of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early writing at the turn of the
                    twentieth century is bound up, on one hand, with Ruskin&#x02BC;s construction of
                    his youth in the autobiographical narratives of <hi rend="italic">Fors
                        Clavigera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>, and, on another hand,
                    with the cultural context of fine book collecting centering on modern authors
                    that flourished in the 1890s. <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> provides a means to
                    study these later contexts of transmission of the early Ruskin, which helped to
                    shape subsequent scholarship, as well as the contexts of the early
                    writing&#x02BC;s first creation. <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> also advances an
                    early twentieth-century project initiated by <persName>Helen Gill
                        Viljoen</persName>, who started her scholarship early enough to have met
                    Collingwood and to have examined the Ruskin manuscripts remaining in situ at
                        <placeName>Brantwood</placeName>, Ruskin&#x02BC;s last house, across
                        <placeName>Coniston Water</placeName> from the village of
                        <placeName>Coniston</placeName> in <placeName>Cumbria</placeName>. Viljoen
                    went on to track (and did her part to secure) the early manuscripts&#x02BC;
                    subsequent fortunes, as they made their way from the 1930&#x2013;31 auctions and
                    private sales, through the hands of collectors, to widely scattered
                    depositories. Viljoen&#x02BC;s papers, recording her extensive bibliographic
                    sleuthing that built on Collingwood&#x02BC;s foundations, have formed an
                    important resource for the present edition. The papers, now deposited at the
                    Pierpont Morgan Library should be regarded as forming an impressive archive in
                    their own right.</p>
                <p>Viljoen&#x02BC;s efforts were sustained throughout the second half of the
                    twentieth century by <persName>Van Akin Burd</persName> and <persName>James
                        Dearden</persName>, who continued to edit unpublished early manuscripts,
                    correct errors in the <hi rend="italic">Library Edition</hi>, and carry out
                    other original bibliographical research, including a key edition for the present
                    archive, Burd&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi> (1973).
                    Building on this tradition and (it is hoped) contributing new avenues of
                    scholarship, <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> assembles digital facsimiles of the
                    manuscripts along with transcripts encoded according to the standards of the
                    Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), allowing for expansion in content and
                    extensibility in markup unavailable to earlier editors. The edition is offered
                    as an interdisciplinary research site for a new generation of Romantic and
                    Victorian studies.</p>
                 </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
