<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Work</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="subtype">
                <head type="title">Title of Note</head>
                <p>Huntington.—Only two early manuscripts are held by the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery in San Marino, California, the “Practical Geometry” (MS XIA) and the Fragment on the Expedition of Darius into Scythia (part 1, “Undatable,” no. C). A third, a group of autograph letters to Edward Clayton published in part as Letters Addressed to a College Friend, begin in 1839 and therefore lie just beyond the scope of this edition. Owing to the obscurity enshrouding the provenance of these and other manuscripts that form the core collection of Ruskin at the Huntington, a general introductory note proves more convenient than discussing the provenance of the two manuscripts separately.
                    The earliest date when MS XIA can be definitely proved to have been in the Huntington Library—i.e., a date for which a record exists of the manuscript having been charged out—is 1955, at least twenty-five years after its presumed acquisition. In “A Checklist of Pre-Raphaelite Manuscripts in the Huntington Library,” Sara S. Hodson describes the provenance of MS XIA as “unknown, but acquired before 1930.” The basis for this upper limiting date is not specified, which Hodson assigns also to some other items in the Ruskin collection. In any case, given that limiting date, the following possibilities can be hazarded on the basis of what can be more definitely established about the provenance of the core collection of Ruskin at the Huntington.
                    A centerpiece of the core collection is Ruskin’s 1872–87 correspondence with his Coniston neighbor, Susanna Beever, along with other letters and documents relating to the publication of that correspondence as Hortus Inclusus, edited by Albert Fleming. This collection cannot be proved to have any association with MS XIA. I have searched Ruskin’s letters to Beever in vain for clues that he might have given her the juvenile notebook. He does frequently mention loaning her other books, pictures, and manuscripts, however; and the filial, even infantile, stance that Ruskin adopted toward Beever suggests a greater likelihood that juvenilia was associated with this collection than with the library’s other pre–1930 acquisitions.
                    If we entertain a possible connection with the Ruskin/Beever collection, the acquisition of MS XIA may be pushed back even further than 1930. According to the Huntington’s earliest summary report of the Ruskin Collection, the 874 pieces in the Ruskin/Beever collection “have been in the Library since 1925. No source is known.” At a later, unspecified time, an unknown person scored through this remark and corrected, in ink, “Purchased from Goodspeed’s, September 1923.” This document makes no mention of MS XIA; “874 pieces” seems to refer only to letters. For that matter, however, the summary report fails to list any Ruskin manuscript besides the Ruskin/Beever correspondence as forming the “John Ruskin Collection,” even though the core collection is known to have included other manuscripts, such as several that were purchased from W. S. Allen in 1925 and from William Bixby in 1918. Thus, omissions from the earliest summary report prove only that the library’s Ruskin materials remained uncataloged for many years.	Thus, the Huntington’s summary report of the Ruskin collection proves only that cataloging proceeded very slowly. Other manuscripts besides the Ruskin/Beever correspondence must have been present in the library when the first two-page summary report was prepared, since Hodson lists, for example, several items that were purchased from W. S. Allen in 1925 (“Checklist,” 194–96 [items 390, 392, 398, 402, 404]). One suspects, in fact, that it was a confusion with the Allen lot that led the author of the original summary report to claim that the Ruskin/Beever letters “have been in the Library since 1925.”
                    Regrettably, no record of a 1923 Goodspeed transaction can presently be found. In one respect, the year 1923 is surprising, since, in his autobiography, the Boston book dealer mentions no acquisitions of manuscripts prior to the Sotheby sales of 1930 and 1931. Goodspeed does remark, however, that, for many years during trips to England, he routinely stocked up on Ruskin first editions to supply a steady market in America (YB, 262). Perhaps during one of these expeditions, he was able to acquire the Ruskin/Beever collection. In another respect, September 1923 is not surprising as the date of acquisition, since Albert Fleming, the heir of Beever’s Ruskin correspondence and the editor of Hortus Inclusus, died on 21 March 1923 at his home in Skelwith Bridge near Ambleside.
                    Prior to coming (putatively) into Goodspeed’s hands, the Ruskin/Beever correspondence is last known to have been owned by Fleming, who removed the letters from Beever’s home. Although letters and manuscripts related to Hortus have ended up widely scattered among collections in England and America, the Huntington obviously holds the main lode that belonged to Fleming, since it includes his own correspondence and other documents concerning the publication and revision of Hortus.	Fleming did turn over the letters to E. T. Cook for editing in the Library Edition, but, especially in view of his thorny relations with Cook and Wedderburn, it is highly unlikely that he would have relinquished ownership. In his introduction to the volumes of letters for the Library Edition, Cook is careful to specify that Beever “bequeathed her Ruskin letters” to Fleming, who “has some nine hundred of them” (Works 36:cviii).
                    The Lake District connection with Fleming is highly suggestive for the provenance not only of these letters but also of Ruskin juvenilia that might have accompanied them in a sale. Another collector who depended largely on Lake District sources to amass his Ruskin collection, Haddon Clifford Adams, owned a holograph preface to Hortus Inclusus as well as some juvenilia (RBB 198, and see MS IC, “Provenance”). This is not to imply that Adams might have served as Goodspeed’s source for the Ruskin/Beever collection, for Adams would surely have kept such a find for himself. Rather, the intersection between the Adams collection and Goodspeed’s putative 1923 sale to the Huntington points to Lake District sources. These could include Fleming himself, who might have made arrangements for the collection before he died; an Ambleside dealer, Arnold Varty, who is definitely known to have offered Ruskin/Beever material—Beever’s sketchbook—although Dearden suggests that Varty would have acquired this sketchbook later than the time I am discussing, at the 1931 Brantwood sale (RBB 118–19); T. H. Telford, the Grasmere dealer, who did acquire materials from Brantwood prior to the sales of the 1930s, and who is known to have held at least a few Ruskin/Beever letters (RBB 212–13); and, at Brantwood itself, Violet Severn and the Wilkinson family, who sold items directly to collectors, including Adams, prior to the authorized auctions (see above, Viljoen and Sharp).
                    If the Huntington’s Ruskin juvenilia did not come to the library along with the purchase through Goodspeed of the Ruskin/Beever/Fleming materials, it might have been connected with other sources of the Ruskin collection acquired “before 1930.” The most intriguing of these is one listed by Hodson as “William K. Bixby, 1918, through George D. Smith” (“Checklist,” 197, 198, 201 [items 406, 408, 421 442–43]). Bixby was a St. Louis industrialist and collector, who, probably in 1902, acquired from George Allen the important manuscripts of The Seven Lamps of Architecture; two essays of Unto This Last; and, most significant for our purposes, twenty-four autograph Ruskin letters to Edward Clayton, twenty-two of which were published in 1894 as Letters Addressed to a College Friend. These were sold as part of Bixby’s private collection to Henry Huntington in 1918.	Bixby’s ownership of these manuscripts is confirmed by the Library Edition, if sketchily, although here Bixby’s source is identified as George Allen, rather than as George D. Smith (of Smith, Elder, Ruskin’s publisher prior to Allen), named in the Huntington record. For the Clayton letters, Bixby is identified by name as the owner, while the seller is not identified, although Allen was the publisher of the 1894 volume (Works 1: 400; see also Sidney M. B. Coulling, “Two Unpublished Letters of John Ruskin to Edward Clayton,” Huntington Library Quarterly 27 [1963]: 87–92). The reverse is the case in the Library Edition volumes of Seven Lamps and Unto This Last, where the “American collector” is left anonymous, while Allen is identified as the seller (Works 8: 278, 17: cxiii). The editors attach a specific date of sale, 1902, only to the Seven Lamps manuscript.
                    Bixby’s group of Clayton letters provides the nearest relative in the Ruskin collection to the prose translation from Herodotus, the Fragment on the Expedition of Darius into Scythia, whose provenance is otherwise “unknown; in library 1961” (Hodson, “Checklist,” 195 [item 395]). As discussed in the note on dating this manuscript in part 1 (“Undatable,” no. C), the fragment may have been written between 1837 and 1840 at Oxford, where Ruskin’s study of Herodotus inspired the composition of such poems as “The Tears of Psammenitus,” which he discusses in the Clayton letters (Works 1:434–44). The topics and dates of the fragment and the Clayton letters roughly correspond, although no documentation establishes a shared provenance.
                    Other pre–1930 provenances of Ruskin material at the Huntington furnish no clues about early manuscripts. Most prominent is a 1925 lot acquire</p>
                <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                        <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                        <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Body paragraph.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>