<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Seaside Resorts</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-26">October 26, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">Seaside Resorts</head>
                <p>In June 1819, Margaret Ruskin wrote to John James when he was at <placeName>Weymouth</placeName>, recommending that he 
                    &#x201C;try cautiously the sea&#x201D;: &#x201C;take but one plunge come out instantly rub yourself perfectly dry and if you should feel no cold nor headake try it again at the interval of the day.&#x201D; 
                    If this experiment made him &#x201C;sensible of benefit,&#x201D; she urged him to &#x201C;stay [at] the seaside as long as business will permit&#x201D; in order to strengthen his health 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 95). Apparently, the trial convinced the couple of the salubriousness of sea bathing, 
                    as in 1822 Margaret referred pleasantly to <placeName>Sandgate</placeName> (a journey that must have occurred in the interval, in the summer of 1820 or 1821, 
                    and that in 1822 already represented to John at age three the standard for outdoor pleasure); and Ruskin&#x02BC;s earliest sustained narrative, 
                    <ref type="works" target="harry_and_lucy_vol1_apparatus.html">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1,</ref> recounts a visit to <placeName>Hastings</placeName> 
                    (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 107, 108; and see also 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="tours_of_1822-25_note.html">Tours of 1822&#x2013;25</ref> and 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="tours_of_1826-27_note.html">Tours of 1826&#x2013;27</ref>).</p>
                <p>Weymouth ranked among the most splendid early seaside destinations, having served as the resort for <persName>George III</persName>, 
                    who acquired from his brother, <persName>Duke of Gloucester</persName>, a residence on the Esplanade. For family holidays, the Ruskins, however, appear to have been drawn to less grand
                    (and less expensive?) resorts closer to London, Hastings and Sandgate. . . . [more on early Victorian sea bathing]</p>
                <p>In 1823, at the same time that the Ruskins showed so much delight in their seaside visits, William Cobbett, while admiring the beauty of Sandgate and Folkstone, 
                    was struck mainly by the area&#x02BC;s Mortello towers, defensive works that had been erected to guard against Napoleonic invasion. 
                    Cobbett railed against the costliness of &#x201C;these ridiculous things,&#x201D; thirty of which he counted stretching in a &#x201C;chain&#x201D; from Sandgate &#x201C;all the way to Hastings!&#x201D; 
                    For him, they represented the government&#x02BC;s extravagance that was &#x201C;sending some farmers to the workhouse and driving others to flee the country or to cut their throats!&#x201D; 
                    (Cobbett, <hi rend="italic">Rural Rides</hi>, September 3, 1<!-- bibliog ref needed -->). The Ruskins are likely to have gazed on these structures with opposite feelings of patriotism.</p>
            </div>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head type="subsection">Hastings</head>
                <p> A town and port on the shore (or <hi rend="italic">rape</hi>) of Sussex. In the
                    1820's, the distance from London was 64 miles. [Pick up on tourism, Moss 123,
                    145-46] <!--Entry needed here.--> </p>
                <p>The vicinity was best known as the historical site of the Battle of Hastings,
                    which, in the language of an 1824 history of the town, &#x201C;changed the destinies .
                    . . of the nation, by annihilating the Saxon dynasty, and substituting that of
                    the Norman in its stead&#x201D; (Moss, <hi rend="italic">Hastings</hi> 1). When the
                    Ruskins visited in 1826, attractions would have included the castle ruins, of
                    which survived &#x201C;a few fragments . . . , presenting grotesque and fantastic
                    forms, from different points in which they may be viewed. The only remains now
                    [in 1824] in any degree perfect, are small portions of a round and square Tower,
                    with a part of the sally-port. Its site is on a rocky cliff on the westward of
                    the Town&#x201D; (Moss, <hi rend="italic">Hastings</hi> 60).</p>
                <p>Of ecclesiastical ruins, &#x201C;gloomy but interesting vestiges of monastic grandeur
                    remain[ed] . . . heighten[ing] the picturesque beauties of the local scenery.&#x201D;
                    The most prominent churches were All Saints, believed to stand &#x201C;in its original
                    state&#x201D; from the early fourteenth century; and St. Clements, parts of which also
                    dated to the fourteenth century (Moss, <hi rend="italic">Hastings</hi> 78, 97,
                    112). </p>
                <p>[Pick up on views, Moss 123-24, 126] <!--Entry needed here.-->. There was also a view of the town from the
                    site of a Roman encampment, on the hill east of the town.</p>
                <p> On the shore, there was a fort and a landing place (<hi rend="italic">stade</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">staithe</hi>), where Ruskin was probably diverted by
                    observing the bustle of related to shipping, fishing, and boat&#x2010;building, such as
                    watching vessels launched&#x2014;perhaps the model for Harry&#x02BC;s experiments with his toy
                    boat, or for the drawing &#x201C;Harry Seeing a Ship Launch,&#x201D; [Plate] <!--Entry needed here.--> &#x201C;6,&#x201D; [&#x201C;Harry and
                    Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1] (See &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1, <!--Entry needed here.-->).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>