<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Transcription</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="HMT">Heidi M. Toloudis</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-25">October 25, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head>Transcription and Markup</head>
                <div type="subsection">
                <head type="subsection">Documentary Editing</head>
                <p>Peter Shillingsburg argues that &#x201C;an editor&#x02BC;s fundamental
                    orientation&#x201D; to the question of authority, and &#x201C;not the
                    intrinsic merits of any textual problem,&#x201D; tends to determine how
                    editors assess textual problems and propose solutions (Shillingsburg, <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age</hi>, 54). [Discuss
                    whether this is true of Juvenilia Press books. Aesthetic orientation there<!--Entry needed here-->] </p>
                <p>In fact, editors&#x02BC; predilections aside, juvenilia do present an
                    intrinsic case favoring documentary editing, since the authority tends not to be
                    divided among multiple witnesses&#x2014;and monolithic authority calls for
                    historical, documentary treatment rather than the production of an eclectic
                    text. In the case of the early Ruskin manuscripts, of the approximately 3<!--Entry needed here-->?
                    &#x201C;works&#x201D; (see Plan of the Edition) contained in
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s written corpus between 1826 and 1842, 00 survive in
                    solitary versions from that period. In 00 of those cases, the versions are
                    represented by a single manuscript in draft or fair&#x2010;copy form; and in 00 of
                    those cases, the versions survive in a single printed form. Another 00 of the
                    3<!--Entry needed here-->? survive in two or more manuscript versions, typically one draft and one fair
                    copy, but other combinations are extant. And 00 survive in some combination of
                    draft and/or fair&#x2010;copy manuscript version plus a printed version produced within
                    the time frame of the edition, 1826&#x2013;42. Thus, a documentary approach
                    seems intrinsically weighted by the fact that, in 00% of the extant cases,
                    authority is not divided at all, being represented by a unique manuscript or
                    printed witness; in 00% of cases, authority is divided between very few
                    manuscript witnesses; and in only 00% of cases, authority is divided between
                    witnesses that entail some degree of editorial intervention. </p>
                <p>Alternatively, a case for an eclectic approach hinges on what happened when a
                    given work was caught up in one or more of the three major editing projects
                    involving the early manuscripts: the editing of <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>
                    (1850) by John James Ruskin and W. H. Harrison; the editing of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Poems</hi> (1891) by W. G. Collingwood, along with the editing (in a more
                    modest sense of the term) and printing in the 1890s of various early prose works
                    by George Allen; and the editing or reissue (the levels of intervention varied)
                    of these and some additional early works by the editors of the Library Edition,
                    E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn. I will argue that Ruskin himself was so
                    little involved with these editorial projects that their interest is primarily
                    sociological&#x2014;that the editors&#x02BC; orientation to this
                    material at their differing historical moments is more interesting than
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s involvement, who was disengaged by, and even contemptuous
                    of the 1850 project, and who was supportive of, but unable to participate in the
                    1890s projects. Thus, the sociological interest of these editorial situations
                    calls for a historical approach rather than one favoring an eclectic text. </p>
                <p>In taking a documentary approach&#x2014;what Mary&#x2010;Jo Kline defines as
                    orienting a modern edition toward preserving the nuances of
                    &#x201C;inscribed artifacts whose unique physical characteristics and
                    original nature give them special evidentiary value&#x201D; (Kline, <hi
                        rend="italic">Guide to Documentary Editing</hi>, 2)&#x2014;more is to
                    be learned, I believe, about the early manuscripts <emph rend="italic"
                        >both</emph> as imaginative works and as documents yielding evidence about
                    the history of education, the early Victorian family, literary production in the
                    marketplace of the annuals, scientific production in the marketplace of the
                    natural history magazines, and the wealth of other historical, cultural, and
                    biographical topics that early Ruskin corpus touches on. For the latter kinds of
                    topics, the evidentiary value of the early manuscripts in their original form is
                    self&#x2010;evident. As for these early works considered as imaginative creations, one
                    must admit from the start that what interest they possess pales next to
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s mature prose. Still, it is an essential to understanding
                    Ruskin that he found an imaginative resource in revisiting his early writing and
                    drawing&#x2014;and doing so, it appears, by reexamining the early
                    manuscripts and not, for example, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1850) or the
                    versions of his poems published in the annuals of the 1830s and 1840s. It is
                    telling that, when Ruskin [1870 story; Emerson] </p>
                <p>Collingwood&#x02BC;s contention about elder Ruskins&#x02BC; lack of
                    interference in. . . . Relation of 1891 poems to Praeterita</p>
                <p>Even for those works surviving in more than one version, a documentary rather
                    than eclectic approach is preferable since one interest in juvenilia and
                    youthful writing must reside in the possible collaboration represented by any
                    given version. Ruskin&#x02BC;s early texts probably rarely represent the
                    collaborative play at the pitch of the Brontes&#x02BC; plays and sagas. The
                    family letters amply show that he shared his writing with his parents, however,
                    and any given version might reflect a spectrum of collaboration. Admittedly,
                    orthographic evidence of some form of joint writing is scarce (e.g., Ruskin and
                    Mary Richardson&#x02BC;s 1830 diary; Ruskin and his father&#x02BC;s
                    commonplace book); and even orthographic examples of the boy&#x02BC;s
                    writing and a parent&#x02BC;s editing are not common (e.g., <!--Entry needed here-->??). But the
                    letters show repeatedly that Ruskin wrote primarily for his parents&#x02BC;
                    ears, and that he heard their voices, particularly his father&#x02BC;s, as
                    he drafted and revised his works. </p>
                <p>Printed works: JJR and Harrison <!--Entry needed here.-->.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head type="subsection">Manuscript Transcription and Markup Procedures</head>
                    <p><!--Entry needed here.--></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>