<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <fileDesc xml:id="source_of_the_arveron_prose_le">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"The Source of Arveron" [essay]</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in <hi rend="italic">Title of Printed Work</hi> (Date)</title>
                <!--The xml:ids for author and editor below should include the first, middle, and last initials of the author and the editor, respectively.-->
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#">E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#KBV">Kyle B. Volkmann</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <filiation><ref type="apparatus" target="apparatuses/account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_apparatus.php#account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_le"></ref></filiation>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Works of John Ruskin</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">Library<hi rend="superscript"></hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1903">1903</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">386-87</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="witness" subtype="essay">
                <head type="title"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRSOURCEOFTHEARVERON">The Source of Arveron</title><ref type="gloss_textual" target="source_of_the_arveron_prose_glosses_textual.php#SOURCEOFTHEARVERONTITLE" /></head>
                <p>W<hi rend="smallcaps">hat</hi> a delicious thing is a reverie, that total abstraction from all 
                    things present&#x2014;that stilly, dreamy, waking vision that places you where 
                    you are not, that carries you where you wish to be, that presents the past 
                    to your recollection, and the future to your fancy, so forcibly, so impressively, 
                    so lovelily, throwing a glow on every circumstance, and a halo on every 
                    feature, giving the vivid, the magic colouring of the dream to the defined 
                    and distinct recollection of the reality. It is thus that I look back upon 
                    our first walk at <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, to the Source of the <geogName corresp="#ARVERON">Arveron</geogName>.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="source_of_the_arveron_prose_glosses_contextual.php#WALKTOTHESOURCE"/> What varieties 
                    of childish beauty we met with in that short walk, every little mountaineer 
                    was a perfect picture; one little fellow insisted upon conducting us to the 
                    source, and as <hi rend="italic">notre guide principale</hi> piloted us proudly through the crowd 
                    of little fry who were lying in wait, all expecting a similar distinction, 
                    but who, finding the post of honour preoccupied, followed very gravely <hi rend="italic">en suite</hi>.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="source_of_the_arveron_prose_glosses_contextual.php#VARIETIESOFCHILDISHBEAUTY"/> 
                    &#x201C;Voil&#x00E0; la source,&#x201D; quoth our <hi rend="italic">petit conducteur</hi>, as we emerged from a 
                    dark wood of pines bordering on the waves of the flowing <geogName corresp="#ARVERON">Arveron</geogName>. It was 
                    exceeding lovely. The day had been one continued succession of storms, 
                    but the eve was breaking and giving fair promise of a sunny morrow. 
                    Right in front a few exhausted but lingering tempest clouds shadowed 
                    the dark masses of pine that girdle the <geogName corresp="#MONTANVERT">Montanvert</geogName>,<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="source_of_the_arveron_prose_glosses_contextual.php#MONTANVERT"/> but farther to 
                    the west broke away into fleecy masses, scarcely distinguishable from the 
                    eternal snow that flashed through their openings, and farther still a serene 
                    evening sky glowed peacefully. A lurid, ominous light pervaded the 
                    whole air, that stormy and murky lume, the effect of the strange combat 
                    between the sun and tempest; the one casting the whole body of gigantic<pb/>
                    mountains into a dreary darkness, the other pouring a stream of red, 
                    ghostly, dusky light up the valley, that caught as it past the projecting 
                    pinnacled spires of the <geogName corresp="#BOSSONS">glacier des Bossons</geogName>, which flashed dazzling forth 
                    from the gloom of the ribbed crags as the lightning leaps from the 
                    thunder cloud. A low, hollow, melancholy echoing was heard issuing from 
                    the recesses of the mountains, the last sighing of the passing-away tempest, 
                    the last murmurs of the storm spirit as he yielded up his reign; it past 
                    away, and the blue rigidness of the transparent cavern of the glacier woke 
                    rosily to the departing sun.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>