<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Bibliography of Ruskin (1878&#x2013;81)</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="subtype">
                <head type="title"><hi rend="italic">Complete Bibliography of . . . Ruskin</hi> (1889&#x2013;93)</head>
                <p>Thomas H. Wise and James P. Smart compiled this exhaustive bibliography, 
                    <hi rend="italic">A Complete Bibliography of the Writings in Prose and Verse of John Ruskin, LL.D., with a List of the More Important Ruskiniana</hi>. 
                    It was initially issued in parts:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD1">&#x201C;From 1835 to the Present Time (September 1878)&#x201D; [1st ed.]</ref>;</item>
                        <item><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD2">&#x201C;From 1834 to the Present Time (October 1878)&#x201D; [2d ed.]</ref>;</item>
                        <item><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD3">&#x201C;From 1834 to the Present Time (November 1878)&#x201D; [3d ed.]</ref>;</item>
                        <item><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD4">&#x201C;(From 1834 to 1879), 4th edition, revised and enlarged&#x201D;</ref>;</item>
                        <item><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD5">&#x201C;(From 1834 to 1881), 5th edition, revised and enlarged&#x201D;</ref>.</item>
                    </list>
                <p>In addition, an American edition, published in New York by John Wiley and Sons in 1878, was based on the second edition. 
                    Of the British editions, only the fifth carries a publisher's imprint on the title page: 
                    London: / Elliot Stock, 62, Paternoster Row. This edition was issued also in a large format, 
                    a "special edition printed for the members of the Ruskin Society." Of the British editions prior to the fifth&#x2014;certainly the first, and presumably the second through the fourth, as well&#x2014;were 
                    "printed for private circulation," 
                    according to a clipping attached to a copy of the first edition held by the Ruskin Library, and copies were available "on application to the editor." See also the description of the publication 
                    in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 38:110. 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#SHEPHERDDNB">Collins, &#x201C;Richard Herne Shepherd,&#x201D;</ref> mentions that some of Shepherd's works were published by his brother, 
                    who ran a bookshop in Holborn under the name of Frank Hollings, but this arrangement would not have come about prior to 1892 
                    (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#TENNYSONSHEPHERDWISE">Paden, &#x201C;Tennyson&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">The Lover&#x02BC;s Tale</hi>, Shepherd, and Wise,&#x201D; 117n</ref>).</p>
                <p>The first, third, and fifth editions appear to have been published without the compiler's name anywhere indicated, whether on the title page or at the end of the introduction.</p> 
                <p>The first four editions carry a dedication to the artist, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="backhouse_h_f_note.html">Henry Backhouse</ref> 
                    (his full name given as Henry Fleetwood Backhouse, starting with the third edition), &#x201C;who first
                    suggested to the compiler the idea of this little bibliography,&#x201D; Perhaps Backhouse originally helped subsidize the publication, 
                    since the dedication is dropped from the fifth edition, published by Elliot Stock; 
                    or perhaps Backhouse was simply one of the avid Ruskin "collectors" to whom the author hoped the bibliography would "prove useful," according to the clipping on the Ruskin Library copy.</p>
                <p>Expansion and reissue of the bibliography was planned from the start, since, in the introduction to the first edition, the author anticipates "more fortunate or more persistent research" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD1">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of Ruskin</hi> [1st ed.]</ref>, vii). Already expanded for reissue a month later, 
                    the second edition names with thanks several individuals who supplied additional items for description 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD2">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of Ruskin</hi> [2d ed.]</ref>, viii). The list attests that influential persons 
                    took an interest in the project.</p> 
                <p>Doubtless Shepherd had also hoped from the start to gain an acknowledgment from Ruskin himself. In a letter of 30 September 1878, written apparently in response to receiving the first edition, 
                    Ruskin answered Shepherd: 
                    &#x201C;So far from being distasteful to me, your perfect reckoning up of me not only flatters my vanity extremely, but will be in the highest degree useful to myself. 
                    But you know so much more about me than I now remember about anything, that I can't find a single thing to correct or add&#x2014;glancing through at least. 
                    I will not say you have wasted your time; but I may at least regret the quantity of trouble the book must have given you. . . .&#x201D; In a second letter, dated 23 October 1878, 
                    Ruskin acknowledges receipt undoubtedly of the second edition: "I am very deeply grateful to you, as I am in all duty bound, for this very curious record of myself. It will be of extreme value to me 
                    in filling up what gaps I can in this patched coverlid of my life, before it is draped over my coffin&#x2014;if it may be. I am especially glad to have note of the letters to newspapers.&#x201D; 
                    These letters are printed as loose inserts included with the second edition, at least as found in the Ruskin Library's copy, 
                    but various evidence confirms that the letters did originally belong to that edition.<note>The American edition, published by Wiley and based on the second edition, carries the 30 September letter, 
                        printed opposite the title page. In both the American and the British second editions, this letter is prefaced by the explanation: 
                    "The Compiler of this Bibliography has had the honour to receive, in acknowledgment of a copy which he sent to Brantwood, 
                    the following letter from Mr. Ruskin." The second letter, as suggested by its 23 October 1878 date, may likewise have accompanied the second edition; 
                    however, the origin of its separate printed card is unclear. The Bodleian Library copy of the second edition, as shown online in Google Books, includes only the first Ruskin letter.</note> 
                It is no accident, therefore, that the second edition carried Shepherd's name in print, as did the fourth, which likewise involved self-advertisement using Ruskin's letters (see below).</p> 
                <p>Ruskin's comment in the October letter about his interest in "the letters to newspapers" refers to a particular interest of Shepherd's. In the introduction to the first edition of the bibliography, 
                    Shepherd expressed his special solicitude to track down the public letters, and the second edition does 
                    contain additional entries of this kind. One wonders if Shepherd was planning to collect these ephemera; if so, he was trumped by Alexander Wedderburn, who with Ruskin's support collected 
                    Ruskin's public letters to newspapers in  
                    <hi rend="italic">Arrows of the Chase</hi>, published in 1880 (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 34:xxxviii).<note>Wedderburn 
                        prints Ruskin's letters to Shepherd in <hi rend="italic">Arrows of the Chase</hi>, noting that the letters are "given in the List of 'Mr. Shepherd's Publications,' 
                        printed at the end of his <hi rend="italic">The Bibliography of Dickens</hi>, 1880" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 34:537). The texts of both letters, September and October 1878, are indeed 
                    found in the back matter of <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#DICKENSBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">The Bibliography of Dickens</hi></ref>), 
                    following numerous complimentary squibs from journals about Shepherd's Ruskin bibliography. Wedderburn's remark in <hi rend="italic">Arrows of the Chase</hi> suggests that he took the texts of the letters 
                    from this source and knew nothing about their prior printing to accompany the Ruskin bibliography. The list printed at the back of the Dickens bibliography advertises specifically the fourth edition 
                    of the bibliography, which is the one other edition besides the second to bear Shepherd's name in print.</note></p>
                <p>In each edition of the bibliography except the last, which drops the author's introduction, Shepherd dwells on his care: &#x201C;the materials for [the bibliography&#x02BC;s] compilation have taken many years to collect, 
                    and much anxious labour has been spent on its preparation and arrangement. No entry has in any case been made at second&#x2010;hand; but always with the actual book, pamphlet,
                    magazine, or journal described lying before the compiler.&#x201D; Indeed, the thoroughness of Shepherd's sleuthing is impressive. Entries on Ruskin's early publications are in some cases annotated 
                    with quotations identifying or legitimating the piece. For example, Shepherd authenticates his entry for Ruskin's two 1834 essays published in <hi rend="italic">The Magazine of Natural History</hi>, 
                    &#x201C;Enquiries on the Causes of the Colour of the Water of the Rhine,&#x201D; 
                    and &#x201C;Facts and Considerations on the Strata of Mont Blanc,&#x201D; by quoting a footnote from the so&#x2010;called 
                    <hi rend="italic">Instructions in Use of the Rudimentary Series</hi> for the Drawing Schools at Oxford (1872), where Ruskin remarks that &#x201C;Mr. Loudon was the first
                        literary patron who sent words of mine to be actually set up in print, in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Magazine of Natural History</hi>, when I was sixteen&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD2">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of Ruskin</hi> [2d ed.]</ref>, 1-2; see also 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE"><hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref> 21:243n). 
                    Similarly, in the entry for <hi rend="italic">The Poetry of Architecture</hi> (1839), Shepherd appends a nugget from Ruskin&#x02BC;s 1878 essay on 
                    W. H. Harrison, &#x201C;My First Editor: An Autobiographical Reminiscence.&#x201D; Shepherd quotes: &#x201C;the series of essays written for the <hi rend="italic">Architectural Magazine</hi>, 
                    under the signature of Kata Phusin, contain sentences nearly as well put together as any I have done since&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYSHEPHERD2">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of Ruskin</hi> [2d ed.]</ref>, 2; see also
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE"><hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 34:97). In the quotation from the <hi rend="italic">Instructions</hi> for the Drawing Schools, 
                        Shepherd not only references an obscure footnote; he must have obtained the pamphlet itself with some difficulty, it having never been issued for sale, but printed only for
                        students of the Drawing Schools (perhaps obtained from Backhouse or one of the contributors thanked in the introduction). Ruskin's essay on Harrison was likewise somewhat obscure. 
                        Familiar nowadays to Ruskin scholars, as it was reprinted in 1885 in <hi rend="italic">On the Old Road</hi>, in 1878 the piece would have been accessible to Shepherd 
                    only as a preface to Harrison&#x02BC;s memoir, recently published in the <hi rend="italic">Dublin University Magazine</hi>. (In fact, since Ruskin's essay on Harrison appeared in April 1878, 
                    and Shepherd's first issue of the bibliography later that year in September, one wonders if it was Ruskin's tribute to his first editor 
                that first inspired Shepherd's project.) Similarly, in his edition of Barrett Browning's juvenilia, Shepherd cites journal and encyclopedia articles authenticating the poet's early volumes, 
                and those essays, too, may have prompted Shepherd's undertaking  
                (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#BARRETTBROWNINGEARLIERPOEMS1878">Barrett Browning, <hi rend="italic">Earlier Poems</hi>, ed. Shepherd</ref>, v-viii).</p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>