<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Forgery and Piracy</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-11-01">November 1, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">Forgery and Piracy</head>
                <p>Pirated editions of early Ruskin poetry or prose were produced primarily by
                    American publishers prior to international copyright agreements. Forged editions
                    were produced by Thomas J. Wise and H. Buxton Forman.</p>
                <div type="section">
                <head type="section">Wise and Forman Forgeries</head>
                <p>Of the approximately one hundred nineteenth&#x02010;century literary
                    pamphlets that have been identified as being forgeries by T. J. Wise and Buxton
                    Forman, eight capitalized on works by Ruskin, of which two were juvenile pieces,
                    &#x201C;Leoni&#x201D; and &#x201C;The Scythian Guest&#x201D;
                    (Barker and Collins, A Sequel, 368&#x2013;75, esp. 371). For details about
                    the latter two forged pamphlets, see &#x201C;Leoni&#x201D;: Composition
                    and Publication, and &#x201C;The Scythian Guest&#x201D;: Composition
                    and Publication. For biographical details about the forgers specifically
                    relevant to Ruskin scholarship, see the notes on Thomas J. Wise and H. Buxton
                    Forman. The present note is concerned with forgery of the juvenilia more
                    broadly.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                <head type="section">The Discovery of the Forgeries</head>
                <p>Like many other pamphlets exposed in 1934 by Carter and Pollard, Enquiry, the
                    Ruskin juvenilia pamphlets represented an unprecedented kind of forgery. They
                    were not spurious imitations of existing rarities but inventions of rarities.
                    Exploiting genuine and accessible texts, the forgers created hitherto unknown
                    editions, for which Wise prepared the appearance of legitimacy by listing them
                    in his own scholarly bibliographies of authors (see Note on Bibliography),
                    describing them in bibliographic articles for the Bookman, and, more loosely, by
                    concocting and disseminating elaborate stories about their production and
                    provenance.</p>
                <p>For some of the forged pamphlets, the claim for rarity was founded on their
                    alleged priority, as in the case that finally undid Wise, the &#x201C;1847
                    Reading&#x201D; private printing of Barrett Browning&#x02BC;s Sonnets
                    from the Portuguese, which the author, according to Wise, entrusted to Mary
                    Russell Mitford to see through press three years earlier than the
                    sonnets&#x02BC; known publication. Of the Ruskin forgeries, Wise claimed a
                    similar case of prior publication for the pamphlet of Queen&#x02BC;s [sic]
                    Gardens, a printing of the lecture bearing the year and imprint of its original
                    delivery (Manchester, 1864)&#x2014;a year earlier than its known first
                    appearance as part of Sesame and Lilies in 1865.</p>
                <p>The claim for the juvenilia pamphlets was different, however. Wise explained the
                    &#x201C;1868&#x201D; Leoni and the &#x201C;1849&#x201D; Scythian Guest <!--Correction needed here?-->
                    pamphlets, not as previously unknown first editions, but as
                    later, fugitive reprintings at the behest of unidentified friends. Ironically,
                    as it turned out, concocting the juvenile pieces as alleged first editions might
                    have been faked more safely. It was suspicion of these two pamphlets along with
                    two other Ruskin pamphlets that initially prompted the systematic investigations
                    by John Carter and Graham Pollard that fully exposed the forgeries in
                    1934&#x2014;exposure aimed at first at Wise, as by far the more prominent
                    public figure of the pair, and extended only gradually over the years to
                    Forman.</p>
                <p>Carter and Pollard were first alerted to the possibility of forgery by E. T. Cook
                    and Alexander Wedderburn. In volumes 1 and 2 (1903&#x2013;4) of the Library
                    Edition, Cook and Wedderburn declared the two juvenilia printings probable
                    fakes, and, soon thereafter in volumes 12 and 18 (1904&#x2013;5), condemned
                    both the &#x201C;1864&#x201D; separate issue of the
                    &#x201C;Queens&#x02BC; Gardens&#x201D; lecture and an
                    &#x201C;1852&#x201D; pamphlet, The National Gallery, <!--Correction needed here?--> which collected
                    certain letters by Ruskin to the Times.</p>
                <p>In hindsight, one can see the happy convergence of talents that enabled Cook and
                    Wedderburn to detect the frauds: Cook possessed outstandingly thorough knowledge
                    of Ruskin, and, as a journalist, he would have known his way around London
                    publishers and printers. Wedderburn was an experienced Ruskin bibliographer;
                    and, in particular, as editor of Arrows of the Chace, a collection of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s letters to newspapers, he would have been especially keen
                    to sniff out the doubtfulness of the National Gallery pamphlet. Moreover,
                    Wedderburn was by profession a barrister.</p>
                <p>Cook and Wedderburn spied signs of forgery in the fact that independent records
                    of the pamphlets&#x02BC; existence bore only recent dates, long after their
                    supposed publication. For example, the juvenilia pamphlets were not mentioned in
                    Shepherd, Bibliography of Ruskin <!--Entry needed here.--> (from 1834 to 1879), first published in
                    1878. (Neither were they mentioned in Shepherd&#x02BC;s subsequent
                    expansions of the bibliography.)<note n="1" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    The entries for Leoni (no. 4) in R. H. Shepherd, Bibliography of Ruskin <!--Entry needed here.--> (from 1834 to
                    1879), p. 3, and in R. H. Shepherd, Bibliography of Ruskin <!--Entry needed here.--> (from 1834
                    to 1881), p. 3, carry the annotation, &#x201C;The Prose Legend has never
                    been reprinted.&#x201D; The comment bears no necessary relation to Wise
                    and Forman&#x02BC;s faked pamphlet, presumably yet to be fabricated,
                    since Shepherd attached a similar note to two early poems (no. 2, p. 2),
                    published in gift annuals, that were not included in Poems (1850).</note>
                    The pamphlets were conspicuous, however, in Wise and Smart, Complete
                    Bibliography of <!--Entry needed here.--> Ruskin (1889&#x2013;93). Likewise of recent date was
                    the pamphlets&#x02BC; emergence on the rare book market&#x2014;and at
                    high prices.</p>
                <p>Concerning the other two pamphlets suspected by Cook and Wedderburn, the evidence
                    was even surer. Collation of the &#x201C;1852&#x201D; National Gallery
                    pamphlet with the original 1847 and 1852 letters to the Times and with their
                    later reprinting in Arrows of the Chase (1880), which Wedderburn had edited,
                    revealed that the alleged &#x201C;first edition&#x201D; was based on
                    the 1880 text&#x2014;an obvious impossibility (Ruskin, Works, 12:396).
                    Similarly, by collating the &#x201C;1864&#x201D; Queen&#x02BC;s
                    Gardens pamphlet with versions of the lecture that appeared in Sesame and
                    Lilies, the editors concluded that &#x201C;the person who put [the pamphlet]
                    upon the market, not knowing that Ruskin had revised the lecture in 1871,<note n="2" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Cook and Wedderburn refer to the text as revised for the
                    first volume, Sesame and Lilies, of the Works Series, launched in
                    1871.</note> had his &#x2018;original edition of the utmost
                    scarcity,&#x2019; set up from the later editions,&#x201D; while
                    clumsily and unconvincingly deleting portions of the text to make the pamphlet
                    appear to be a transcript of the lecture as originally delivered (Works, 18:15).<note n="3" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    James Dearden points out that the apparent apostrophe error
                    in the pamphlet&#x02BC;s title, which Cook and Wedderburn treated as a
                    dead giveaway&#x2014;&#x201C;the title &#x2018;The
                    Queen&#x02BC;s Gardens&#x2019; was certainly not
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s&#x201D; (Works, 18:15)&#x2014;may have been
                    meant as a cleverly chosen &#x201C;authentic&#x201D; detail since
                    newspaper reports of the original lecture did tend to give the title in this
                    form (Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin II,&#x201D;
                    179&#x2013;80).</note> With their suspicions aroused by the
                    pamphlets&#x02BC; internal evidence of chicanery, Cook and Wedderburn
                    followed up with inquiries into the pamphlets&#x02BC; production. For
                    example, they made inquiries at the alleged printer of the Leoni pamphlet, but
                    the firm&#x02BC;s records recorded no such job (Ruskin, Works, 1:288,
                    2:101&#x2013;2).</p>
                <p>If in the course of their investigation Cook and Wedderburn connected the recent
                    appearances of the Leoni and Scythian Guest pamphlets in the sale rooms with
                    their timely listings in Wise and Smart, Complete Bibliography of <!--Entry needed here.--> Ruskin,
                    they made no public accusation about the bibliographers&#x02BC;
                    honesty.<note n="4" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    In the case of the Scythian Guest forgery, Cook
                    and Wedderburn noted a sale at the very high price of £65 in 1892, a year
                    earlier than the publication date of 1893 that they cite for Wise and Smart,
                    Complete Bibliography of <!--Entry needed here.--> Ruskin. In fact, appearances were more
                    damning, since the serial part of the Bibliography describing the pamphlet
                    was issued the same year as the sale, and Wise had written to W. G.
                    Collingwood about the pamphlet&#x02BC;s existence even before that (see
                    Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Smart II,&#x201D; 177).</note> Later,
                    however, when the editors questioned the authenticity of the National Gallery
                    pamphlet, their language grew blunter: &#x201C;the reprint &#x2018;of
                    extreme scarcity&#x2019;&#x201D;&#x2014;they wrote in the
                    pamphlet&#x02BC;s bibliographic note for the Library Edition, tartly
                    quoting Wise and Smart, Complete Bibliography of <!--Entry needed here.--> Ruskin, although without
                    attribution<note n="5" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    See Thomas J. Wise and James P. Smart, Complete
                    Bibliography of <!--Entry needed here.--> Ruskin, 1:44n.</note>&#x2014;&#x201C;is what
                    is known in the trade as a &#x2018;fake&#x2019;&#x201D; (Works, 12:396).
                    Finally, in discussing the bibliography of the Queen&#x02BC;s Gardens
                    pamphlet, they all but accused Wise publicly of collusion with forgery, since
                    they pointedly referred to an &#x201C;elaborately described&#x201D;
                    account of the alleged rarity in the Bookman (February 1893) as being
                    signed &#x201C;W.,&#x201D; and they noticed that facsimiles of the
                    title page were given both in that article and in Wise and Smart, Complete
                    Bibliography of <!--Entry needed here.--> Ruskin. Such remarks, at the very least, mocked a
                    well&#x2010;known and respected scholar for incompetence. Nonetheless, as
                    late as the 1920s, Dearden points out, Joan Severn trusted Wise enough to
                    consult with him about the sale of one of Ruskin&#x02BC;s Walter Scott
                    manuscripts (Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin I,&#x201D; 45). After
                    all, as Wise&#x02BC;s biographers point out, he had built up tremendous
                    authority as a bibliographer. (Nowadays, as far as Ruskin bibliography is
                    concerned, it is assumed that Wise duped J. P. Smart, while relying on that
                    scholar to provide the far greater part of the substance of the
                    bibliography.)</p>
                <p>Whatever the Brantwood circle may have believed privately about either Wise or
                    Smart, Wise escaped exposure for three decades after Cook and
                    Wedderburn&#x02BC;s discoveries, and Forman&#x02BC;s involvement was
                    not proved until later still. Perhaps, as Wilfred Partington suggests, Cook and
                    Wedderburn&#x02BC;s condemnations were too deeply buried in the vast bulk
                    of the Library Edition for most readers to have noticed. Moreover, the minutiae
                    of bibliographical notes on a few pamphlets were all the likelier to have been
                    ignored at the turn of the century, when interest in Ruskin was starting to
                    decline among collectors, except by the devoted few (Partington, Forging Ahead,
                    134&#x2013;38; Partington, Thomas J. Wise in the Original Cloth,
                    151&#x2013;54).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                <head type="section">The Lure of Ruskin and the Progress of the Forgery</head>
                <p>Why Ruskin, and why the juvenilia in particular? One obvious answer is that
                    Ruskin and his circle appeared to present an easy target for Wise&#x02BC;s
                    combination of duplicity and sycophancy. The forgers must have known enough
                    about Ruskin&#x02BC;s mental health to gamble that the writer&#x02BC;s
                    memory would pose a weak obstacle to their impostures.<note n="6" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    <!--Entry needed here.--> Need filling in here re. how widely known JR&#x02BC;s
                    breakdown was. Quote place in Rutgers letters where Wise trying to probe how
                    crazy ruskin was.</note> Meanwhile, the unsuspecting Brantwood circle rose
                    to the bait of Wise&#x02BC;s
                    bibliographic &#x201C;research.&#x201D; As W. G. Collingwood remarked
                    in his &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the
                    Poems&#x201D; in Poems (1891), &#x201C;[f]ull account of the published
                    poems [as opposed to the manuscripts surveyed in the
                    &#x201C;Note&#x201D;] has been given by Mr. Thomas J. Wise in his
                    &#x2018;Bibliography of the Writings, &#x0026; c.
                    of John Ruskin,&#x0219; part I, Sept. 1889 (printed for subscribers only);
                    of which I have gladly availed myself&#x201D; (Poems <!--Entry needed here.-->
                    1:268). This acknowledgment (omitted, one wonders if pointedly so, from Cook and
                    Wedderburn&#x02BC;s later reprinting of Collingwood&#x02BC;s
                    &#x201C;Note&#x201D; in the Library Edition, vol. 2) is telling for
                    indicating Wise&#x02BC;s persuasiveness, since Collingwood neglects even to
                    mention J. P. Smart, who, as secretary of the London Ruskin Society, would have
                    been deserving, one would think, of as much regard as a book collector (not yet
                    the famed and authoritarian bibliographer with his &#x201C;Ashley
                    Library&#x201D;).<note n="7" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Joan Severn also tended to credit Wise
                    exclusively with the Bibliography, as appears in a letter quoted in Dearden,
                    &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin III,&#x201D; 323.</note> But Wise had a
                    way of impressing people with their indebtedness to him. (It was at this time,
                    in 1889, that F. J. Furnivall, for example, discharged a debt for
                    Wise&#x02BC;s gifts of &#x201C;privately&#x2010;printed
                    rarities&#x201D; by allowing Wise to reprint the Ruskin/Maurice
                    correspondence [Partington, Thomas J. Wise in the Original Cloth, 111;
                    Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin III,&#x201D; 318].)<note n="8" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    An even more impressionable audience for Wise&#x02BC;s
                    stories, it appears, was George Allen. In their bibliographic note
                    questioning the authenticity of the Leoni pamphlet, Cook and Wedderburn
                    reported, in fairness against their own accusations, that &#x201C;Mr.
                    George Allen has some recollection of the pamphlet being at Denmark Hill,
                    and himself presented a copy to Mr. T. J. Wise, whose Bibliography
                    (1889&#x2013;93) recording the 1868 edition was also sent to Brantwood,
                    though it does not appear that Ruskin was at that time able to give it his
                    personal attention&#x201D; (Works, 1:288). At what point Allen
                    developed (or was fed) the false memory of the pamphlet at Denmark Hill does
                    not appear; however, the forgers have to gotten the pamphlet into
                    Allen&#x02BC;s hands by 1893, in order for him to have
                    &#x201C;presented&#x201D; it in turn to Wise&#x2014;with
                    &#x201C;friendly regards,&#x201D; as is legible in the photograph
                    of the pamphlet in the October 1893 final part&#x2010;issue of the
                    Smart and Wise Bibliography (<!--Entry needed here.-->). Allen was induced to believe likewise
                    that he formerly possessed a copy of the Scythian Guest pamphlet (Dearden,
                    &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin II,&#x201D; 171, 177).</note> With this
                    debt of scholarship established, Wise could risk the audacity of presenting
                    Collingwood&#x2014;the most knowledgeable living authority on
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s poetry&#x2014;with the Scythian Guest forgery in 1892,
                    the year after the publication of Poems (1891) (see &#x201C;Scythian
                    Guest&#x201D;: Composition and Publication).</p>
                <p>Equally interesting for the study of juvenilia and youthful writing are the
                    cultural factors that must have played a part in Wise&#x02BC;s forgery. In
                    Partington&#x02BC;s exposé, his liveliness of tone relies on an assumption
                    that the legitimate can be sharply distinguished from the illegitimate, the
                    learned bibliographer and honest bookseller from the charlatan and cheat
                    (distinctions that often involve Partington&#x02BC;s writing in a great
                    deal of special pleading). The biographer accordingly treated Forman as a member
                    of the &#x201C;conclave of ardent bookmen&#x201D; whom Wise merely
                    imitated and exploited&#x2014;Forman&#x02BC;s mind being set on higher
                    things, Partington assumes, whereas Wise grubbed for &#x201C;hard
                    cash&#x201D; (Forging Ahead, 177&#x2013;78; Thomas J. Wise in the
                    Original Cloth, 196).<note n="9" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    To some degree, these characterization remain in
                    force today, Barker and Collins portraying Wise as
                    the &#x201C;five&#x2010;pound note&#x201D; sort of forger with
                    a &#x201C;genius for commerce&#x201D; who &#x201C;brutally
                    bullied the agents who trusted him,&#x201D; while they class Forman
                    among &#x201C;the artists who want to deceive themselves as much as or
                    more than the rest of the world&#x201D; (Barker and Collins, A Sequel,
                    181&#x2013;82). Nonetheless, Barker and Collins considerably refine the
                    portraits of the forgers, and they judge one to have been as damaging as the
                    other in their differing ways.</note> John Carter pronounced
                    Partington&#x02BC;s book &#x201C;vulgarly written,&#x201D; but he
                    praised its research and appears to have been no more alert than Partington to
                    the ambiguities of context that gave rise to the forgers
                    (Carter, &#x201C;Wise in Perspective,&#x201D; 8n.). In contrast, Barker
                    and Collins&#x02BC;s keynote is that &#x201C;forgery thrives on
                    ambiguity&#x201D; (Barker and Collins, A Sequel, 127). This observation
                    deserves exploration here specifically with respect to why the forgers were
                    frequently drawn to forging juvenilia, Ruskin&#x02BC;s in particular.</p>
                <p>Whatever the compound of duplicitous aims with reverence of literary celebrity in
                    Wise and Forman&#x02BC;s individual makeups, Nonetheless, if
                    the forgers relied on Ruskin&#x02BC;s frail memory to accept the invented
                    pamphlets as plausible, an opposite approach was taken (with what deliberation
                    can never be known) in the vehicle of these impostures, Wise and
                    Smart&#x02BC;s Bibliography of Ruskin (initially published in eighteen
                    parts [September 1889&#x2013;May 1893], plus an additional part of
                    illustrations [October 1893]). Here, oversight and contributions by learned
                    Ruskinians were sought and acknowledged, brazenly lending credibility to the
                    forgeries planted among the legitimate (and highly accurate) listings.</p>
                <p>The Wise and Smart Bibliography was apparently the first publication in which the
                    forgers used the technique of preparing the way for a forgery by announcing it
                    in print: part 2 (November 1889) described the bogus National Gallery pamphlet
                    as &#x201C;probably printed only for private distribution&#x201D; since
                    Smith, Elder &#x0026; Co. showed no record of copies for sale (vol. 1 [1893],
                    p. 44); part 3 (<!--Entry needed here.--> date) recorded the Catalogue of the Turner Sketches, of
                    which Wise and Forman produced a binary forgery<note n="10" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    The term binary edition was used by Carter and Pollard to designate pamphlets forged from a
                    genuine printed original, as opposed to creative forgeries that (as in the
                    cases of the &#x201C;1852&#x201D; National Gallery pamphlet and the
                    &#x201C;1849&#x201D; Scythian Guest <!--Correction needed here?-->) invented a formerly
                    nonexistent but plausible publication (Barker and Collins, A Sequel, 70).
                    The Bibliography, of course, contains no direct indication of the binary
                    forgery of the Catalogue of the Turner Sketches, although a note presumably
                    authored by Wise (vol. 1 [1893], p. 72) comments on the extreme scarcity of
                    pamphlet, paving the way for the profitability of a binary forgery (see
                    Todd, &#x201C;Handlist of Wise,&#x201D; 95).</note> (ibid., p.
                    72); part 5 (May 1890) contained descriptions of three more forgeries, The
                    Future of England (ibid., pp. 138&#x2013;39), Leoni (ibid., pp. 147&#x2013;48),<note n="11" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    As Dearden (&#x201C;Wise and Ruskin I,&#x201D; 48; &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin II,&#x201D; 170) has
                    shown, however, one of two known prospectuses for the bibliography,
                    presumably ca. 1889, described the &#x201C;1868&#x201D; Leoni,
                    indicating that this forgery may have been physically in production at least
                    a year prior to its formal announcement in part 5 of the
                    Bibliography.</note> and Samuel Prout (ibid., p. 154); and part 7 (December
                    1890), The Nature and Authority of Miracle (ibid., p. 211) (Barker and Collins,
                    A Sequel, 135, 138; Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin II,&#x201D; 174).
                    The illustrations supplied in part 19 of the Bibliography (October 1893) showed
                    photographs of six forgeries, including Leoni and Scythian Guest. <!--Correction needed here?--></p>
                <p>The first publication to exploit a scholarly context to lend legitimacy to
                    forgery, the Bibliography of Ruskin was also the first of Wise&#x02BC;s
                    privately printed scholarly bibliographies. It has always been assumed that
                    Smart, who as secretary of the Ruskin Society of London is likelier to have
                    possessed the requisite knowledge, performed the lion&#x02BC;s share of
                    compiling and writing the bibliography, with Wise serving merely as publisher
                    while also conveniently filling gaps in Smart&#x02BC;s scholarship with
                    alleged finds of fugitive Ruskin pamphlets from his own collection. In the
                    unsigned May 1893 preface to the completed bibliography, it is presumably
                    Wise&#x02BC;s hand that inserted falsehoods in Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    bibliographic history, asserting that the lectures of the 1860s were
                    &#x201C;sometimes printed&#x201D; separately prior to revision and
                    publication in their now familiar form, a claim supported by citation of the
                    Queen&#x02BC;s [sic] Gardens pamphlet, unknown &#x201C;until February
                    of the present year&#x201D; (p. xxii).<note n="12" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Wise&#x02BC;s invention of a pedigree for this pamphlet is an interesting example of his
                    covering his tracks by complicating the (false) record: the bibliographic
                    description of Sesame and Lilies in part ? of the Bibliography, issued
                    December 1892, included no record of the forged Queen&#x02BC;s Gardens
                    pamphlet; instead, in the preface to the Bibliography, issued in part 18
                    along with the other preliminaries in May 1893, Wise declared that,
                    &#x201C;so little known was the genesis even of Sesame and
                    Lilies&#x2014;the most widely popular of all Mr. Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    books&#x2014;that not until February of the present year [when Wise
                    himself described it in the Bookman] did it become generally known that The
                    Queen&#x02BC;s Gardens had been printed apart in pamphlet
                    form&#x201D; (vol. 1 [1893], p. xxii).</note></p>
                <p>Was it mockery, or even spite? (Collingwood had kept Wise at a distance from
                    Brantwood.) Certainly, there was caution shown in the timing. Dearden
                    (&#x201C;Wise and Ruskin II,&#x201D; 177) cites a letter in which
                    Collingwood thanks Wise for the collation of the Scythian Guest <!--Correction needed here?--> pamphlet with
                    earlier appearances <!--Correction needed here?--> of the poem. This was on 13 September 1892, three months
                    prior to the published description in the Bibliography, but still too late for
                    the Poems (1891), and noticeably without permitting Collingwood examination of
                    the physical pamphlet itself <!--Correction needed here?--></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                <head type="section">Juvenilia in a Culture of Forgery</head>
                <p>Partington represents Wise as entering the fin de siècle London literary scene as
                    the demonic other among legitimate bibliophiles and members of literary
                    societies. According to Parkington, if to idealists like James Dykes Campbell
                    &#x201C;literature was more than Mammon,&#x201D;
                    Wise &#x201C;never lost the true shopman&#x02BC;s&#x201D; taint;
                    if Stopford Brooke rated &#x201C;love of poetry&#x201D;
                    above &#x201C;bibliographical curiosities,&#x201D; &#x201C;the
                    truth&#x201D; about Wise was &#x201C;that he was generally more
                    captivated by the story behind the story than by the work itself&#x201D;
                    (Forging Ahead, 14, 112, 49, 20).</p>
                <p> In contrast to this determination to demonize Wise (and save Forman for the
                    elect), Barker and Collins point out that &#x201C;forgery thrives on
                    ambiguity.&#x201D; The forgers characteristically covered their trail by
                    confusion, and even the physical forged object gained more credibility by aiming
                    at resemblance than at exact imitation. Bibliographic culture in
                    late&#x2010;century London permitted these ambiguities because good
                    printing was cheap, copyright loose, and the market ripe for
                    small&#x2010;run collectors&#x02BC; publications. This publishing
                    culture provided &#x201C;the source and base&#x201D; of the
                    forgers&#x02BC; work &#x201C;as well as its inspiration&#x201D;
                    (A Sequel, 127, 128):</p>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                        <item>&#x2014; juvenilia is itself ambiguous and an imitation of others;</item>
                        <item>&#x2014; it&#x02BC;s by nature rare;</item>
                        <item>&#x2014; it&#x02BC;s of paradoxical value, scorned yet sought.</item>
                    </list>
                <p>A part of that inspiration was the lure of forging famous authors&#x02BC;
                    juvenilia. As an explanation of how Wise started on his career of forgery,
                    Partington points to the young collector&#x02BC;s excitement over the
                    rarity of Browning&#x02BC;s early Pauline <!--Correction needed here?--> and his subsequent facsimile of
                    the poem, a &#x201C;page&#x2010;for&#x2010;page&#x201D; type imitation,
                    for the Browning Society. This along with his facsimiles of first editions for
                    the Shelley Society &#x201C;started Wise on his remarkable series of
                    typographical forgeries&#x201D;; Partington is confident
                    that &#x201C;the idea [for the future forgeries and piracies] was in
                    Wise&#x02BC;s mind&#x201D; (Forging Ahead, 30).</p>
                <p>Of course, the most obvious temptation, whether of legitimate collecting or
                    forging, is the genuine scarcity of juvenile publications. Browning himself was
                    unaware of the existence of Elizabeth Barrett&#x02BC;s Battle of Marathon <!--Correction needed here?-->
                    (<!--Entry needed here.-->), until Wise escorted the elderly poet to a bookseller to examine a copy that
                    had recently surfaced. Browning remained skeptical, until seeing the autograph
                    inscription, which he authenticated as Barrett&#x02BC;s hand. Such
                    scarceness was sufficient temptation to forgery, which Wise and Forman proceeded
                    to carry out with Matthew Arnold&#x02BC;s Alaric at Rome <!--Correction needed here?-->, Algernon
                    Swinburne&#x02BC;s <!--Entry needed here.-->.</p>
                <p>The paradox of these values is their accompaniment by expressions of contempt for
                    the artifacts themselves. (Browning&#x02BC;s distaste;
                    Partington&#x02BC;s mockery of Swinburne as if the poet were a child.)</p>
                <p>Similarly, when Wise and Smart sent Ruskin the prospectus for their Bibliography
                    of Ruskin, Joan Severn communicated Ruskin&#x02BC;s thanks to Smart while
                    also passing along his scorn for the bibliographers taking &#x201C;so much
                    trouble over a lot of worthless stuff!&#x201D;<note n="13" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Joan Severn to J. P. Smart, 19 June 1889, in Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin
                    I,&#x201D; 48.</note> What Ruskin deemed worthless must have been the
                    subject of the specimen sheets, which, as Dearden has shown, exhibited (along
                    with &#x201C;Ruskiniana&#x201D;) entries on the Poems (1850), the
                    collection of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early poems edited by his father and his
                    first editor, W. H. Harrison. A second possible prospectus, of which a portion
                    survives,<note n="14" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    <!--Entry needed here--> Need accession no. for both prospectuses.</note>
                    unearthed by Dearden, presented a sample based on Poems and on
                    the &#x201C;1868&#x201D; Leoni (Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin
                    I,&#x201D; 48; &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin II,&#x201D; 170). If the
                    now fragmentary prospectus was issued, thrusting the Leoni forgery under the
                    noses of the experts at Brantwood, it was a bold move. The genuineness of the
                    Leoni pamphlet aside, the focus on such a boyhood production along with the
                    early poems was also controversial, since Ruskin had so recently ridiculed these
                    works in Praeterita.</p>
                <p>Doesn&#x02BC;t it gesture at the erotic while seeming its opposite?</p>
                <p>Wise&#x02BC;s biographer, Wilfred Partington&#x2014;who, as editor of
                    the Bookman between the wars, had insufficient distance from this culture to see
                    its implication in Wise and Forman&#x02BC;s
                    activities&#x2014;suppresses ambiguity by. Partington most scornfully
                    banishes Wise from the true believers by branding him a pornographer who,
                    refusing to concede to appeals to decency, hinted publicly at
                    Swinburne&#x02BC;s &#x201C;naughty&#x201D; manuscripts (Forging
                    Ahead, 79). But <!--Entry needed here.-->.</p>
                <p>The forgers had a policy of aiming deceptions especially at the American market
                    since distance discouraged collectors from doubting authenticity or from
                    haggling over the price of items that had never before been offered for sale;
                    moreover, the American market tended to more rapid turnover, which benefited the
                    forgers (Barker and Collins, A Sequel, 122, 147, 148). That the collecting of
                    juvenilia tended also to be concentrated there, as argued in <!--Entry needed here.-->, is probably a
                    coincidence <!--Entry needed here.-->.</p>
                <p>Barker and Collins point out that private sales offered the safest way to trickle
                    forgeries into the market, but public sales, while risking exposure, presented
                    the most convenient way to establish a price (A Sequel, 147&#x2013;48). In
                    1897, when the forgers grew bolder in allowing their work into the showroom,
                    Ruskin juvenilia made its first appearance among other Ruskin pamphlets, and it
                    is interesting to note that Leoni fetched three times or more the price of
                    alleged mature pamphlets (£6. 15s compared to between £1. 18s and £2. 12s</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                <head  type="section">Leoni</head>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>£6. 15s (12 May 1897)</item>
                        <item>$16.00 (31 Mar 1898)</item>
                        <item>£2. 6s (20 Jul 1898)</item>
                        <item>£6. 15s (27 Feb 1899)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><!-- added 4/12 -->A vivid example of the excitement that could form around the spurious pamphlets is related in the 1898 <hi rend="italic">Romance of Book Collecting</hi> 
                        by J. H. Slater, who tells a story about a society formed to ferret out rare and curious volumes. One of its members 
                        triumphantly reported finding at auction a copy of the Manchester pamphlet, <hi rend="italic">The Queens' Gardens</hi>, which, Slater comments, "every collector of Mr. Ruskin's works knows" to exist in 
                        "only three copies"; and if a collector "is very well informed indeed he will know who has them, and where they got them from, and at what price." The prize turned out to be an ordinary edition 
                        of <hi rend="italic">Sesame and Lilies</hi>, and the moral of the tale for Slater was "how easy it was to tumble into error"&#x2014;and even persist in the error, as did this auction hunter 
                        who remained convinced of his find. Similarly, Slater relates, "on another occasion a member bought 'Friendship's Offering,' for 1840, merely because it contains 'The Scythian Guest'"; and this member, 
                        "too, could not be persuaded that the error was his rather than that of the bookseller who sold it him." Slater did not need even to apprise his reader of the rarity of the 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scythian Guest</hi> pamphlet, and he evinces no irony about the value of the pamphlets themselves 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#SLATERROMANCE">Slater, <hi rend="italic">Romance of Book&#x2010;Collecting</hi></ref>, 56&#x2013;57).
                        excitedly</p>
                    <p>Roberts comments that "the reproduction of first editions not long since became a trade, and a somewhat prolific source of trouble to the novice in book-collecting; 
                        whilst facimiled leaves have the questionable merit of too closely resembling the missing ones, and make all the difference in the value of the book" 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RAREBOOKS">Roberts, <hi rend="italic">Rare Books and Their Prices</hi></ref>, 7).</p>
                    
                <p>See Note on Bibliography; Note on Collecting; Note on Editing the Juvenilia; Note
                    on Interest in Juvenilia; Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin I,&#x201D; &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin
                    II,&#x201D; and &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin III.&#x201D;</p>
                    <p>HEREthat the interests
                        of the disinterested bibliographer had nefariously colluded with the interests
                        of the dealer and in the case of <persName corresp="#TJW">T. J. Wise</persName>
                        and his forgeries. In the narrative laid out in <ref type="bibliography"
                            target="bibliography.html#ENQUIRY">Carter and Pollard, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Enquiry</hi></ref> (pp. 99&#x2013;109), <date notBefore="1837-06-20"
                                    notAfter="1901-01-22">Victorian</date> sentimentality was vulnerable not
                        only to being duped&#x2014;a susceptibility from which the modern analytical
                        bibliographer was shielded by his rigorous scientific methods of paper analysis
                        and comparison of type sets&#x2014;but also to becoming as greedy as the forger
                        who preyed on the collector. It was the &#x201C;collecting public,&#x201D; who,
                        according to <persName corresp="#JC">Carter</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#HGP">Pollard</persName> declared, had shown itself &#x201C;eager,
                        credulous and greedy&#x201D; (Carter and Pollard, Enquiry, 107). There is also a
                        suggestion in this account that the collecting public had been feminized by its
                        greed and vulnerability&#x2014;a suggestion that would have been felt as a
                        needling accusation against a hobby that, in the <date notBefore="1890"
                            notAfter="1899">1890s</date>, was a predominantly male pursuit, prone even
                        to misogyny.<note n="3" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">In the <date notBefore="1890"
                            notAfter="1899">1890s</date>, women were not taken seriously as book
                            collectors, and in fact were treated as enemies of bibliophiles. <persName
                                corresp="#WR">William Roberts</persName> , for example, in a chapter on
                            <!--Should the Book Hunter ref tag be used here?  A specific chapter of the book is being cited and not the whole book.-->&#x201C;Women
                            as Book&#x2010;Collectors,&#x201D; reviews a long line of female collectors,
                            but nonetheless concludes &#x201C;that the femme bibliophile is an all but
                            unknown quantity. The New Woman may develop into a genuine
                            book&#x2010;lover; it is certain that the old one will not. The <placeName
                                corresp="#CHINA">Chinese</placeName> article of belief that women have
                            no souls has, after all, something in its favour&#x201D; (Roberts,
                            Book&#x2010;Hunter in London, 273). <persName corresp="#AL">Andrew
                                Lang</persName> roundly declared &#x201C;all women . . . the inveterate
                            foes . . . of books worthy of the name&#x201D; (<ref type="bibliography"
                                target="bibliography.html#THELIBRARY">Lang, <hi rend="italic">The
                                    Library</hi></ref>, 61).</note></p>
                    <p>As the <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> affair grew into legend, aloofness from the filthy lucre of rare book market became a standard by which 
                        &#x201C;bibliographers&#x201D; distinguished themselves from &#x201C;collectors&#x201D;; and disinterestedness became a refrain in ostracizing <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> himself. 
                        Justly or not, <persName corresp="#JC">Carter</persName> declared <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> &#x201C;not so much a bibliographer as a collector and dealer&#x201D;
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#BOOKCOLLECTORS">Carter, <hi rend="italic">Books and Book&#x2010;Collectors</hi></ref>, 163), a view that Sadleir shared, 
                        pronouncing <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> to have been &#x201C;not really a bibliographer at all&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#DEVELOPMENTBIBLIOGRAPHICALSTUDY">Sadleir, &#x201C;Development of Bibliographical Study&#x201D;</ref>, 151). 
                        The characterization was not without justification, as, <persName corresp="#MSS">Sadleir</persName> argued, <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> operated
                        according to &#x201C;rule of thumb&#x201D; in describing a perfect copy, an approach that was fallible (based, in brief, on what <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> happened to
                        possess). Less provably, <persName corresp="#MSS">Sadleir</persName> declared that <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> lacked &#x201C;curiosity&#x201D; about the &#x201C;principal quality which distinguishes&#x201D; the true
                        bibliographer from the tradesman&#x2014;an interest in publishing history 
                        (Sadleir, &#x201C;Development of Bibliographical Study,&#x201D; 151, 152, 154, and see 154&#x2013;57). 
                        Quickly, it became enough to brand <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> as &#x201C;both a collector and a
                        dealer,&#x201D; as compared with <persName corresp="#HBF">H. Buxton Forman</persName> (not yet exposed as
                        <persName corresp="#HBF">Wise&#x02BC;s henchman</persName>), who was pronounced &#x201C;both a scholar and
                        collector&#x201D; (see Carter, Taste and Technique in Book&#x2010;Collecting, 24).
                        And on booksellers&#x02BC; behalf, a similar distinction between vulgarity and professionalism was advanced by <persName corresp="#WP">Wilfred 
                            Partington</persName> in his biography of <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName>, who insisted that
                        antiquarian book dealers (like <persName corresp="#WP"> 
                            Partington</persName> himself) operate disinterestedly as
                        compared with mere money&#x2010;grubbers like <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#FORGINGAHEAD">Partington, <hi rend="italic">Forging Ahead</hi></ref>, ???; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#ORIGINALCLOTH">Partington, <hi rend="italic">Thomas J. Wise in the Original Cloth</hi></ref>, ???).<!--p. nos. needed--></p>
                    <p>As <persName corresp="#NB">Nicolas Barker</persName> and <persName corresp="#JCC">John Collins</persName> have remarked, however, what allowed forgers to operate successfully in the first place was the milieu of
                        late&#x2010;century collecting and publishing, which traded in ambiguity. Legitimate editors and publishers produced facsimiles already only a step
                        away from &#x201C;fakes&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#SEQUELTOENQUIRY">Barker and Collins, <hi rend="italic">Sequel to &#x201C;Enquiry&#x201D; by Carter and Pollard</hi></ref>, ???).<!-- p nos. needed --> 
                        In <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> edition of <hi rend="italic">The Earlier Poems of <persName corresp="#EBB">Elizabeth Barrett Browning</persName></hi> (<date when="1878">1878</date>), 
                        close replication of <persName corresp="#EBB">Barrett&#x02BC;s</persName> original texts was evidently a desired feature, but clearly not with an intention to deceive. The volume could not be mistaken for forgery, 
                        since <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> title and preface explain the venture; and the miscellaneous poems, drawn from <persName corresp="#EBB">Barrett&#x02BC;s</persName> <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Bound</hi> volume, 
                        are set consistently with the typography of the main text chosen for reproduction, 
                        <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Mind</hi>, rather than in imitation of the poems&#x02BC; original state. But in many other respects, <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> and  
                        the printer<note n="4" place="botwin" resp="#DCH"><persName corresp="#BR">Bartholomew Robson</persName> of <placeName corresp="#CRANBOURNST">Cranbourn&#x2010;street</placeName>, identified as a
                            bookseller in <!-- Unsure of what this is for tagging purposes. Is it a place name?-->Paden, &#x201C; <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#TENNYSONSHEPHERDWISE">Tennyson&#x02BC;s The Lover&#x02BC;s Tale</ref>, <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName>, and <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName>&#x201D; 122,
                            one who advertised <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> reprint of <hi rend="italic"><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#TENNYSONSHEPHERDWISE">Tennyson&#x02BC;s Lover&#x02BC;s Tale</ref></hi>.</note> took considerable trouble to
                        replicate <persName corresp="#EBB">Barrett&#x02BC;s</persName>  original. Even the miscellaneous poems, while not set in their original type, maintain the same lines per page as in the original 
                        <hi rend="italic">Prometheus</hi> volume. Such subtle forms of replication would multiply in the next decades. As <persName corresp="#NB">Barker</persName> and <persName corresp="#JCC">Collins</persName> remark, while <persName corresp="#JC">Carter</persName> and <persName corresp="#HGP">Pollard&#x02BC;s</persName> 
                        <hi rend="italic"><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#ENQUIRY">Enquiry</ref></hi> &#x201C;dealt with one class [of forgery] only: books with false dates and imprints,&#x201D; there were also among <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> and <persName corresp="#HBF">Forman&#x02BC;s</persName> productions 
                        &#x201C;books with correct dates but false imprints; 
                        piracies (books, that is, printed where and when they are stated to be, but without the author&#x02BC;s approval); books without date and imprint, but intended to be taken, 
                        by association with other books, as of earlier or different issue; and, most extraordinary of all, books which are physically divided, part genuine and part false.&#x201D; 
                        <persName corresp="#NB">Barker</persName> and <persName corresp="#JCC">Collins&#x02BC;s</persName> research shows that &#x201C;none of these different forms can be neglected or wholly separated from the others,&#x201D; for &#x201C;forgery thrives on ambiguity&#x201D;; 
                        and if <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> was a master at exploiting this murkiness, for <persName corresp="#HBF">Forman</persName> &#x201C;ambiguity for its own sake&#x201D; was &#x201C;an obsession&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#SEQUELTOENQUIRY">Barker and Collins, <hi rend="italic">Sequel to &#x201C;Enquiry&#x201D; by Carter and Pollard</hi></ref>, 129, 130).</p>
                    <p>For <persName corresp="#JC">Carter</persName> and <persName corresp="#HGP">Pollard</persName>, their focus on the starkest form of forgery would have seemed to justify their equal starkness in forming a narrative of how the forgery thrived&#x2014;by 
                        its exploitation of collectors&#x02BC; sentiment for their favorite authors. However, the most brazenly false of <persName corresp="#HBF">Forman&#x02BC;s</persName> and <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise&#x02BC;s</persName> forgeries cannot be easily 
                        disengaged from an environment of  
                        Just so, what <persName corresp="#JC">Carter</persName> stigmatized as the sentiment
                        of the collector cannot be so readily distinguished from the editorial and bibliographical stance that, in <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> formulation, 
                        &#x201C;owned&#x201D; a modern author by virtue of &#x201C;sympathy.&#x201D;</p></p>
                </div>
             </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>