<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">H. Buxton Forman</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-26">October 26, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">H. Buxton Forman (1842&#x2013;1917)</head>
                <p>Forman is now recognized as the equally active, if more shadowy, partner of the
                    most notorious of late nineteenth&#x2010;century forgers, Thomas J. Wise. Their
                    activities are largely discussed in the main note on forgery and, in greater
                    detail, in the publication histories for <hi rend="italic">Leoni</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Scythian Guest</hi>. In the present note, some biographical
                    details relevant to Ruskin scholarship is discussed; for more extensive
                    biography, readers should consult Collins, <hi rend="italic">Two
                    Forgers</hi>.</p>
                <p>Partington&#x02BC;s popular exposé, like Carter and Pollard&#x02BC;s
                    scientific one, was focused on Wise, but the forgeries gradually came to be
                    understood as the products of a partnership between Wise and Harry Buxton
                    Forman. Partington was reluctant to accuse Forman in the 1939 biography of Wise, 
                    <hi rend="italic">Forging Ahead</hi> (e.g., 74&#x2013;76, 158); and he
                    wrote even more defensively on Forman&#x02BC;s behalf in the 1946 revised
                    version of the biography, <hi rend="italic">Thomas J. Wise in the Original
                        Cloth</hi> (84&#x2013;92), by which time various conspiracy theories
                    were afloat. More recently, Nicolas Barker and John Collins have extended the
                    arguments of Carter and Pollard and established both Forman&#x02BC;s
                    complicity and a more extensive series of crimes than formerly suspected.
                    Respecting Forman&#x02BC;s involvement, Barker and
                    Collins &#x201C;conclude . . . that the partnership was an equal one. One
                    partner might originate, manufacture and distribute one title more than another,
                    even to all appearances exclusively; but the weight of the evidence suggests
                    that the vast majority of the pamphlets were jointly manufactured and may be
                    presumed to have been sold for joint profit&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">A
                        Sequel</hi>, 181). Nonetheless, a useful inquiry remains, which may require
                    separating the forgers, respecting their motives and methods in faking Ruskin
                    publications.</p>
                <p>Another question concerns the extent and nature of the crime. In terms of simple
                    numbers of forgeries, whereas Carter and Pollard were able definitively to
                    condemn thirty of the nineteenth&#x2010;century pamphlets they examined, Barker
                    and Collins have raised the tally to nearly a hundred. This more than tripled
                    effort that the forgers are now known to have devoted to manufacture and
                    dissemination of the fakes bears on the question of motive, which can now be
                    understood more clearly in terms of crude gain (see Barker and Collins, <hi
                        rend="italic">A Sequel</hi>, 122). Interestingly, however, Barker and
                    Collins also pursue the nature of the crime itself into &#x201C;a range of
                    activities that also included piracy and the adaptation of legitimate
                    publications in a number of ways, whose object was to deceive the collector of
                    modern writers (and also to cheat the author)&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">A
                        Sequel</hi>, 121). This complexity affects how the crime is perceived.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>