<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Work</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="subtype">
                <head type="title">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1931</head>
                <p>On 18 May 1931, Sotheby &#x0026; Co. held a second sale of Ruskin's literary remains, 
                    ten months following on the first, the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1930</ref>. 
                    As described in the title of the catalogue, the sale represented 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SOTHEBYCAT1931"><hi rend="italic">The Final Portion of the Manuscripts &#x0026; Library of John Ruskin, 
                        Removed from His Residence, Brantwood, Coniston, Which Is about To Be Offered for Sale, and the Property of the Late Joseph Arthur Palliser Severn, Esq., 
                        Removed from 9, Warwick Square, S.W.; and . . . a Small Library, Principally of Modern Authors and of Finely Printed and Illustrated Books, the Property of Mrs. Mander, 
                    Blacketts, Chorley Wood, Herts.</hi></ref>. 
                    The 1930 sale had been the more consequential event, and neither of the Sotheby's sales was the sole occasion when Ruskin manuscripts were sold or given away 
                    (see <ref type="essay" target="provenance_essay.php">Essay on Provenance</ref>), but the 1931 sale was nonetheless significant for the continuing dispersal of early manuscripts.</p>
                <p>In the Ruskin manuscript portion of the sale, lot 27 included 7 items, of which 5 were early manuscripts 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SOTHEBYCAT1931">Sotheby &#x0026; Co., <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the Final Portion of the Manuscripts &#x0026; Library of John Ruskin</hi></ref>, 6). 
                    The catalogue, unlike that for the 1930 sale, does not identify these manuscripts using the roman-numeral designations that Collingwood established in 
                    &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&#x201D; for the <hi ref="italic">Poems</hi> (1891). That source may have supplied summary descriptions of the contents of two manuscripts 
                    (MS VI, MS X), but the other three early manuscripts in this lot are not found in the &#x201C;Preliminary Note,&#x201D; since they probably did not exist as a bound compilation at that time.</p>
                <p>In fact, if in the 1930 sale the lots containing early manuscripts were presented as if stamped with the scholarly imprimatur of Collingwood's <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)&#x2014;and 
                    with no reference to the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref> (see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1930</ref>)&#x2014;the lots 
                    in the 1931 sale seem associated more with Cook and Wedderburn's activities. 
                    Instead of the elegant blue-morocco bindings and slipcases, which had been constructed for most of the early manuscripts gathered for the 1930 sale, 
                    and at least some of which bindings had probably been made when Collingwood was editing <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891), 
                    most of the manuscripts in the 1931 sale were bound in "cloth"&#x2014;that is, the red buckram used when the editors were working through the editing of the Library Edition 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_brantwood_note.php">Provenance of Early Manuscripts at Brantwood</ref>).</p>
                <p>Of the seven items in lot 27, the following five pertain to <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>:
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">Item I, <ref type="ms" target="msvi.php">MS VI</ref>, limp roan, 12.75 &#x00D7; 4.5 in. The catalogue describes the contents as: 
                            "First drafts of the Iteriad and other Poems. Essay on the Comparative Advantages of Music and Painting (1838); Macbeth (prose)." This description of the contents could have been summarized 
                            from Collingwood, &#x201C;Preliminary Note,&#x201D; or from the revised version of the &#x201C;Preliminary Note,&#x201D; in the Library Edition.</item>
                        <item n="2">Item II, <ref type="apparatus" target="msia_apparatus.php">MS IA</ref></item>
                        <item n="3">Lot 112, "Early Poems and Juvenilia," consisting of six blue-morocco slipcases containing early manuscripts, as follows.</item>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <item>A slipcase, <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="harry_lucy_poems_c_note.php">HARRY &#x0026; LUCY &#x007C; POEMS &#x007C; &#x0026;c</ref>, 
                                    containing <ref type="apparatus" target="msi_apparatus.php">MS I</ref>, 
                                    <ref type="apparatus" target="msii_apparatus.php">MS II</ref>, 
                                    <ref type="apparatus" target="msiii_apparatus.php">MS III</ref>, 
                                    <ref type="apparatus" target="msiiia_apparatus.php">MS IIIA</ref>, and 
                                    <ref type="apparatus" target="msiv_apparatus.php">MS IV</ref>.</item>
                                <item>A slipcase, <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="juvenilia_note.php">RUSKIN &#x007C; MS. &#x007C; JUVENILIA</ref>, 
                                    containing <ref type="apparatus" target="msja_apparatus.php">MS Juvenilia A</ref>, 
                                    <ref type="apparatus" target="msjb_apparatus.php">MS Juvenilia B</ref>, 
                                    <ref type="apparatus" target="msjc_apparatus.php">MS Juvenilia C</ref>.</item>
                                <item>A slipcase, RUSKIN &#x007C; MS. &#x007C; POEMS &#x007C; 1829&#x2013;32 &#x007C; 1902, containing <ref type="apparatus" target="msv_apparatus.php">MS V</ref>.</item>
                                <item>A slipcase, RUSKIN &#x007C; MS. &#x007C; ITERIAD &#x007C; &#x0026;c &#x007C; 1902, containing <ref type="apparatus" target="msvii_apparatus.php">MS VII</ref>.</item>
                                <item>A slipcase, RUSKIN &#x007C; MS. &#x007C; POEMS &#x007C; ETC. &#x007C; 1831&#x2013;38, containing <ref type="apparatus" target="msviii_apparatus.php">MS VIII</ref>.</item>
                                <item>A slipcase, RUSKIN &#x007C; MS. &#x007C; POEMS &#x007C; 1833, containing <ref type="apparatus" target="msix_apparatus.php">MS IX</ref>.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="4">Lot 113, "The Poetry of Architecture and Modern Painters."</item>
                        <item n="5">Lot 114, "The King of the Golden River."<!-- describe slipcase --></item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Sotheby’s 1931.—Much clearer documentation traces juvenilia included in lot 27 of the second Sotheby’s sale, 18 May 1931. Item I of lot 27 is MS VI; item II is MS IA; item III is MS X; item IV is MS XB; and item V is MS IVD (Sotheby Cat. 1931, 6). (A significant item formerly in MS X, the 1830 diary, had been separated prior to the sale. See TLC, 4; RBB, 49; and Sharp below.) In his memoirs, Goodspeed mentions purchasing the items in this lot (YB 267–68), and he later issued an undated catalog of Goodspeed’s Book Shop listing the entirety of lot 27 as “manuscripts 1825–1840” (Goodspeed, Cat., items 79–83, pp. 18–22). Goodspeed was a major bidder at the 18 May sale, buying not just “one or two more manuscripts” (RBB, 138) but at the very least lots 27–29 and 31, with each of these lots comprising numerous and varied manuscripts.
                    Three of the early manuscripts that came into Goodspeed’s possession (MSS IVD, VI, XB) were sold in 1939 to the Princeton University Library, along with several other items that he had acquired at the 1931 sale—a quite ambitious purchase by the library.	The final item in Thorp’s description consists of six notebooks, including two containing studies for The Seven Lamps of Architecture. I have not been able to examine these, and they are difficult to trace in the published accounts. I find no such specific listing in Goodspeed, Cat., unless the six were included in item 40, sixteen “Sketch Books” (p. 11); however, only eight of the sixteen were known to have remained to Goodspeed in 1933, when the dealer offered them along with all his Ruskin drawings to Whitehouse, and Whitehouse is believed to have acquired this lot in 1936 (RBB 138–39). I am also unable to find a listing specifically matching the Princeton notebooks in the Sotheby’s catalogs. They might have formed part of lot 122, “Miscellaneous Note Books,” from the 1930 sale, of which Hogan lists only nine as coming to Yale through Goodspeed (pp. 67–68; and see n. 31, above). The notebooks might also have derived from the 20 May 1931 Sotheby’s sale of Ruskin drawings, at which Goodspeed was represented by Ralph Brown (RBB, 138; and see, e.g., Sotheby & Co., Catalogue of the Collection of Pictures and Drawings, formerly the property of the late Professor John Ruskin . . . , 20 May 1931, item 9). Prior to the Princeton purchase, Goodspeed had offered all his Ruskin drawings to Whitehouse, who finally agreed to a purchase in 1936 (RBB, 136–39). Although the correspondence suggests that Goodspeed sent all the drawings in his possession for Whitehouse’s approval and that Whitehouse retained the entire lot, in 1944 Goodspeed was still able to donate fourteen “drawings and paintings” to Yale, following the dealer’s 1941 fire.
                    A decade after the Sotheby sale, the items remaining from lot 27 that were not sold to Princeton remained in Goodspeed’s house when it caught fire in February 1941 (Hogan, 69). Having rescued many books and manuscripts from the catastrophe, Goodspeed began making gifts of Ruskin manuscripts to Yale, starting in March 1941 with the manuscript of Praeterita. The items remaining from the 1931 purchase of juvenilia (MSS IA, X) were also fortunately rescued, and these were donated to Yale in 1942 and 1943. The contents of MSS IA and X had been disassembled from Wedderburn’s bindings, many individual items had been charred around the edges, and a few may have been destroyed completely.	These acquisition notices in YULG mention only one other manuscript, the Laws of Fiesole, of those that Goodspeed purchased in 1931 and that have not been otherwise accounted for in the preceding discussion (see also part 2, MS IA, “Description”). . . . [information to come] The reconstruction of the contents of MSS IA and X, before and after Goodspeed’s fire, requires detailed discussion, which is provided in part 2.
                    Throughout this edition, the preceding discussion is designated in shorthand as Sotheby’s 1931.</p>
                <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                        <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                        <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Body paragraph.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>