<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">C. B. Tinker</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="HMT">Heidi M. Toloudis</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-25">October 25, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head>Chauncey B. Tinker (1876-1963)</head>
                <p>Tinker was a memorable teacher of eighteenth- and nineteenth-century English literature at Yale University from 1903 to 1945, 
                    and served as keeper of rare books for Yale University Library starting in 1930 or 1931, and remained in that post for some years beyond his retirement from teaching. 
                    A collector himself, Tinker was known for his generosity in opening his personal library of manuscripts and rare books 
                    for students' use (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#PATHAKTINKER"><persName corresp="#SBPATHAK">Pathak</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="PATHAKTINKER">&#x201C;Chauncey Brewster Tinker&#x201D;</title></ref>, 278-81; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#METZDORFTINKERLIBRARY"><persName corresp="RFMETZDORF">Metzdorf</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="METZDORFTINKERLIBRARY"><hi rend="italic">The Tinker Library</hi></title></ref>, viii).</p>
                
                <p>Tinker, who had always been a zealous advocate for building the library's collections, was just beginning his formal duties 
                    as keeper of rare books, when Ruskin collectors and scholars on both sides of the Atlantic were surprised by the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date></ref> and the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1931</date></ref>. 
                    Documentation has not been found of Tinker's role in Yale's significant acquisitions from these sales, which were mediated 
                    primarily though not exclusively through the agency of the Boston dealer in rare books and Ruskin collector, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="goodspeed_charles_note.php"><persName corresp="#CG">Charles E. Goodspeed</persName> (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1950">1867&#x2013;1950</date>)</ref>, 
                    but it seems unlikely that this significant investment could have gone forward without Tinker's championship.</p>
                
                <p>The Sotheby's sales exactly coincided with the overwhelming project of constructing the new Sterling Memorial Library (1927-31). 
                    While additional acquisitions to be housed in the library's new rare book room must have competed for the attention of library administrators, 
                    much less for available funding, the peculiar relevance of acquiring Ruskin materials would not have been lost on Tinker. 
                    At the heart of the university, Yale was completing vast neo-Gothic library, which blended cathedral- and cloister-like architecture 
                    for its entryway and reading spaces, symbolizing veneration, with skyscraper-like architecture for the bookstacks. 
                    The architect, James Gamble Rogers, was determined to preserve "religion, or at least a version of it, at the Yale center, 
                    by creating a new kind of sacred space for the modern American university--a cathedral library laden with quasi-religious iconography". 
                    The design not only "placed the functions of a modern library within the shell of a neo-Gothic cathedral", 
                    but also incorporated an iconographic scheme that was perceived as important enough to sacrifice "six tiers of book stacks 
                    in order to fund more ornament" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GRUBIAKSTERLINGLIBRARY"><persName corresp="#MMGRUBIAK">Grubiak</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#GRUBIAKSTERLINGLIBRARY">&#x201C;Reassessing Yale&#x02BC;s Cathedral Orgy&#x201D;</title></ref>, 171, 174, 178; 
                    and for the iconographic program of the decorative scheme, see "The Sterling Memorial Library"). 
                    Ornament is central to Ruskin's writing about architecture.
                    </p>
                
                <p>While his scholarship was centered in Boswell and Johnson studies, Ruskin and the Pre-Raphaelites held an important place 
                    in his teaching, collecting, and writing. In 1908, he published 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRSELECTIONSTINKER"><title type="anthology" corresp="#JRSELECTIONSTINKER"><hi rend="italic">Selections from the Works of John Ruskin</hi></title></ref>, 
                    which he distanced from "such a volume as used to be entitled Elegant Extracts", instead anthologizing chapters and lectures 
                    in as complete form as practicable "to insure a correct notion of the general complexion of Ruskin's work", 
                    which he characterized as a unity and "one continuous development" in thought and style (pp. iii, xii, xix). 
                    His personal collection included five autograph letters; and his rare and first-edition printed Ruskin, 
                    while not aspiring to comprehensiveness, ranged widely across Ruskin's interests and rhetorical styles 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#METZDORFTINKERLIBRARY"><persName corresp="RFMETZDORF">Metzdorf</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="METZDORFTINKERLIBRARY"><hi rend="italic">The Tinker Library</hi></title></ref>, 371-74). 
                    He had access to a comprehensive Ruskin collection belonging his friend, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="adam_r_b_note.php">R. B. Adam (1863-1940)</ref>, 
                    a collection donated to Yale University Library in 1929.</p>
                
                <p>Less happily, Tinker was Goodspeed's correspondent when the retired bookseller donated to Yale the Ruskin manuscripts salvaged from his house fire in 1941.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>