<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="plan_of_archive_note.php">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Plan of the Archive</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing review, encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-07-25">July 25, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0 (TC)</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>
                    <name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name>
                </distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="bibilographical">
                <head type="title">Plan of the Archive</head>
                <p>The archive <hi rend="italic">Early Ruskin Manuscripts</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>)
                    contains, at the most fundamental level, two sets of edited primary materials: 
                    <hi rend="italic">works</hi> and <hi rend="italic">manuscripts</hi>.</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>A <hi rend="italic">work</hi> in this edition consists of a discrete text 
                            by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> (e.g., a poem, an essay, a 
                            sermon, a mathematical proof), including all available witnesses of that 
                            text (each of these edited and annotated), and accompanied by the 
                            work&#x02BC;s explanatory apparatus and available facsimiles. The scope of a work may be comprised 
                            by a poem of only a few lines or by a composite&#x2010;genre project extending over many lengthy sections of verse, prose, and illustration.</item>
                        <item>A <hi rend="italic">manuscript</hi> is a physical document manifesting 
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s texts, 
                            represented in the archive by its own explanatory apparatus in addition to 
                            the <hi rend="italic">works</hi> that make up the manuscript.</item>
                    </list>
                <p>Organizationally, the archive turns on these basic units, 
                    as represented by a given work&#x02BC;s <ref type="internal" target="#WORKSPAGES">Work Pages</ref> 
                    and by a given manuscript&#x02BC;s <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref>. 
                    The fundamental relation between these two kinds of units is the manuscript as container and the work as contained. 
                    For <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>, however, the separate integrity of these units often posed a creative tension. 
                    He treated some manuscript notebooks as anthologies that assembled many separate works, but he also developed single works 
                    into complex, lengthy composites that usurped the borders of their manuscript witness.
                    The archive aims to represent and preserve this creative tension through its editorial methodology (see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology)</ref>.</p>
                    
                <div type="section" xml:id="WORKSPAGES">
                    <head type="section">Work Pages</head>
                    <p>A given work is typically represented by the following kinds of documents:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Work Apparatus Page</ref>;</item>
                            <item>the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKTEXTPAGES">Work Text Pages</ref>, consisting of</item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <item><ref type="internal" target="#WORKWITNESSES">transcript(s) of witness(es)</ref>;</item>
                                    <item>the <ref type="internal" target="#GLOSSES">glosses</ref> that annotate specific passages of the witness(es);</item>
                                    <item><ref type="internal" target="#WORKFACSIMILES">facsimile(s)</ref> associated with the respective witness(es).</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item><ref type="internal" target="#WORKDRAWINGS">Drawings</ref> integral to the work.</item>
                        </list>
                    
                    <p>When a work is selected from the indicies (by title or first line), the selection defaults to the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Work Apparatus Page</ref>.
                        From here, the reader may choose from the list of witnesses, and read the main body of commentary on the work. 
                        This page is headed by the editorial title of the work, 
                        a form of the title that is standardized according to rules given in 
                        the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="title_citation_note.php">System of Title Citation for Works</ref>, 
                        in order to insure consistent reference throughout the archive. (The <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Work Apparatus Page</ref> also includes 
                        a section, <ref type="internal" target="#TITLE">Title</ref>, devoted to explaining <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s own title or titles for the work, if any, 
                        along with the often complex subsequent history of entitling the work.)</p>
                
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">
                    <head type="subsection">Work Apparatus Page</head>
                    <p>The Apparatus Page for each work is divided into seven sections, listed in a menu at the top of the page: 
                        Witnesses, Title, Genre, Manuscripts, Date, Composition and Publication, Discussion.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Witnesses</hi>. All available witnesses for a given work are listed, with each item hyperlinked 
                                to an edited transcription. Clicking the item displays the transcript along with its associated facsimile in <ref type="internal" target="#SHOWCASE">Showcase</ref>.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Title</hi>. This section declares the editorial title of the work, 
                                followed by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s form(s) of the title, if any, 
                                along with discussion of sources or other matters relevant to the entitling of the work by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                                or by his editors.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Genre</hi>. This section declares the work&#x02BC;s genre and provides additional relevant information, such as 
                                (in the case of poems) a brief commentary on prosody.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Manuscripts</hi>. All known physical manifestations of the work (e.g., drafts, fair copies, published versions) are listed, 
                                with each item hyperlinked to the Apparatus Page of the manuscript in question (see 
                                <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref>).</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Date</hi>. This section contains the argument for the date assigned to the work.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Composition and Publication</hi>. This section analyzes the work&#x2010;s publication history, if any, 
                                and reconstructs the compositional history, if materials are available to form such an argument.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>. A final section takes up contextual matters not previously covered, 
                                such as evidence for a work&#x02BC;s sources, the occasion of its
                                composition, and other topics suggested by the work&#x02BC;s contents.</item>
                        </list>
                </div>
            
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="WORKTEXTPAGES">
                    <head type="subsection">Work Text Pages and Showcase</head>
                    <p>From the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Work Apparatus Page</ref>, the reader may select available witnesses and corpora connected with the work, 
                        each of which opens a Work Text Page in Showcase, consisting of an edited transcription paired with a corresponding facsimile of the physical witness. 
                        At present, only edited transcriptions but not facsimiles are provided of commonly available printed witnesses, such as those in 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1891_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</ref> and the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref>.</p>
                    
                    <div type="sub-subsection" xml:id="SHOWCASE">
                        <head type="sub-subsection">Showcase</head>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Showcase</hi> is the display space for Text Pages. The controls in Showcase include the following functions, ordered from left to right atop the Showcase window.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Arrows</hi>. Left and right arrows respectively reverse and advance the reader through a work&#x02BC;s available facsimiles for a particular witness, 
                                provided that witness occupies more than one facsimile. The reader may also select the available facsimiles 
                                from the pull&#x2010;down menu between the arrows.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Windowpane</hi>. A facsimile and its transcript for a particular witness are tied together, and by default they appear side by side in Showcase. 
                                Using the windowpane control, however, the reader may fill the window with the facsimile alone, 
                                or with the transcript alone, and then return to the divided window.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Magnification</hi>. A pull&#x2010;down menu increases or decreases magnification of the facsimile.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Font</hi>. A pull&#x2010;down menu increases or decreases font size of the transcript.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Revision view toggle</hi>. Where possible without confusion to the reader, deletions and insertions are rendered in transcriptions 
                                exactly as they appear in the manuscript witness&#x2014;for example, with the deletion scored through, and the insertion 
                                above the line. In such cases as overwriting, however, which are difficult to represent, 
                                a toggle tool (shown as a curved arrow) advances the reader through the original text and then the overwritten text. 
                                Three successive points on the toggle respresent, first, the original text (in gray); second, the overwritten text (in standard text color); 
                                and third, the darker overwritten text and the gray underlying text simultaneously. Since the toggle suggests a timeline, 
                                it is activated only by XML/TEI markup justifiably interpreting a sequence of actions, as in the case of overwriting and certain other substitutions.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Hand toggle</hi>. Another toggle tool (shown as a pen) allows the user to filter multiple hands 
                                in a witness. The default view exhibits all hands without descrimination. A pull-dowm menu allows the user to filter 
                                only <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s hand, or only other hands that may be present, such as 
                                <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s, or 
                                <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="sub-subsection" xml:id="WORKWITNESSES">
                        <head type="sub-subsection">Witnesses and Commentary</head>
                    <p>For discussion of the transcription and encoding methodologies governing the transcription of witnesses, see 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology</ref>.</p>
                        <p>Transcriptions carry metadiscursive information and editorial commentary tied to specific passages of text. Unlike <ref type="internal" target="#NOTES">Notes</ref>, 
                            which deal with global topics hyperlinked throughout the archive, and the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Apparatus Page</ref>, 
                            which supplies general commentary on a work as a whole, these more specialized annotations are accessed primarily at the local level of the textual witness, 
                            although this commentary is also searchable by keyword using the archive&#x02BC;s main Search tool.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item xml:id="GLOSSES"><hi rend="italic">Glosses</hi>. These annotations are tied to specific passages in textual witnesses 
                                by superscript characters (letters or numbers, colored blue to distinguish from the original text). The hyperlinked characters open 
                                a separate window, with the desired commentary shaded for ease of reference. There are two types of glossses.</item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Contextual glosses</hi>. Hyperlinked using Arabic numerals, these glosses annotate persons, 
                                        places, literary and mythical references, historical background, and other contextual information needed to appreciate 
                                        a particular passage. Also, annotations by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s earlier editors and by 
                                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself are included here. These are distinguished from the current editor&#x02BC;s 
                                        glosses by a bracketed comment, such as [Ruskin&#x02BC;s note].</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Textual glosses</hi>. Hyperlinked using lowercase alphabetical Latin characters, these glosses annotate 
                                        textual matters affecting a particular passage, which are too specific to be treated in the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Apparatus Page</ref>.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Page notations</hi>. A gray bar marks page breaks in the witness, 
                                as reflected in the the corresponding facsimile.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Line Numbers</hi>. For poems, line numbering is transcribed only from 
                                <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s own marginal numbering in a manuscript, since this information 
                                can prove useful for textual analysis. At present, no additional editorial line numbering is provided.</item>
                        </list>
                </div>
                    
                <div type="sub-subsection" xml:id="WORKFACSIMILES">
                    <head type="sub-subsection">Facsimiles</head>
                    <p>Facsimile views, in the case of bound manuscripts, open to the page(s) containing the chosen witness of the work. At present, in most cases, this view will appear as a
                        two&#x2010;page spread. These views are identical to what the reader finds when opening the facsimile from the <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref>.</p>
                    <p>For manuscripts that were formerly bound but now disassembled owing to damage, such as those comprised in <ref type="apparatus" target="msia_apparatus.php">MS IA</ref>, 
                        the facsimile view is often similar to a two&#x2010;page spread. Loose single&#x2010;sheet manuscripts are shown one side per view, recto followed by verso.</p>
                </div>
                </div>
                </div>
            
                <div type="section" xml:id="MANUSCRIPTPAGES">
                    <head type="section">Manuscript Pages</head>
                    <p>The only Web pages representing a manuscript are the <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTAPPARATUSPAGE">Manuscript Apparatus Page</ref> 
                        and the <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTFACSIMILE">Manuscript Facsmile</ref>. 
                        There are no Text Pages as in the case of works, as Manuscript Text Pages would effectively be identical to the sum of the Text Pages
                        belonging to the work(s) contained within the manuscript.</p>    
                
            
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="MANUSCRIPTAPPARATUSPAGE">
                    <head type="subsection">Manuscript Apparatus Page</head>
                    <p>The Manuscript Apparatus Page is the default destination for any hyperlinked occurrence of a manuscript title, whether accessed through the indices, Works Pages, or various forms of commentary. 
                        The page is headed by the manuscript&#x02BC;s editorial title, as governed by rules given in the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="title_citation_for_major_mss_note.php">System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts</ref>.</p>
                    <p>The Apparatus is a single page consisting of seven sections: Title, Location, Provenance, Description, Contents, Discussion.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Title</hi> declares the editorial title, and goes on to discuss the history of entitling the manuscript, including <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s
                                own title, if any, and his editors&#x02BC; titles.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Location</hi> identifies where the manuscript is currently held, along with any helpful cataloging information.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Provenance</hi> describes the history of ownership and transmission. For many manuscripts, which share a common provenance with others, this section consists simply of a
                                link to the appropriate section of the long note on <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_note.php">Provenance</ref>. For some manuscripts, however, the Apparatus
                                requires this section in order to elaborate on a unique history.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Description</hi> supplies physical characteristics, such as size, color, and kind of binding materials. The description also include what in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> is
                                termed a <hi rend="italic">Collation</hi>. Rather than an account of the assemblage of signatures in a printed book, however, <hi rend="italic">collation</hi> here refers to
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s (and, sometimes, his and/or others&#x02BC;) pagination. This pagination applies either to an originally blank, bound notebook or of a bound
                                compilation of originally separate leaves. In the case of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s own page numbering, collations must often take account of the misnumbering of
                                pages and of missing pages. The collation provides the basis for a somewhat more speculative reconstruction of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s patterns of use of the manuscript,
                                a narrative reserved for the Discussion. Page references in the collation list are active, capable of opening the corresponding Manuscript Facsimile views. In some cases, descriptions of a
                                manuscript&#x02BC;s cover and endpapers contain active links to facsimile views, as well.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Contents</hi> lists sequentially the works contained in the manuscript. The titles in the list are active, hyperlinked to their respective Work Apparatus Page.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Date</hi> gives the inclusive dates for use of the manuscript by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and sometimes by others.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>, like the corresponding section in a Work Apparatus, is a catch&#x2010;all for topics that cannot be accommodated in other sections. For example,
                                one frequently recurring topic placed here is an attempt to reconstruct <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s palimpsest&#x2010;like uses and reuses of an originally bound manuscript.
                                These reconstructions propose sequences of composition rarely corresponding to the <hi rend="italic">sequential</hi> list given in the Contents, which describes the physical order of a
                                manuscript&#x02BC;s contents: <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> seldom worked straightforwardly from beginning to end of a notebook. Other topics taken up in this section include
                                discussion of the hand(s) characterizing the manuscript, its relation to similar manuscripts, and so on.</item>
                        </list>
                    
                </div>
            
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="MANUSCRIPTFACSIMILE">
                    <head type="subsection">Manuscript Facsimile</head>
                    <p>The complete facsimile of a manuscript&#x2014;from cover to cover, if bound, viewed as a sequence usually of two&#x2010;page spreads&#x2014;is the same as what a reader would view when selecting
                        sequentially the Work Facsimiles it contains. (The difference in the terms <hi rend="italic">Manuscript Facsimile</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Work Facsimile</hi> is merely one of convenience referring,
                        not to differing entities, but to viewing the same entity from different places in the archive&#x2014;the Manuscript Pages and Works Pages, respectively.)</p>
                    <p>See <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology</ref>for an explanation of how manuscripts 
                        are represented in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> using the &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; element.</p>
                </div>
                </div>
                    
                    <div type="section" xml:id="NOTES">
                        <head type="section">Notes</head>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> contain commentary, which can be hyperlinked from any point in the archive 
                            (unlike <ref type="internal" target="#GLOSSES"><hi rend="italic">Glosses</hi></ref>, 
                            which are anchored to transcripts of <ref type="internal" target="#WORKWITNESSES">witnesses</ref>) 
                            Notes are grouped in four subtypes:</p>
                                <list>
                                    <item>bibliographical;</item>
                                    <item>biographical;</item>
                                    <item>contextual;</item>
                                    <item>geographical.</item>
                                </list>
                        
                        </div>
                    
                    <div>
                        <div type="section" xml:id="ESSAYS">
                            <head type="section">Essays</head>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Essays</hi> provide broad overviews of large topics pertinent to the archive. 
                                They are intended as pathways into the archive for readers who do not wish to enter by selecting a specific work, manuscript, or note 
                                from the indices, but who prefer to explore the archive to discover its resources supporting a broad research interest. 
                                For such readers, the essays supply richly, though not exhaustively hyperlinked guided tours of works related to major topics. As presently planned, 
                                the topical essays will include:</p>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Bibliography;</item>
                                    <item>Literature;</item>
                                    <item>Education;</item>
                                    <item>Travel;</item>
                                    <item>Science;</item>
                                    <item>Religion.</item>
                                </list>
                            
                    </div>
                        
                    <div type="section" xml:id="BIBLIOGRAPHY">
                            <head type="section">Bibliography</head>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Bibliography</hi> is the reference point for bibliographical citations of works, published and unpublished, 
                                exclusive of the manuscripts and edited witnesses of works of which the archive itself consists. Scattered througout the archive, the reader will find 
                                bibliographical citations in short&#x2010;title form, which are hyperlinked to full citations in the Bibliography. 
                                Viewed as a full document, the Bibliography is divided into sections:</p>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Primary Sources
                                        <list>
                                            <item>Works by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and the Ruskin Family in Manuscript Other than the Manuscripts Constituting This Edition</item>
                                            <item>Works by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> in Published Editions</item>
                                            <item>Works by Other Authors in Manuscript</item>
                                            <item>Works by Other Authors in Published Editions</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Secondary Sources
                                        <list>
                                            <item>Unpublished</item>
                                            <item>Published</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            
                    </div>
                            
                        <!--<p><ref type="internal" target="#WORKSPAGES">Work Pages</ref> and <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref> consist respectively 
                            of consistent sets of XML/TEI documents, discussed below. At a global level, the archive also contains editorial 
                            materials&#x2014;<ref type="internal" target="#NOTES">Notes</ref>, <ref type="internal" target="#ESSAYS">Essays</ref>, and 
                            <ref type="internal" target="#BIBLIOGRAPHY">Bibliography</ref>&#x2014;that are not anchored to particular works or manuscripts, 
                            but serve as universally accessible resources, and that are indexed at the same level as works and manuscripts. 
                            These materials, like the various <ref type="internal" target="#WORKSPAGES">Work Pages</ref> and <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref>, each open on a separate 
                            tab in the user's browser.
                            
                            
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Textual Note</hi> contains summmary remarks based on collations performed by the <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> editor and staff. 
                                The reader can also perform collations of witnesses using a tool such as <orgName corresp="#NINES">NINES</orgName>&#x02BC;s Juxta.</item>
                        </p>-->
            </div>
           
            </div>      
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>