<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="plan_of_archive_note.php">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Plan of the Archive</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing review, encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-07-25">July 25, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0 (TC)</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>
                    <name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name>
                </distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="bibilographical">
                <head type="title">Plan of the Archive</head>
                <p>The archive <hi rend="italic">Early Ruskin Manuscripts</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>)
                    contains, at the most fundamental level, two sets of edited primary materials: 
                    <hi rend="italic">works</hi> and <hi rend="italic">manuscripts</hi>.</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>A <hi rend="italic">work</hi> in this edition consists of a discrete text 
                            by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> (e.g., a poem, an essay, a 
                            sermon, a mathematical proof), including all available witnesses of that 
                            text (each of these edited and annotated), and accompanied by the 
                            work&#x02BC;s explanatory apparatus and available facsimiles.</item>
                        <item>A <hi rend="italic">manuscript</hi> is a physical document manifesting 
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s texts, 
                            represented in the archive by its own explanatory apparatus in addition to 
                            the <hi rend="italic">works</hi> that make up the manuscript.</item>
                    </list>
                <p>Organizationally, the archive turns on these basic units, 
                    as represented by a given work&#x02BC;s <ref type="internal" target="#WORKSPAGES">Work Pages</ref> 
                    and by a given manuscript&#x02BC;s <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref>. 
                    The fundamental relation between these two kinds of units is the manuscript as container and the work as contained. 
                    For <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>, however, the separate integrity of these units often creates a creative tension, 
                    which the archive aims to preserve through its editorial methodology (see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology)</ref>.</p>
                <p><ref type="internal" target="#WORKSPAGES">Work Pages</ref> and <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref> consist respectively 
                    of consistent sets of XML/TEI documents, discussed below. At a global level, the archive also contains editorial 
                    materials&#x2014;<ref type="internal" target="#NOTES">Notes</ref>, <ref type="internal" target="#ESSAYS">Essays</ref>, and 
                    <ref type="internal" target="#BIBLIOGRAPHY">Bibliography</ref>&#x2014;that are not anchored to particular works or manuscripts, 
                    but serve as universally accessible resources, and that are indexed at the same level as works and manuscripts. 
                    These materials, like the various <ref type="internal" target="#WORKSPAGES">Work Pages</ref> and <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref>, each open on a separate 
                    tab in the user's browser.
                </p>
            
                    
                <div type="section" xml:id="WORKSPAGES">
                    <head type="section">Work Pages</head>
                    <p>A given work may be represented by the following kinds of documents:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Work Apparatus Page</ref>;</item>
                            <item>the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKTEXTPAGES">Work Text Pages</ref>, consisting of</item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <item><ref type="internal" target="#WORKWITNESSES">Transcript(s) of witness(es)</ref>,</item>
                                    <item>the <ref type="internal" target="#GLOSSES">Glosses</ref> that annotate the witness(es),</item>
                                    <item><ref type="internal" target="#WORKFACSIMILES">Facsimile(s)</ref> associated with the respective witness(es);</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item><ref type="internal" target="#WORKDRAWINGS">Drawings</ref>.</item>
                        </list>
                    
                    <p>If a work is selected by title from the indicies, the selection defaults to the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Work Apparatus Page</ref>. 
                        This page is headed by the editorial title of the work, 
                        a form of the title that is standardized according to rules given in 
                        the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="title_citation_note.php">System of Title Citation for Works</ref>, 
                        in order to insure consistent reference throughout the archive. (The <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Work Apparatus Page</ref> includes 
                        a section, <ref type="internal" target="#TITLE">Title</ref>, devoted to explaining <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s own title or titles for the work, if any, 
                        along with the often complex subsequent history of entitling the work.)</p>
                
            
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">
                    <head type="subsection">Work Apparatus Page</head>
                    <p>Each work defaults to an Apparatus Page, which is divided into six (or, in some cases, seven) sections, listed in a menu at the top of the page: 
                        Witnesses, Title, Genre, Manuscripts, Date, Composition and Publication, Discussion, and, in 
                        some cases, Textual Note.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Witnesses</hi>, the first section on the Apparatus Page, consists of a list of hyperlinks to the available 
                                witnesses and associated facsimiles, which constitute the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKTEXTPAGES">Text Pages</ref> for a given work.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Title</hi> declares the editorial title, followed by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s
                                form(s) of the title, if any, along with discussion of sources or other matters relevant to the entitling of the work by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                                or by his editors.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Genre</hi> declares the work&#x02BC;s genre and, in some cases, subgenre. 
                                For poems, the section also supplies commentary on its prosody.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Manuscripts</hi> identifies the physical manifestations of the work (e.g., drafts, fair copies, published versions), 
                                each hyperlinked to the Apparatus Page of the manuscript in question (see 
                                <ref type="internal">Manuscript Pages</ref>).</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Date</hi> contains the argument for the date assigned to the work.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Composition and Publication</hi> describes the publication history, if any, for the work, 
                                and reconstructs the compositional history, if materials are available to form such an argument.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi> takes up contextual questions not covered in the previous sections, such as evidence for a work&#x02BC;s sources, the occasion of its
                                composition, and so on.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Textual Note</hi> contains summmary remarks based on collations performed by the <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> editor and staff. 
                                The reader can also perform collations of witnesses using a tool such as <orgName corresp="#NINES">NINES</orgName>&#x02BC;s Juxta.</item>
                        </list>
                    
                </div>
            
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="WORKTEXTPAGES">
                    <head type="subsection">Work Text Pages and Showcase</head>
                    <p>From the <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Work Apparatus Page</ref>, the reader may select available witnesses and corpora connected with the work. 
                        Each of these witnesses or corpora is represented by Work Text Pages, 
                        which open in Showcase windows as a transcript of a witness paired with a corresponding facsimile of the physical witness. 
                        Acknowledgement is made if a facsimile is unavailable for a given witness.</p>
                    
                    <div type="sub-subsection" xml:id="SHOWCASE">
                        <head type="sub-subsection">Showcase</head>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Showcase</hi> is the display space for Text Pages. The controls in Showcase include the following functions, ordered from left to right atop the Showcase window. 
                        (These functions are also identified by mouseover.)</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>Forward arrows advance the reader through a work&#x02BC;s available facsimiles for a particular witness, provided that witness occupies more than one facsimile; 
                                and backward arrows reverse the reader through those same facsimiles. 
                                The reader may also select these available facsimiles from the pull&#x2010;down menu between the arrows.</item>
                            <item>A facsimile and its transcript for a particular witness are tied together, and by default they appear side by side in Showcase. 
                                Using a windowpane control, however, the reader may fill the window with the facsimile alone, 
                                or the transcript alone, or return to the divided window.</item>
                            <item>A pull&#x2010;down menu increases or decreases magnification of the facsimile.</item>
                            <item>A pull&#x2010;down menu increases or decreases font size of the transcript.</item>
                            <item>A toggle view advances the reader through layers of additions, deletions, overwriting, etc., as interpreted by the <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> team and 
                                encoded in the edited witness of a work. The baseline view is a representation of all of these layers simultaneously.</item>
                            <item>A toggle view separates the hands (e.g., <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s, <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s, 
                                <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s) responsible for all or portions of a witness.</item>
                        </list>
                    
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="sub-subsection" xml:id="WORKWITNESSES">
                        <head type="sub-subsection">Work Witnesses</head>
                    <p>By default, when a given witness is selected by the reader, its transcript along with the corresponding facsimile appears in 
                        <ref type="internal" target="#SHOWCASE">Showcase</ref>. 
                        For discussion of the transcription and encoding methodologies governing these transcriptions, see 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology</ref>.</p>
                        <p>Transcripts of witnesses carry some editorial features, which are local to this level of the archive and cannot be accessed through the archive indices, 
                            although occasionally a hyperlink elsewhere in the archive will point directly to one of these features.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item xml:id="GLOSSES"><hi rend="italic">Glosses</hi> are editorial commentary linked to specific features of a transcript 
                                (as opposed to the global <ref type="internal" target="#NOTES">Notes</ref>). This commentary cannot be conveniently discussed in the 
                                <ref type="internal" target="#WORKAPPARATUSPAGE">Apparatus Page</ref> of a work, as the glosses depend on a specific context. 
                                Hyperlinks (reference numbers) to glosses are colored to distinguish them from the transcript as editorial. 
                                On occasion, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> annotated texts himself, 
                                and these reference numbers or characters, because they are originally present in the manuscript, appear in the same color as the transcript. 
                                <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s corresponding note is distinguished from the editors&#x02BC; notes by the bracketed comment: 
                                [Ruskin&#x02BC;s note]. When summoned, glosses appear as an ordered list in a single document, which opens on a separate tab.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Page notations</hi> identify page breaks in the witness, as reflected in the the corresponding facsimile.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Line Numbers</hi> (in the case of poems) in a transcript at present record only 
                                <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s own marginal numbering in a manuscript.</item>
                        </list>
                    
                </div>
                    
                <div type="sub-subsection" xml:id="WORKFACSIMILES">
                    <head type="sub-subsection">Work Facsimiles</head>
                    <p>Facsimile views, in the case of bound manuscripts, open to the page(s) containing the chosen witness of the work. In most cases, this view will appear as a
                        two&#x2010;page spread. These views are identical to what the reader finds when opening the facsimile from the <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTPAGES">Manuscript Pages</ref>. 
                        If a given work continues beyond the two&#x2010;page spread, the reader can advance the pages using the <ref type="internal" target="#SHOWCASE">Showcase</ref> controls.</p>
                    <p>For manuscripts that were formerly bound but now disassembled owing to damage, such as <ref type="apparatus" target="msia_apparatus.php">MS IA</ref>, 
                        the facsimile view is often similar to a two&#x2010;page spread. Loose single-sheet manuscripts are shown one side per view, recto followed by verso.</p>
                </div>
                </div>
                </div>
            
                <div type="section" xml:id="MANUSCRIPTPAGES">
                    <head type="section">Manuscript Pages</head>
                    <p>The only Web pages representing a manuscript are the <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTAPPARATUSPAGE">Manuscript Apparatus Page</ref> 
                        and the <ref type="internal" target="#MANUSCRIPTFACSIMILE">Manuscript Facsmile</ref>. 
                        There are no Text Pages as in the case of works, as Manuscript Text Pages would effectively be identical to the sum of the Text Pages
                        belonging to the work(s) contained within the manuscript.</p>    
                
            
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="MANUSCRIPTAPPARATUSPAGE">
                    <head type="subsection">Manuscript Apparatus Page</head>
                    <p>The Manuscript Apparatus Page is the default destination for any hyperlinked occurrence of a manuscript title, whether accessed through the indices, Works Pages, or various forms of commentary. 
                        The page is headed by the manuscript&#x02BC;s editorial title, as governed by rules given in the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="title_citation_for_major_mss_note.php">System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts</ref>.</p>
                    <p>The Apparatus is a single page consisting of seven sections: Title, Location, Provenance, Description, Contents, Discussion.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Title</hi> declares the editorial title, and goes on to discuss the history of entitling the manuscript, including <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s
                                own title, if any, and his editors&#x02BC; titles.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Location</hi> identifies where the manuscript is currently held, along with any helpful cataloging information.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Provenance</hi> describes the history of ownership and transmission. For many manuscripts, which share a common provenance with others, this section consists simply of a
                                link to the appropriate section of the long note on <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_note.php">Provenance</ref>. For some manuscripts, however, the Apparatus
                                requires this section in order to elaborate on a unique history.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Description</hi> supplies physical characteristics, such as size, color, and kind of binding materials. The description also include what in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> is
                                termed a <hi rend="italic">Collation</hi>. Rather than an account of the assemblage of signatures in a printed book, however, <hi rend="italic">collation</hi> here refers to
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s (and, sometimes, his and/or others&#x02BC;) pagination. This pagination applies either to an originally blank, bound notebook or of a bound
                                compilation of originally separate leaves. In the case of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s own page numbering, collations must often take account of the misnumbering of
                                pages and of missing pages. The collation provides the basis for a somewhat more speculative reconstruction of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s patterns of use of the manuscript,
                                a narrative reserved for the Discussion. Page references in the collation list are active, capable of opening the corresponding Manuscript Facsimile views. In some cases, descriptions of a
                                manuscript&#x02BC;s cover and endpapers contain active links to facsimile views, as well.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Contents</hi> lists sequentially the works contained in the manuscript. The titles in the list are active, hyperlinked to their respective Work Apparatus Page.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Date</hi> gives the inclusive dates for use of the manuscript by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and sometimes by others.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>, like the corresponding section in a Work Apparatus, is a catch&#x2010;all for topics that cannot be accommodated in other sections. For example,
                                one frequently recurring topic placed here is an attempt to reconstruct <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s palimpsest&#x2010;like uses and reuses of an originally bound manuscript.
                                These reconstructions propose sequences of composition rarely corresponding to the <hi rend="italic">sequential</hi> list given in the Contents, which describes the physical order of a
                                manuscript&#x02BC;s contents: <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> seldom worked straightforwardly from beginning to end of a notebook. Other topics taken up in this section include
                                discussion of the hand(s) characterizing the manuscript, its relation to similar manuscripts, and so on.</item>
                        </list>
                    
                </div>
            
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="MANUSCRIPTFACSIMILE">
                    <head type="subsection">Manuscript Facsimile</head>
                    <p>The complete facsimile of a manuscript&#x2014;from cover to cover, if bound, viewed as a sequence usually of two&#x2010;page spreads&#x2014;is the same as what a reader would view when selecting
                        sequentially the Work Facsimiles it contains. (The difference in the terms <hi rend="italic">Manuscript Facsimile</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Work Facsimile</hi> is merely one of convenience referring,
                        not to differing entities, but to viewing the same entity from different places in the archive&#x2014;the Manuscript Pages and Works Pages, respectively.)</p>
                    <p>See <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology</ref>for an explanation of how manuscripts 
                        are represented in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> using the &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; element.</p>
                </div>
                </div>
                    
                    <div type="section" xml:id="NOTES">
                        <head type="section">Notes</head>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> contain commentary, which can be hyperlinked from any point in the archive 
                            (unlike <ref type="internal" target="#GLOSSES"><hi rend="italic">Glosses</hi></ref>, 
                            which are anchored to transcripts of <ref type="internal" target="#WORKWITNESSES">witnesses</ref>) 
                            Notes are grouped in four subtypes:</p>
                                <list>
                                    <item>bibliographical;</item>
                                    <item>biographical;</item>
                                    <item>contextual;</item>
                                    <item>geographical.</item>
                                </list>
                        
                        </div>
                    
                    <div>
                        <div type="section" xml:id="ESSAYS">
                            <head type="section">Essays</head>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Essays</hi> provide broad overviews of large topics pertinent to the archive. 
                                They are intended as pathways into the archive for readers who do not wish to enter by selecting a specific work, manuscript, or note 
                                from the indices, but who prefer to explore the archive to discover its resources supporting a broad research interest. 
                                For such readers, the essays supply richly, though not exhaustively hyperlinked guided tours of works related to major topics. As presently planned, 
                                the topical essays will include:</p>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Bibliography;</item>
                                    <item>Literature;</item>
                                    <item>Education;</item>
                                    <item>Travel;</item>
                                    <item>Science;</item>
                                    <item>Religion.</item>
                                </list>
                            
                    </div>
                        
                    <div type="section" xml:id="BIBLIOGRAPHY">
                            <head type="section">Bibliography</head>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Bibliography</hi> is the reference point for bibliographical citations of works, published and unpublished, 
                                exclusive of the manuscripts and edited witnesses of works of which the archive itself consists. Scattered througout the archive, the reader will find 
                                bibliographical citations in short&#x2010;title form, which are hyperlinked to full citations in the Bibliography. 
                                Viewed as a full document, the Bibliography is divided into sections:</p>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Primary Sources
                                        <list>
                                            <item>Works by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and the Ruskin Family in Manuscript Other than the Manuscripts Constituting This Edition</item>
                                            <item>Works by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> in Published Editions</item>
                                            <item>Works by Other Authors in Manuscript</item>
                                            <item>Works by Other Authors in Published Editions</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Secondary Sources
                                        <list>
                                            <item>Unpublished</item>
                                            <item>Published</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            
                    </div>
                            
                
            </div>
           
            </div>      
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>