<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="adam_r_b_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">R. B. Adam II (1863-1940)</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="biographical">
                <head type="title"><persName corresp="#RBA">R. B. Adam II</persName> (1863-1940)</head>
                <p><persName corresp="#RBA">Robert Borthwick Adam II</persName> of Buffalo, New York, inherited and dramatically expanded the book collection of his uncle, 
                    <persName corresp="#RBAI">Robert Borthwick Adam I</persName> (1833-1904), a native of Scotland who emigrated to the United States in the 1850s 
                    and established a successful and respected dry goods business in Buffalo, which he expanded to a major department store. 
                    The senior Adam and his wife being childless, they adopted his namesake nephew, then nine, and his sister from Scotland. 
                    For both father and son, the main focus of the book collection was Samuel Johnson and his circle, 
                    but Adam senior collected other writers, including Robert Burns and Ruskin; 
                    and while it was the Johnson collection that earned the Adamses of Buffalo world-wide fame, 
                    Adam II remained committed also to the Burns and Ruskin until about 1923-24
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LOOSADAM"><persName corresp="#WHLOOS">Loos</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#LOOSADAM">&#x201C;Robert Borthwick Adam II&#x201D;</title></ref>, 3-5; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON1"><persName corresp="#MHYDE">Hyde</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON1">&#x201C;Adam, Tinker, and Newton&#x201D;</title></ref>, 287-88, 297).</p>
                
                <p>In the 1920s, Adam II decided to sell his Burns and Ruskin collections, in order to devote his attention solely 
                    to Johnson and the eighteenth century. (Tragically, he would be forced by the stock market crash of October 1929 
                    to break up his Johnson collection, as well.) In 1923, he sent the Ruskin collection to the firm of the rare book and manuscript dealer, 
                    A. S. W. Rosenbach (1876-1952) in New York. The firm attempted to interest Henry Huntington (1850-1927) in the collection, 
                    but it remained unsold for six years, when, in April 1929, Adam retrieved it for presentation to Yale University Library. 
                    He donated the collection in memory of his adopted father, who started it, but he also wished to support the efforts 
                    by his good friend, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="tinker_c_b_note.php">Chauncey B. Tinker (1876-1963)</ref>, 
                    to build up the Yale library's rare books and manuscripts department 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON1"><persName corresp="#MHYDE">Hyde</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON1">&#x201C;Adam, Tinker, and Newton&#x201D;</title></ref>, 297-98, 304; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON2"><persName corresp="#MHYDE">Hyde</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON2">&#x201C;Adam, Tinker, and Newton, 1909&#x2013;1948&#x201D;</title>, 561</ref>).</p>
                
                <p>In a 1929 issue of the Yale University Library Gazette, the Adam Ruskin collection was described as constituting 
                    "virtually the whole body of Ruskin's works, from the earliest to the latest, just as they were first issued: 
                    <hi rend="italic">editiones principes</hi> literally by the score, rare pamphlets, 
                    occasional adddresses, unique copies,--everything that might be needed . . . for the professional scholar 
                    bent upon a thorough and serious study in the works of John Ruskin". The article acknowledged, however, 
                    that Adam had previously sold off "some of the rarest items", including two copies of the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1850_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1850)</ref>, 
                    as well as "several autograph letters and manuscripts, which added luster to Mr. Adam's library, but had no essential place,
                    perhaps, in the collection that has just been given to Yale". The article ascribes the sale of these Ruskin items, 
                    not to the Rosenbach firm, but to an auction at the Anderson Galleries in February 1926--a major disposal of over 400 lots 
                    of non-Johnsonian materials and some Johnsoniana, of which 38 items related to Ruskin, according to the Gazette 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRENCHADAMCOLLECTION"><persName corresp="#RDFRENCH">French</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#FRENCHADAMCOLLECTION">&#x201C;The R. D. Adam Collection of Ruskin&#x201D;</title></ref>, 1, 6; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON1"><persName corresp="#MHYDE">Hyde</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON1">&#x201C;Adam, Tinker, and Newton&#x201D;</title></ref>, 298). 
                    The relation of these offerings in 1926 to what had been turned over to Rosenbach in 1923 is not clear.</p>
                
                <p>Nonetheless, the remaining collection given to Yale was so large that the annual "Report of the Librarian" for 1928-29 
                    reflected difficulty getting a grip on the numbers of items. First listed in the "Report" as consisting of 
                    "over three hundred and seventy volumes by and about Ruskin", elsewhere in the same annual report 
                    the gift is numbered at "some 500 volumes and pamphlets". Six years later, "after an unusual amount of bibliographical study and revision", 
                    another annual "Report" set the total at "464 volumes and 271 pamphlets", although it is unclear whether these figures refer solely to the Adam bequest 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#KEOGHREPORT_1928-29">"Report of the Librarian, July 1, 1928-June 30, 1929"</ref>, 6, 36-37; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#KEOGHREPORT_1934-35">"Report of the Librarian, July 1, 1934-June 30, 1935"</ref>, 15).</p>
                
                <p>Like Tinker, Adam was generous to scholars who requested access to his collections for research. Johnson scholars in particular 
                    benefited from access to and even loan of his possessions, so it is possible that scholars may have taken advantage 
                    of Adam's Ruskin collection as well, before it came to Yale. Charles Grosvenor Osgood (1871-1964), 
                    the literary scholar from Princeton University, visited Adam and lectured on Ruskin in Buffalo; 
                    and Tinker's graduate students were granted access to Adam's collections as well 
                    (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON1"><persName corresp="#MHYDE">Hyde</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#HYDEADAMTINKERNEWTON1">&#x201C;Adam, Tinker, and Newton&#x201D;</title></ref>, 290-92, 294-96).</p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>