<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Camberwell</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2018-01-31">January 31, 2018</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="contextual">
                <head type="title">Camberwell</head>
                <p>Camberwell is the London suburb in which the Ruskins' home, no. 26 Herne Hill, was located.</p>
                <div>
                    <head type="section" xml:id="COMMUTER">London Commuter Transport</head>
                    <p>The Ruskins' house stood four miles from the "Standard in Cornhill" in the City (Hilton 8), 
                        marking the crossroads of Cornhill, Gracechurch Street, 
                        Leadenhall Street, and Bishopsgate--very near to John James Ruskin's business premises 
                        in Billiter Street (see City of London; Smith and Elder). Travelers between London and Camberwell south of the river 
                        could cross London Bridge connecting with Old Camberwell Road, 
                        which ran along the western side of the parish (the most convenient route between Billiter Street and Herne Hill), 
                        or they could take Blackfriars Bridge connecting with the Old Kent road, 
                        which ran along the eastern side of the parish. The traveler inevitably encountered turnpike roads on the south side of the river, 
                        requiring tolls (Dyos, Victorian Suburb, 64-65).</p>
                    <p>The Ruskins did not maintain a carriage of their own (Dearden, John Ruskin's Camberwell, 8), 
                        so John James Ruskin must have taken public transport into the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="london_city_note.php">City of London</ref>. 
                        According to H. J. Dyos, by 1834 these roads between Camberwell and London were traversed each day by seventeen coaches 
                        running ninety journeys between them. Omnibuses were introduced in 1835, at first used mainly by casual travelers into the city, 
                        not businessmen who departed earlier than these conveyances started. The frequency of omnibus schedules 
                        accommodating all commuter travel increased at mid-century. Then in the 1860s, 
                        railways became a practical means of suburban commuting to and from work in the city. 
                        The preceding decades of rail development was associated with distance travel 
                        (Dyos 66-67, 70-71).
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                <p>[More to come.]</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>