<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="evangelical_magazine_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main"><orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName> and the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title></title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#IB">Isabella Bairnsfather</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#JADAMS">Jazmin J. Adams</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#GMS">Gabriella M. Smith</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="bibliographical">
                <head type="title"><orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName> and the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title></head>
                
                <p>In a <title type="letter" corresp="mr_to_jjr_1823-03-03">letter of <date when="1823-03-03">3 March 1823</date> to <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName></title>,
                    <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret Ruskin</persName> mentions receiving this publication 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><title type="book" corresp="#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></title>, ed. <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd</persName></ref>, 121). 
                    Her remark does not make clear when the Ruskins&#x02BC; subscription began, 
                    but it might be significant that, with the <date when="1823">1823</date> issues, the magazine initiated volume one of a new series. 
                    The magazine influenced <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> both in content, for example by contributing to the family&#x02BC;s zeal for missionary causes 
                    (see, e.g., <ref type="apparatus" target="a_theme_apparatus.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRATHEME">&#x201C;a theme&#x201D;</title></ref>), 
                    and in elements of print culture, for example by supplying models for compiling, entitling, and fair&#x2010;copying poetry anthologies and occasional poems 
                    (see, e.g., <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="new_years_poems_note">New Year&#x02BC;s Poems</ref>).
                </p>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Foundational Aims and Audience of the Magazine in the Movement for Evangelical Unity</head>
                    
                    <p>The <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title> was founded in <date when="1793">1793</date> as a non&#x2010;denominational voice of evangelical culture, 
                    embracing <orgName corresp="#EVANGELICALANGLICANISM">Anglican Evangelicalism</orgName>, Old Dissent, and New Dissent 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ALTHOLZRELIGIOUSPRESS"><persName corresp="JLA">Altholz</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#ALTHOLZRELIGIOUSPRESS"><hi rend="italic">Religious Press in Britain</hi></title></ref>, 45). 
                        <!-- START NEW MARKUP -->In the preface to the first issue, the magazine situates itself in a world of advancing literacy in which "it will be a rare thing to find a beggar in the land who has not been taught to read" and in which 
                    "[t]housands read a Magazine, who have neither money to purchase, nor leisure to peruse, large volumes". Yet, this progress is co-opted by 
                    "a certain description of writers" who, by monopolizing a work of this kind, have made more converts to their opinions, and done more mischief to the cause of religion, than all the folios of <persName corresp="#FSOZZINI">Socinus</persName> 
                    [i.e., <orgName corresp="#SOCINIANISM">Socinianism</orgName>]". To counter this influence, the Evangelical Magazine will convey "the collected knowledge and experience of various Ministers and Christians" 
                    in a form that is level "to every one's capacity, and suited to every one's time and circumstances", as "elucidated" by the "fundamental doctrines of the Gospel" 
                    and by "the lives and experience of eminent Christians"--that is, "Experimental and Practical Theology". Against the more "artful attacks of atheistical philosophers" 
                    and "infidel and illiberal critics", the magazine poses "a manly and impartial Review of Religious Books" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#PREFACEEVANGELICALMAG1793-01">&#x201C;Preface&#x201D; [<date when="1793-01">January 1793</date>]</ref>, 1-2).</p>
                    
                    <p>In its aspiration to represent a catholicity of evangelical aims and opinion based on experiential religion, the magazine was oriented to a broad movement 
                        for evangelical union that originated in the Great Awakening of the eighteenth century. In Scotland, the movement was forwarded in the first decade of the nineteenth century 
                        by the preaching and organizational efforts of the Haldane brothers, Robert (1764-1842) and James (1768-1851). Their organizing was associated with the rise 
                        of Scottish Congregationalism--the worship that the Ruskins favored in their first decades in London--and in their preaching, the Haldanes were partnered by English evangelicals, 
                        Charles Simeon (1759-1836) and Rowland Hill (1744-1833). Their itinerant preaching tours took in central Scotland, especially Perthshire, 
                        where John James Ruskin's sister, Jessie<!-- NAME AND LINK -->, eventually settled. Throughout central and northern Scotland, 
                        Robert funded the establishment of independent chapels or <hi rend="italic">tabernacles</hi>, including the three-thousand-seat 
                        Leith Walk Tabernacle in Edinburgh--a large place of worship that, like Hill's Surrey Chapel in Blackfriars, London, 
                        and the Reverend Dr. Edward Andrews's<!-- NAME AND LINK --> Beresford Chapel, which the Ruskins attended, was 
                        built to occupy a space between evangelicalism and the church establishment. Nonetheless, in Scotland, the Haldanes' evangelical fervor and criticism 
                        nettled the ministers of the Church of Scotland, whose pulpits the Haldanes and their associates often borrowed during their itinerant tours. 
                        Moreover, a social division prevailed between the populist movement and the more formally educated and conservative 
                        clergy of the established church, the kirk. (John James Ruskin's mother, Catherine, was the daughter of a minister of the Church of Scotland.) 
                        Robert Haldane, in particular, provoked conservatives early in his career by fomenting his advocacy of principles of the French Revolution. 
                        Eventually, the Haldanes splintered their movement owing to their conversion to Baptism, among other reasons, but this development appears only marginally 
                        connected to the Ruskins' experience of Congregational worship in the suburbs south of London 
                        (Brownell, "Robert and James Haldane and the Quest for Evangelical Union"; 
                        Lovegrove, &#x201C;Haldane, James Alexander [<date notBefore="1768" notAfter="1851">1768&#x2013;1851</date>]&#x201D;; 
                        Lovegrove, &#x201C;Haldane, Robert [<date notBefore="1764" notAfter="1842">1764&#x2013;1842</date>]&#x201D;).</p>
                    
                    <p>Despite the pull for unity, the Congregational wing of the early nineteenth century was firmly Calvinist in theology; and in keeping with that emphasis, 
                        the 1793 preface to volume one of the Evangelical Magazine proudly numbers among the "persons of evangelical principles in the kingdom" currently 
                        "three hundred thousand Calvinists" while perhaps nodding distantly to the Arminian Wesleyans among the "many others, savingly converted to God, 
                        who trust in the merits of Christ alone for salvation". Still, the magazine pronounces itself "devoid of personality and acrimonious reflections 
                        on any sect of professing Christians" and commits to including both "Churchmen and Dissenters" among the team of "twenty-four Ministers" who serve as editors and contributors. 
                        The editorial approach is to amass a "collected knowledge", drawn not only from the ecumenical panel of editors but also from readers, 
                        whose "judicious pieces" are invited for submission, "especially well-authenticated accounts of triumphant deaths, and remarkable providences". 
                        Thus, whereas the Ruskins were not magazine readers by necessity--since they ranked comfortably among those with "money to purchase", and "leisure to peruse, large volumes" 
                        denied to many among the magazine's target audience--John was exposed to an early Victorian model of crowdsourcing in print culture 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#PREFACEEVANGELICALMAG1793-01">&#x201C;Preface&#x201D; [<date when="1793-01">January 1793</date>]</ref>, 1-3).</p>
                    
                    <p>Addressing younger readers, "the children of religious parents", the magazine offers to "allure" them "through pleasure, 
                        into the paths of true wisdom" by means of entertaining genres such as "Biography, Memoirs, Diaries, Authentic Anecdotes, 
                        Striking Providences, and the expressions of Dying Chriſtians". Add to these life-writing genres the magazine's single feature of visual art, 
                        the engraved portrait that accompanies the lead biography in each issue, these attractions cannot fail to "arrest the mind" and "make a deep impression" on young persons, 
                        while the more exciting reading is tempered by sober instruction in "Ecclesiastical History, Jewish and Christian Antiquities, Sacred Criticism, 
                        Select Sentences, Short Poems, and Natural Philosophy". Thus, on the one hand "charmed" with the testimony of 
                        "the illustrious virtues and rich experience of those very people whom the world has treated with contempt"
                        and on the other hand "impressed with admiration of the works of God", young readers 
                        "will insensibly be led to examine the far superior displays of divine perfections, and the foundation of Christian hope and practice" 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#PREFACEEVANGELICALMAG1793-01">&#x201C;Preface&#x201D; [<date when="1793-01">January 1793</date>]</ref>).</p>
               <!-- END NEW MARKUP - CONTINUE BELOW-->
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine and Missionary Chronicle</hi></title>, the <orgName corresp="#LMS">London Missionary Society</orgName>, and Middle&#x2010;Class <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName></head>
                    
                    <p>In <date when="1823">1823</date>, with the start of the new series of the magazine, the spirit of pan&#x2010;evangelical catholicity of opinion and mission was reaffirmed, 
                        but with the acknowledgment that the commitment had undergone strain over the first three decades of publication. 
                        A <title type="essay" corresp="#RETROSPECTEVANGELICALMAG">&#x201C;Retrospect&#x201D;</title> published in the first issue of the new series 
                        admitted to the emergence of rival denominational publications on both the <orgName corresp="#EVANGELICALANGLICANISM">Anglican Evangelical</orgName> 
                        and <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregational</orgName> sides. In fact, the editorship of the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title> 
                        had itself become dominated by <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalists</orgName>, just as that sect held increasing sway over the organization 
                        that the magazine prominently represented, the <orgName corresp="#LMS">London Missionary Society (LMS)</orgName>
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RETROSPECTEVANGELICALMAG"><title type="essay" corresp="#RETROSPECTEVANGELICALMAG">&#x201C;Retrospect of the Former Series of the <hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi>&#x201D;</title></ref>, 1; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ALTHOLZRELIGIOUSPRESS"><persName corresp="JLA">Altholz</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#ALTHOLZRELIGIOUSPRESS"><hi rend="italic">Religious Press in Britain</hi></title></ref>, 46; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#THORNECONGREGATIONALMISSIONS"><persName corresp="#STHORNE">Thorne</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#THORNECONGREGATIONALMISSIONS"><hi rend="italic">Congregational Missions and the Making of an Imperial Culture</hi></title></ref>, 24).</p>
                <!-- START MORE NEW MARKUP -->
                    <p>Starting in 1813, the magazine expanded its title to the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine and Missionary Chronicle</hi></title>,
                        having already begun in previous issues to devote "a fifth of their pages to . . . religious information, under the title of <hi rend="italic">The Missionary Chronicle</hi>; 
                        which includes the Proceedings of all Societies instituted for the spread of the gospel" but especially the activities of the <orgName corresp="#LMS">LMS</orgName> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#PREFACEEVANGELICALMAG1813-12">&#x201C;Preface&#x201D; [<date when="1813-12-12">12 December 1813</date>]</ref>, iii&#x2013;iv). 
                        So prominent and detailed are the reports of LMS activity that the Ruskins&#x02BC; (or at least <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName>&#x02BC;s) regular reading of the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title> 
                        necessarily implies a strong interest in missionary work. Indeed, the enthusiasm surrounding foreign missions appears to account for a significant part of what tied the Ruskins to <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName> at this time, 
                        as documented by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s <ref type="apparatus" target="a_theme_apparatus.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRATHEME">&#x201C;a theme&#x201D;</title></ref>, which is a transcript or summary of a meeting for soliciting support of missionary work. 
                        The Ruskins' interest in missions can also be measured by the entire family&#x02BC;s eager reading of the journals and poetry of the <persName corresp="#RHBC">Reverend Reginald Heber, Bishop of <placeName corresp="#CALCUTTA">Calcutta</placeName></persName>. 
                        They were drawn to <persName corresp="#RHBC">Heber</persName>&#x02BC;s celebrity, just as they were impressed by the rising reputation of the 
                        <ref type="note" target="andrews_edward_note.php"><persName corresp="#EA">Reverend Dr. Edward Andrews</persName></ref>, who likewise encouraged the missionary cause.</p>
                    
                <p>The Ruskins were not uncharacteristic in being bound to <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName> by the excitement surrounding foreign missions. 
                    The spread of the gospel to foreign places was regarded as a key motivation driving the pan-evangelical spirit that united Congregationalism 
                    with the broader Evangelical Revival. As the Anglican and Methodist-leaning clergyman and missionary, Melville Horne (ca. 1761-1841), put the case 
                    for a unified British Protestant missionary enterprise: "I would not have him [the British missionary] indifferent to his own peculiarities, 
                    whether they respect the doctrines he receives as truth, or the points of ecclesiastical polity he considers most friendly to religion; 
                    but I would have him thoroughly sensible, that the success of his ministry rests not on points of separation, but on those wherein all godly men are united. . . . 
                    His object is to serve the Church Universal" (Letters on Missions [1794], quoted in Brownell, "Robert and James Haldane and the Quest for Evangelical Union", 7).</p>
                    <!-- END MORE NEW MARKUP -->
                    <p>Even more fundamental to the Ruskins' Christian position, the commitment to missionary labor was, as <persName corresp="#STHORNE">Susan Thorne</persName> argues, 
                        key to coalescing a middle&#x2010;class identity within <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName>. 
                        In the <date notBefore="1767" notAfter="1799">late eighteenth century</date>, <persName corresp="#STHORNE">Thorne</persName> explains, &#x201C;missions [both home and foreign] were a distinctively middle&#x2010;class alternative to gentry modes of authority, 
                    a means of controlling the lower orders at home as well as abroad that was in direct opposition to traditional or gentry forms of rule&#x201D;. 
                    &#x201C;This is not to say&#x201D;, she goes on, &#x201C;that the missionary language of opposition was antiauthoritarian, much less antinational&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#THORNECONGREGATIONALMISSIONS"><persName corresp="#STHORNE">Thorne</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#THORNECONGREGATIONALMISSIONS"><hi rend="italic">Congregational Missions and the Making of an Imperial Culture</hi></title></ref>, 39, 43). 
                    The latter caveat applies especially to the Ruskins, whose middle-class, evangelical identity had no stake in radical Dissent<!-- nor were the <date notBefore="1820" notAfter="1829">1820s</date> the revolutionary <date notBefore="1780" notAfter="1799">1780s and &#x02BC;90s</date>-->, 
                        and whose loyalties probably adhered more to a national Protestant and anti-Roman Catholic sense of mission than a sectarian Dissenter spirit. 
                        There appears no mention of the Ruskins attending the <placeName type="building" corresp="#PDMH">Protestant Dissenting Meeting House</placeName>, 
                        as a <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregational</orgName> chapel was called in their neighborhood of <placeName corresp="#CAMBERWELL">Camberwell</placeName> 
                        in the second half of the <date notBefore="1825" notAfter="1829">1820s</date>. That congregation was led by 
                        the <persName corresp="#WO">Reverend William Orme</persName> (<date notBefore="1787" notAfter="1830">1787&#x2013;1830</date>), 
                        who had parted ways with his first mentor, <persName corresp="#RHALDANE">Robert Haldane</persName>, in their Perth years, 
                        when Haldane was known both as &#x201C;one of <placeName corresp="#SCOTLAND">Scotland</placeName>&#x02BC;s leading advocates of foreign missionary expansion&#x201D; and as a fervent supporter of the French Revolution. 
                        Was <persName corresp="#WO">Orme</persName>&#x02BC;s respectability insufficient to dispel an air of working&#x2010;class Dissent surrounding a "Protestant Meeting House"? 
                        The Ruskins drove a longer distance to attend &#x201C;<persName corresp="#EA">Dr. Andrews</persName>&#x02BC;s Chapel&#x201D; as the Beresford Street Chapel was identified in the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WORMEDNB"><persName corresp="#AGORDON">Gordon</persName> and <persName corresp="#APB">Pimlott</persName>, <title type="dictionary_entry" corresp="#WORMEDNB">&#x201C;Orme, William [<date notBefore="1787" notAfter="1830">1787&#x2013;1830</date>]&#x201D;</title></ref>; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#THORNECONGREGATIONALMISSIONS"><persName corresp="#STHORNE">Thorne</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#THORNECONGREGATIONALMISSIONS"><hi rend="italic">Congregational Missions and the Making of an Imperial Culture</hi></title></ref>, 44 [on <persName corresp="#RHALDANE">Haldane</persName>], 58&#x2013;59 [on the increased working&#x2010;class presence in <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName> in the wake of the Evangelical Revival]; 
                    and see <ref type="apparatus" corresp="a_theme_apparatus.php#DISCUSSION"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRATHEME">&#x201C;a theme&#x201D;</title>: Discussion</ref>).</p>
                    
                    <p>Foreign missions and middle&#x2010;class identity were interdependent in <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName> in part because the <orgName corresp="#LMS">London Missionary Society</orgName> centered church activity on fundraising for the missions. 
                        The first <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregational</orgName> foreign missions (sent to the South Seas) were funded by a few wealthy patrons, as tended to be the case in other churches, and relied for success on the will of <persName type="scriptural" corresp="#CREATOR">God</persName>. 
                        Fervent but ill&#x2010;equipped and uninformed, these first missions fell apart; and consequently, 
                        the <orgName corresp="#LMS">LMS</orgName> reorganized fundraising on a broader basis, soliciting contributions both large and small, metropolitan and provincial, but most substantially from the urban middle class 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#THORNECONGREGATIONALMISSIONS"><persName corresp="#STHORNE">Thorne</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#THORNECONGREGATIONALMISSIONS"><hi rend="italic">Congregational Missions and the Making of an Imperial Culture</hi></title></ref>, 59&#x2013;62).
                        The fundraising and network of related activities were reported in detail in the <hi rend="italic">Missionary Chronicle</hi> section of the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title>. 
                        The published tables of contributions to the <orgName corresp="#LMS">LMS</orgName>, along with reports of activities in the local and regional auxiliary <orgName corresp="#LMS">LMS</orgName> societies, 
                        were calculated, as <persName corresp="#SSIVASUNDARAM">Sujit Sivasundaram</persName> argues, to inspire readers with a collective experience of evangelical zeal. 
                        The lists were observantly detailed, even listing contributors of used copies of the magazine to be sent to missionaries abroad, 
                        who duly reported back with their gratitude to receive reports from the parent and auxiliary organizations, not to mention their relief for fresh reading to palliate the tedium of their missions. 
                        Readers, in turn, felt they played a part in a worldwide evangelistic effort, regardless of their level of donation 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SIVASUNDARAMPERIODICAL"><persName corresp="#SSIVASUNDARAM">Sivasundaram</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#SIVASUNDARAMPERIODICAL">&#x201C;The Periodical as Barometer&#x201D;</title></ref>, 43&#x2013;48).</p>
                <here></here>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title>, the <orgName corresp="#LMS">London Missionary Society</orgName>, and Print Culture</head>
                    <p>This extensive outreach reported in the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title> and <hi rend="italic">Missionary Chronicle</hi> was characteristic 
                        of the <orgName corresp="#LMS">LMS</orgName>&#x02BC;s broader effort in print culture including and beyond the journal. 
                    As <persName corresp="#AJOHNSTON">Anna Johnston</persName> describes its aim, the <orgName corresp="#LMS">LMS</orgName> constructed &#x201C;a reading audience through its canny manipulation 
                    of textual and media technologies, a readership that would unite religious Britons in a common cause 
                    despite differences of class, region, gender, and age&#x201D; (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JOHNSTONMISSIONARYPUBLISHING"><title type="essay" corresp="#JOHNSTONMISSIONARYPUBLISHING">&#x201C;British Missionary Publishing&#x201D;</title></ref>, 30). 
                        <!--Thorne comments also on the breadth of social class comprised within Victorian <orgName corresp="#CONGREGATIONALISM">Congregationalism</orgName> while also remarking middle&#x2010;class members&#x02BC; shyness of their working&#x2010;class brethren.
                    The young <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName> was captured by the excitement, as evidenced by "a theme", 
                    which appears to record a speech or sermon at a meeting of a missionary society. 
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> was also vulnerable to the appeal of missionary celebrity, as shown by his starstruck enthusiasm 
                        for the poetry and journals of <persName corresp="#RHBC">Reginald Heber, Bishop of <placeName corresp="#CALCUTTA">Calcutta</placeName></persName> --></p>
                
                    <p><!--For one middle&#x2010;class family, in any case, the print features of the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title> probably influenced many productions by the ten&#x2010;year&#x2010;old boy 
                    whom <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> addressed as if he were destined for a sacred mission: &#x201C;You are blessed with a fine Capacity &#x0026; even Genius 
                    &#x0026; you owe it as a Duty to the author of your Being &#x0026; the giver of your Talents to cultivate your powers &#x0026; to use them 
                    in his Service &#x0026; for the benefit of your fellow Creatures. You may be doomed to enlighten a People by your Wisdon &#x0026; to adorn an age 
                    by your Learning&#x201D; and to &#x201C;aid the cause of Truth &#x0026; of Religion &#x0026; enable you to become in many ways a Benfactor to the Human Race&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="letter" corresp="#jjr_to_jr_1829-11-06">John James to John Ruskin, <date when="1829-11-06">6 November 1829</date></title>, in <title type="book" corresp="#RFL"><hi rend="italic">RFL</hi></title>, ed. <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd</persName>, 209&#x2013;10).-->For <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> as a young writer, 
                        the magazine appears to have served as a model in a variety of ways, although one might speculate that <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> meant for the publication to exert its unifying infuence within the home as well as beyond. 
                        regularly featured a section of poetry, 
                    albeit almost exclusively pious in subject matter; and in particular the January issue routinely 
                    printed poems for the New Year, which may have influenced <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s custom of composing a 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="new_years_poems.php">New Year&#x02BC;s ode</ref> to be fair&#x2010;copied 
                    and presented to his father on New Year&#x02BC;s.</p>
                    
                    <p>Feature articles mainly concerned religious topics but occasionally encompassed other areas of knowledge, such as natural history. 
                    A section of book reviews and brief notices of religious publications, including pious works for children, 
                    evidently informed the elder Ruskins&#x02BC; choice of some books for <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName>, since some notices correspond to books 
                    that he is known to have owned (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="boyhood_books_note#DESCRIPTIONS">Books Used by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> in His Youth&#x2014;Physical Descriptions</ref>).</p>
                    
                    <p>Prominent in each issue were lengthy obituaries and biographies of celebrated clergy, 
                    embellished by their engraved portraits, which supplied the sole graphic interest in each issue apart from the engraved banner. 
                    These biographies exposed the reader to peoples, landscapes, and customs of cultures around the world, 
                    albeit filtered through the perception of missionaries.</p>
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>