<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="goodspeed_charles_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main"><persName>Charles E. Goodspeed</persName> (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1950">1867&#x2013;1950</date>)</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="biographical">
                <head type="title"><persName corresp="#CG">Charles E. Goodspeed</persName> (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1950">1867&#x2013;1950</date>)</head>
                <p>Charles Eliot Goodspeed was significant both as a personal collector of Ruskin and as a seller to other Ruskin collectors, 
                    operating from his shop in Boston, Massachucetts, first opened in 1898 (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WHITEHILLGOODSPEED"><persName corresp="WMWHITEHILL">Whitehill</persName>, "Charles Eliot Goodspeed"</ref>, 261). 
                    In his memoir, Yankee Bookseller (1937), Goodspeed dates his Ruskin collecting from his youth in the 1880s, 
                    giving two reasons for "the spell of Ruskin". First, his books occupied, "if not the highest, at least high rank in modern English literature", 
                    for "although his style is criticised", he "is conceded to be a great prose writer". Second, for collectors, Ruskin's books presented outstanding 
                    "examples of book-making", excelling "principally in illustration" (pp. 263, 264).</p>
                
                <p>Ruskin's standard for "book-making" inspired Goodspeed not only as a collector and dealer but also as a publisher. 
                    In the 1939 edition of <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LEHMANNHAUPTBOOKINAMERICA">Lehmann&#x2010;Haupt, <title type="book" corresp="#LEHMANNHAUPTBOOKINAMERICA"><hi rend="italic">The Book in America</hi></title></ref>, 
                    Goodspeed is characterized as a disciple of Ruskin, and moved by many interests shared with the Stone and Kimball generation (p. 254), 
                    referring to the small art&#x2010;nouveau publishers of the 1890s, such as Stone &#x0026; Kimball in Chicago and 
                    Copeland &#x0026; Day in Boston, who had in common a determination to publish only works of literary quality and 
                    to bring out their selections in an attractive and distinctive format (p. 211). From the founding of his bookselling business 
                    through the early 1930s, Goodspeed realized these art-book ambitions in small publishing projects of his own, 
                    which were printed by the Merrymount Press (Mahoney, "C. E. Goodspeed and Company", 180).</p>
                
                <p>As a bookseller, Goodspeed describes himself as having served a steady--albeit, he wrote, a "fading"--New England market 
                    for Ruskin, which he traced to the influence of Ruskin's American friend and Harvard professor of the history of art, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" corresp="norton_charles_eliot_note.php"><persName corresp="#CEN">Charles Eliot Norton</persName></ref>. 
                    Goodspeed regarded himself as having cornered this New England market, 
                    having "bought more . . . [Ruskin first editions] abroad than any other American dealer". He "found no competition" 
                    in scouring London particularly for first editions of lesser-known Ruskin titles--the many books and pamphlets beyond 
                    "the nine-volume set comprising Modern Painters, The Seven Lamps of Architecture, and The Stones of Venice" 
                    that "was always on the shelves of the larger booksellers" (Yankee Bookseller, 262-63).</p>
                
                <p>Part of Goodspeed's interest in the lesser-known earlier and later publications of Ruskin was owing to the "minute attention" that the author gave to all aspects 
                    of book-making in such works as "Praeterita, Deucalion, Proserpina, and the other books issued [originally] in parts" 
                    (Yankee Bookseller, 264). The spell of these volumes for Goodspeed was not confined to their bibliographical appeal, however. 
                    Goodspeed was also a thorough and admiring student of Ruskin, as demonstrated by the scholarship supporting his descriptions of items in his <orgName corresp="#GOODSPEEDSBOOKSHOP">Goodspeed&#x02BC;s Book Shop</orgName> 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GOODSPEEDCAT"><title type="catalogue" corresp="#GOODSPEEDCAT"><hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Paintings, Drawings, and Manuscripts by John Ruskin</hi></title></ref> 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php#BUYERS"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1931</date>: The Buyers</ref>). 
                    Goodspeed also took a practical interest in Ruskin: as Whitehill remarks about the bookseller's retirement years, 
                    Goodspeed pursued the interests sponsored by Ruskin's works, such as collecting minerals, and tending to rare, wild plant species in his woodland garden 
                    ("Charles Eliot Goodspeed", 361).</p>
                
                <p>As a Ruskin collector in his own right, Goodspeed represented stateside the characteristics of the trend, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.html">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>, 
                    which committed collectors to seeking comprehensiveness in assembling an author's first editions and to preserving firsts in their original condition. 
                    In his memoir, Goodspeed comments on his "mistake" as a young collector in causing his fledgling Ruskin collection to be uniformly rebound, 
                    instead of preserving the items' original state. He therefore disposed of that false start and rebuilt his Ruskin collection 
                    on "the primary rule that pamphlet issues of all kinds, if intended for sale to collectors, 
                    must be preserved in their original form" (Yankee Booksellder, 261-62). Eventually, his comprehensive collection reached over five hundred items 
                    of first editions along with "all the authorized editions of Ruskin and his biographies", a count comparable with the scope 
                    of a contemporaneous American comprehensive Ruskin collection assembled by 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="adam_r_b_note.php"><persName corresp="#RBA">R. B. Adam II</persName> (1863-1940)</ref> and his father by adoption, 
                    <persName corresp="#RBAI">Robert Borthwick Adam I</persName> (1833-1904). Goodspeed donated his collection to Wellesley College, 
                    "in consideration of Ruskin's interest in the education of girls and from the fact that both of [his] daughters were graduated" from that institution (Yankee Bookseller, 265). 
                    He made the initial donation in 1920-21, which along with the print collection included Ruskin drawings, proofs of engravings touched by Ruskin, marked printer proofs, 
                    and other unique items (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WELLESLEYPRESREPORT_1919-21">Wellesley College, "Annual Reports . . . 1919-21"</ref>, 45-46). 
                    Goodspeed continued to contribute to the collection from the 1920s through the 1940s, the collection presently totaling nearly nine hundred items.</p>
                
                <p>Goodspeed knew R. B. Adam only by reputation, not as a client. The American Ruskin collectors whom Goodspeed 
                    singles out in his memoir as his customers and memorable Ruskin collectors included <persName corresp="#CT">Caleb Benjamin Tillinghast</persName> (1843-1909), 
                    librarian of the Massachusetts State Library; and John G. Winant (1889-1947), 
                    governor of New Hampshire and ambassador to the United Kingdom. As a Boston bookseller, 
                    Goodspeed was well positioned not only to supply New Englanders with Ruskin items but also to acquire 
                    Ruskin rarities connected with the region--for example, acquisitions from the estate of Ruskin's friend, 
                    <persName corresp="#FALEXANDER">Francesca Alexander</persName>, which he also eventually donated to Wellesley  
                    (Yankee Bookseller, 262, 265; and see 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BOLTONTILLINGHAST"><persName corresp="#CKBOLTON">Bolton</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#BOLTONTILLINGHAST">&#x201C;Memoir of <persName corresp="#CT">Caleb Benjamin Tillinghast</persName>&#x201D;</title></ref>).</p>
                
                <p>One of Goodspeed's most significant legacies proved to be his highly competitive role in the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date></ref>, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1931</date></ref>, and the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_pictures_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Pictures and Drawings, <date when="1930">1931</date></ref>. 
                    A key figure in the provenance of manuscripts edited in ERM, Goodspeed took a particular interest in the early as well as late manuscripts, 
                    a strategy corresponding to his approach as a dealer to published Ruskin items--that is, seeking out what was then considered non-canonical Ruskin, 
                    for which competition was less keen. In this respect, he was also drawn to items that matched his own interests as a collector; for example, 
                    he particularly treasured the manuscript of Ruskin's autobiography, which he kept for himself: 
                    "It is for the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>", he wrote of his acquisitions from the 1930 Sotheby's sales, 
                    "that I have most regard. I had bought it when published in periodical form, looking forward to each succeeding number 
                    with a keener interest than the modern reader would have for the weekly installment of a story by Agatha Christie 
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Evening Post</hi>. . . . I cannot imagine a temptation sufficent to make me part with Ruskin's portrait of Rose La Touche 
                    and his manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>" (Yankee Bookseller, 269). In 1933, returning to Wellesley 
                    to give a talk at the library, he concentrated on "Ruskin's youth" and "his love in later life for Rose La Touche", 
                    illustrating the talk with "his own collection of early Ruskin drawings and other material illustrative of his life", 
                    including Ruskin's portrait drawing of Rose, and George Richmond's portrait drawing of Ruskin 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WELLESLEYPRESREPORT_1932-33">Wellesley College, "Annual Reports . . . 1932-33"</ref>, 42-43). 
                    Goodspeed's substantial scholarship in Ruskin, and his particular affection for the early manuscripts, is reflected in his circa 1931-32 catalogue, 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GOODSPEEDCAT"><orgName corresp="#GOODSPEEDSBOOKSHOP">Goodspeed&#x02BC;s Book Shop</orgName>, <title type="catalogue" corresp="#GOODSPEEDCAT"><hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of Paintings, Drawings, and Manuscripts by John Ruskin; To which is added a description of Ruskin's Celestial Globe and of a few Books from his Library at Brantwood</hi></title></ref> 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php#BUYERS"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1931</date>: Buyers</ref>).</p>
                
                <p>Within only four months of the London auction, Goodspeed sold most of his acquisitions from the <date when="1930">1930</date> 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library</ref> 
                    to Yale University Library. He appears also to given Yale first offering of his acquisitions from the <date when="1931">1931</date> 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library</ref>, 
                    but Yale purchased only two items, and Goodspeed listed remaining items (other than those he wished to retain for his private collection) in his 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GOODSPEEDCAT"><title type="catalogue" corresp="#GOODSPEEDCAT"><hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Paintings, Drawings, and Manuscripts by John Ruskin</hi></title></ref> (n.d., probably ca. 1931-32). 
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> drawings to <persName corresp="#JHW">Whitehouse</persName>, 
                    and <persName corresp="#JHW">Whitehouse</persName> is believed to have acquired this lot in <date when="1936">1936</date> (RBB 138&#x2013;39).lingered on his hands, but many of the items finally were sold to Princeton University Library in 1939.</p>
                
                <p>The time did come when Goodspeed faced a situation he had said he could not imagine, one forcing him to part with his manuscript of Praeterita and other personal Ruskin treasures. 
                    The circumstances proved even more unthinkable, the devastating damage to his collection by fire. 
                    After publishing his memoir of book dealing and collecting in 1937 and retiring to Shirley, Massachusetts, 
                    Goodspeed's house burned in February 1941 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WHITEHILLGOODSPEED"><persName corresp="WMWHITEHILL">Whitehill</persName>, "Charles Eliot Goodspeed"</ref>, 361, 363; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#YALECOLLECTION"><persName corresp="#CBHOGAN">Hogan</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#YALECOLLECTION">&#x201C;Yale Collection of the Manuscripts of John Ruskin&#x201D;</title></ref>, 69). 
                    Portions of his personal library were destroyed and other portions severely damaged. The Praeterta manuscript survived, though damaged, 
                    and in March 1941 it became the first of the surviving manuscripts that Goodspeed presented to Yale University Library. 
                    Other gifts to Yale as the result of this catastrophe consisted largely of items remaining in Goodspeed's possession from the 1931 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library</ref>. 
                    The damage affecting individual manuscripts of early works is discussed in connection with particular items throughout ERM.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>