<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="goodspeed_charles_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main"><persName>Charles E. Goodspeed</persName> (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1950">1867&#x2013;1950</date>)</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="biographical">
                <head type="title"><persName corresp="#CG">Charles E. Goodspeed</persName> (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1950">1867&#x2013;1950</date>)</head>
                
                <p>Charles Eliot Goodspeed was significant both as a personal collector of Ruskin and as a seller to other Ruskin collectors, 
                    operating from his shop in Boston, Massachucetts, first opened in 1898 (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WHITEHILLGOODSPEED"><persName corresp="WMWHITEHILL">Whitehill</persName>, "Charles Eliot Goodspeed"</ref>, 261). 
                    In his memoir, Yankee Bookseller (1937), Goodspeed dates his Ruskin collecting from his youth in the 1880s, 
                    giving two reasons for "the spell of Ruskin". First, his books occupied, "if not the highest, at least high rank in modern English literature", 
                    for "although his style is criticised", he "is conceded to be a great prose writer". Second, for collectors, Ruskin's books presented outstanding 
                    "examples of book-making", excelling "principally in illustration" but also in the "minute attention" that the author gave to all aspects 
                    of book-making in such works as "Praeterita, Deucalion, Proserpina, and the other books issued [originally] in parts" (pp. 263, 264). 
                    It was perhaps the bibliophile's enchantment with the illustrations in Ruskin's books that caused Goodspeed to take a special interest in Ruskin's own drawings.</p>
                
                <p>Ruskin's standard for "book-making" inspired Goodspeed also as a publisher. In the 1939 edition of 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LEHMANNHAUPTBOOKINAMERICA"><title type="book" corresp="#LEHMANNHAUPTBOOKINAMERICA"><hi rend="italic">The Book in America</hi></title></ref>, 
                    Hellmut Lehmann&#x2010;Haupt characterized Goodspeed as a disciple of Ruskin, and moved by many interests shared with the Stone and Kimball generation (p. 254), 
                    referring to the small art&#x2010;nouveau publishers of the 1890s, such as Stone &#x0026; Kimball in Chicago and 
                    Copeland &#x0026; Day in Boston. These publishers had in common the determination to publish only works of literary quality and 
                    to bring out their selections in an attractive and distinctive format (p. 211). From the founding of his bookselling business 
                    through the early 1930s, Goodspeed realized these art-book ambitions in small publishing projects of his own, 
                    which were printed by the Merrymount Press (Mahoney, "C. E. Goodspeed and Company", 180).</p>
                
                <p>The spell of Ruskin for Goodspeed was not confined to bibliographical appeal, however. Goodspeed was a thorough and admiring student of Ruskin's ideas, 
                    as demonstrated by the scholarship he brought to a not insignificant bibliographical contribution to Ruskin studies in the 1930s, his 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GOODSPEEDCAT"><title type="catalogue" corresp="#GOODSPEEDCAT"><hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Paintings, Drawings, and Manuscripts by John Ruskin</hi></title></ref>, 
                    published by <orgName corresp="#GOODSPEEDSBOOKSHOP">Goodspeed&#x02BC;s Book Shop</orgName> 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php#BUYERS"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1931">1931</date>: The Buyers</ref>). 
                    Goodspeed's approach to thinking through Ruskin appears to have been primarily biographical. 
                    His most cherished collector's possession was the manuscript of Praeterita; 
                    and according to a record of a talk he gave at Wellesley College Library in 1933, 
                    he concentrated on "Ruskin's youth" and "his love in later life for Rose La Touche", 
                    illustrating the talk with "his own collection of early Ruskin drawings and other material illustrative of his life", 
                    including Ruskin's portrait drawing of Rose La Touche, and one of George Richmond's portrait drawings of Ruskin 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WELLESLEYPRESREPORT_1932-33">Wellesley College, "Annual Reports . . . 1932-33"</ref>, 42-43). 
                    In Yankee Bookseller, he planned but had to defer giving "the story of Ruskin and Rose La Touche, prefaced by an account of Ruskin's 
                    marriage with Euphemia Gray" (p. 268).</p>
                
                <p>Goodspeed also took a practical interest in Ruskin: as Walter Muir Whitehill remarks about the bookseller's retirement years, 
                    Goodspeed pursued interests sponsored by Ruskin's works, such as tending to rare, wild plant species in his woodland garden 
                    ("Charles Eliot Goodspeed", 361). His most regretted loss at the final Brantwood estate sale in July 1931 was Ruskin's 
                    mineral cabinet, an "item [that] excited me greatly, for it revived my early interest in mineralogical specimens, never entirely lost" 
                    (Yankee Bookseller 269).</p>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="NEWENGLANDCOLLECTING">
                    <head type="section"><persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName> and the New England Ruskin Collecting Community</head>
                    
                    <p>As one of most prominent Ruskin collectors stateside in the first half of the twentieth century, 
                        Goodspeed exhibited characteristics of the trend for 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.html">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>, 
                        which committed collectors to assembling comprehensive runs of an author's first editions in their original condition. 
                        In his memoir, Goodspeed comments on his "mistake" as a young collector in causing his fledgling Ruskin collection to be uniformly rebound, 
                        instead of preserving the items in their original state. He therefore disposed of that false start and rebuilt his Ruskin collection 
                        on "the primary rule that pamphlet issues of all kinds, if intended for sale to collectors, 
                        must be preserved in their original form". Eventually, Goodspeed's Ruskin collection reached over five hundred items 
                        of first editions along with "all the authorized editions of Ruskin and his biographies" (Yankee Booksellder, 261-62, 265). 
                        The volume count is comparable in scope with a contemporaneous comprehensive Ruskin collection assembled by the American collector, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="adam_r_b_note.php"><persName corresp="#RBA">R. B. Adam II</persName> (1863-1940)</ref> 
                        and his father by adoption, <persName corresp="#RBAI">Robert Borthwick Adam I</persName> (1833-1904).</p>
                    
                    <p>As a bookseller as well as collector, Goodspeed held to the standard of "Ruskin firsts", 
                        of which he believed he "bought more . . . abroad than any other American dealer". As a Ruskin specialist, 
                        he distinguished his shop from the "larger booksellers", who could be counted on to stock 
                        "the nine-volume set comprising Modern Painters, The Seven Lamps of Architecture, and The Stones of Venice" 
                        in a uniform size with illustrations--the latter caveat obscuring what the initiated Ruskin collector would recognize, 
                        that these sets were made up with later editions of Modern Painters I and Modern Painters II rather than the first editions, 
                        not because the firsts were a different size than the other volumes, but because the firsts were extremely rare. 
                        Scouring London for Ruskin firsts, Goodspeed says that, other than the prized Modern Painters I and II and 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1850_note.php"><title type="book" corresp="#JRPOEMS1850"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi></title> (<date when="1850">1850</date>) by J.R.</ref>, 
                        he "found no competition" for first editions of lesser-known Ruskin titles--the dozens of books and pamphlets beyond 
                        nine-volume sets "always on the shelves of the larger booksellers" (Yankee Bookseller, 262-63). 
                        The alertness for early and late Ruskin titles appears to have marked Goodspeed's strategy as a buyer and seller, 
                        not only for print but also for manuscripts. His knowledge about the full scope of Ruskin's writing and bibliography 
                        probably made him unique among American dealers, and certainly the single most influential force in the provenance of manuscripts constituting ERM.</p>
                    
                    <p>Goodspeed credited the influence of Ruskin's American friend and Harvard professor of the history of art, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" corresp="norton_charles_eliot_note.php"><persName corresp="#CEN">Charles Eliot Norton</persName> (1827-1908)</ref> 
                        for the "mild local interest in Ruskin then prevalent" in the first third of the twentieth century, 
                        and he believed his own "earnestness" contributed to upholding the "fading Ruskin tradition" at least in New England. 
                        (He hoped that the chapter on Ruskin in his memoir would "arouse a new interest in Ruskin, at least with collectors", 
                        when the author had become so "strangely neglected today".) While he knew the Ruskin collector R. B. Adam only by reputation, not as a client, 
                        Goodspeed supplied other important American collectors, including 
                        <persName corresp="#CT">Caleb Benjamin Tillinghast</persName> (1843-1909), 
                        librarian of the Massachusetts State Library; and John G. Winant (1889-1947), 
                        governor of New Hampshire and ambassador to the United Kingdom  
                        (Yankee Bookseller, 262, 264-65; and see 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BOLTONTILLINGHAST"><persName corresp="#CKBOLTON">Bolton</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#BOLTONTILLINGHAST">&#x201C;Memoir of <persName corresp="#CT">Caleb Benjamin Tillinghast</persName>&#x201D;</title></ref>).</p>
                    
                    <p>In 1920-21, Goodspeed donated his personal Ruskin collection to Wellesley College, "in consideration of Ruskin's interest in the education of girls 
                        and from the fact that both of [his] daughters were graduated" from that institution (Yankee Bookseller, 265). 
                        Along with the print holdings, the collection included Ruskin drawings, proofs of engravings touched by Ruskin, marked printer proofs, 
                        and other unique items (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WELLESLEYPRESREPORT_1919-21">Wellesley College, "Annual Reports . . . 1919-21"</ref>, 45-46). 
                        Goodspeed continued to contribute to the collection from the 1920s through the 1940s, the collection presently totaling nearly nine hundred items.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="GOODSPEEDANDJRMSS">
                    <head type="section"><persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName> and the Acquisition of Ruskin Manuscripts</head>
                    
                    <p>As a Boston dealer, Goodspeed was well positioned to acquire Ruskin rarities connected with the region--for example, 
                        acquisitions from the estate of Ruskin's friend, <persName corresp="#FALEXANDER">Francesca Alexander</persName>, which he gave to Wellesley. 
                        The thoughtful variety and scope of his collection when donated to Wellesley shows, however, that he had long searched beyond used book trading 
                        to build up his holdings. His most significant opportunity to contibute stateside to Ruskin archives came in 1930-31, 
                        when he played a highly competitive role in the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date></ref>, the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1931">1931</date></ref>, and the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_pictures_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Pictures and Drawings, <date when="1931">1931</date></ref>.</p>
                    
                    <p>Goodspeed's strategy as a buyer in these sales of manuscripts and drawings appears to have corresponded to his approach as a dealer 
                        in printed Ruskin items--that is, to seize on what was then considered non-canonical Ruskin, 
                        for which competition could be expected to be less keen. (His agent at these sales, the London firm, B. F. Stevens &#x0026; Brown, 
                        assured their other major Ruskin client, W. H. Whitehouse, that the firm could work with mutual advantage for both Goodspeed and Whitehouse.<!-- SOURCE -->) 
                        It seems likely, however, that, while avoiding squaring off against competitors for the canonical 
                        Ruskin manuscripts like Whitehouse, Goodspeed took on considerable risk. Not only had the Great Depression begun in America, 
                        but, even before the crash, interest in Ruskin was declining. In 1929, R. B. Adam had donated his Ruskin collection to Yale, 
                        after unsuccessfully attempting for six years to sell the collection through the major New York dealer, A. S. W. Rosenbach 
                        (see <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="adam_r_b_note.php"><persName corresp="#RBA">R. B. Adam II</persName> [1863-1940]</ref>).</p>
                    
                    <p>At first, Goodspeed was fortunate. Within only four months of the <date when="1930">1930</date> 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library</ref>, 
                        he sold most of his acquisitions to Yale University Library. He had less luck following the <date when="1931">1931</date> 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library</ref> and 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_pictures_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Pictures and Drawings</ref>. 
                        A quotation of items from the 1931 manuscript sale on file at the Beinecke Library suggests that Goodspeed 
                        offered first chance at these items to Yale, but the library purchased only two items
                        (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php#YALE1931"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library: <persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName>, the 1931 Acquisitions, and <orgName corresp="#YALEUNIVLIBRARY">Yale University Library</orgName></ref>. 
                        He then compiled the offerings in the scholarly and elegantly produced <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GOODSPEEDCAT"><title type="catalogue" corresp="#GOODSPEEDCAT"><hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Paintings, Drawings, and Manuscripts by John Ruskin</hi></title></ref>, 
                        which must have entailed a significant expense in itself. One recipient of the catalogue in 1932<!-- CHECK --> was <persName corresp="#JHW">J. H. Whitehouse</persName>, 
                        whom Goodspeed hoped to interest especially in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> drawings, though <persName corresp="#JHW">Whitehouse</persName> 
                        is believed to have delayed acquiring a group of these drawings until <date when="1936">1936</date> (RBB 138&#x2013;39). 
                        In Yankee Bookseller, published in 1937, Goodspeed's 
                        observation of declining interest in Ruskin, and his bid to revive interest at least among collectors, 
                        must have been prompted by the slowing sales of his Sotheby's acquisitions. Not until 1939 were many of the items in Goodspeed's 
                        <title type="catalogue" corresp="#GOODSPEEDCAT"><hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi></title> finally were sold to Princeton University Library 
                        (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php#YALE1931"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library: <persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName> and <orgName corresp="#PRINCETONLIBRARY">Princeton University Library</orgName></ref>).</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="YALE1941">
                    <head type="section">The Damage by Fire to the <persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName> Ruskin Collection and Its Donation to <orgName corresp="#YALEUNIVLIBRARY">Yale University Library</orgName></head>
                    
                    <p>A decade after the <orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> sales, the items remaining unsold 
                        from <persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName>&#x02BC;s <title type="catalogue" corresp="#GOODSPEEDCAT"><hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi></title> 
                        along with his personal collection were damaged or destroyed when his house in Shirley, Massachusetts, caught fire on <date when="1941-02-22">22 February 1941</date> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WHITEHILLGOODSPEED"><persName corresp="WMWHITEHILL">Whitehill</persName>, "Charles Eliot Goodspeed"</ref>, 361, 363). 
                        Salvaging viable remains of books and manuscripts from the catastrophe, <persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName> donated 
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> manuscripts to <orgName corresp="#YALEUNIVLIBRARY">Yale University Library</orgName> in the hope that they could be preserved in spite of damage. 
                        He chose the Sterling Library because "it was his wish to complete Yale's holdings of the available major Ruskin manuscripts, 
                        so many of which had passed through his hands on their way to New Haven" 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#YALECOLLECTION"><persName corresp="#CBHOGAN">Hogan</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#YALECOLLECTION">&#x201C;Yale Collection of the Manuscripts of John Ruskin&#x201D;</title></ref>, 69).</p>
                
                    <p>The first of these gifts, sent soon after the fire in <date when="1941-03">March 1941</date>, was the manuscript of <title type="book" corresp="#JRPRAETERITA">Praeterita</title>, 
                        which he had kept for himself from the 1930 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale</ref>. 
                        Before the fire, in Yankee Bookseller, he confessed: "It is for the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> 
                        that I have most regard. I had bought . . . [the autobiography] when published in periodical form, looking forward to each succeeding number 
                        with a keener interest than the modern reader would have for the weekly installment of a story by Agatha Christie 
                        in the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Evening Post</hi>. . . . I cannot imagine a temptation sufficent to make me part with Ruskin's portrait of Rose La Touche 
                        and his manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>" (Yankee Bookseller, 269). When that time did come, 
                        not as a temptation, but as an unthinkable catastrophe, Goodspeed was devastated with remorse. Writing to 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="tinker_c_b_note.php">Chauncey B. Tinker (1876-1963)</ref>, the keeper of rare books at Yale University Library, 
                        whether he would "care to be bothered with material in such damaged condition", Goodspeed thought it "fitting that what is left of it should be preserved there. . . . 
                        I myself do not feel like putting it in shape for better preservation. . . . 
                        I hardly need to say how keenly I regret that, as the custodian of a manuscript of this kind, I have been so negligent in properly caring for it. 
                        We think of these things, however, when it is too late". In a subsequent letter, Goodspeed rejoiced in having recovered more of the manuscript, 
                        but two octavo volumes had perished altogether 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GOODSPEEDALSBEINECKEPRAETERITA"><title type="letter" corresp="#goodspeed_to_tinker_1941-03-25">Goodspeed to Tinker, 25 March 1941</title> and <title type="letter" corresp="#goodspeed_to_tinker_1941-03-31">31 March 1941</title></ref>).</p>
                    
                    <p>For Goodspeed's other gifts to Yale as the result of fire damage, which consisted largely of items remaining in Goodspeed's possession from the 1931 Sotheby's acquistions, see 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php#YALE1941"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1931">1931</date>: The Damage by Fire to <persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName>&#x02BC;s <date when="1931">1931</date> Acquisitions and Their Donation to <orgName corresp="#YALEUNIVLIBRARY">Yale University Library</orgName></ref>. 
                        The damage affecting individual manuscripts of early works is discussed in connection with particular items throughout ERM.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>