<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="grindlay_r_m_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Robert Melville Grindlay</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="biographical">
                <head type="title">Robert Melville Grindlay (1786-1877)</head>
                <p>Grindlay was an amateur artist, whose drawings formed the basis of engravings published by <!-- link to note -->Smith, Elder &#x0026; Company. 
                    Grindlay's Scenery, Costumes and Architecture, Chiefly on the Western Side of India 
                    was published in engraving and aquatint, in part by Rudolph Ackermann and in full by Smith, Elder, between 1826 and 1830. 
                    A sketch by Grindlay from travel in Italy also was worked into an engraving for Smith, Elder's annual, 
                    Friendship's Offering, in 1830 (see <!--note to apparatus-->Saltzburg.</p>
                
                <p>From 1803, Grindlay served in the East India Company's military service (the Bombay Native Infantry) and other official positions, 
                    which enabled him to travel extensively throughout western India. Retiring from the service in 1817 and returning to England, 
                    in 1828 (?) Grindlay founded a London agency, Leslie &#x0026; Grindlay, for shipping and passenger travel to and from India. 
                    The agency, which eventually grew into a major Anglo-Indian banking firm, was situated in Birchin Lane, 
                    near the second location of Smith, Elder, at 65, Cornhill (Rohatgi and Parlett, Indian Life and Landscape by Western Artists, 213-16). 
                    As both firms dealt in Anglo-Indian travel and trade, it seems likely that Grindlay and Alexander Elder were brought together by their shared artistic as well as business interests.
                </p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>