<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="hypothyroidism_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Hypothyroidism in the Alps</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#BSP">Brianna Poch&#x00E9;</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="contextual">
                <head type="title">Hypothyroidism in the <geogName corresp="#ALPS">Alps</geogName></head>
                <p>Hypothyroidism is defined as a condition of &#x201C;mild to severe impairment of physical and mental development due to an untreated deficiency of thyroid hormones&#x201D;. 
                    Historically, the condition has been endemic to regions with diets deficient in iodine. The resulting disorders include goiter (enlargement of the thyroid gland) 
                    and the severe stunting of development that in the <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth century</date> was called <hi rend="italic">cretinism</hi>. 
                    Many Alpine regions are severely deficient in iodine, with the result that, prior to the <date notBefore="1901" notAfter="2000">twentieth century</date>, travelers came to associate <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Switzerland</placeName> with these disorders. 
                    Yet regional variations in soil geology and water supply, along with such accidental circumstances as access to an iodine&#x2010;rich salt mine, 
                    led to sharply localized differences in the incidence of goiter and cretinism in parts <placeName corresp="#FRANCE">France</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Switzerland</placeName>, and <placeName corresp="#ITALY">Italy</placeName>, 
                    which mystified researchers attempting to isolate a cause. Not until the <date notBefore="1920" notAfter="1929">1920s</date> did researchers successfully link the disorders with iodine deficiency 
                    and undertake a program in <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Switzerland</placeName> to supplement the deficiency in diet, which produced dramatic improvements in health 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#PAPAGEORGOPOULOUHYPOTHYROIDISM"><persName corresp="#CPAPAGEORGOPOULOU">Papageorgopoulou</persName>, <persName corresp="#KSTAUB">Staub</persName>, and <persName corresp="#FRUHLI">R&#x00FC;hli</persName>, <title type="article" corresp="#PAPAGEORGOPOULOUHYPOTHYROIDISM">&#x201C;Hypothyroidism in Switzerland&#x201D;</title></ref>, 77, 80, 82).</p>
                
                <p>On the evidence of <note type="biographical" target="richardson_mary_note.php"><persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName></note>&#x02BC;s diary, the Ruskins first came face to face 
                    with victims of severe goiter and cretinism&#x2014;at least, on a widespread scale&#x2014;in <placeName corresp="#SION">Sion</placeName>, the chief municipality of <placeName corresp="#CANTONVALAIS">Canton Valais</placeName>, where she, <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName>, and <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> on a walk through town 
                    found it &#x201C;dirty and desolate looking&#x201D;, and in <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary</persName>&#x02BC;s view &#x201C;the people all miserable creatures, two out of three hav[ing] goitre very bad, and many of them . . . idiots&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48">Diary of <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName>, <date when="1833">1833</date></ref>, 69). 
                    <placeName corresp="#CANTONVALAIS">Valais</placeName> was indeed known for these afflictions: in <date when="1800">1800</date>, <persName corresp="#NBE">Napoleon</persName> ordered a census, which counted 4,000 cretins among 70,000 inhabitants of the canton; 
                    and as late as <date when="1920">1920</date>, a national survey of young men&#x02BC;s eligibility for military service discovered that, in the southern half of the country, 
                    the greatest density of disqualifying goiter lay around <placeName corresp="#SION">Sion</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#MARTIGNY">Martigny</placeName> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#PAPAGEORGOPOULOUHYPOTHYROIDISM"><persName corresp="#CPAPAGEORGOPOULOU">Papageorgopoulou</persName>, <persName corresp="#KSTAUB">Staub</persName>, and <persName corresp="#FRUHLI">R&#x00FC;hli</persName>, <title type="article" corresp="#PAPAGEORGOPOULOUHYPOTHYROIDISM">&#x201C;Hypothyroidism in Switzerland&#x201D;</title></ref>, 80, 82). 
                    Guidebooks published in the <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date> warned British travelers about the phenomenon, particularly in connection with the <geogName corresp="#RHONE">Rh&#x00F4;ne</geogName> valley in the <placeName corresp="#CANTONVALAIS">Valais</placeName> 
                    (e.g., <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#EBELTRAVELLERSGUIDE"><persName corresp="#JGE">Ebel</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#EBELTRAVELLERSGUIDE"><hi rend="italic">Traveller&#x02BC;s Guide through Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 361; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><persName corresp="#JM">Murray</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 156).</p>
                
                <p>In guidebooks such as these, <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth&#x2010;century</date> British writers compared environmental causes that were commonly proposed for hypothyroidism, 
                    and finding the evidence inconsistent advanced their own theories, confident in the shrewdness of their personal observations. 
                    In <date notBefore="1837" notAfter="1829">1827&#x2013;29</date>, <persName corresp="#WBI">William Brockedon</persName> favored the idea that the disorders arose from &#x201C;dirty habits&#x201D;: 
                    &#x201C;The author&#x201D;, <persName corresp="#WBI">Brockedon</persName> wrote about himself, &#x201C;has adopted an opinion, arising from extensive observation, that one of the chief causes of these complaints 
                    is to be found in the dirty habits of the communities afflicted. This is an opinion entertained by the clean and healthy mountaineers, 
                    who are free from goitre, and by the inhabitants of those valleys where personal cleanliness is regarded: 
                    for this the <orgName corresp="#ANZASCANS">Anzascans</orgName> [i.e., inhabitants of <geogName corresp="#ANZASCA">Anzasca</geogName> valley], a race of fine men and beautiful women, 
                    are remarkable; whilst the dirty wretches where the affliction is found, sty all the winter with their cattle, 
                    seldom or never change their clothes, and dread water as if their disease were hydrophobia. Three or four filthy generations produce goitre, 
                    and it requires as many of clean habits to remove the punishment for their foul offences&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BROCKEDONILLUSTRATIONS"><title type="book" corresp="#BROCKEDONILLUSTRATIONS"><hi rend="italic">Illustrations of the Passes of the Alps</hi></title></ref>, 
                    <geogName corresp="#SIMPLON">&#x201C;The Simplon&#x201D;</geogName>, ??).<!-- p. no. needed --></p>
                
                <p>Writing in <date when="1838">1838</date>, <persName corresp="#JM">John Murray III</persName> insisted for his part that &#x201C;careful attention to the circumstances accompanying its [goiter&#x02BC;s] appearance 
                    will show that it is connected with the condition of the atmosphere, and is found in low, warm, and moist situations, 
                    at the bottom of valleys, where a stagnation of water occurs, and where the summer exhalations and autumnal fogs arising from it 
                    are not carried off by a free circulation of air. It is found in places where the valley is confined, and shut in, as it were&#x2014;where 
                    a free draft is checked by its sides being clothed with wood, or by a sudden bend occurring in its direction&#x2014;where, at the same time, 
                    the bottom is subject to the overflowings of a river, or to extensive artificial irrigation. The conjecture which derives the disease 
                    from breathing an atmosphere of this kind, not liable to be purified by fresh currents of air to carry off the vapours, 
                    is, perhaps, the one most deserving of consideration&#x201D;. It was surely no accident that this list of environmental conditions matches exactly 
                    (one wonders if even uniquely matches) those surrounding <placeName corresp="#MARTIGNY">Martigny</placeName>, where the <geogName corresp="#RHONE">Rh&#x00F4;ne</geogName> makes an almost ninety&#x2010;degree bend, 
                    and the broad flat of the valley formed a marsh between the extraordinary heights of the <geogName corresp="#BERNESEALPS">Bernese Alps</geogName> on the north side and the <geogName corresp="#PENNINEALPS">Pennine Alps</geogName> on the south. 
                    In the section of the guidebook devoted to <placeName corresp="#MARTIGNY">Martigny</placeName>, <persName corresp="#MURRAY">Murray</persName> circularly applies his general theory to explain the prevalence of cretinism in the locale 
                    that probably inspired the theory in the first place 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><persName corresp="#JM">Murray</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, lix, 156).</p>
                
                <p>The language used by such writers to describe the effects of hypothyroidism is often blunt in its moralizing implications; 
                    no lessons in sympathetic imagination with disability were taken from <persName corresp="#WW">Wordsworth</persName>&#x02BC;s <title type="poem" corresp="#WORDSWORTHIDIOTBOY">&#x201C;The Idiot Boy&#x201D;</title>. 
                    For <persName corresp="#WBI">Brockedon</persName>, cretins are &#x201C;objects of disgust and pity&#x201D;; for <persName corresp="#JM">Murray</persName>, &#x201C;[t]he cretin is an idiot&#x2014;a melancholy spectacle&#x2014;a creature who may almost be said to rank a step below a human being. 
                    There is vacancy in his countenance; his head is disproportionately large; his limbs are stunted or crippled; he cannot articulate his words with distinctness; 
                    and there is scarcely any work which he is capable of executing. He spends his days basking in the sun, and, from its warmth, appears to derive great gratification. 
                    When a stranger appears, he becomes a clamorous and importunate beggar, assailing him with a ceaseless chattering; 
                    and the traveller is commonly glad to be rid of his hideous presence at the expense of a batz&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BROCKEDONILLUSTRATIONS"><title type="book" corresp="#BROCKEDONILLUSTRATIONS"><hi rend="italic">Illustrations of the Passes of the Alps</hi></title></ref>, 
                    <geogName corresp="#SIMPLON">&#x201C;The Simplon&#x201D;</geogName>, ??;<!-- p. no. needed --> <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><persName corresp="#JM">Murray</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, lviii).</p>
                
                
                    
                
                
              
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>