<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="monro_robert_mrs_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Mrs. [Robert?] Monro</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#AEH">Aimee E. Harris</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2018-02-28">February 28, 2018</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="biographical">
                <head type="title"> <persName corresp="#MONROROBERTMRS">Mrs. Monro</persName> </head>
                <p>Mrs. Monro, whom Ruskin addresses in the letter copied in MS II, may have been the mother of Mary Monro, 
                    the "extremely good and beautiful Scotch girl" who married Richard Gray, as described in Praeterita 
                    (Ruskin, Works, 35:100). Gray was a Scotsman who pursued a career much like that 
                    of John James Ruskin. In 1812, when John James was growing frustrated with his position in the wine firm 
                    of Gordon, Murphy & Company, he remarked that "Gray is doing a great deal at Lisbon & is a Merchant of consequence 
                    now . . . I look upon his fortune as made" (John James to Catherine Ruskin, 5 October 1812, in 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RFL">Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 1:58</ref>). 
                    In Praeterita, Ruskin also characterizes Richard as resembling his father 
                    in the "scholarly love of good literature", and even exceeding him in "romantic sentiment". 
                    Gray probably helped John James navigate foreign life in Spain and Portugal, when John James traveled there sometime between 1815 and 1817 
                    to learn about sherry production (Ruskin, Works, 35:100; 
                    Viljoen, Ruskin's Scottish Heritage, 238-39 n. 14). It was during Gray's time in Lisbon, according to Ruskin, 
                    that he met and married Mary Monro.</p>
                
                <p>Later, in 1823, when John James was becoming securely positioned with his own firm, Ruskin, Telford, & Domecq, 
                    he moved his family to a house atop Herne Hill in the London suburb of Camberwell, where 
                    Mary and Richard Gray were either already established or would soon became near neighbors. 
                    (Dearden suggests that the Grays arrived at 2 Grove Hill Terrace in Camberwell after the Ruskins had settled in Herne Hill; 
                    however, a letter by Margaret to John James Ruskin of 30 January 1822 indicates that the Grays were then living in Camberwell, 
                    where Margaret took John for an extended stay [John Ruskin's Camberwell, 23; Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 107).
                    Living with the Grays was Mary's mother, "old Mrs. Monro" and her "white French poodle, Petite" 
                    (Ruskin, Works, 35:101). Even prior to the Camberwell residence at Herne Hill, however, "Mrs. Gray & Mrs. Monro" 
                    were apparently regular visitors to the Ruskins' Hunter Street house in London. In 1821, for example, 
                    Margaret wrote to John James describing a visit by Mary and her mother during which Mary sat with John 
                    "on the drawing room floor very deeply engrossed" in teaching John to play the flute. 
                    Since the Gray household proved childless, the Grays and Mrs. Monro continued to take great interest in John's development 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RFL">Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters</ref>, 59-60 n. 8, 100-101).</p>
                
                <p>While Mary's mother seems the likeliest addresse of Ruskin's letter copied in MS II, 
                    another possible Mrs. Monro may have been the wife of Robert Monro, a brother of Mary. 
                    The maiden name of this Mrs. Monro was Dowie. All three families--the Grays, the Monros, and the Dowies--were 
                    lifelong friends of the Ruskins
                    (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RFL">Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 1:100. 101 n. 5, 121, 123 n. 4).</ref>.</p>
               
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
