<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="widow_of_roseneath_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Anonymous, <title type="book" corresp="#ANONWIDOWOFROSENEATH"><hi rend="italic">The Widow of Roseneath</hi></title> (1822)</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#SAS">Sarah Silk</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#MJF">Madeline Felps</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="subtype">
                <head type="title">Anonymous, <title type="book" corresp="#ANONWIDOWOFROSENEATH"><hi rend="italic">The Widow of Roseneath</hi></title> (<date when="1822">1822</date>)</head>
                <p>For bibliographical details describing the copy of this book owned by the Ruskins, see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="boyhood_books_note.php#WIDOW">Books Used by Ruskin in His Youth</ref>. 
                    In the Ruskin family, the tale would have served&#x2014;in the terms of the book&#x02bc;s subtitle&#x2014;as &#x201c;A Lesson of Piety Affectionately Dedicated to the Young&#x201d;; and its lessons may have been considered appropriate not only 
                    for <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName> but also for his cousins who survived the deaths of their parents, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_patrick_note.php"><persName corresp="#PR">Patrick</persName></ref> and <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_jessie_note.php"><persName corresp="#JRP">Jessie Richardson</persName></ref> of <placeName corresp="#PERTH">Perth</placeName>. 
                    The role in the tale of the benevolent American merchant&#x2010;uncle may have strikingly suggested the generous support that <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> 
                    lent to <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName>&#x02bc;s orphaned cousins.
                </p>
                <p>Access to the text of the tale appears to be limited. In an <date when="1823">1823</date> review, the plot is summarized and commented on as follows. (For ease of reading, paragraph breaks have been added editorially to the plot summary, which is published as a single paragraph in the original.)</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div type="essay">
                            <p><persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHMRSSTEWART">Mrs. Stewart</persName>, who had lived in a respectable sphere of life in <placeName corresp="#SCOTLAND">Scotland</placeName>, becomes a widow; 
                                and as her husband died insolvent, no reversion is left for her and her two orphan children, 
                                <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName> and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName>. She parts with most of her now useless furniture, and retires with her sons to a small cottage 
                                in <placeName corresp="#ROSNEATH">Roseneath</placeName>; &#x201C;where seeking a solace to her griefs in works of piety and affection, she devoted herself diligently 
                                to the care of their instruction&#x201D;, and in bringing them up in the ways of truth and goodness. Thus consoling herself 
                                in her misfortunes under the influence of religion, and firmly believing that the <persName type="scriptural" corresp="#CREATOR">God</persName> who governs the world 
                                never chastens unkindly, she submits in pious resignation to his sovereign will.</p>
                            
                            <p>Years roll on, and the period arrives when it becomes necessary that her children should go forth 
                                to some employment in the world. <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName>, her eldest son, a boy about fifteen years of age, is destined for <placeName corresp="#USA">America</placeName>, 
                                in the employ of an affectionate uncle; and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName>, about fourteen, is to be apprenticed to a goldsmith in <placeName corresp="#GREENOCK">Greenock</placeName>. 
                                They leave their widowed mother with accumulated anguish upon her wrinkled brow. They embark&#x2014;the fond parent becomes 
                                inconsolable at her additional bereavement&#x2014;she revives;&#x2014;but she no longer embraces them with maternal tenderness, 
                                for they are beyond her reach; and all her concern is, how they will preserve those pious habits which she had endeavoured 
                                to impress upon their minds, and avoid the dread infection of temptation and of crime, to which it would be their lot 
                                to be exposed.</p>
                            
                            <p>They arrive at their looked&#x2010;for homes; <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName> at <placeName corresp="#GREENOCK">Greenock</placeName>, and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName> at <placeName corresp="#NEWYORK">New York</placeName>. 
                                <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName>&#x02bc;s uncle meets him on the quay, and welcomes his young nephew to the shores of <placeName corresp="#USA">America</placeName>: 
                                every thing looks auspicious. After spending nearly three years upon the beautiful banks of the <geogName corresp="#HUDSONRIVER">Hudson</geogName>, 
                                and having raised himself high in the estimation of his kind relative and benefactor, 
                                by his attentive conduct and exemplary deportment, <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHSTEWARTUNCLE">Mr. Stewart</persName> (the uncle) having some business to transact 
                                in <placeName corresp="#GLASGOW">Glasgow</placeName>, determines to entrust his faithful nephew, <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName>, with the important commission; 
                                at the same time appointing him to be the bearer of an invitation to his mother and brother <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName>, 
                                to take up their abode in <placeName corresp="#NEWYORK">New York</placeName>.</p>
                            
                            <p><persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName> embarks with the pleasing intelligence;&#x2014;he sets his feet once more 
                                on Scottish ground; he looks forward with anxious solicitude again to embrace his best of parents. 
                                As he approaches nearer home, he redoubles his eager steps&#x2014;at last, his eye catches in the distance 
                                his widowed mother&#x02BC;s dwelling&#x2014;he presses onward&#x2014;he beholds the cottage door, but sees not his parent 
                                upon her wonted seat. His heart beats high with doubt and suspense&#x2014;every filial emotion is excited&#x2014;scarcely 
                                a tiny vapour from the chimney tells that there is an inhabitant within. He lightly raises the latch&#x2014;he 
                                witnesses his mother once again in the weeds of her widowhood, but, insensible of his return, 
                                and wringing her hands in agony, and her eyes drowned in tears. He inquires the cause of such lamentation; 
                                the mother identifies his voice; she looks upward, and, in a compound paroxysm of ecstasy and grief, 
                                beholds her son <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName>; but nature cannot sustain the struggle. At length he extorts the fact, 
                                that his brother <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName> is incarcerated in a dungeon, and is to be tried on the morrow for forgery 
                                on the <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#GREENOCKBANK">Greenock Bank</orgName>.</p>
                            
                            <p>The widowed mother and her pious son repair with hurried steps to the prison&#x2010;house, 
                                to catch one glance of their son and brother. She lies down to sleep; but the still darkness of midnight 
                                affords her no repose: images of terror, dungeons, gibbets, and executioners, rise in her feverish dreams; 
                                and the only balm to her racking mind is to call upon <persName type="scriptural" corresp="#CREATOR">God</persName> to preserve his life; to interpose his grace, 
                                and save his precious soul. They arrive in <placeName corresp="#GLASGOW">Glasgow</placeName>, and behold the streets unusually crowded;&#x2014;they witness 
                                the lords justiciary passing to the court&#x2010;house. They hurry to the jail, and inquire for <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan Stewart</persName>; 
                                but admittance is denied them, as he is summoned to the bar, to be put first upon trial. 
                                With much urgent solicitation, they obtain a place in court; they immediately fix their eyes upon the bar 
                                where the culprits stand; but no prisoner is there. They turn pale, and tremble&#x2014;they shrink from every sound 
                                of the coming footsteps. <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName> at last appears as the criminal between the liveried officers. 
                                The indictment is read; <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName> pleads Not Guilty!&#x2014;the trial proceeds&#x2014;the evidence is unquestionable;&#x2014;not 
                                even a mother&#x02BC;s fondness can deny that the charge looks black against him. The verdict of the jury 
                                is unanimous and unhesitating. The solemn word of &#x201C;Guilty&#x201D; is recorded. The judge pronounces the awful sentence; 
                                and implores him to pass the remainder of his time in genuine repentance and <orgName corresp="#CHRISTIANITY">Christian</orgName> meditation.</p>
                            
                            <p>They visit him in his gloomy abode, chained in fetters. The interview is melting. <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName> and his mother urgently intreat him 
                                to seek remission of his sins through the blood of the <persName type="scriptural" corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Saviour</persName>; and endeavour to dissipate, by the radiance of <orgName corresp="#CHRISTIANITY">Christian</orgName> faith, 
                                the fearful cloud of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName>&#x02BC;s despair. Time rapidly advances&#x2014;and poor <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName>&#x02BC;s life is drawing to a close. 
                                Three sleepless nights remain, and the destined morning will arrive, when the heavens shall be clothed with sackcloth. 
                                <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName> and his mother hasten once more to the dreary dungeon; and in unutterable anguish at the thought of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHALLANSON">Allan</persName>&#x02BC;s speedy dissolution, 
                                endeavour to console him with the unspeakable comforts of religion; but powerful nature seems to invade, as it were, 
                                the still more powerful empire of religious trust. A pardon, however, unexpectedly arrives; <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHGILBERTSON">Gilbert</persName> conveys the pleasing 
                                intelligence to his disconsolate parent; but she cannot survive the past overwhelming shock; she closes her eyes in death, 
                                before her liberated son reaches her abode.</p>
                            <p>Thus have we hastily glanced at the history of the pious <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ROSENEATHMRSSTEWART">widow of <placeName corresp="#ROSNEATH">Roseneath</placeName></persName>, 
                                and with much pleasure we recommend it to the perusal of our readers.
                            We have already stated that it is a work of fiction; but it has none of the unmeaning and ungovernable incidents 
                                of an overdrawn romance, which has seldom any thing to recommend it but the delusions of a disordered or uncultivated mind&#x2014;the 
                                visionary speculations of a fanciful imagination&#x2014;wild in its scenery&#x2014;improbable in its situations&#x2014;distorted 
                                in its character&#x2014;inconsistent with itself&#x2014;and baneful in its tendency;&#x2014;but it is a work which bears 
                                so close an approximation to real life itself, as it is continually verified by our own daily observation, 
                                that it might well pass current as a narrative of fact, had not our author apprised us of the contrary.
                            </p>
                            <lb/>
                            <p>(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REVIEWANONWIDOWOFROSENEATH">Unsigned review of <title type="book" corresp="#ANONWIDOWOFROSENEATH"><hi rend="italic">The Widow of Roseneath</hi></title></ref>)</p>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The source of this review, the <title type="periodical" corresp="#IMPERIALMAGAZINE"><hi rend="italic">Imperial Magazine</hi></title>, was, according to <persName corresp="#WMCCARTHY">William McCarthy</persName>, a pro&#x2010;Dissent, pro&#x2010;Reform, and anti&#x2010;slavery periodical, addressed to a lower&#x2010;middle&#x2010;class readership. 
                    The magazine was a loyal admirer of <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="barbauld_anna_laetitia_note.php"><persName corresp="#ALB">Anna Laetitia Barbauld</persName> (<date notBefore="1743" notAfter="1825">1743&#x2013;1825</date>)</ref> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MCCARTHYBARBAULDRECEPTION"><persName corresp="#WMCCARTHY">McCarthy</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#MCCARTHYBARBAULDRECEPTION">&#x201C;&#x2018;A High&#x2010;Minded Christian Lady&#x2019;&#x201D;</title></ref>, 167).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>