<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Early Ruskin MSS 1826-42: Drawings: electronic edition</title>
<author>John Ruskin</author>
<sponsor>
</sponsor>
<funder>
</funder>
<respStmt><resp>compiled by</resp>
<name>David Hanson</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition n="0.03">First Pre-release Version<date>September 2009</date></edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>
</authority>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<group>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;frontispiece&rdquo; on the drawing. Also, above a line in a space corresponding to what possibly mimics a half-title in a printed work (&ldquo;HARRY AND LUCY / concluded&rdquo;), he added a numeral &ldquo;1&rdquo; at the side. That this signifies that the frontispiece should also be considered plate 1 appears likely, given that the next plate in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is numbered &ldquo;2.&rdquo; (He may have added this number belatedly: <xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="DISCUSSION">see Discussion</xref>.) Of course, the &ldquo;1&rdquo; next to the half-title might also refer to volume 1 of &ldquo;Harry and Lucy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 1r). The plate along with its legend, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew the &ldquo;Frontispiece&rdquo; near the start of that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Previously unpublished.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>Following the title page (<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3#date">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1: Date</xref>), Ruskin drew this frontispiece, showing a horse, house, tree, and bridge. Behind these objects is an outline that looks like a hill but that the boy labeled &ldquo;a rainbow.&rdquo; The rainbow emerges from a cloudy sky, through which the sun is breaking. This carefully labeled detail at the start of the volume complements, whether intentionally or not, the poem that neatly closes the volume, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="9">&ldquo;On the Rainbow: In Blank Verse.&rdquo;</xref> The drawing also complements Harry&rsquo;s vision of the Witch of the Alps at the end of the prose narrative (chap. 10).</p>
<p>What the author calls his &ldquo;frontispiece&rdquo; and &ldquo;plates&rdquo; for this volume of &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; may have been inspired by engravings in volumes in the Ruskin household, but the precise sources are unknown. One of the sources for &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Joyce, <hi rend="italic">Dialogues,</hi> is illustrated, but the plates provide only schematics of apparatus, and such technical drawings exceeded Ruskin&rsquo;s skill at this time. A year later, in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref>, he would attempt to copy only the simplest of Joyce&rsquo;s diagrams (see ???).</p>
<p>In volume 1, the frontispiece makes good a broadly regular pattern of one plate per chapter of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1: </xref>chapter 1 contains no &ldquo;plate&rdquo; other than the frontispiece, which precedes the first chapter but which is numbered &ldquo;1&rdquo; (<xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="TITLE">see Title</xref>). Ruskin visibly renumbered some of the following plates, for which the simplest explanation is that he belatedly started the numbering anew from the frontispiece.</p>
<p>Following chapter 1, chapters 2&ndash;7 each have one plate, correspondingly numbered and falling within the chapter&rsquo;s boundary (with two anomalies in chapters 3 and 4, respectively, explained below). This pattern is broken, however, with chapter 8, which contains within its bounds both plates 8 and 9, and with chapter 9 containing plate 10, and chapter 10 containing plate 11. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref> for a sequential list of titles.</p>
<p>Since Ruskin&rsquo;s renumbering shows most obviously on plates 5&ndash;9, that attempt at correction may have been related to his perceived mistake of the extra plate in chapter 8. This hypothesis is complicated, however, by two more anomalies: in chapter 3, plate 3 is missing the expected numeral <hi rend="italic">3,</hi> although Ruskin assigned it a title (<xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="3">&ldquo;Lucy&rsquo;s Hutch of Rabbits and Her Silkworms,&rdquo; [Plate 3, &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</xref>); and in chapter 4, a plate 4 is missing altogether&mdash;probably, although not provably, lost with a missing leaf (see <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref>Description). Notice that plate 3 pertains to text in chap. 2.</p>
<p>Ruskin&rsquo;s renumbering of the plates may be connected with all the reasons described above, but in some way that we can no longer exactly reconstruct. But since the renumbered plates are sequenced correctly if one assumes the existence of a lost plate 4, the renumbering seems most likely connected to the redundancy of drawings starting in chapter 8. A possible explanation of the extra plate, particularly since the redundancy occurs toward the end of a manuscript that is otherwise rather scrupulously regular (see <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1#discussion">MS I: Discussion</xref>) is that Ruskin drew his plates for &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; prior to wrapping his text around them. This procedure almost certainly explains the placement of drawings vis-B-vis text in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref> (see <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3#discussion">MS III: Discussion</xref>). Perhaps, toward the end of the manuscript, the length of his chapters was outrunning the available space between drawings. The drawings, however, are not regularly spaced in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1#discussion">MS I</xref>, as one might expect, if Ruskin had begun with them.</p>
<p>In the earlier plates, Ruskin tends to line up objects in a horizontal row, on a plane directly facing the viewer. Starting with plate 7, he attempts more complex spatial relationships: see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3#discussion">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1: Discussion</xref>.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rsquo;s House,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;2,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rsquo;s House,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;2,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;harry and Lucys / house&rdquo; centered above the drawing, and below the page number. At the top and to the left of the drawing is the numeral &ldquo;2,&rdquo; which numbers the plate. Beneath the title is what looks like a letter, but it is illegible: this could be a remnant of renumbering the plates (see &ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1&rdquo; [to <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]: Discussion).</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 13). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 2 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Previously unpublished.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>The drawing depicts Harry and Lucy&rsquo;s house as a brick house with a door and four windows, two on each story. Lined up next to the house are a tree and a circular object surmounting a tall, narrow triangle. The latter might be interpreted as the sun sending down its beams, or, referring to the text that wraps around the drawing, to a balloon with &ldquo;a rod that communicated with it&rdquo; (chap. 2).</p>
<p>In these earlier plates in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref>, Ruskin tends to line up objects in a horizontal row, on a plane directly facing the viewer. Starting with plate 7, he attempts more complex spatial relationships. See <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3#discussion">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1: Discussion</xref>.</p>
<p>See also &ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]: Discussion.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Lucy&rsquo;s Hutch of Rabbits and Her Silkworms,&rdquo; [Plate 3, &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Lucy&rsquo;s Hutch of Rabbits and Her Silkworms,&rdquo; [Plate 3, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;Lucy hutch of rabbits and her silkworms&rdquo; above the drawing, and to the right of the page number. He did not assign a numeral to the plate, unlike other drawings in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref>.</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 24). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 3 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Previously unpublished.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>The drawing depicts a cage on legs with a rabbit inside and, next to the cage, a table-like structure with apostrophe-like objects attached, perhaps meant for caterpillars. A tree bough hangs above, with small globes attached, perhaps meant for cocoons or for mulberries, which are associated with silkworms.</p>
<p>The drawing bears no obvious connection to its immediately surrounding text at the end of chap. 3, which concerns Harry and Lucy breaking a window with a cane. In chap. 2, however, Lucy visits her white rabbit, which she discovers has borne &ldquo;young ones&rdquo; (not shown in this plate); and, immediately following the visit to the rabbits, Mamma asks Lucy how the silkworms are &ldquo;getting on.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In the earlier plates, Ruskin tends to line up objects in a horizontal row, on a plane directly facing the viewer. Starting with <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, plate 7, he attempts more complex spatial relationships. See <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3#discussion">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1: Discussion</xref>.</p>
<p>See also &ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]: Discussion.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">[Plate 4, &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>[Plate 4, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Unknown.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref>, presumed missing with [pp. 30&ndash;31].</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>Unknown. But since the period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date), Ruskin presumably would have drawn a plate 4 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Not published. Since the current state of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> corresponds to its description by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> in <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> (see <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref>Description), the leaf that possibly contained the drawing has been missing throughout the time when anyone, besides Ruskin himself, is likely to have reproduced its contents.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>In <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref>, a leaf is missing that would have contained pp. 30&ndash;31, which possibly included a plate 4. The evidence is ambiguous, since Ruskin did not assign a numeral to the extant preceding plate (<xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="3">&ldquo;Lucy&rsquo;s Hutch of Rabbits and Her Silkworms,&rdquo; [Plate 3, &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</xref>). Ruskin did, however, assign first a &ldquo;4,&rdquo; which he erased and replaced with a &ldquo;5,&rdquo; to the following extant illustration, &ldquo;Lucy&rsquo;s Drawing Room,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;5,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>], and so it appears likely that a plate 4 did exist. It would have been lost along with text that is unquestionably missing between p. 29 and p. 32, since the extant text between those pages does not form a coherent sentence. The existence of a plate 4 would, moreover, have been in keeping with a pattern of one plate per chapter, which holds up to chapter 8 of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref> (see &ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]).</p>
<p>Another possibility for the missing plate is that Ruskin intended to use p. 25, the blank verso of plate 3, for this purpose; however, there is no indication that <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is unfinished, whereas there is definite evidence of a missing leaf.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Lucy&rsquo;s Drawing Room,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;5,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1&rdquo;]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Lucy&rsquo;s Drawing Room,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;5,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;Lucys drawing room&rdquo; above the drawing, and below the page number. To the left of the title, he originally numbered the plate as <hi rend="italic">4,</hi> but scored through that number and wrote a <hi rend="italic">5</hi> in the remaining space next to the title.</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 37). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 5 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Previously unpublished.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>The drawing depicts a door, a person seated at a round table, with what may be an open book on the table. Pictures of a landscape and a seascape hang on the walls. The drawing bears no obvious connection to its immediately surrounding text of chap. 5.</p>
<p>The leaf containing plate 5 (pp. 36&ndash;37) has been torn out and reattached. Evidence suggests that the leaf was reattached much later, in the 1880s at <xref type="note" doc="note" target="brantwood">Brantwood</xref> and not at the time of the manuscript&rsquo;s use (see <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref>Description). There is no way to determine when or why the leaf was torn out, however, or whether this had any bearing on the renumbering of this and following plates (see &ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]: Discussion).</p>
<p>In the earlier plates, Ruskin tends to line up objects in a horizontal row, on a plane directly facing the viewer. Here, apparently a corner of the room appears as a straight line dividing the continuing horizontal lines of the wall. Starting with plate 7, Ruskin attempts more complex spatial relationships.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Harry Seeing a Ship Launch,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;6,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Harry Seeing a Ship Launch,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;6,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;harry seeing a ship launch&rdquo; below the page number, and above the drawing (and running into its frame). He originally numbered the plate as &ldquo;5,&rdquo; which he scored through, and wrote &ldquo;6" in the remaining space next to the title.</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 42). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 6 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Previously unpublished.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>The drawing depicts a ship with three masts, and a person standing beneath the ship&rsquo;s bow. In the immediately surrounding text of chap. 6 of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, Harry and Lucy are on their way to the sea at <xref type="note" doc="note" target="hastings">Hastings</xref>. No mention is made here of a ship&rsquo;s launch, but earlier, in chap. 4, Harry launches his toy boat; and, in chap. 2, he uses a toy boat to show Lucy &ldquo;how ships were floated into docks to be repaired.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In the earlier plates, Ruskin tends to line up objects in a horizontal row, on a plane directly facing the viewer. Starting with plate 7, he attempts more complex spatial relationships.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s New Road,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;7,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s New Road,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;7,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;harrys new road&rdquo; below the page number, and inside the frame of the drawing. Above the title, and to the left of the frame, he numbered the plate originally as &ldquo;6,&rdquo; which he scored through, and wrote &ldquo;7&rdquo; in the remaining space next to the title.</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 48[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>], i.e., the <hi rend="italic">second</hi> p. 48; see <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref>Description). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 7 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Ruskin had the drawing engraved by ??? so that he could facsimile the plate with text in <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="jrworksle">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></xref>, 35:54). As thus reproduced, however, the page of &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; in <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> is misleading in that Ruskin combined plate 7, not with its actual surrounding text from chap. 7, but with text from chap. 10 (pp. 93&ndash;96).</p>
<p>Apparently, for the autobiography, Ruskin chose to combine a drawing that happened to interest him with the text that he found useful. In doing so, he was not taking undue liberties with the original, in which the plates and immediately surrounding text often appear unrelated. In <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref>, the text about an electrical storm, which Ruskin chose for <hi rend="italic">Praeterita,</hi> is juxtaposed with <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="11">&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s Garden, Plate 11,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</xref>, which bears no more obvious relation with the text than does &ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s New Road,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;7,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>].</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>The drawing depicts a road curving up and around a cliff. The immediately surrounding text of chap. 7 concerns an exploding ship; however, the drawing might be related to this passage in the chapter: &ldquo;Papa and [Harry] . . . went out for a walk and after having climbed a high hill they came on a sort of plain composed of a great many fields only separated by hedges and where they had a full view of the sea.&rdquo; If connected (and several of the drawings in &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; have no necessary connection with the text), this excursion might explain the appointment of the path as Harry&rsquo;s &ldquo;<hi rend="italic">new</hi> road,&rdquo; in that the road was new to him. Otherwise, it is unclear why Harry&rsquo;s road is new, unless the drawing is meant to suggest that the road may have been recently cut sharply into a steep hillside.</p>
<p>In the earlier plates, Ruskin tends to line up objects in a horizontal row, on a plane directly facing the viewer. Plate 7 is the first to show noticeably more complex spatial relationships, as the bends in the climbing road reveal, and then hide, the cliff at its edge.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s Dock,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;8,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s Dock,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;8,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;harrys dock&rdquo; below the page number, and above the drawing. Above the title, and to the left of the frame, he originally numbered the plate as &ldquo;7,&rdquo; but scored through it and wrote an &ldquo;8&rdquo; in the remaining space between the page number and the title.</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 54). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 8 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Previously unpublished.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>The drawing depicts an arched bridge, possibly with stairs leading to water. Part of the plate appears to have been erased. The drawing appears unrelated to the immediately surrounding text of chap. 8, which presents Harry drawing a tree, when he is interrupted by a new arrival at the inn.</p>
<p>The drawing might be generally related to Harry and Lucy&rsquo;s continuing visit in chap. 8 to <xref type="note" doc="note" target="hastings">Hastings</xref>, but the bridge in the drawing suggests a river rather than at a seaport. In chap. 1, Mamma tells Lucy that Papa left for work early because he &ldquo;has got to go to town and then into the city and then to the docks.&rdquo; As a wine importer, <xref type="note" doc="note" target="ruskinjohnjames">John James Ruskin</xref> had frequent business at the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="londondocks">London Docks</xref>.</p>
<p>In the earlier plates, Ruskin tends to line up objects in a horizontal row, on a plane directly facing the viewer. Just as <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="7">&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s New Road,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;7,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</xref> is the first to show noticeably more complex spatial relationships, plate 8 possibly attempts a complex problem: stairs at the side of a bridge leading down to the water. Perhaps Ruskin&rsquo;s frustrated attempt&mdash;the stairs appear to go under the water&mdash;may account for the appearance of erasure in the drawing.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s Ship,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;9,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s Ship,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;9,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;harrys ship&rdquo; below the page number, inside the frame of the drawing. Above the title, and to the left of the frame, he originally numbered the plate as &ldquo;8,&rdquo; but scored through it and wrote a &ldquo;9&rdquo; in the remaining space.</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 59). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 9 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Previously unpublished.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>Harry&rsquo;s ship appears to be outward bound. Ruskin kept up a considerable interest in ships, as in his poems <xref type="works" doc="works" target="11">&ldquo;The Ship&rdquo; [1827]</xref> and &ldquo;The Ship [1828&ndash;29].</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s River, Pl[ate] 10,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s River, Pl[ate] 10,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;harrys river&rdquo; above and below the frame of the drawing. To the left of the title, and opposite the page number, he numbered the plate as &ldquo;pl. 10.&rdquo; This is the first plate without evidence of renumbering, except for &ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>], and <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="4">[Plate 4, &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</xref>, which has no number. Ruskin did score through something next to the title, however&mdash;perhaps a word.</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 86). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 10 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p><xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx">Emerson, <hi rend="italic">Genesis of Invention</hi></xref> (p. 00).</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>The plate bears no obvious relation to the surrounding text; however, in chapter 5, on their way to <xref type="note" doc="note" target="hastings">Hastings</xref> the travelers come &ldquo;to a river and . . .  ride along the side of it,&rdquo; until they arrive, in chapter 6, at an inn &ldquo;close by the bank of the river.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As discussed in Emerson, <hi rend="italic">Genesis of Invention,</hi> the depiction of space and perspective in this plate departs from the flat planes of earlier plates.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s Garden, Plate 11,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>&ldquo;Harry&rsquo;s Garden, Plate 11,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]</p>
<p>Ruskin wrote title as &ldquo;harrys garden&rdquo; inside the frame of the drawing. Above the title, he numbered the plate as &ldquo;plate 11,&rdquo; scoring through an earlier &ldquo;12.&rdquo;</p>
<p>See System of Title Citation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="medium">
<p>Pencil.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="major ms">
<p><xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> (p. 94). The plate along with its title, like all the other plates in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, takes up a full page. See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p>See <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I: </xref><xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">Provenance</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>The period of composition for most of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> is September or October 1826 through January 1827 (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>&rdquo;: Date). Presumably, Ruskin drew plate 11 during that period.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="comppub">
<p>Previously unpublished.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>A person is digging in the rows of a garden, which is enclosed by a wall apparently built from brick. Like plate 10, this scene shows a more advanced portrayal of space and depth.</p>
<p>The Edgeworths&rsquo; Harry plants a garden at the beginning of part 2 of <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy</hi> (Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi>, 100&ndash;103).</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</group>
</text>
</TEI.2>
