<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Early Ruskin MSS 1826-42: MSS: electronic edition</title>
<author>John Ruskin</author>
<sponsor>
</sponsor>
<funder>
</funder>
<respStmt><resp>compiled by</resp>
<name>David Hanson</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition n="0.03">First Pre-release Version<date>September 2009</date></edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>
</authority>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<group>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">MS I</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>MS I</p>
<p><xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> assigned roman numeral I to this <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&rdquo; for <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems4d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:262; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:263).</p>
<p>Two decades earlier, Ruskin himself had set the precedent for numbering the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref>, including this one: at the bottom of &ldquo;Frontispiece&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; Vol 1], he wrote &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref>. No. 3. Sept 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1870.&rdquo; On the same day, he docketed <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="4">MS IV</xref> as &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref> No. 1,&rdquo; and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref> as &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref> No. 2.&rdquo; For the meaning of this numbering, see <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref>.</p>
<p>Apart from these numerical designations, Ruskin&rsquo;s title&mdash;intended originally, it appears, for MS I in its entirety as well as for its main work&mdash;is &ldquo;HARRY AND LUCY / CONCLUDED / BEING THE LAST / PART OF / EARLY LESSONS / in four volumes / vol I / with copper / plates / PRINTED and composed by a little boy / and also drawn&rdquo; (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3#title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1: Title</xref>). This title does not take account of the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref> at the end of the manuscript, a feature in addition to &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; that Ruskin may not have envisioned when he devised the title page. <xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="DISCUSSION">See Discussion</xref>, however, for Ruskin&rsquo;s addition, following the anthology, of a colophon that does account for the contents of MS I as a totality.</p>
<p>See also <xref type="note" doc="note" target="titlecitationmss">System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="location">
<p>Beinecke Library, Yale University, cataloged as . . . Formerly, the Beinecke kept the manuscript inside the slip case <xref type="note" doc="note" target="harry&amp;lucyslipcase">&ldquo;Harry &amp; Lucy, Poems &amp;c,&rdquo;</xref> which contained it along with four other manuscripts when purchased. The slip case is now preserved separately.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p><xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="PROVENANCE">See Provenance</xref>: Sotheby&rsquo;s 1930.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="description">
<p><xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref>. 9.5 &times; 15.2 cm. 42 leaves.</p>
<head type="subheading">Collation</head>
<p><xref type="works" doc="works" target="3#title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1: Title</xref> (inside front endboard) +  &ldquo;Frontispiece,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1,&rdquo; [<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3#title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>]  (1r) + pp. (starting on 1v)  1&ndash;29, [30&ndash;31] (missing), 32&ndash;43, 44[<hi rend="italic">a</hi>], 45, 44[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>] (i.e., a second p. 44 given for what should be p. 46), 47, 48[<hi rend="italic">a</hi>], 49[<hi rend="italic">a</hi>], 48[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>], 49[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>] (i.e., p. 48 and p. 49 given twice], 50&ndash;59, 80&ndash;86 (numbering of a p. 87 skipped), 88&ndash;106 + <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="12">&ldquo;Heights of Wisdom, Depth of Fools&rdquo; [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS I]</xref> (inside back endboard).</p>
<p>A loose leaf (not counted in the collation) was inserted between the title page and 1r; it holds a clipping from <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891)</xref> describing MS I, along with brief remarks possibly in the hand of <xref type="note" doc="note" target="wedderburn">Alexander Wedderburn</xref>. It is not clear whether, for this purpose, an existing notebook leaf was used (e.g., whether Ruskin&rsquo;s &ldquo;frontispiece&rdquo; originally began on 2r, following this leaf), or whether a piece of paper was trimmed to the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref>&rsquo;s size and inserted here. The latter is more probable, since similar insertions in other <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref> (e.g., <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref>) certainly formed no part of the original notebook.</p>
<p>Despite Ruskin&rsquo;s erratic page numbering, no leaves appear to be missing, except for pp. 30&ndash;31, which cause a gap in the text. This missing leaf probably included a &ldquo;plate,&rdquo; <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="4">[Plate 4, &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1]</xref>. The leaf containing plate 5, <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="5">&ldquo;Lucy&rsquo;s Drawing Room,&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;5,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1&rdquo;]</xref> (pp. 36&ndash;37) was likewise torn out, although this leaf was reattached, using a glued, perforated sticker (since the tear line fits the remaining stub, this leaf was evidently not moved here from elsewhere). The gummed strip used to mend this leaf&mdash;resembling the edge of a sheet of postage stamps&mdash;is similar to one put to a similar use in proof sheets for <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> (RF MS 70), so one might infer that he had a hand in the preservation of MS I, an inference coincident with his preparing the first bibliography of these manuscripts, the &ldquo;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&rdquo; (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems4d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:261&ndash;67; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:262&ndash;68).</p>
<p>Ruskin&rsquo;s erratic page numbering up through page 50 probably arose from his attempt to correct earlier misnumbering. Erased earlier numbering remains visible starting on the present p. 21 (&ldquo;19&rdquo; is the erased number, an error since p. 19 had already appeared) and continuing consecutively through p. 49[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>] (i.e., the <hi rend="italic">second</hi> p. 49). Since the latter was written over top of &ldquo;47,&rdquo; it appears that, at about this point, Ruskin realized an error, went back to the present p. 21, and began renumbering; however, he made some new errors and possibly deliberately repeated pp. 48&ndash;49 in an attempt to bring his numbering in sync with following pages. The erratic numbering after p. 50 appears to have resulted from Ruskin writing &ldquo;80&rdquo; for &ldquo;60,&rdquo; and carrying on without correction. The missing p. 87 is probably a mere oversight.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="contents">
<p><hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref> (inside front endboard, containing the title page + pp. 1&ndash;96, as numbered by Ruskin [see Description]). Illustrated by a &ldquo;frontispiece&rdquo; and nine &ldquo;plates&rdquo; (pp. 1r, 13, 24, 37, 42, 48[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>], 54, 59, 86, 94; see <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msidrawings">MS I Drawings</xref>). The verso of plate 3 (i.e., p. 25) is blank, and some text and probably a &ldquo;plate&rdquo; have been lost with the missing leaf, pp. 30&ndash;31.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref>: <xref type="works" doc="works" target="5">&ldquo;When furious up from mines the water pours&rdquo; [&ldquo;The Steam Engine&rdquo;]</xref> (pp. 97&ndash;100), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="6">&ldquo;On Scotland&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 100&ndash;101), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="7">&ldquo;The Defiance of War&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 101&ndash;2), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 102&ndash;3), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="8">&ldquo;On Papa&rsquo;s Leaving Home&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 103&ndash;4), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="9">&ldquo;On the Rainbow: In Blank Verse&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 105&ndash;6).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">c</hi>. <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="12">&ldquo;Heights of Wisdom, Depth of Fools&rdquo; [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS I]</xref> (inside back endboard).</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>September 1826&ndash;21 March 1827.</p>
<p>Toward the end of MS I, <xref type="note" doc="note" target="ruskinmargaret">Margaret Ruskin</xref> wrote, &ldquo;this book begun about Sep<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> or Oct 1826 / finished about Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 1827&rdquo; (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>). Since she inserted her annotation toward the end, within the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref>, it is probable that Ruskin devoted approximately the first month of 1827 to fair-copying (and possibly also composing) the poems, whereas he had spent the fall/winter 1826 composing and fair-copying <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, along with its plates.</p>
<p>Margaret&rsquo;s annotation, depending on how one interprets it, possibly suggests also that at least one of the poems, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm,&rdquo;</xref> was composed earlier than its copy in MS I, while the rest of the poems may be dated no earlier than their copies at the end of this manuscript (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1#date">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;: Date</xref>; and <xref type="works" doc="works" target="5#date">&ldquo;When furious up from mines the water pours&rdquo; [&ldquo;The Steam Engine&rdquo;]: Date</xref>).</p>
<p>Probably a few months after Margaret entered her note dating the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref>, Ruskin added <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="12">&ldquo;Heights of Wisdom, Depth of Fools&rdquo; [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS I]</xref> to the back inside endboard and dated the drawing 21 March, although no year is given. This appears to establish the latest date of Ruskin&rsquo;s work on the manuscript.</p>
<p>Thus, in summary, while Ruskin probably composed or at least fair-copied the manuscript between September 1826 and March 1827, he may have composed some of the contents earlier. In particular, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="1">&ldquo;The Needless Alarm&rdquo;</xref> may date from early 1826; and <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, probably at least describes some events that occurred before fall 1826, if not actually drafted earlier. See the individual works for further discussion.</p>
<p>See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="datecitation">System of Date Citation</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<head type="subheading">Hand</head>
<p>MS I is written entirely in large penciled print, more childish than that in any other <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref>; nonetheless, Ruskin was already carefully imitating published books by justifying the margins; devising a title page, frontispiece, and colophon; labeling his drawings as &ldquo;plates&rdquo;; and filling out the volume with the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref>, which he entitled &ldquo;Poetry.&rdquo;</p>
<head type="subheading">Composition and Sources</head>
<p>MS I shows more uniform control over the entirety of its contents than tended to be the case in later <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref>, which grew more miscellaneous with successive uses at different times. For example, the title page appears more nearly to serve for the entire <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> than is the case in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref> and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS IIIA</xref>, which likewise begin with volumes of &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; but which also contain much else that is altogether unrelated to the Edgeworthian narrative. By comparison, the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref>, which fills out MS I, is not an entirely haphazard miscellany. The first of these poems, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="5">&ldquo;When furious up from mines the water pours&rdquo; [&ldquo;The Steam Engine&rdquo;]</xref>, condenses a portion of <hi rend="italic">The Botanic Garden</hi> by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="darwinerasmus">Erasmus Darwin</xref>, thus sustaining the Enlightenment, entrepreneurial spirit of the immediately preceding <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, which imitates works by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="edgeworthmaria">Maria Edgeworth</xref> and <xref type="note" doc="note" target="joycejeremiah">Jeremiah Joyce</xref>.</p>
<p>As a visual artifact, MS I imitates the appearance of books Ruskin would have known: the title page is modeled directly on <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx">Maria Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy Concluded</hi></xref>; and the &ldquo;plates&rdquo; imitated any number of books in the Ruskin family library (Edgeworth&rsquo;s volumes were not illustrated). Most of Ruskin&rsquo;s &ldquo;plates&rdquo; bear no apparent relation with the text, but the frontispiece, &ldquo;Frontispiece&rdquo; [Plate] &ldquo;1&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; Vol 1], which features &ldquo;a rainbow,&rdquo; may be complemented by the last of the poems in the anthology, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="9">&ldquo;On the Rainbow: In Blank Verse.&rdquo;</xref> The rainbow drawing, moreover, could refer to Harry&rsquo;s vision of the Witch of the Alps at the end of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>. (Ruskin could have added the rainbow to the frontispiece as an afterthought: we cannot know for certain whether the textual rainbow suggested the graphic one, or vice versa, or whether the two are definitely related at all. But it seems likely that he arranged the contents in order to frame the book with the theme of the rainbow as both promise and closure.)</p>
<p>Another sign of control over the entirety of the contents appears at the end of the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref>, on p. 106, where Ruskin placed a colophon: &ldquo;The end / hernhill / fountain street / end of the poems[strikethrough] / juvenile library fountain street.&rdquo; The colophon is followed by <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="12">&ldquo;Heights of Wisdom, Depth of Fools&rdquo; [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS I]</xref>, in which the concave shape of the narrow valley appears to answer to the convex form of the rainbow in the frontispiece. The colophon could be based on <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx">Maria Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy Concluded</hi></xref>, which concludes in the fourth volume with &ldquo;<hi rend="smallcaps">THE END.</hi>&rdquo; and, below that, &ldquo;<hi rend="smallcaps">LONDON:</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PRINTED BY CHARLES WOOD,</hi> / Poppin&rsquo;s Court, Fleet Street.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The colophon evidently unifies <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, and the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref>, but the deletion within the colophon (end of the poems[strikethrough]) may point to how attempts at symmetry and closure were ongoing decisions. Since the final two poems of the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref> fall after Margaret&rsquo;s annotation dating the whole of MS I, Ruskin could have added them after he had already written &ldquo;end of the poems&rdquo; on p. 106, deleting the phrase as he added the poems on pp. 103&ndash;6. Or the phrase may have formed an original colophon, deleted as he elaborated the revised colophon (reading, in effect, &ldquo;The end / hernhill / fountain street / juvenile library fountain street&rdquo;). Or he may have originally included the phrase as part of the colophon but deleted it as erroneous or misleading, since the colophon ends the entire book, not just the poems. (It is also possible, of course, that the deletion was made by someone else.)</p>
<head type="subheading">Domestic Scene</head>
<p>MS I is the only <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> to locate its imaginary publisher, the &ldquo;juvenile library,&rdquo; in &ldquo;hernhill / fountain street,&rdquo; other <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref> mentioning simply <xref type="note" doc="note" target="hernehill">Herne Hill</xref>. Could Ruskin be referring to what <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> records as an early memory, the water carts being filled in front of the house (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="jrworksle">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></xref>, 35:21)? In <hi rend="italic">Praeterita,</hi> Ruskin leaves unclear whether he observed the carts from the windows of <xref type="note" doc="note" target="hernehill">Herne Hill</xref> or of the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="hunterstreet">Hunter Street</xref> house&mdash;where the family lived prior to <xref type="note" doc="note" target="hernehill">Herne Hill</xref>, until March 1823 (see <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx">Dearden, <hi rend="italic">Ruskin&rsquo;s Camberwell</hi></xref>, 1). By the time Ruskin first wrote about this memory in 1871 (in <hi rend="italic">Fors Clavigera</hi> [<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="jrworksle">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></xref>, 27:169]), he might well have confused memories of the two locations; or the colophon itself might have suggested such a memory to him, when he doubtless reviewed his juvenilia for those later autobiographical writings. Unfortunately, attempts have been unsuccessful to gain information about either a Fountain Street or water mains in the vicinities of the two houses.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">MS IB</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>MS IB</p>
<p>The editors of the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="libraryedition">Library Edition</xref> designated this bound manuscript as MS IB, fitting it into the series of manuscripts as numbered by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&rdquo; for <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref>. Collingwood had omitted it, the editors explained, because its existence was unknown at <xref type="note" doc="note" target="brantwood">Brantwood</xref> until after Ruskin&rsquo;s death in 1900 (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="jrworksle">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></xref>, 2:530): <xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="PROVENANCE">see Provenance</xref>.</p>
<p>Better known than this numerical designation is Ruskin&rsquo;s original title, intended both for the manuscript and for the sole work it contains: <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Puppet Show.&rdquo;</xref> The title page for this work and thus for the manuscript as a whole reads: &ldquo;THE PUPPET SHOW / <hi rend="smallcaps">OR</hi> / AMUSING CHARACTERS / <hi rend="smallcaps">FOR CHILDREN</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WITH COLORED PLATES</hi> / BY JOHN RUSKIN / 1829.&rdquo;</p>
<p>See also <xref type="note" doc="note" target="titlecitationmss">System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="location">
<p>Pierpont Morgan Library (MA ?).</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p><xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="PROVENANCE">See Provenance</xref>: <hi rend="italic">Sharp.</hi> In one of his few remarks about <xref type="note" doc="note" target="xxx">provenance</xref> in his notes on his collection (PML MA 3451), F. L. Sharp comments that <xref type="note" doc="note" target="severnjoan">Joan Severn</xref> paid &pound;105 for MS IB at Sotheby&rsquo;s. This is somewhat inaccurate, according to Dearden, [private communication, but also book on Whitehouse collection?]. At the time of <xref type="note" doc="note" target="ruskinmargaret">Margaret Ruskin</xref>&rsquo;s death in 1871, Ruskin gave MS IB to his valet, F. Crawley, and it passed in turn to Crawley&rsquo;s son-in-law. It next emerged in a Sotheby&rsquo;s sale catalog for 3&ndash;8 December 1900 (lot 1015) but was bought privately, prior to the sale, by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="severnarthur">Arthur Severn</xref>, for &pound;105, thus returning MS IB to <xref type="note" doc="note" target="brantwood">Brantwood</xref>. These circumstances account for the comment in the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="libraryedition">Library Edition</xref> that &ldquo;the existence of [MS IB] was not known at <xref type="note" doc="note" target="brantwood">Brantwood</xref> till after Ruskin&rsquo;s death,&rdquo; and therefore was omitted from <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="jrworksle">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></xref>, 2:530 n. 2).</p>
<p>MS IB differs from the other manuscripts possessed by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="severnjoan">Joan Severn</xref>&mdash;MS VII, MS IX, MS X, and MS XA&mdash;which contain the major tour poems, and which were given directly to her by Ruskin. The manuscript&rsquo;s charm is sufficient justification, and Joan may have known about its association with Grimm&rsquo;s <hi rend="italic">German Popular Stories</hi>, illustrated by Cruikshank: in 1869, Ruskin published a preface to a new edition of this book (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="jrworksle">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></xref>, 19:231&ndash;39), and Joan owned a copy inscribed by Ruskin (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx">Dearden, &ldquo;Haddon C. Adams Bequest&rdquo;</xref>???, 315&ndash;16). Beyond this, there was an effort to gather in all manuscripts and letters at <xref type="note" doc="note" target="brantwood">Brantwood</xref> for the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="libraryedition">Library Edition</xref>, and Joan may have particularly bridled at a former servant&rsquo;s family putting a personal gift by Ruskin up for public auction. The price of &pound;105 is notable, compared to the &pound;260 paid for <hi rend="italic">twelve </hi>juvenile notebooks in 1930.</p>
<p>Subsequently, the manuscript was not included in the Sotheby&rsquo;s sales of 1930&ndash;31, so either it was sold before or during the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="brantwood">Brantwood</xref> dispersal sale to a local dealer and then to Sharp, or it was acquired by Sharp directly from <xref type="note" doc="note" target="brantwood">Brantwood</xref> or from Violet Severn.</p>
<p>The more intriguing story, which we can probably no longer recover, is Ruskin&rsquo;s thinking in giving this boyhood production to his valet in memory of his mother. From the start, Margaret must have liked <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Puppet Show,&rdquo;</xref> as, in 1831, anxious to &ldquo;stop his rhyming,&rdquo; she  &ldquo;begged him to turn to something else to take exercise[,] copy Crookshanks [sic] &amp;c &amp;c&rdquo; (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></xref>, 224). (It is noteworthy that the handmade book had been preserved with a professional binding sometime prior to the sales; see Description.) Ruskin&rsquo;s feelings may have been mixed, however, since the manuscript also therefore represented Margaret&rsquo;s preference for his obsessive copying of George Cruikshank&rsquo;s illustrations for<hi rend="italic"> German Popular Stories</hi> over his original poetic invention.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="description">
<p>Handmade book from unruled plain paper, afterward professionally bound in green leather with greenish marbled boards, 17.8 &times; 11.5 cm. (This binding, which existed in 1900, may have been added at any point during the 70 years prior to the Sotheby&rsquo;s listing.) 30 leaves.</p>
<head type="subheading">Collation</head>
<p>Following binder&rsquo;s flyleaves, 30 original leaves (approximately 17.4 &times; 10.5 cm): unnumbered title page + &ldquo;Introduction&rdquo; (verso of title page), numbered by Ruskin as p. 1; the following recto and verso&mdash;for figure  I, &ldquo;George of England&rdquo;&mdash;numbered as pp. 2 and 3; and, from p. 4, sequential numbers assigned only to the rectos, with the versos ignored (i.e., for Ruskin&rsquo;s pp. 4&ndash;31, one should read pp. 4r/v&mdash;31r/v). Ruskin assigns p. 28 twice, but compensates by skipping a p. 29. In addition to this page numbering, Ruskin also numbers the figures sequentially.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="contents">
<p><xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Puppet Show.&rdquo;</xref></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>1829, possibly continuing into later years. See <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Puppet Show.&rdquo;</xref> See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="datecitation">System of Date Citation</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>For the title page, titles of sections, and some initial letters, Ruskin employed the taxing &ldquo;double letter&rdquo; print that he had used in &ldquo;A Battle: Irregular Measure.&rdquo; The flair of Ruskin&rsquo;s fancy lettering is matched by his increased self-assertiveness on the title page: compare the precious but anonymous self-identification of the <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> title page, &ldquo;PRINTED and composed by a little boy / and also drawn&rdquo; (<xref type="works" doc="works" target="3#title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1: Title</xref>).</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">MS III</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>MS III</p>
<p><xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> assigned the roman numeral III to this <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&rdquo; for <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems4d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:262; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:263).</p>
<p>Two decades earlier, Ruskin himself had set the precedent for numbering the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref>, including this one: on the title page for <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref>, he wrote &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref> No. 2. Sept 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1870&rdquo; (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20#title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2: Title</xref>). On the same day, he docketed <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="4">MS IV</xref> as &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref> No. 1,&rdquo; and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> as &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref> No. 3.&rdquo; For the meaning of this numbering, see <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref>.</p>
<p>Apart from these numerical designations, Ruskin&rsquo;s title&mdash;intended originally, it appears, for MS III in its entirety as well as for its main work&mdash;is &ldquo;HARRY AND LUCY / CONCLUDED / BEING / THE LAST PART / OF / EARLY LESSONS / IN / FOUR VOLS / VOL 2 / WITH COPPER PLATES / HERNHILL&rdquo; (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20#title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2: Title</xref>). This title page, like that for <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> and its main work, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="3">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 1</xref>, fails to take account of a poetry anthology situated toward the end of the manuscript, an anthology named, in this case, <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>. Despite its omission on the title page, however, Ruskin probably inserted the anthology at about the same time he entered the manuscript&rsquo;s main work, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20#title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref>, because he wanted the manuscript&rsquo;s contents to complement those of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref>. Despite this original intention, the contents of MS III over time grew much more miscellaneous than the title page indicated.</p>
<p>See also <xref type="note" doc="note" target="titlecitationmss">System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="location">
<p>Beinecke Library, Yale University, cataloged as. . . . Formerly, the Beinecke kept the manuscript inside the slip case <xref type="note" doc="note" target="harry&amp;lucyslipcase">&ldquo;Harry &amp; Lucy, Poems &amp;c,&rdquo;</xref> which contained it along with four other manuscripts when purchased. The slip case is now preserved separately.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p><xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="PROVENANCE">See Provenance</xref>: Sotheby&rsquo;s 1930.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="description">
<p><xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref>. 9.9 &times; 15.2 cm. 42 leaves.</p>
<head type="subheading">Collation</head>
<p><xref type="works" doc="works" target="20#title">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2: Title</xref> (inside front endboard) + frontispiece, <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="xxx">&ldquo;Harry Going across the Sea in a Steamboat,&rdquo; [&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2]</xref> (1r) + pp. numbered by Ruskin (starting on 1v) as 1&ndash;64, 65[<hi rend="italic">a</hi>], 65[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>], 66&ndash;82 (i.e., p. 65 given twice) + inside back endboard. Some page numbers are corrected in ink over top of penciled numbers beneath. The page numbering may have been entered complete from the start, since, later in the book, writing crowds the numbers at the top of the pages.</p>
<p>As in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref>, between the title page and 1r is inserted a loose page (not counted in the collation above) with a clipping from <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891)</xref> describing MS III and containing a brief identification, possibly in the hand of <xref type="note" doc="note" target="wedderburn">Alexander Wedderburn</xref>. For this purpose, an existing page in MS III was not exploited; rather, a piece of paper was cut to size and inserted, as can be seen from how the leaf is pasted.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="contents">
<p><hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2: </xref>(inside front endboard + pp. 1&ndash;21, as numbered by Ruskin [see Description]). Illustrated by a frontispiece (1r) and three plates (pp. 8, 15) (see <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msiiidrawings">MS III Drawings</xref>).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msiiipoetryanthology2">MS III Second Poetry Anthology</xref>, poems of early 1828 and earlier: <xref type="works" doc="works" target="21">&ldquo;The Constellations: Northern, Some of the Zodiac, and Some of the Southern&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 21&ndash;25), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="4">&ldquo;Time: Blank Verse&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 25&ndash;27), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="22">&ldquo;The Sun&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 28&ndash;29), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="23">&ldquo;Glen of Glenfarg&rdquo; (&ldquo;Papa how pretty those icicles are&rdquo;)</xref> (p. 30), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="11">&ldquo;The Ship&rdquo; [1827]</xref> (pp. 31&ndash;32), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="24">&ldquo;The British Battles&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 32&ndash;33). <xref type="works" doc="works" target="4">&ldquo;Time: Blank Verse&rdquo;</xref> wraps around the drawing, <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="xxx">Ship and House, [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS III]</xref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">c</hi>. <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="xxx">&ldquo;Ragland Castle When Newly Built,&rdquo; [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS III]</xref> (p. 34); blank page (p. 35).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">d</hi>. <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msiiipoetryanthology3">MS III Third Poetry Anthology</xref>: <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Of rocks first and of caverns now I sing&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 36, 38), with pencil notation for &ldquo;chap. 6&rdquo; (p. 36); ???? [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS III] (p. 37); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Ship&rdquo; [1828&ndash;29]</xref> (pp. 39&ndash;40); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Sonnet to the Sun&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 40&ndash;41); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Adventures of an Ant: A Tale&rdquo;</xref> (p. 41); blank page, except for pencil notation for &ldquo;chap. 7 (p. 42); <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="xxx">????, [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS III]</xref> (p. 43); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;On the Appearance of a Sudden Cloud of Yellow Fog Covering Everything with Darkness&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 44&ndash;45); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;A Fragment&rdquo; (&ldquo;The summit of Skiddaw was gilt by the sun&rdquo;)</xref> (p. 45); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;A Shipwreck&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 45&ndash;47); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;A Fragment&rdquo; (&ldquo;The world that in its orbit flies&rdquo;)</xref> (p. 47); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Another&rdquo; (&ldquo;Far towards Chelsea&rdquo;)</xref> (pp. 47&ndash;48); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Another&rdquo; (&ldquo;On the noble Ben Lomond arose the bright sun&rdquo;)</xref> (p. 48); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Another&rdquo; (&ldquo;Thy winding rivers Scotland and thy rocks&rdquo;)</xref> (p. 48); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;A Psalm&rdquo; (&ldquo;I will extol thee O my Lord&rdquo;)</xref> (pp. 48&ndash;50); blank page (p. 51).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">e</hi>. <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Monastery,&rdquo;</xref> books 3&ndash;4 (pp. 52&ndash;56 [bk. 3], pp. 56&ndash;58 [bk. 4]); blank pages (pp. 59&ndash;61).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">f</hi>. <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>: <xref type="works" doc="works" target="14">&ldquo;Ragland Castle&rdquo;</xref> (p. 62); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="15">&ldquo;Lochleven&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 62&ndash;63); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="16">&ldquo;Nature&rdquo;</xref> (p. 63); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="13">&ldquo;Spring: Blank Verse&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 63&ndash;65[<hi rend="italic">a</hi>]); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="12">&ldquo;Wales&rdquo;</xref> (p. 65[<hi rend="italic">a</hi>]&ndash;65[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>]); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="17">&ldquo;The Hill of Kinnoul&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 65[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>]&ndash;66); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="2">&ldquo;Glen of Glenfarg&rdquo; (&ldquo;Glen of Glenfarg thy beauteous rill&rdquo;)</xref> (pp. 66&ndash;68); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="18">&ldquo;The Sea&rdquo;</xref> (p. 68); <xref type="works" doc="works" target="19">&ldquo;The Storm&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 69&ndash;70).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">g</hi>. <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Monastery,&rdquo;</xref> books 1&ndash;2 (pp. 70&ndash;75 [bk. 1], pp. 75&ndash;80 [bk. 2]).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">h</hi>. &ldquo;<xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">A Puzzle in Prose</xref>&rdquo; (p. 81); blank page (p. 82).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">i</hi>. Random words and letters (inside back endboard).</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>Fall 1827&ndash;March 1829.</p>
<p><xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="DISCUSSION">See Discussion</xref>: Ruskin started composition in the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> in autumn 1827 through early 1828, and then returned to it about March 1829. One poem among those in <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref> is dated one year earlier, September 1826, but MS III itself was not in use at that time.</p>
<p>See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="datecitation">System of Date Citation</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<head type="subheading">Hand</head>
<p>MS III reflects some Ruskin&rsquo;s of fledgling uses of pen and ink, first taken up in April 1827, as compared with the earlier <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> and MS IVA, which he wrote entirely in pencil. It was probably to practice printing with pen and ink that he covered the inside back endboard with random words and letters.</p>
<p>To print <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref> and <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>, he copied his letters in ink over top of pencil, which remains visible beneath. He continued to rely on pencil for the drawings in MS III, but not for their legends, which he printed in ink.</p>
<head type="subheading">Collation</head>
<p>As <xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> remarked, Ruskin worked in differing parts of MS III at widely differing times. A rough chronology of his use of this <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> can be sorted out as follows, incorporating but revising and elaborating on both Collingwood&rsquo;s reconstruction (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems4d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>,1:262; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:263; and <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="jrworksle">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></xref>, 2:530) and <xref type="note" doc="note" target="viljoenhg">Helen Gill Viljoen</xref>&rsquo;s (&ldquo;Dating MSS. of Boyhood,&rdquo; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx">Viljoen Papers</xref>, box F).</p>
<p>1. As indicated by the travel itinerary in <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref>, Ruskin may have begun this &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; narrative during an autumn 1827 visit to Wales and Scotland (see Tours 1826&ndash;27). He appears originally to have reserved three-quarters of the notebook for &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; since later pages (pp. 36, 42) retain the penciled indications, &ldquo;chap 6&rdquo; and &ldquo;chap 7.&rdquo;  The narrative never extended that far, instead ending with the unfulfilled promise, &ldquo;But I will put them [Harry and Lucy] on to scarthing moor in another chapter.&rdquo; He did, however, possibly intend the drawings on pp. ??, 34, 37, and 43 to accompany the projected narrative (see <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msiiidrawings">MS III Drawings</xref>).</p>
<p>2. At about the same time that he composed <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref>, Ruskin entered&mdash;farther in the book, following the space left blank for expansion of &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo;&mdash;the anthology <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>. As Viljoen comments, the ink printing used for these poems resembles that used for <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref>, tending to confirm that the two projects were roughly contemporaneous. Certainly, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="12">&ldquo;Wales&rdquo;</xref> and <xref type="works" doc="works" target="13">&ldquo;Spring: Blank Verse,&rdquo;</xref> included in the anthology, were composed not much earlier than May 1827, and their copies here occur among poems likely inspired by the Wales and Scotland journey recorded in &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; (e.g., the poems <xref type="works" doc="works" target="14">&ldquo;Ragland Castle,&rdquo;</xref> <xref type="works" doc="works" target="15">&ldquo;Lochleven,&rdquo;</xref> <xref type="works" doc="works" target="17">&ldquo;The Hill of Kinnoul&rdquo;</xref>).</p>
<p>3. No earlier than the start of 1828, in a smaller, neater print, Ruskin briefly rounded out <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref>, and followed it with the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msiiipoetryanthology2">MS III Second Poetry Anthology</xref> (second, that is, after <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>). Ruskin entitled this second anthology &ldquo;POETRY,&rdquo; just as he had headed the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref> &ldquo;Poetry.&rdquo; The anthology included <xref type="note" doc="note" target="newyearspoems">New Year&rsquo;s Poems</xref>, both old and new, so this stage of MS III presumably served as a New Year&rsquo;s present.</p>
<p>The terminus for the MS III Poetry Anthology is the drawing <xref type="drawings" doc="drawings" target="xxx">&ldquo;Ragland Castle When Newly Built,&rdquo; [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS III]</xref>. Nothing indicates whether Ruskin drew the picture in early 1828, shortly after entering that second anthology of poems, or whether he carried the anthology up to the pre-existing drawing, perhaps having drawn it in fall/winter 1827 to accompany the poem <xref type="works" doc="works" target="14">&ldquo;Ragland Castle&rdquo;</xref> in <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>.</p>
<p>4. By a year later, Ruskin had returned to MS III to copy <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Monastery,&rdquo;</xref> his versification of Scott&rsquo;s novel. Some portion of this poem, probably the later books, can be dated firmly as early March 1829. To fair-copy the poem, Ruskin used blank pages following <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref> until, running out of room at the end of the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref>, he continued the poem in blank pages that had remained just preceding <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>. He made this clear by, at the end of book 2 of the poem on p. 80, instructing the reader to &ldquo;go back to page 52 / <hi rend="smallcaps">END OF BOOK SECOND</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">HERN HILL</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">DULWICH</hi>.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Viljoen believed she detected a steady sophistication in the script for <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Monastery,&rdquo;</xref> over the course of its four books, suggesting &ldquo;that [Ruskin] worked at these transcriptions from early into late 1828&rdquo; (&ldquo;Dating MSS. of Boyhood,&rdquo; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx">Viljoen Papers</xref>; she was unaware of the firm evidence placing some portion of the poem in March 1829, although it is true that Ruskin might have started the MS III version sometime in 1828). It is unwise to rely on distinctions in handwriting to date manuscripts so narrowly as a matter of months, since other circumstances besides practice can affect handwriting. One can hazard with some confidence, however, that the tiny ink hand (with no pencil outline beneath) for book 1 of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Monastery&rdquo;</xref> must be significantly later than the awkward ink lettering (over top of pencil) for <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>, which precedes <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Monastery.&rdquo;</xref></p>
<p>5. Around 9 March 1829, at about the same time that he was entering some portion of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Monastery,&rdquo;</xref> Ruskin showed he was attentive to his parents&rsquo; criticism of leaving his projects unfinished by using blank pages after the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msiiipoetryanthology2">MS III Second Poetry Anthology</xref> to copy several recent poems&mdash;thus forming the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msiiipoetryanthology3">MS III Third Poetry Anthology</xref>. In so doing, he scotched any plans to continue <xref type="works" doc="works" target="20">&ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; Vol. 2</xref>, the pencil notations for &ldquo;chap. 6&rdquo; and &ldquo;chap. 7&rdquo; still remaining to witness to this intention. But, in any case, he had already wrapped the Second Poetry Anthology around a drawing probably meant for &ldquo;Harry and Lucy.&rdquo;</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">MS IV</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>MS IV</p>
<p><xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> assigned roman numeral IV to this <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&rdquo; for <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems4d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:262; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:263).</p>
<p>Two decades earlier, Ruskin himself had set the precedent for numbering the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref>, including this one: at bottom of the title page for <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Eudosia,&rdquo;</xref> he wrote &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref> No. 1. Sept 8th 1870&rdquo; (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx#title">&ldquo;Eudosia&rdquo;: Title</xref>). On the same day, he docketed <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref> as &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref> No. 2,&rdquo; and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref> as &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref> No. 3.&rdquo; For the meaning of this numbering, see <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref>.</p>
<p>Apart from these numerical designations, Ruskin&rsquo;s title&mdash;intended originally, it appears, both for MS IV in its entirety as well as for its main work&mdash;is &ldquo;EUDOSIA OR / A POEM / ON THE / UNIVERSE / BY JOHN RUSKIN / VOL I / These are thy glorious works parent of good / Almighty thine this universal frame / Thus wondros fair MILTON / BOTANY / HERN HILL / DULWICH.&rdquo;</p>
<p>See also <xref type="note" doc="note" target="titlecitationmss">System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="location">
<p>Beinecke Library, Yale University, catalogued as . . . Formerly, the Beinecke kept the manuscript inside the slip case <xref type="note" doc="note" target="harry&amp;lucyslipcase">&ldquo;Harry &amp; Lucy, Poems &amp;c,&rdquo;</xref> which contained it along with four other manuscripts when purchased. The slip case is now preserved separately.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p><xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="PROVENANCE">See Provenance</xref>: Sotheby&rsquo;s 1930.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="description">
<p><xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red book</xref>; 9.7 &times; 14.6 cm. ?? leaves.</p>
<head type="subheading">Collation</head>
<p>Inside front endboard + <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx#title">&ldquo;Eudosia&rdquo;: Title</xref> (1r) + pp. 1&ndash;33, with p. 1 started on 1v + ?? unnumbered leaves (or ??r/v&ndash;??r/v, with ??r/v&ndash;??r/v blank and ??r/v&ndash;??r/v containing text written reverso from back of book.</p>
<p>Pasted to inside front endboard: clipping from <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> describing MS IV.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="contents">
<p><hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Eudosia,&rdquo;</xref> including &ldquo;The Yew&rdquo; incorporated into the end of the poem (1r, containing the title page + pp. 1&ndash;17, with p. 1 on verso of title page [blank apart from page number], and p. 2 containing the beginning of the text).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. Blank, except for Ruskin&rsquo;s page numbering (pp. 18&ndash;19).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">c</hi>. List of Ruskin&rsquo;s Published Poems, 1830&ndash;46, Compiled by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="ruskinjohnjames">John James Ruskin</xref> (pp. 20&ndash;33 + the immediately following unnumbered leaf).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">d</hi>. 21 blank, unnumbered leaves.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Reverso, from back of book, the sequential order of contents: </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">e</hi>. <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">Mineralogy Notes [ca. 1829]</xref> (1r&ndash;3r).</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>September 1828 to early 1830; 1836; ca. 1845&ndash;46 (by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="ruskinjohnjames">John James Ruskin</xref>).</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>MS IV is like some other <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref> (e.g., <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref> and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS IIIA</xref>) in that it starts with a title page announcing a single work (<xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="TITLE">see Title</xref>) but&mdash;Ruskin failing to realize the ambitious length and predominance of that work&mdash;the manuscript was left open to being filled by other kinds of writing. MS IV, however, was left with an unusually large blank section: from the page containing the final fair-copied lines of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Eudosia&rdquo;</xref> (p. 17) to the <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">Mineralogy Notes [ca. 1829]</xref> entered reverso from the other end, MS IV contained a section of 29 leaves, blank except for numbering on some pages, until two decades after its initial use, when <xref type="note" doc="note" target="ruskinjohnjames">John James Ruskin</xref> used some of those leaves for his catalog of his son&rsquo;s published poems. Over time, Ruskin put space in other <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref> to various uses&mdash;the additional poetry anthologies in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref>, the mineralogy notes in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS IIIA</xref> (although that <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> also retained blank sections extending to significant lengths), the sermon drafts in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">Juvenilia MS A</xref>. That Ruskin left so much of MS IV unused may suggest that he persisted longer in an intention to carry on with the manuscript&rsquo;s main work, <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Eudosia,&rdquo;</xref> compared to ambitions for &ldquo;Harry and Lucy,&rdquo; which he relinquished more easily in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref> and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS IIIA</xref>. If so, his lingering ambitions for a long poem would be more expected than for Edgeworthian lessons, which he more quickly outgrew.</p>
<p>If Ruskin had devoted additional <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref> to further &ldquo;volumes&rdquo; of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Eudosia&rdquo;</xref>&mdash;beyond the first volume he planned for MS IV, which he gave over to the subject of &ldquo;Botany&rdquo;&mdash;he presumably would have continued to follow something like the plan found in his source, <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="xxx">Lofft, <hi rend="italic">Eudosia</hi></xref>. Since Ruskin subdivides his first volume of his &ldquo;Poem on the Universe&rdquo; into &ldquo;books&rdquo; (of which he never got beyond the start of book 2), he is even more ambitious than Lofft, whose &ldquo;Poem on the Universe&rdquo; is divided only into books (not volumes containing books), of which the first is &ldquo;The Earth,&rdquo; corresponding to Ruskin&rsquo;s &ldquo;Botany.&rdquo; It is possible that one of the fair-copy versions of <xref type="works" doc="works" target="21">&ldquo;The Constellations: Northern, Some of the Zodiac, and Some of the Southern&rdquo;</xref>&mdash;that in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS IA</xref>, or <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">RF T70</xref>&mdash;represents a continuation of Ruskin&rsquo;s scheme beyond the first volume in MS IV, as a volume on the stars would correspond to Lofft&rsquo;s poem: see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx#discussion">&ldquo;Eudosia&rdquo;: Discussion</xref>.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
<text>
<body>
<head type="title">MS V</head>
<div type="section" n="title">
<p>MS V</p>
<p><xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> assigned the roman numeral V to this notebook in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&rdquo; for <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems4d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:263; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:264).</p>
<p>Apart from the editor&rsquo;s numerical designation, Ruskin&rsquo;s title&mdash;intended, it appears, for the manuscript in its entirety&mdash;is &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="miscellaneouspoetry">MISCELLANEOUS POETRY</xref>.&rdquo; Unlike his full-page titles for <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="1">MS I</xref>, <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="2">MS IB</xref>, <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref>, <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS IIIA</xref>, and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="4">MS IV</xref>, which Ruskin apparently intended to serve both for the manuscript in its entirety and for its single main work (despite the more or less miscellaneous contents that eventually filled out some of these manuscripts), his title for MS V does not take up an entire page in imitation of a published book. Rather, he wrote it in capitals on p. 1, above the first of the poems in the anthology, which starts on the same page (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx#title">&ldquo;Helvellyn&rdquo;: Title</xref>).</p>
<p>A handmade pamphlet tipped in at the end of MS V (see Description) bears its own title by Ruskin: &ldquo;BATTLE OF WATERLOO / A PLAY / IN TWO ACT&rsquo;S / WITH OTHER SMALL / POEMS / DEDICATED TO HIS FATHER / BY JOHN RUSKIN / 1829 / HERNHILL / DULWICH.&rdquo;</p>
<p>See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="titlecitationmss">System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="location">
<p>Beinecke Library, Yale University. Cataloged as &ldquo;Poems 1829&ndash;1832,&rdquo; which is the title on the spine of the slip case containing the manuscript when purchased. The slip case is now preserved separately.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="provenance">
<p><xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="PROVENANCE">See Provenance</xref>: Sotheby&rsquo;s 1930.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="description">
<p>A 12 &times; 18.5 cm, pre-ruled notebook, covered with greenish marbled boards, half-bound in chocolate calf, and gilt (the same binding as that described by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> [<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems4d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891)</xref>, 1:263; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891)</xref>, 1:264]). The leaves measure 11 &times; 17.7 cm.</p>
<head type="subheading">Collation</head>
<p>Following and not including the marbled front endpaper: three blank leaves + 167 pp. as numbered by Ruskin (with p. 1 starting on a recto, and with p. 37 given twice) + 3 blank leaves + back marbled endpaper.</p>
<p>The three leaves at the beginning and end of the notebook are unruled and, unlike the ruled leaves that make up the main part of the notebook, bear the watermark &ldquo;Smith &amp; A[(?)] / 18[(?)].&rdquo; This difference in papers might suggest a rebinding of MS V, but the worn marbled boards appear original, as do the leather corners. Also, the edges of the paper were marbled in a color that may once have matched the boards. It seems likely, therefore, that MS V has come down to us in the same binding in which Ruskin first used it.</p>
<head type="subheading">Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts, with Other Small Poems</head>
<p>A handmade pamphlet with this title, its pages disassembled, is tipped in at the back of MS V. Originally, the pamphlet formed no part of MS V, and it must not have been inserted when Collingwood described MS V, as he does not mention it. (See <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts&rdquo;</xref> for the likelihood that Collingwood was unaware of this pamphlet at all when compiling <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [1891].)</p>
<p>The pamphlet was probably inserted by <xref type="note" doc="note" target="wedderburn">Alexander Wedderburn</xref>, and no later than 1903, since Collingwood&rsquo;s &ldquo;Notes on the Original MSS. of Poems,&rdquo; as elaborated in the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="libraryedition">Library Edition</xref>, adds to the description of MS V: &ldquo;In this book . . . are now inserted the leaves of a thin paper book&rdquo; containing <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts&rdquo;</xref> and other works (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="jrworksle">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></xref>, 2:531). The addition is mentioned also on a leaf tipped in between the marbled front endpapers of MS V; like similar leaves in some of the <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref>, these hold a clipping from <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref> describing MS V, along with brief remarks penned probably by Wedderburn. It is perplexing why this pamphlet was not included in <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS IA</xref>, a collection compiled after Collingwood&rsquo;s editing of <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poems1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</xref>, just as it is perplexing, and intriguing, why the contents of <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS IA</xref> were omitted from MS XI.</p>
<p>The pamphlet requires a description of its own:</p>
<p>Most of the booklet&rsquo;s leaves have been cut at the fold and tipped separately onto successive pages of the notebook. If nothing is lacking&mdash;and only a front portion of cover, made of heavier paper, has likely disappeared&mdash;the booklet consists of 8 leaves that were folded once to form 16 pp., 10 x 16 cm. The innermost fold, leaves 4&ndash;5, remains intact, tending to confirm how the booklet was constructed. Ruskin numbered the pages 1&ndash;14, starting with 2r.</p>
<p>In addition to this gathering, a back cover remains that is white on the inside, facing p. 16, and bright pink on the outer side, and that looks to be the same age as the other leaves. No matching front cover is extant. Nothing is written on the back cover, but it presumably formed part of the pamphlet when the editors discovered the little anthology; otherwise, they would have had no reason to include it. There is no assurance, however, that Ruskin himself was responsible for the pink cover, when he constructed the pamphlet in 1829, and there is no way of knowing what, if anything, might have been written or drawn on the front cover.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="contents">
<p><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Fair copies of poems, most of them originally drafted in MSS VI and VIII, but not necessarily fair-copied here in order of composition: <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Helvellyn&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 1&ndash;2), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Moon&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 2&ndash;3), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Wood of Birches near Tunbridge&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 3&ndash;4), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;On Happiness&rdquo;</xref> (p. 4), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The IX Psalm&rdquo;</xref> (p. 5), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Sabbath Morning&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 6&ndash;7), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Shagram&rsquo;s Farewell to Shetland&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 7&ndash;9), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Etna&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 9&ndash;10), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Bosworth Field&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 10&ndash;13), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Vesuvius&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 13&ndash;16), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Trafalgar&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 17&ndash;20), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Death&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 20&ndash;23), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Day of Judgement&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 24&ndash;29), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Battle of Preston Pans&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 29&ndash;35), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Revenge&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 36&ndash;37[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>] [i.e., the poem takes up a total of three pages, including the two pages that Ruskin mistakenly numbered redundantly as p. 37: p. 37[<hi rend="italic">a</hi>] and p. 37[<hi rend="italic">b</hi>]]), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Despair&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 38&ndash;46), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Love&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 46&ndash;51), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Haddon Hall&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 52&ndash;53), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;My Dog Dash&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 53&ndash;54), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;On the Death of My Cousin Jessy&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 54&ndash;55), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;My Fishing Rod&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 55&ndash;59), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Ascent of Skiddaw&rdquo;</xref> [book ?, lines ??&ndash;?? of &ldquo;Iteriad&rdquo;] (pp. 59&ndash;78), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Going to Covent Garden Theatre To See the &pound;100 Note &amp; Harlequin Fat and Harlequin Bat&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 78&ndash;83), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Fairies&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 84&ndash;86), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;To My Heart&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 86&ndash;88), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;To Poesie&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 88&ndash;90), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;A Dirge for Nelson&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 90&ndash;92), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;To the Ocean Spirits&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 92&ndash;94), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;To the Fairies&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 95&ndash;97), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;To the Spirits of the Earth&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 97&ndash;99), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;To the Spirits of the Fire&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 100&ndash;102), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;To the Wind&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 102&ndash;3), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Weep for the Dead&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 103&ndash;4), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Mariner&rsquo;s Song&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 105&ndash;6), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;On the Want of a Subject&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 106&ndash;8), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;To the Spirit of Mount Pilate, Written on Reading the Description of That Mountain in Sir Walter Scott&rsquo;s Novel of Anne of Gierstein&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 109&ndash;11), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Site of Babylon&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 111&ndash;12), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Repentance of Nineveh: A Fragment&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 112&ndash;13), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Dash&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 113&ndash;15), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Curtained in cloudy drapery&rdquo; [&ldquo;Moonlight on the Mountains&rdquo;]</xref> (pp. 115&ndash;16), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Sonnet to a Cloud&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 116&ndash;17), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Creation: A Fragment&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 117&ndash;18), &ldquo;??? first line&rdquo; [book 1, lines 401&ndash;28 of &ldquo;Iteriad&rdquo;] (pp. 118&ndash;20), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Athens&rdquo;</xref> [17 stanzas] (pp. 121&ndash;29), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Sonnet to the Morning&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 129&ndash;30), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Song of the Southern Breeze&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 130&ndash;33).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. Pp. 134&ndash;67 blank; of these, pp. 136&ndash;48 used to tip in the handmade booklet, <xref type="note" doc="note" target="battlewaterloomsv">Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts, with Other Small Poems</xref> (see Description). Contents of the booklet: no. <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts&rdquo;</xref> (title page, 1r; list of characters, 1v; text, pp. 1&ndash;7 [2r&ndash;5r]), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Ballad on Waterloo&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 7&ndash;8), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Description of an Afternoon&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 8&ndash;9), <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;May&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 9&ndash;10) <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Skiddaw and Derwent Water&rdquo;</xref> (pp. 10&ndash;13).</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="date">
<p>Date of composition summer 1829 to early 1832.</p>
<p>Beneath Ruskin&rsquo;s main title for the anthology, &ldquo;<xref type="note" doc="note" target="miscellaneouspoetry">Miscellaneous Poetry</xref>,&rdquo; and above the title of the first poem, <xref type="note" doc="note" target="ruskinjohnjames">John James Ruskin</xref> wrote,  &ldquo;By J. Ruskin from 10 years to 11 to 12 to         of age,&rdquo; with a long space left perhaps to allow for adding Ruskin&rsquo;s ages as the years went by. As it turned out, the fair-copied poems in the notebook did not extend quite far enough into 1832 to justify John James entering age &ldquo;13&rdquo; into the space.</p>
<p><xref type="note" doc="note" target="collingwoodwg">W. G. Collingwood</xref> remarks: &ldquo;The poems are nearly all dated, and range from <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 28, 1829, to <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 1832. The dates are probably those of production, for they are slightly inconsecutive; which would not be the case if they were dates of entry; and, when chronologically arranged, they tally with the order of the first drafts in No. VI&rdquo; (<xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems4d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:263; <xref type="biblio" doc="biblio" target="poems8d1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</xref>, 1:264). <xref type="internal" doc="internal" target="DISCUSSION">See Discussion</xref> for speculation about why the anthology was not carried beyond 1832.</p>
<p>The handmade booklet tipped in the back of MS V, <xref type="note" doc="note" target="battlewaterloomsv">Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts, with Other Small Poems</xref>, dates from 1829 in fair copy.</p>
<p>See <xref type="note" doc="note" target="datecitation">System of Date Citation</xref>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="discussion">
<p>MS V is the earliest major manuscript that was originally neither a <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Book</xref> nor a homemade booklet. Another new development that Ruskin starts with MS V is the practice of keeping one notebook for carefully copied presentation of his poetry, while drafting his poems in other notebooks&mdash;MS VI and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="xxx">MS VIII</xref>, especially. Some evidence suggests that he took both sorts of notebooks along with him on journeys (see <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;The Day of Judgement&rdquo;</xref>), entering the fair copies in MS V on Sundays or other days when the family paused from traveling. Just so, the Diary of 1830 was &ldquo;written up&rdquo; from notes during a lengthened stop.</p>
<p>Ruskin did compile poetry anthologies prior to MS V, but they were comparatively brief and served to fill out <xref type="note" doc="note" target="redbook">Red Books</xref> whose main feature was the ongoing &ldquo;Harry and Lucy&rdquo; narrative: see <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msipoetryanthology">MS I Poetry Anthology</xref>, <xref type="note" doc="note" target="poetrydiscriptive">Poetry Descriptive</xref>, <xref type="note" doc="note" target="msiiipoetryanthology2">MS III Second Poetry Anthology</xref>, and <xref type="mss" doc="mss" target="3">MS III</xref> Poetry Anthology.</p>
<p>While no apparent logic governs completion of the anthology other than filling the notebook, it appears from <xref type="note" doc="note" target="ruskinjohnjames">John James Ruskin</xref>&rsquo;s open-ended record of his son&rsquo;s age as the boy entered successive fair copies (see Description) that the father at least may have looked for completion on those terms. Ruskin, however, left over thirty pages blank at the end of the manuscript (see Contents); and the likeliest explanation for this neglect may be that he was drawn to a grander project&mdash;the fair copy in MS VII of &ldquo;Iteriad&rdquo; and <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Athens.&rdquo;</xref> Selections from these epic-length poems appear toward the end of MS V, suggesting that Ruskin grew dissatisfied with their constrained appearance in <xref type="note" doc="note" target="miscellaneouspoetry">Miscellaneous Poetry</xref> and abandoned the anthology for grander presentation in MS VII. (Since Ruskin did not complete fair-copying <xref type="works" doc="works" target="xxx">&ldquo;Athens&rdquo;</xref> in MS VII, however, it is also possible that he returned to MS V to enter 17 stanzas of that poem on a less ambitious scale than that begun in MS VII.)</p>
<p>On p. 167&mdash;a verso, facing the first of the three blank final leaves (see Description)&mdash;Ruskin wrote in ink, but then erased,  <xref type="note" doc="note" target="miscellaneouspoetry">MISCELLANEOUS POETRY</xref> / HELVELLYN.  This is how the notebook begins on p. 1, so the reason for the erasure is not apparent. Since the erased material is upside down to the text coming from the other direction, perhaps it represents a false start.</p>
<p>On the back inside endpaper, Ruskin scribbled some numbers.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</group>
</text>
</TEI.2>
