<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject MANUSCRIPT followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "msi_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "msi_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_manuscript_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Manuscript</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>            
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
            <head type="title">Title of Manuscript</head>
                <!--A manuscript apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>BMS XID</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="LOCATION">
                    <head type="section">Location</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    PML (MA 2389)
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="PROVENANCE">
                    <head type="section">Provenance</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    Purchased by Morgan Library at Sotheby’s, 16 December 1964.
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DESCRIPTION">
                    <head type="section">Description</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    Two notebooks contained in dark-blue morocco-covered slipcase, gilded on the spine with the designation  RUSKIN / MS. / POETRY / OF / ARCHITECTURE / MODERN / PAINTERS. / VOL. I. / &#x0026;C. / 1902. 
                    As described in Works 1:2, two identical notebooks contain the incompletely surviving manuscript of The Poetry of Architecture, the series of essays originally published in ?? Loudon’s magazine, ??. The second of the two notebooks contains also manuscript of Ruskin’s letter to the Times of 7 January 1847 (Works 12: 397-406), and early draft of the opening of Modern Painters I (first printed in part, in a heavily edited version, in Works 3: 680-82). The texts are written in ink on lightly ruled, unwatermarked paper, bound in half-calf and marbled boards, approx. 16.8 × 20.3 cm. The binding appears original, as the marbling on the boards matches that on the edges of the paper. The following detailed discussion is focused especially on The Poetry of Architecture. For discussion of the other two manuscripts, see the appropriate volumes in Works and....
                    Notebook 1.--The first volume contains 64 leaves, including endpapers. The text begins on 3r, and is accurately numbered by Ruskin as pp. 1-122 (page numbers are frequently omitted, but the next page to be numbered is always counted accurately, as if all pages had numbered consistently throughout). Although this notebook contains fewer leaves than does notebook 2, it shows no evidence of leaves having been removed.
                    Tipped into the front of the notebook 1 is a description, in Wedderburn’s hand, listing the contents as follows:
                    
                    Ruskin MS.
                    This book contains the original MS. of the following chapters of  The Poetry of Architecture 
                    Part I.	Chap.	3.
                    4.
                    5.
                    6.
                    Part II.	Chap.	1.
                    2.
                    3.
                    4.
                    5.
                    Wedderburn’s table accurately lists the contents, according to the chapter’s numbering first adopted in ? and carried through ?. Notebook 1 begins with what Ruskin designates in manuscript as  No. 4,  a chapter found as chapter 3 in the Library Edition. This discrepancy carries through the draft’s  Chap. 7th --that is, chapter 6 of part 1 in the Library Edition--and on into the draft’s  Ch. 8. The Villa,  which forms chapter 1 of part 2 in the Library Edition. Notebook 1 continues in this manner through  Chap 12. <No 3.> The Villa. --that is, in the Library Edition numbering, chapter 5 of part 2.
                        Notebook 1 contains the originals of a few, by no means all, of the diagrams and sketches used to illustrate the published papers. One pencil sketch on the back endpaper of a roofline with gothic arches is not published, so far as I am aware.
                        Notebook 2.--This notebook is second in the sense that it contains the continuation of the Poetry of Architecture essays from notebook 1. Notebook 2 nonetheless displays a large, handwritten numeral  1  on the front cover. If by Ruskin, the numeral perhaps refers to the Modern Painters manuscript, which was begun on a recto immediately following the Poetry of Architecture the last installment of the manuscript.
                        Notebook 2 consists of 83 leaves, including some that have been partially cut away. A few more leaves were cut away altogether, with only very small stubs left behind.
                        Wedderburn’s table of contents, tipped into the front of notebook 2, reads as follows:
                        Ruskin MS.
                        This book contains
                        1.	Chapter VII of Part II of the Poetry of Architecture--arranged in the MS as two chapters 14 &#x0026; 15.
                        2.	MS. of parts of Modern Painters. Vol. 1.
                        3.	The draft of the letter on the  National Gallery  (Times Jan 7, 1847), p. 38
                        The major portion of The Poetry of Architecture contained in the second notebook is chapter 7 of part 2, the final chapter published by Loudon before ceasing publication of his magazine. In draft, this chapter is divided in two, designated as chapters 14 and 15. The division occurs at paragraph 230 as presently numbered, this paragraph forming the opening of the draft chapter 15. Since the two draft chapters are entitled identically in draft, as  The mountain Villa. England,  Ruskin must always have conceived of them as a unit.
                        Wedderburn’s table of contents for notebook 2 fails to list a portion of what is now known as chapter 6. Wedderburn may well have overlooked the chapter 6 fragment, since these few paragraphs follow chapter 7 in manuscript, and are not separately headed--only a blank line space indicating the separation between chapters. Wedderburn’s omission is corrected in the description of the manuscript provided in the Library Edition (Works 1:2), but this description, while generally accurate, allows the impression that the first notebook ends with the fragment of chapter 6--that is, with paragraphs 182-84, as numbered in the Library Edition--whereas, in fact, notebook 1 ends with paragraph 181 (Works 1:138), the conclusion of chapter 5, part 2. Paragraphs 182-84 constitute the fragment of chapter 6 that follows chapter 7 in notebook 2.
                        More precisely, the fragment of chapter 6 in notebook 2 extends from its opening (paragraph 182) through the middle of paragraph 184, ending with the phrase  fine detached specimens of the picturesque blue country  (in the published version,  fine detached specimens of the natural ‘green country’  [Works 1:140]). According to the Library Edition, this opening of chapter 6 plus a few more paragraphs existed also in a separate manuscript:  §§ 182-194 are preserved in the four pages of a separate sheet of foolscap. Thus of §§ 182-184 there are two MS. copies  (Works 1:2). This second foolscap copy must have been what was reproduced for the Library Edition (Works 1:140 opp.), since that facsimile shows a portion of manuscript later in paragraph 184 than what is available in notebook 2. The foolscap manuscript is not held by PML....
                        As for the remainder of The Poetry of Architecture manuscript, not contained in the PML notebooks or the ? foolscap manuscript, the Library Edition’s statement apparently remains correct, that  of §§ 1-37 and §§ 194-212 there is no MS extant  (Works 1:2).
                        In notebook 2, the text begins on 3r, and, as in notebook 1, the pages are accurately but erratically numbered by Ruskin--i.e., he counts the pages correctly, but actually writes numbers on the pages sporadically, starting from page 7. This continues through page 34; pages 35-36 (unnumbered by Ruskin) hold the end of chapter 7, and the fragment of chapter 6. Then begin the later manuscripts included in notebook 2, the Times letter (Works 12:397-406), and the Modern Painters I fragment.
                    <!--The subsection that follows, Collation, is common to all manuscript apparatuses and was, accordingly, assigned an xml:id by
                        the Ruskin Project Team during work on the "First Twenty."-->
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="COLLATION">
                    <head type="subsection">Collation</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="CONTENTS">
                    <head type="section">Contents</head>
                    <!--Typically, this section will begin:-->
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <!--and continue with a list, which may group items according to type (e.g. prose, poetry) or other similiarity. Note: drawings
                        may be included as items in this list.-->
                    <list xml:id="LIST" type="ordered">
                        <item n="a">Item belonging to Group A.</item>
                        <item n="b.1">First item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.2">Second item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.3">Third item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="c">Item belonging to Group C.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    Content
                    Notebook 1:
                    a) Blank colored endpaper (1r), with penciled note in Latin on verso (1v), and followed by blank leaf (2r-v).
                    b) Chapters of no. 255, as described above (3r-? [pp. 1-123, in Ruskin’s numbering). Pagination of individual chapters:
                    No. 4. The Mountain Cottage. Switzerland  (i.e., pt. 1, chap. 3), 3r-8v (pp. 1-12).
                    Chapter 5th The Mountain Cottage. Westmoreland  (i.e., pt. 1, chap. 4), 8v-15r (pp. 12-25).
                    Chap 6th A Chapter on Chimnies  (sic) (i.e., pt. 1, chap. 5), 15r-22r (pp. 25-39).
                    Chap. 7th  (i.e., pt. 1, chap. 6), 22r-27v (pp. 39-50).
                    Ch. 8. The Villa  (i.e., pt. 2, chap. 1), 28r-35v (pp. 51-66).
                    Ch. 9. The villa. Italy  (i.e., pt. 2, chap. 2), 35v-44r (pp. 66-83).
                    Ch. 10. The Villa. Italy  (i.e., pt. 2, chap. 3), 44r-50r (pp. 83-95.
                    Ch. 11. The Villa. England  (i.e., pt. 2, chap. 4), 50v-56r (pp. 96-107).
                    Chap 12. <No 3.> The Villa.  (i.e., pt. 2, chap. 5), 56v-63v (pp. 108-22).
                        c) Drawing, diagrams, and brief notes, 64r.
                        d) Blank colored endpaper, 64v, and inside back cover.
                        
                        Notebook 2:
                        a) Blank colored endpaper and first leaf (1r-2v).
                        b) Chapters of no. 255, as described above (3r-20v). Pagination of individual chapters:
                        3r-11r (i.e., pp. 1-17):  Chap. 14. The mountain villa. England,  i.e., as published, pt. 2, chap. 7 through § 229.
                        11v-20r (i.e., pp. 18-34 plus recto of the following, unnumbered leaf):  Chap. 15. The mountain Villa. England,  i.e., as published, pt. 2, chap. 7 from § 230 to end.
                        20r-v (unnumbered): untitled ms., i.e., as published, pt. 2, chap. 6, §§ 182-84 (§ 184 partial).
                        c) Draft of an early opening to Modern Painters, which was written largely on rectos only, many of the remaining blank versos being used later for (d) below. Pagination of specific portions of manuscript as follows:
                        21r (with a brief insertion in the text spilling onto a blank portion of 20v), 22r, 23r: untitled draft, printed in Works 3: 680-81, as draft (a).
                        24r, 25r, 26r, 27r, 28r, 29r, 30r-v, 31r-v, 32r, 33r: draft entitled  Chap. 1. Of Imitative art,  which is described and quoted in Works 3: 681, as draft (b). It is worth noting that, after two pages of this draft (24r and 25r), which seem to constitute an abortive beginning, Ruskin began numbering (from 26r) the rectos as pp. 1-8 (26-33 rectos only; versos ignored in his pagination, which, at the time, would have been blank). This numbering probably points to a second start on this chapter.
                        34r, 35r, 36r-v, 37r, 38r, 39r (mutilated), 40r, 41r-v, 42r-v, 43r, 44r, 45r-v, 46r-v, 47r (these rectos numbered by Ruskin as pp. 9-22, including the mutilated leaf): called  Chap II  in draft, the Library Edition identifies this as  substantially the same  as pt. 2, sec. 1, chap. 2 (i.e., Works 3: 140-48; see also 681). A beginning on the chapter was made on 34r, 35r, and 36r; then the chapter was begun anew on 37r, carrying through 47r--rectos mainly, with some brief notes and draft on 36v, 41v, 42v, 45v, and 46v.
                        The next section is complex owing to leaves having been mutilated or cut away altogether, after Ruskin numbered the rectos. As suggested in the Library Edition, the lost leaves probably contained the beginning of a chapter 4, since this portion of the manuscript begins with  Chap. III. Of the relative importance of truths  (47r), and arrives at  Chap. 5  (60r). This material was identified by the editors of the Library Edition as the germ of pt. 2, sec. 2, chaps 1-3 of Modern Painters--the truths of tone, color, and chiaroscuro.
                        The original pagination of this section of notebook 2 is somewhat doubtful, for it is difficult to determine the original position of the removed leaves, but the following is reasonably accurate (Ruskin’s pagination is cited in parentheses, which continues to refer to rectos only). Chapters 3/4 of manuscript are contained in 47r (p. 22), 48r (p. 23, with a brief note on 48v), 49r (p. 24), 50r (p. 25, with a long  note  on 50v), 51r (p. 26), 52r (p. 27).
                        Then, according to Ruskin’s numbering, which next shows a p. 30, two leaves have been removed. One of these remains present as a mutilated (partially cut away) 53r; as this leaf, along with p. 30, forms the center of a 12o gathering, it would have been numbered p. 29 on its recto. The other removed leaf, evidenced only by small torn stubs, would have been the preceding p. 28.
                        Chapters 3/4 continue with 54r (p. 30), 55r (p. 31), 56r (p. 32), 57r (p 33), 58r (p. 34), 59r (p. 35), 60r (p. 36). Separately from this run of text, Ruskin inserted a distinct piece of text on a series of versos, 54v, 55v, 56v, 57v, which would later be incorporated into the  Truth of Chiaroscuro  chapter of Modern Painters (pt. 2, sec. 2, chap. 3).
                        Chap. 5,  which the editors of the Library Edition connect with pt. 2, sec. 2, chaps. 4-5 of the published Modern Painters, is contained in 60r-81r, with briefer notes on 60v, 63v, 65v, 67v, 71v, 79v, 80v. The rectos were numbered by Ruskin up through p. 45 (69r).
                        d) Nearly complete manuscript of letter to the Times, 7 January 1847, up to  mighty foundation  in middle of closing sentence on 21v, 22v, 23v, 24v, 25v, 26v, 27v, 28v, 29v, 32v, 33v, 34v, 35v, 36r (following a fragment of Modern Painters draft at top of page), 36v (following a fragment of Modern Painters draft at top of page), 37v, 38v, 39v (a mutilated page, of which the verso contains only one word  foundation,  which should indeed follow  mighty,  end of 38v). (Two versos, 30v and 31v, were skipped over in drafting the letter, because these pages had already been used for overflow from the Modern Painters text.). The closing words of the letter do not appear to be extant; their draft may have been lost with the portion of 39r-v that was cut away.
                        e) Blank 82r-v and 83r-v. The inside back board contains diagrams of curves.
                        
                        Dating: the Times letter is dated Jan 6, 1847 in Lib Ed (12:406), and is said to have been published Jan 7 (12:396). If that’s right we can take the composition of that portion of ms. as Jan 5-6 (see 12:397 and n. 2).
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <!--The Discussion section may contain all or only some of the following subsections.-->
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Hand</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Composition &#x0026; Sources</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Domestic Scene</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>