<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "the_steam_engine_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department
                        of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;Title of Work&#x201D;</head>
                <!--An apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>“Skiddaw and Derwent Water,”</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>MSS II, V.MS V, begins tipped-in booklet, p. 10, opposite p. 144]</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>composed between late February or early March and May Misdated 1828, Works
                        2:536. In his May 10, 1829, letter presenting the poem for his father’s
                        birthday, Ruskin says “I think I began it about three months ago” (RFL,
                        200)--i.e., late February or early March (at the latest), which would
                        correspond to the position of the draft in MS II, following no. 43.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>Revised and split into two poems for inclusion in Spiritual Times (August
                        1829 and February 1830), as Ruskin’s first two publications. Printed in PJR,
                        1:11-14 (MS II version, edited and split into two poems, but not the same
                        division as that in Spiritual Times); Works, 2:265-68 (MS V and February
                        1830 Spiritual Times versions); Cook, Life, 23 (amalgam of portions of
                        February 1830 Spiritual Times and PJR editing of MS II version); and in John
                        Ruskin, Three Lakeland Poems, ed. and ptd. by J. S. Dearden (Bembridge:
                        Yellowsands Press, 1971) (MS V version).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>This draft must be “that blank verse upon Lake Derwent” that Ruskin “demurred
                        at bringing” to his father, as he reminds John James in the May 10 letter,
                        since “it was designed for your birthday and I did not wish you to see it
                        beforehand,” and “there was a line saying something about this happy day and
                        I was afraid you would ask me what happy day and then the whole secret would
                        gradually have been hauled out of my unwilling mouth” (RFL, 199). The draft
                        does contain such a line at the end of first section, that on Skiddaw (“. .
                        . but no more [on deleted] / on this sad subject on this happy day”), and
                        this line is present also in the fair-copy MS V version. (This penultimate
                        half-line and concluding line are omitted from PJR, 1:11-12, which prints
                        the MS II version, but which silently edits out these lines, presumably in
                        keeping with the policy that “Birthday Addresses usually need lopping to be
                        presentable as ‘poems’” [1:270].) Ruskin’s evasive maneuveurs to prevent his
                        father from reading the poem may have been negotiated about April, when a
                        gap in the family letters suggests that John James was at home. The
                        presentation copy of no. 44 alluded to in the May 10 letter is probably that
                        contained in the handmade booklet tipped into MS V, “Battle of Waterloo: A
                        Play,” a booklet that also presents fair copies of the (formerly misdated)
                        birthday poem no. 41 as well as of nos. 29, 36, 44, 57. That this fair copy
                        of no. 44 is Ruskin’s intended birthday presentation becomes more evident,
                        if one omits Burd’s bracketed editorial insertion in Ruskin’s remark, “On
                        Newyearsday I prepared a small poem for you,” so “on your birthday it
                        becomes me to have a much larger [one] for you” (RFL, 199); i.e., by a
                        “larger,” Ruskin may mean, not just a larger poem, but a much larger
                        project--the handmade booklet containing several poems and a play. The fair
                        copy of the poem in this booklet was not used by Collingwood as copytext,
                        probably because he had not seen the booklet by 1891, its insertion into MS
                        V being first mentioned in the Library Edition bibliography of the poetry
                        manuscripts (compare PJR, 1:264, and Works 2:531; Collingwood had seen the
                        booklet by 1893, however, when he summarizes it in Life, 32). If Burd takes
                        it too much for granted (RFL, 200 n. 3) that the enclosure with Ruskin’s 10
                        May 1829 letter must have been only one poem--a “missing” presentation copy
                        of no. 44, rather than, as I believe, the “Waterloo” booklet--nonetheless
                        one cannot entirely discount the possibility that no. 44 once existed in a
                        separate birthday presentation copy by itself. Such a copy might explain
                        Ruskin’s perplexing remark in the May 10 letter that he had “found a way of
                        evading this line” about the “happy day,” which the “poem sounded quite well
                        without” (RFL, 200)--perplexing, since the booklet version does retain the
                        line from MS II. Ruskin may mean, however, that he evaded the line when
                        reading the draft aloud to his father. In the MS II draft, the section that
                        Collingwood printed separately and entitled “Skiddaw” is followed by no. 45;
                        however, when the draft resumes after no. 45, there is no indication that
                        Ruskin intended a separate poem called, as Collingwood entitles it,
                        “Derwentwater” (PJR, 1:13-14). The draft following no. 45 begins “skiddaw
                        derwent water / Now derwent water come a looking glass,” a transition of a
                        like kind with one in the preceding draft that Collingwood omitted from his
                        printing of “Skiddaw”: “But enough / Ive treated of the clouds. now skiddaw
                        come” (falling in lines 14-15, as printed in PJR, 1:11). In other words, the
                        MS II version was intended as the integral piece that is fair-copied in MS V
                        (see Works, 2:266-68 n.), an intention evident from the start in Ruskin’s
                        draft title “description of skiddaw &#x0026; lake derwent.” The Library
                        Edition added both important textual and bibliographic detail and further
                        confusion, by claiming to print the text as it “first appeared in The
                        Spiritual Times . . . February 1830”--“the earliest printed work of Ruskin”
                        (Works, 2:265 n. 1). The claim is only half true, as James Dearden has
                        discovered (“John Ruskin’s First Published Work,” Book Collector 42, no. 2
                        [summer 1994]: 299-300). Ruskin’s first publication in fact occurred half a
                        year earlier, in the August 1829 number of The Spiritual Times, which
                        printed a version of the third strophe of the MSS II/V poem--i.e., the
                        strophe that in the MS II draft is designated “conclusion,” beginning “sweet
                        derwent on thy winding shore.” The printing appears as follows (with several
                        interesting variants from the earlier MSS II/V versions of the strophe;
                        compare Works, 2:267-68): This strophe, it was believed, had been cut when
                        the first “two sets of verses, on Skiddaw and Derwent Water respectively,
                        [were] run together,” as Cook and Wedderburn (misleadingly) state, and were
                        printed in the February 1830 Spiritual Times as “On Skiddaw and
                        Derwent-Water.” In fact, the concluding strophe was cut because it had
                        already been separately printed; and the remaining Skiddaw and Derwent Water
                        sections were not “run together,” since they had never been separated in the
                        first place (except for later, in Collingwood’s misinterpretation of the MS
                        II draft). Thus, among the decisions made in the few months between May and
                        August 1829--not the two years between 1828 and 1830, as believed until
                        recently--was, first, to separate the third, concluding strophe from the
                        body of the poem, as it had appeared in the draft and fair copy--a
                        separation never evident in any of Ruskin’s manuscripts. Second, significant
                        revisions were made to the now separated parts of the poem. Most notably, a
                        pious concluding couplet was added in the published “Lines,” and decorous
                        revisions transformed the ending of the 1830 “On Skiddaw and Derwent-Water,”
                        as well. The sentiment in these revisions can be seen as contradictory to
                        the spirit of the original versions. The friction caused by the revising
                        process is probably reflected in debates over worldly beauty versus
                        religious asceticism carried on in nos. 58-59. The debate seems to culminate
                        in no. 60--unusually illegible, scrawled draft that almost certainly
                        represents Ruskin’s troubled attempt at revising the Skiddaw and Derwent
                        Water poem for publication. The greater piety and decorum of the published
                        versions make sense in light of their venue. The Spiritual Times: A Monthly
                        Magazine was edited and owned by Ruskin’s tutor, the Reverend Edward
                        Andrews, who had been hired to teach Ruskin only a few months earlier, in
                        April (RFL 200). For information about Andrews as the magazine’s editor,
                        Dearden, in “John Ruskin’s First Published Work,” points to Ian Anstruther’s
                        Coventry Patmore’s Angel: A Study of Coventry Patmore, His Wife Emily and
                        “The Angel in the House” (London: Haggerston Press, 1992). Andrews, it
                        appears, published his own children’s verse in the journal, and so it was
                        natural enough that he would edit verse by his precocious new student.
                        (Reciprocally, John James would later copy verse by Andrews’s daughter Eliza
                        in Ruskin’s MS VI [see part 1, MS VI, e].) In retrospect, then, it was
                        auspicious that, in Ruskin’s May 10 birthday letter to his father
                        accompanying the MS V “On Skiddaw and Derwent Water,” he devoted a quarter
                        of the space celebrating the recent “coming of the tutor”--“a most important
                        aera of my life” (RFL, 200). Worshiping Andrews’s mirthful yet learned
                        character, Ruskin must have been ecstatic to be published in his tutor’s
                        magazine, whatever he may have felt about the revisions demanded of his
                        poem. The subsequent oversight of the 1829 printing of “Lines” cannot be
                        attributed entirely to Cook and Wedderburn’s carelessness. John James
                        himself seems to cite the 1830 “On Skiddaw and Derwent-Water” as Ruskin’s
                        first publication in a list he compiled of Ruskin’s poetry publications (“on
                        Skiddaw &#x0026; Derwent Water / page 72 Spiritual Times / Feby 1830 age 11
                        years”; see part 1, MS IV). Although John James compiled this list in the
                        later 1840s, almost two decades following the publication of “Lines,” it is
                        very odd that the admiring father could have forgotten even the slightest
                        detail about Ruskin’s first appearance in print. Surely, John James would
                        have recalled not only his own pride but also, if a now common belief can be
                        credited, his part in revising the poem for press (see B. E. Maidment,
                        “‘Only Print’--Ruskin and the Publishers,” Durham University Journal 63, no.
                        3 [n.s. 32, no. 3] [June 1971]: 196). (No copies, incidentally, of either
                        the August 1829 or the February 1830 issues of the Spiritual Times are
                        presently known to have been owned by the Ruskins--the Bembridge copies, one
                        of the last additions to the collection prior to its move to Lancaster,
                        having originally belonged to Andrews--but it is beyond credibility that the
                        family did not own both issues. See RBB, 214; and James S. Dearden, “The
                        Ruskin Galleries at Bembridge School, Isle of Wight,” Bulletin of the John
                        Rylands Library 51, no. 2 [Spring 1969]: 334.) John James’s mistaken entry
                        in MS IV is crossed out in pencil, which may mean that somebody in the
                        family had spotted its inaccuracy; however, the scoring could also represent
                        John James’s decision, a curious one, not to include his son’s first two
                        publications in the 1850 Poems by “J.R”--not even the 1830 “On Skiddaw and
                        Derwent-Water,” which he certainly remembered. The omission raises
                        interesting questions that cannot be resolved in light of the available,
                        largely negative evidence, but that at least challenge prevailing
                        assumptions. Did John James, for example, in fact have a hand in revising
                        the 1829/30 poems for press--a notion, after all, that started with a mere
                        hazarded opinion by Cook and Wedderburn that “it is possible that Ruskin’s
                        father or the editor touched them up for publication” (Works, 2:265 n.)? Was
                        there, rather, something in the editing of the poems, and Andrews’s role in
                        their publication, that either John James or Ruskin himself disliked enough
                        to exclude them, two decades later, from the private-circulation collection?
                        In 1850, John James informed his son that “we shall not print your 12 year
                        poems which the marvellous are better in your own printed written [i.e.,
                        hand-lettered] little Book--We shall begin with Months age 16 I believe
                        unless you desire earlier pieces” (qtd. in “Ruskin’s Poems 1850”). This does
                        not explain why John James preferred the earlier poems to remain in their
                        presentation-copy format; and, in any case, the 1850 Poems did not begin
                        with “The Months” (no. 194) but with “Song” (no. 176), a previously
                        unpublished poem of 1833. “Skiddaw” and “Lines” could have been vetoed by
                        Ruskin owing to their trammelment in the religious and intellectual conflict
                        already mentioned. John James could have harbored some resentment of Andrews
                        as the first competition by an older male for his son’s affections, a
                        possible jealousy that might have fed John James’s and Margaret’s later list
                        of reasons for disapproving of the preacher and his family (see RFL 242-43,
                        366). Again, one must guard against overinterpreting negative evidence, but
                        the subsequent bibliographic history concerning Ruskin’s first publications
                        grows irresistibly bizarre. In a part of Deucalion issued in October 1879,
                        Ruskin confidently relayed an anecdote that transferred the event of his
                        first appearance in print to his first prose publication, his 1834 papers
                        for Loudon’s Magazine of Natural History (nos. 190-91, 193): I well yet
                        remember my father’s rushing up to the drawing-room at Herne Hill, with wet
                        and flashing eyes, with the proof in his hand of the first sentences of his
                        son’s writing ever set in type,--“Inquiries on the Causes of the Colour of
                        the Water of the Rhone” . . . . My mother and I eagerly questioning the
                        cause of his excitement,--“It’s--it’s--only print!” said he. Alas! how much
                        the “only” meant! (Works, 26:275) Ruskin may have been misled by a recent
                        bibliography of his published writings, Shepherd, of which the first edition
                        was published in September 1878, and which lists the “Inquiries” as Ruskin’s
                        first periodical publication. In October 1878, Ruskin had written to
                        Shepherd of the bibliography, “It will be of extreme value to me in filling
                        up what gaps I can in this patched coverlid of my life before it is draped
                        over my coffin--if it may be” (Works, 34:537). Shepherd, however, must have
                        been misled in his turn by Ruskin, who, in an 1872 edition of the Catalogue
                        of the Rudimentary Series of drawings at the Oxford schools, had remarked
                        “that Mr. Loudon was the first literary patron who sent words of mine to be
                        actually set up in print, in his Magazine of Natural History, when I was
                        sixteen” (Works, 21:243). The important point, I believe, is that Ruskin--in
                        the 1870s and in the context of his writings on drawing, botany, and
                        geology--wanted to believe that his first publications were scientific and
                        factual, not poetic, in nature. Since Shepherd and Ruskin’s published
                        remarks in the 1870s on his first publication would have been taken as
                        authoritative, the succeeding major bibliographies--Wise (1:302-3, 2:111),
                        and the chronological list of publications appended to Collingwood’s Life
                        (1893, 1:233)--likewise awarded the distinction to the 1834 papers for
                        Loudon’s Magazine. Ruskin’s first poetry publications, according to these
                        bibliographies, were the 1835 contributions to Friendship’s Offering (see
                        nos. 180, 207; Wise, 2:123; Collingwood, Life [1893], 1:233). Wise and his
                        co-editor Smart were unlikely to be disabused by Ruskin or the Severns of
                        any errors, the response from Brantwood to Wise being as politely insouciant
                        and unhelpful as Ruskin had been to Shepherd (“Wise and Ruskin I,” 48,
                        51-52). Collingwood, for his part, may have relied more on Wise and Smart
                        than they did on him (see “Wise and Ruskin I,” 46-47). Collingwood’s
                        persistence in the error is remarkable, however, since he knew about John
                        James’s entry in MS IV on the Spiritual Times publication and even printed
                        it, without comment, in 1891 (PJR 1:264; Collingwood misprinted the 1830
                        date of publication as “1831”). This did not prevent Collingwood two years
                        later in the Life (1893) from maintaining that Ruskin “began his literary
                        career” as the “analytic John Ruskin . . . already an enfant terrible”
                        (1:49-50). In light of what, by the 1890s, appears to have settled into a
                        prejudice favoring Ruskin’s analytic and scientific beginnings, Cook and
                        Wedderburn must be given credit for locating at least the 1830 Spiritual
                        Times version of “On Skiddaw and Derwent-Water,” which they used as their
                        main copytext. Still, this printing contains one-and-a-half dozen
                        punctuation variants from the original Spiritual Times version and changes
                        the wording of three lines (line 11, “Chasing the others off” for “Chasing
                        each other off” in the original; line 17, “majestic, a giant-nature’s work”
                        for “majestic, giant-nature’s work”; and line 42, “And when he’s made it”
                        for “And when he’s made”). The “Lines” were not, as the published title
                        claims, “written at the lakes in Cumberland.” Rather, as Cook and Wedderburn
                        are probably correct in suggesting about “On Skiddaw and Derwent Water,” the
                        poetry harkens back to the family’s 1826 trip to the Lakes (Works, 2:265 n.
                        1); they had also visited the district in 1824 and 1822 (TLC, 6-7). A “great
                        tour” to the Lakes projected for 1828 had been cancelled due to the death of
                        John James’s sister (see no. 25). Perhaps Ruskin believed that poetic
                        compensation for the lost tour and anticipation of next journey to the Lakes
                        (1830) would be appropriate for his father’s 1829 birthday. </p>
                    <p>Body paragraph containing a list: <list type="ordered">
                            <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                            <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                            <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p><p><!--Correction needed here?--> [This belongs in &#x201C;Skiddaw&#x201D; and not here:
                        there&#x02BC;s no reason JJR would have recorded or cared about the
                        drafting date of the poem.] Only a few years prior to this announcement,
                        Dearden, along with Van Akin Burd, had pointed out another major error in the
                        bibliography of Ruskin&#x02BC;s so&#x2010;called first published poem,
                        the belief that &#x201C;On Skiddaw and Derwent Water&#x201D; was first
                        drafted in 1828 (TLC, 7, 20 n. 20). In fact, &#x201C;description of skiddaw
                        &#x0026; lake derwent,&#x201D; as Ruskin entitled the draft and the fair
                        copy of his poem (MSS II, V), was composed between late February or early March
                        and May 1829 for his father&#x02BC;s birthday. Then, within a few
                        months&#x2014;not a few years, as always believed&#x2014;a part of
                        the &#x201C;description&#x201D; was published. That part became
                        the &#x201C;Lines Written at the Lakes in Cumberland&#x201D; in the
                        August 1829 Spiritual Times, a journal owned and edited by Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                        tutor, the Reverend Edward Andrews. In the following February, 1830, the
                        remaining portion of the original &#x201C;description&#x201D; appeared
                        as &#x201C;On Skiddaw and Derwent Water.&#x201D;</p></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TEXTUALNOTE">
                    <head type="section">Textual Note</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
