<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">#########</title>
                <title type="sub">etext generated from a transcription of a manuscript</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>Louisiana Board of Regents</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>ERM version 1.0 encoded Oct. 2009</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>###########</idno>
                <date when="2010-01-14">#######</date>
                <distributor>The Early Ruskin Manuscripts Project</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>###INSERT COPYRIGHT STATEMENT###</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="influence">###Insert notation of poetic influences here###</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <!-- possibly change to <msDesc> tag-->
                    <author>John Ruskin</author>
                    <title>########</title>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from original manuscript</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head>#########</head>
            <!-- Front matter should only be used for acurately representing the manuscript being transcribed... 
                not to display a heading in the website....-->
        </front>
        <body>
            <head type="title">&#x0201C;The Constellations: Northern, Some of the Zodiac, and
                Some of the Southern&#x0201D;</head>
            <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="caps">Title</hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x0201C;The Constellations: Northern, Some of the Zodiac, and Some of the
                    Southern&#x0201D;</p>
                <p>In <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS III</ref>, Ruskin wrote the title as
                        &#x0201C;<hi rend="caps">THE CONSTELLATIONS / NORTHERN, SOME OF THE
                        ZODIAC AND / SOME OF THE SOUTHERN.</hi>&#x0201D; In <ref type="mss"
                        target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref>, he wrote the title nearly identically, merely
                    breaking the lines differently, as &#x0201C;<hi rend="caps">THE
                        CONSTELLATIONS NORTHERN / SOME OF THE ZODIAC / AND SOME OF THE
                        SOUTHERN.</hi>&#x0201D; In <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF
                        T70</ref>, the extension &#x0201C;<hi rend="caps">NOTHERN . . .
                        SOUTHERN</hi> is placed awkwardly, as if possibly inserted as an
                    afterthought.</p>
                <p>See <ref type="note" target="titlecitation.php">System of Title Citation for
                        Works</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="caps">Genre</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Poem; <ref type="note" target="catalog.php">catalog poem</ref>; possibly a <ref
                        type="note" target="newyearspoems.php">New Year&#x02019;s
                    Poem</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="FACSIMILES">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="caps">Facsimiles</hi>
                </head>
                <p>[none]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="caps">Major Manuscripts</hi>
                </head>
                <p><ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref>; <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS
                        III</ref>; <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref>.</p>
                <p>In <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS III</ref>, a <ref type="note" target="redbook.php">Red Book</ref> devoted initially to <ref type="works"
                        target="20.php">&#x0201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x0201D; Vol. 2</ref>,
                    &#x0201C;The Constellations&#x0201D; is the first poem in the <ref
                        type="note" target="msiiipoetryanthology2.php">MS III Second Poetry
                        Anthology</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="caps">Date</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Late 1827 to January 1828.</p>
                <p>The fair copy in <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS III</ref> is undated, but its
                    placement immediately following <ref type="works" target="20.php"
                        >&#x0201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x0201D; Vol. 2</ref>, and before <ref
                        type="works" target="22.php">&#x0201C;The Sun&#x0201D;</ref>
                    suggests New Year&#x02019;s 1828. Thus, the editors of the <ref type="note" target="libraryedition.php">Library Edition</ref> are strictly correct in
                    listing the poem under 1827&#x02014;that is, composition in late 1827 for a
                    New Year&#x02019;s 1828 presentation. However, the editors seem to intend
                    earlier 1827, associating the poem with the rough draft of <ref type="works"
                        target="xxx.php">&#x0201C;The Monastery&#x0201D;</ref> in <ref
                        type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref> (which they misdate as 1827). If
                    they based their dating on harder evidence contained in the rough draft of
                    &#x0201C;The Constellations&#x0201D; in <ref type="mss"
                        target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref> (see <ref type="biblio"
                        target="jrworksle.php">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 2:535),
                    their reasoning cannot be confirmed or denied, since a piece of that rough draft
                    manuscript is now very likely missing (see <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS
                        IA: </ref>Contents, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>).</p>
                <p>The evidence in <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS III</ref> does hold open a
                    possibility for an earlier date. As noted in <ref type="works"
                        target="1.php#DISCUSSION">&#x0201C;The Needless Alarm&#x0201D;:
                        Discussion</ref>, and <ref type="works" target="4.php#DISCUSSION"
                        >&#x0201C;Time: Blank Verse&#x0201D;: Discussion</ref>, Ruskin
                    tended to include his previous year&#x02019;s <ref type="note" target="newyearspoems.php">New Year&#x02019;s Poem</ref> along with the
                    most recent New Year&#x02019;s presentation poem in the anthologies
                    following &#x0201C;Harry and Lucy.&#x0201D; Thus, &#x0201C;The
                    Constellations&#x0201D; could have existed in a version as a New
                    Year&#x02019;s gift for 1827, which Ruskin copied here. Given the evidence
                    in Composition and Publication, however, a likelier scenario has Ruskin
                    preparing a fair copy (<ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref>) for
                    presentation on 1 January 1828 (not 1827)&#x02014;a copy that either he did
                    complete and present, but then retracted for to revise for <ref type="mss"
                        target="3.php">MS III</ref>, or that he sacrificed to revision before
                    presentation and fair-copied the results in <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS
                        III</ref>.</p>
                <p>See <ref type="note" target="datecitation.php">System of Date
                    Citation</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="caps">Composition &#38; Publication</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Quoted in Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works,</hi> 2:260 n. 1. Previously
                    unpublished in entirety.</p>
                <p>The <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref> version appears to be the
                    earliest, a partial pencil draft, which starts with line 27 of the poem. (For
                    possible records of a now missing sheet of this draft, containing the opening 26
                    lines, see <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA: </ref>Contents, <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi>.) This draft provided the basis for a fair copy in <ref
                        type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref>, which follows <ref type="mss"
                        target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref> closely, but which notably omits, at line 64,
                        <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref>&#x02019;s &#x0201C;I
                    end end.&#x0201D; Since even <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref>
                    continues its draft beyond this declaration, Ruskin clearly changed his mind in
                    mid&#45;draft about concluding the poem, and therefore he omitted this line
                    when fair&#45;copying for <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF
                    T70</ref>.</p>
                <p>The <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref> version in turn formed the
                    basis for the <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS III</ref> version. <ref
                        type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref> itself is a photograph, taken for
                    the <ref type="note" target="libraryedition.php">Library Edition</ref> but
                    unused, of a manuscript whose whereabouts is now unknown (see also <ref
                        type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA: </ref>Contents, <hi rend="italic"
                    >b</hi>). There appear to be at least three stages of composition reflected in
                    the manuscript.</p>
                <p>First, the photograph shows a neatly printed, ink fair copy, which runs the full
                    length of the poem, adhering to the text of <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS
                        IA</ref> at least from line 27, the first line currently extant. This fair
                    copy, moreover, improves the draft in <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS
                        IA</ref> by capitalizing first letters of each line (and capitalizing the
                    entire first word of line 1); by punctiliously punctuating the end of each line,
                    through line 19 (after which end&#45;line punctuation is dropped); and by
                    inserting marginal line numbering at the left of the text.</p>
                <p>Next, the fair copy was used for revision, which appears to be represented in two
                    stages, first apparently in pencil and second in ink. Because the photograph can
                    show only relative darkness and texture of these insertions, the two stages
                    cannot always be definitively distinguished. It is unquestionable, however, that
                    the photograph shows a palimpsest since, in places, a dark ink hand overwrites a
                    much lighter hand, and under magnification the lighter hand shows the variable
                    texture of pencil stroke, and the darker hand the evenness of ink.</p>
                <p>Apparently in the first stage of this revision, someone using the lighter hand
                    marked the ends of lines with a short diagonal line (/), sometimes with a double
                    diagonal (//), but marked other lines with a cross (X), and the latter show
                    cancellations and insertions&#x02014;in the form of strikethrough and caret,
                    within the line; in the form of longhand insertion, in the margin. (Minor
                    variations occur in this pattern.) Presumably, the lines with Xs were flagged
                    for revision, but by whom, and whether by the same person who simultaneously or
                    subsequently wrote the insertion, one can only guess. On the whole, the marginal
                    insertions appear to be in pencil, the same color and texture as the diagonals
                    and Xs. The second stage of revision, insofar as it can be distinguished from
                    the first, appears to be represented by the ink overwriting. But the two stages
                    may be only apparent, and the actual sequence more complex.</p>
                <p>The longhand in <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref> is somewhat
                    awkward, in keeping with the fact documented in family letters that Ruskin had
                    only recently started practicing longhand as well as the use of ink (see <ref
                        type="note" target="ruskinshand.php">Ruskin&#x02019;s Hand</ref>). It
                    is possible, however, that more than one hand is represented in the
                    revisions.</p>
                <p>There appear to be several possible reasons why the fair copy shown in <ref
                        type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref> was sacrificed to revision. Ruskin
                    may have felt that the fair&#45;copy was spoiled by the error in line 54,
                    which he ended with <hi rend="italic">appear,</hi> thus repeating the rhyme word
                    at the end of the previous line, in place of <hi rend="italic">bear,</hi> which
                    ends line 54 in <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref>, and to which he
                    returned in <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS III</ref>. Moreover, about the
                    same place, starting with with line 53 in <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF
                        T70</ref>, the printing becomes noticeably larger, as if he was suddenly in
                    a hurry. Perhaps most importantly, two significant confusions arise in the sense
                    of the text at about this point.</p>
                <p>First, the pair of couplets starting at line 57 about the Scales and the Milky
                    Way, which made little sense in <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">MS IA</ref>,
                    made even less sense in <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref>; and
                    hence, lines 57&#x02013;60 of <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref>
                    are heavily scored through (and after line 60, Ruskin also stopped marginally
                    numbering the lines). First, it appears, Ruskin revised the first of these
                    couplets, concerning the scales, to arriving at the <ref type="mss"
                        target="3.php">MS III</ref> version (&#x0201C;The scales in which twas
                    vainly said / The crimes and virtues of men were weighed&#x0201D; [lines
                    57&#x02013;58]). Draft for these lines appear in ink draft at the bottom of
                    this sheet, overwriting an earlier, canceled pencil version (that earlier
                    version apparently still related the Scales to the Milky Way, but the lines are
                    largely illegible in the photograph).</p>
                <p>Then, in place of lines 59&#x02013;60 of <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF
                        T70</ref>, concerning the Milky Way, Ruskin composed five new lines and
                    inserted them as lines 65&#x02013;69 of <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS
                        III</ref>. The draft, which is worked out on both sides of the sheet
                    (including what would have been the blank p. 4 of the <ref type="mss"
                        target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref> folded fair copy), exhibits some tension
                    between an Evangelical assessment of pagan myths and the classical lines that
                    won out in <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS III</ref>. On p. 4, the
                    underwriting in pencil reads, &#x0201C;[to(?)] heaven but / not [to(?)] hell
                    [for when (?)] / they went to / place [I(?)] say [that then (?)] / they took
                    quite / a different way / and this is all that Ive to say about the beauty [(?)]
                    milky way.&#x0201D; Overwriting this are lines approximating, but not
                    identical to the <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS III</ref> version:
                    &#x0201C;which all their best and bravest trod / of heroes that their
                    countrys good / espoused and neer in angry mood / unto great jupiters blest
                    abode.&#x02019; The final version, in <ref type="mss" target="3.php">MS
                        III</ref>, takes a middle way between the Christian piety of the pencil
                    draft and the classical patriotism of the ink draft: &#x0201C;But oh that
                    wonder of them all / Which milky way europeans call / And which the ancients
                    thought the road / Which all their best and bravest trod / Unto great Jupiters
                    blest abode.&#x0201D; (The first three lines of this version are worked out
                    in ink draft on p. 3 [inside spread, recto] of <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php"
                        >RF T70</ref>, &#x0201C;but oh that wonder of them all / which milky way
                    europeans call / and which the ancients thought the road.&#x0201D;)</p>
                <p>Another confusion toward the end of the <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF
                        T70</ref> fair copy (line 64, or line 62 in <ref type="mss" target="3.php"
                        >MS III</ref>), which may have contributed to Ruskin&#x02019;s giving up
                    this fair copy to revision, arose evidently from a muddle over the order of the
                    constellations, which failed to conform with the linear order of his <ref
                        type="note" target="catalog.php">catalog poem</ref>. Line 64 in the earlier
                    version, &#x0201C;I wish I had not observed the lyre,&#x0201D; harkened
                    back to line 17, &#x0201C;After that doth come the lyre.&#x0201D; At
                    both these points in <ref type="mss" target="xxx.php">RF T70</ref>, a revision
                    about the &#x0201C;frightened hare&#x0201D; is entered in the margin,
                    which ultimately replaced line 17.</p>
                <p>The hand for these changes indicate a growing hurry and restlessness. As
                    suggested in Date, the evidence may point to hurried preparations for New
                    Year&#x02019;s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="caps">Discussion</hi>
                </head>
                <p>In <ref type="works" target="20.php">&#x0201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x0201D;
                        Vol. 2</ref>, which precedes &#x0201C;The Constellations,&#x0201D;
                    Harry gives Lucy a drawing of Charles&#x02019;s Wain &#x0201C;as an
                    introduction to astronomy&#x0201D;; and <ref type="works" target="22.php"
                        >&#x0201C;The Sun,&#x0201D;</ref> which follows &#x0201C;The
                    Constellations,&#x0201D; shares an interest in this topic.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
