<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject MANUSCRIPT followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "msi_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "msi_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_manuscript_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Manuscript</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>            
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
            <head type="title">Title of Manuscript</head>
                <!--A manuscript apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>MS IV</p>
                    W. G. Collingwood assigned roman numeral IV to this Red Book in his “Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems” for Poems (1891) (Poems [4o, 1891], 1:262; Poems [8o, 1891], 1:263).
                    Two decades earlier, Ruskin himself had set the precedent for numbering the Red Books, including this one: at bottom of the title page for “Eudosia,” he wrote “Red book No. 1. Sept 8th 1870” (see “Eudosia”: Title). On the same day, he docketed MS III as “Red book No. 2,” and MS I as “Red book No. 3.” For the meaning of this numbering, see Red Books.
                    Apart from these numerical designations, Ruskin’s title—intended originally, it appears, both for MS IV in its entirety as well as for its main work—is “EUDOSIA OR / A POEM / ON THE / UNIVERSE / BY JOHN RUSKIN / VOL I / These are thy glorious works parent of good / Almighty thine this universal frame / Thus wondros fair MILTON / BOTANY / HERN HILL / DULWICH.”
                    See also System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts.
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="LOCATION">
                    <head type="section">Location</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    Beinecke Library, Yale University, catalogued as . . . Formerly, the Beinecke kept the manuscript inside the slip case “Harry & Lucy, Poems &c,” which contained it along with four other manuscripts when purchased. The slip case is now preserved separately. 
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="PROVENANCE">
                    <head type="section">Provenance</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    See Provenance: Sotheby’s 1930.
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DESCRIPTION">
                    <head type="section">Description</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    Red book; 9.7 × 14.6 cm. ?? leaves.
                    Collation
                    Inside front endboard + “Eudosia”: Title (1r) + pp. 1–33, with p. 1 started on 1v + ?? unnumbered leaves (or ??r/v–??r/v, with ??r/v–??r/v blank and ??r/v–??r/v containing text written reverso from back of book.
                    Pasted to inside front endboard: clipping from Poems (1891) describing MS IV.
                    <!--The subsection that follows, Collation, is common to all manuscript apparatuses and was, accordingly, assigned an xml:id by
                        the Ruskin Project Team during work on the "First Twenty."-->
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="COLLATION">
                    <head type="subsection">Collation</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="CONTENTS">
                    <head type="section">Contents</head>
                    <!--Typically, this section will begin:-->
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <!--and continue with a list, which may group items according to type (e.g. prose, poetry) or other similiarity. Note: drawings
                        may be included as items in this list.-->
                    <list xml:id="LIST" type="ordered">
                        <item n="a">Item belonging to Group A.</item>
                        <item n="b.1">First item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.2">Second item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.3">Third item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="c">Item belonging to Group C.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    From front of book, the sequential order of contents:
                    a. “Eudosia,” including “The Yew” incorporated into the end of the poem (1r, containing the title page + pp. 1–17, with p. 1 on verso of title page [blank apart from page number], and p. 2 containing the beginning of the text).
                    b. Blank, except for Ruskin’s page numbering (pp. 18–19).
                    c. List of Ruskin’s Published Poems, 1830–46, Compiled by John James Ruskin (pp. 20–33 + the immediately following unnumbered leaf).
                    d. 21 blank, unnumbered leaves.
                    Reverso, from back of book, the sequential order of contents: 
                    e. Mineralogy Notes [ca. 1829] (1r–3r).
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    September 1828 to early 1830; 1836; ca. 1845–46 (by John James Ruskin).
                    
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    MS IV is like some other Red Books (e.g., MS III and MS IIIA) in that it starts with a title page announcing a single work (see Title) but—Ruskin failing to realize the ambitious length and predominance of that work—the manuscript was left open to being filled by other kinds of writing. MS IV, however, was left with an unusually large blank section: from the page containing the final fair-copied lines of “Eudosia” (p. 17) to the Mineralogy Notes [ca. 1829] entered reverso from the other end, MS IV contained a section of 29 leaves, blank except for numbering on some pages, until two decades after its initial use, when John James Ruskin used some of those leaves for his catalog of his son’s published poems. Over time, Ruskin put space in other Red Books to various uses—the additional poetry anthologies in MS III, the mineralogy notes in MS IIIA (although that Red Book also retained blank sections extending to significant lengths), the sermon drafts in Juvenilia MS A. That Ruskin left so much of MS IV unused may suggest that he persisted longer in an intention to carry on with the manuscript’s main work, “Eudosia,” compared to ambitions for “Harry and Lucy,” which he relinquished more easily in MS III and MS IIIA. If so, his lingering ambitions for a long poem would be more expected than for Edgeworthian lessons, which he more quickly outgrew.
                    If Ruskin had devoted additional Red Books to further “volumes” of “Eudosia”—beyond the first volume he planned for MS IV, which he gave over to the subject of “Botany”—he presumably would have continued to follow something like the plan found in his source, Lofft, Eudosia. Since Ruskin subdivides his first volume of his “Poem on the Universe” into “books” (of which he never got beyond the start of book 2), he is even more ambitious than Lofft, whose “Poem on the Universe” is divided only into books (not volumes containing books), of which the first is “The Earth,” corresponding to Ruskin’s “Botany.” It is possible that one of the fair-copy versions of “The Constellations: Northern, Some of the Zodiac, and Some of the Southern”—that in MS IA, or RF T70—represents a continuation of Ruskin’s scheme beyond the first volume in MS IV, as a volume on the stars would correspond to Lofft’s poem: see “Eudosia”: Discussion.
                    <!--The Discussion section may contain all or only some of the following subsections.-->
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Hand</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Composition &#x0026; Sources</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Domestic Scene</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>