<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "the_steam_engine_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="travel_itinerary_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Travel Itinerary and Tour Notes</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>htts://erm.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">Travel Itinerary and Tour Notes</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Untitled by Ruskin.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Imitation of a travel guide.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>MS IVB.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Before May and through mid-July 1828. The two lists of itineraries (see Composition and Publication) can be dated only approximately, 
                        owing to the failure of any family letters to survive from 1828, except for a New Year’s address dated from the last day of the year 
                        (RFL 170-71). One letter ascribed to earlier in 1828, a poem for John James’s birthday, is an error in RFL (see no. 41); 
                        therefore, we cannot be certain that the family departed Herne Hill following John James’s May 10 birthday. 
                        Some dates in May through July can be attached to the actual tour. The prospective list would have been compiled prior to departure, 
                        of course, presumably at a time when John James was at home to help annotate the list.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition and Publication</head>
                    <p>Portion reproduced in Hunt, John Ruskin: A Wider Sea, fig. 6a. 
                        Quoted in Ruskin, Works, 1:xxv-xxvi n. 2. Previously unpublished in entirety.</p>
                    <p>See Discussion for the genesis of the travel plans. MS IVB contains two itineraries, one at the front of the notebook, and the other at the back, 
                        consisting of lists of city names, sometimes annotated with sightseeing features to be found in those towns and cities.</p>
                    <p>Helen Viljoen interpreted the itinerary at the front of the Red Book as Ruskin’s prospective plan with annotations by John James, 
                        and the list at the end as notes taken during the actual trip (“Dating MSS. of Boyhood,” HGVP, boxes D.V, E.IX). 
                        Viljoen’s interpretation is supported by the prospective list being printed neatly in ink by Ruskin 
                        (longhand annotations by John James), while the notes for the actual tour are more roughly written in Ruskin’s ink longhand.</p>
                    <p>Thus, it appears, sometime prior to departure, Ruskin devised the list of prospective places by dividing pages in half horizontally, 
                        and labeling each half-page with a place name. Most sections were then annotated by John James with features of special interest, 
                        obviously drawing on some guidebook, and, one imagines, consulting with his wife and son.</p>
                    <p>Later, during the journey itself, Ruskin listed merely the names of places they visited, the swing back to London occurring soon after arriving in Plymouth, 
                        where the family learned of Aunt Jessie’s death.</p>
                    <p>Some years later, the lists became densely crowded by Ruskin’s mineralogy notes, written reverso from the other end of the notebook (see no. 171; and part 2, MS IVB, “Content”).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>These travel itineraries and notes record plans for the Ruskins’ “great tour” of the Lake District in 1828. 
                        The tour was planned to compensate for the leaner years of 1826 and 1827, when business kept John James Ruskin 
                        on the road traveling for orders longer into the spring than normal.</p>
                    <p>As it turned out, the tour to the Lakes was not realized until 1830, 
                        the 1828 journey having been interrupted on 24 May by news of the 12 May death 
                        of “Aunt Jessie,” John James’s sister, Mrs. Patrick Richardson (see Tour to the Lakes in Cumberland, ed. Burd and Dearden, 7; 
                        and Ruskin, Works, 35:70, where the death is mistakenly ascribed to 1829).</p>
                    <p>For another instance of Ruskin’s preplanning trips, see RFL, 220.</p>
                     </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>