<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "the_steam_engine_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;The Monastery&#x201D;</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Misdated 1827 in Works, 2:260.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>MSS IA, III.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>Brief excerpts printed PJR, 1:273; Works 2:260 n. 1, 276 n. 1. Previously unpublished in entirety.</p>
                    <p>On <date when="1829-03-04">March 4, 1829</date>, <!-- find out which Margaret -->Margaret refers to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s writing &#x201C;a novel&#x201D; (RFL, 185)&#x2014;i.e., 
                        this versification of the opening of <persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName>&#x02BC;s novel, <hi rend="italic"><title type="book" corresp="SCOTTMONASTERY">The Monastery</title></hi>. 
                        On <date when="1829-03-10">March 10</date>, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> writes to <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName>, 
                        &#x201C;I am trying to get that red book [<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>] of mine which has <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMONASTERY">the Monastery</title> in it finished, by the time you come home&#x201D; (RFL, 192).</p>
                    <p>In <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> &#x201C;<title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMONASTERY">The Monastery</title>&#x201D; is placed following an earlier, late&#x2010;<date when="1827">1827</date> group of poems called &#x201C;poetry descriptive&#x201D; (see no. 12) 
                        but in a more mature hand than that earlier group. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> copied his books 1 and 2 of &#x201C;<title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMONASTERY">The Monastery</title>&#x201D; until he ran out of room at the end of the book, 
                        and then continued with books 3 and 4 on some available blank leaves before the &#x201C;poetry descriptive&#x201D; but immediately following a group of poems dated <date when="1829-03-09">March 9, 1829</date> (see no. 47). 
                        Thus, &#x201C;<title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMONASTERY">The Monastery</title>&#x201D;&#x2014;or, at the very least, its second and third books&#x2014;was finished at about the same time as the <date when="1829-03-09">March 9</date> group 
                        (so far, that is, as &#x201C;<title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMONASTERY">The Monastery</title>&#x201D; ever did reach completion).</p>
                    <p><title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title> includes a one-sheet, ink, longhand set of lines that forms part of the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> poem&#x02BC;s &#x201C;book third,&#x201D; 
                        as well as a one-sheet pencil version of part of the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> poem&#x02BC;s &#x201C;book second&#x201D; (see part 2, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>, &#x201C;Content,&#x201D; a). 
                        It is possible that the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title> pencil version of part of &#x201C;book second&#x201D; is <!-- problematic tag; revisit later. should technically be notAfter 1829 but this causes issue-->earlier than 1829, 
                        since the fair copy of “book third” is the portion positioned following the March 9 group in the MS III, 
                        while “book second” runs continuously to the end of MS III. Even the MS IA ink version of part of “book third,” conceivably, 
                        could significantly predate its March 1829 fair-copying. Moreover, Ruskin’s March 10 letter implies that his father was already familiar with some portion of the project.</p>
                    <p>The MS IA copies, then, do hold open the possibility of a starting date perhaps up to a year prior to the project’s termination in 1829. 
                        Moreover, given Ruskin’s hectic pace of writing and fair-copying for New Year’s 1828 and for his father’s 1829 birthday (see nos. 32-33, 57), 
                        it seems barely credible that even Ruskin could have produced all of his “novel” during the same period. 
                        If these indications are sound, I believe the onset of composition is unlikely to have been much earlier than the middle of 1828, however, 
                        since the handwriting and punctuation in the first two books is reminiscent of “Eudosia” (no. 27).</p>
                    <p>Earlier editors’ assignment of “The Monastery” to 1827 or 1828 seems based on merely impressionistic and circumstantial evidence. 
                        Viljoen viewed the hand in IA as extremely childish, but it in fact resembles other instances of Ruskin’s cursive rough-draft hand in 1829. 
                        No firmer evidence is offered either by Cook and Wedderburn or by Collingwood for their respective dates of 1827 and 1828--the editors 
                        apparently guessing on the basis of remarks in Praeterita, the appearance of the handwriting in the manuscripts, 
                        and connections between the setting of the poem and Ruskin’s travels to Scotland 
                        (see Works, 2:260 n. 1, and PJR, 263, 273; see also, however, part 1, MS IA, “Content,” a, 
                        for the caveat that the early editors may have had access to manuscript of the poem that is now lost).</p>
                    <p>Since the extant manuscript evidence places books 3-4 of the poem (or, at least, their fair-copying) squarely in 1829, 
                        while only permitting an earlier date for books 1-2, the case for assigning an earlier date to some portion of the poem must depend on internal evidence--the events 
                        captured from Scott’s novel, and the order in which Ruskin set them to verse. See Discussion: since book 1 lifts events out of their order in Scott, 
                        the poem could represent an earlier, isolated versification, which Ruskin only later in 1829 decided to develop--“commenc[ing] writing a novel,” as his mother said.</p></div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>The versified selections are as follows: Ruskin’s book 1 begins with the latter half of Scott’s chap. 5, 
                        the Sacristan’s failure to gain passage over the drawbridge and, in fording the Tweed on horseback, his encounter with the White Lady; 
                        and book 1 ends by briefly summarizing portions of Scott’s chap. 7, the Abbot and Father Eustace’s resolve on hearing the Sacristan’s adventure.</p>
                    <p>Ruskin’s book 2 begins with the opening of Scott’s chap. 3, the widowing of the Lady of Avenel and her removal with her daughter 
                        to the shepherd’s cottage of Martin and Tibb Tacket; and book 2 then moves to Scott’s chap. 2, 
                        the confrontation between Captain Stawarth Bolton and Dame Glendinning and her two sons of Glendearg.</p>
                    <p>Ruskin’s book 3 versifies the remainder of Scott’s chap. 3--Martin, Tibb, Mary, and the Lady of Avenel’s journey 
                        to Dame Glendinning’s residence in Glendearg (which Ruskin calls “Glenfarg” and “Glendarg” [see Works, 35:16]), 
                        and their attempted passage across a bog, when Mary and the pony Shagram see the White Lady signaling them to safety.</p>
                    <p>Ruskin’s book 4 is from Scott’s chap. 4, the apparition of her dead father to Mary Avenel on Halloween night.</p>
                    <p>That Ruskin's book 1 lifts events out of their sequential narrative order in Scott--therefore, possibly representing 
                        an earlier, isolated versification of Scott's chapter 5, which Ruskin decided only later in 1829 to develop--points to 
                        a fascinations with Scott’s fifth chapter that was deeply entrenched in Ruskin’s childhood. 
                        Bridges had interested him since 1823, when his aunt presented him with the cherished model of Waterloo Bridge (RFL, 127). 
                        The White Lady may have been associated in Ruskin’s mind with Byron’s “witch of the waters at the Alps” in no. 3 (1826-27), 
                        who occurs to Harry when he “observed a rainbow and a rising mist under it which his fancy soon transformed into a female form” 
                        (in book 3 of “The Monastery,” the White Lady is a “form appearing like a fog”). Of course, these associations 
                        could just as likely have traveled the other way, with witches and bridges leading to his later fascination 
                        with the perils of the White Lady in “The Monastery.”</p>
                    <p>If book 1 probes images that were profoundly arresting for Ruskin throughout his earlier years, 
                        books 2-4 are enriched by a possible connection with the death of Ruskin’s Aunt Jessie of Perth 
                        and the Ruskins’ subsequent adoption of her daughter Mary (see nos. 25-26). 
                        Cousin Mary came to Herne Hill in July 1828 (TLC 7), an event that might well have put Ruskin in mind of the two families joining 
                        in The Monastery--the widowed Lady Avenel and her daughter Mary with the widowed Dame Glendinning and her two sons. 
                        In this light, the end of Ruskin’s poem is moving, breaking off abruptly with the children’s sighting of the “man in the spence,” 
                        the ghost of Mary’s father, and the youngest boy’s tears--events that Ruskin slightly, and perhaps significantly alters from the novel.</p>
                    <p>One other association may be noted, which returns the dating to early 1829, when Ruskin certainly fair-copied books 3-4, 
                        and probably composed at least some portion of them. It is striking that Margaret expressed admiration of her son equally for writing a “novel” 
                        and for making sermon notes (RFL 185). Margaret did not necessarily consider these incompatible pursuits, as did some evangelicals, 
                        but she might have encouraged Ruskin’s reading of The Monastery, owing to her opposition to Cathotic Emancipation, 
                        being debated at the time (see RFL, 177). Scott’s novel makes heroes of the Reformers and satirizes monastic failings, 
                        although Ruskin’s poem largely neglects these themes.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TEXTUALNOTE">
                    <head type="section">Textual Note</head>
                    <p>The copytext is taken from MS III. One peculiarity of punctuation, especially in the first two books, 
                        is the frequent use of a colon, which seems to indicate a pause, as does the two-point ellipsis in “Eudosia” (no. 27). 
                        (In fact, that strange mark in “Eudosia” may be a colon turned on its side.) Perpetually inventive, in “The Monastery,” 
                        Ruskin has come up with yet another mark of his own, the upside-down semicolon, or comma above a period. 
                        I cannot distinguish a consistent function for this mark much different from that of Ruskin’s colon, so, where it appears, 
                        I have put a colon in square brackets.</p>
                    <p>With book 3, the punctuation becomes less idiosyncratic. The MS IA draft is entirely unpunctuated.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>