<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <fileDesc xml:id="msix_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">MS IX</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#AEH">Aimee E. Harris</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2017-09-18">September 18, 2017</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>            
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus" subtype="manuscript">
                <head type="title">MS IX</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="FACSIMILE">
                    <head type="section">Facsimile</head>
                    <list>
                        <item>Coming soon.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>MS IX</p>
                    <p><ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="collingwood_w_g_note.php"><persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood</persName></ref> assigned
                        roman numeral IX to this notebook in his <title type="bibliography_text" corresp="#COLLINGWOODPRELIMINARYNOTE">&#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&#x201D;</title>
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, <date when="1891">1891</date>]</ref>,
                        1:265&#x2013;66; <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, <date when="1891">1891</date>]</ref>, 1:266&#x2013;67).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="LOCATION">
                    <head type="section">Location</head>
                    <p><placeName corresp="#BEINECKE">Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</placeName>, <orgName corresp="#YALE">Yale University</orgName>, <placeName corresp="#NEWHAVEN">New Haven</placeName>,
                        <placeName corresp="#CONNECTICUT">Connecticut</placeName>. Catalogued as &#x201C;Poems <date when="1833">1833</date>&#x201D;.</p>
                    <p>Facsimiles by permission of <title type="archive" corresp="#BEINECKERUSKINCOLLECTION">John Ruskin Collection</title>, General Collection, <orgName corresp="#BEINECKE">Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</orgName>, <orgName corresp="#YALE">Yale University</orgName>. Transcriptions of texts and commentary &#x00A9; <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="PROVENANCE">
                    <head type="section">Provenance</head>
                    <p>See <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date></ref>. 
                        See also <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_american_research_libraries_note.php">Ruskin Manuscript Collecting by American Research Libraries</ref>.</p>
                    <p>On the first leaf following the front flyleaf, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s cousin, <persName corresp="#JAS">Joan Severn</persName>, 
                        inscribed &#x201C;<persName corresp="#JAS">Joan R. Severn</persName> / from <persName type="pen_name" corresp="#JR">Di Pa</persName>&#x201D;,  
                        this manuscript being one of the those associated with touring that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> set aside for her (see Introduction. 
                        Opposite this inscription, on the verso of the flyleaf, is inscribed in pencil &#x201C;Mr Ruskin&#x201D; possibly in the hand of <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName>, 
                        followed by a second line in the same hand, which is difficult to decipher, but which contains the numeral &#x201C;16&#x201D;.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DESCRIPTION">
                    <head type="section">Description</head>
                    <p>Ruled notebook; brown marbled boards and endpapers, three&#x2010;quarter&#x2010;bound in bluish&#x2010;green leather; 20.5 × 16.5 cm.</p>
                    <p>Someone&#x2014;probably <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName>&#x2014;has numbered leaves on their rectos, starting, oddly, with the second leaf following the two front flyleaves; 
                        i.e., the inside first flyleaf has the inscription by (possibl) <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> mentioned above, the second flyleaf has the inscription by <persName corresp="#JAS">Joan Severn</persName> mentioned above, 
                        and then there is another unnumbered leaf before the numbering begins on the following leaf. Despite this irregularity, I employ this numbering for the  Content  below. 
                        In the front of the notebook, eleven leaves (i.e., the first unnumbered leaf following the inscribed flyleaves, plus numbered leaves 1&#x2013;10) have had their right edges cut away&#x2014;to 
                        about one cm. deep&#x2014;but leaving a small tab on the edge of each leaf. On these marginal tabs, someone has printed an alphabet, prepatory for an alphabetical directory of some kind. 
                        These leaves were never used, however, and it is impossible to say whether the alphabetizing was done by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> or by someone who had prepared the notebook before him. 
                        Possibly, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> meant to provide an alphbetized table of contents at the start of his poem. (He did compile an index at the back of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title>, 
                        although that index was probably for his personal use, since <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> was a rough copy notebook.) As it turned out, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> failed to prepare even a title page for <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title>, 
                        and the illustrated poem and prose sequence is untitled.</p>
                    <p>It is also possible that, since <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s writing is the first to appear in the manuscript ( Content,  d), she made the alphabetical tabs for some use of her own. 
                        The paper is watermarked  HAGAR &#x0026; CO / <date when="1822">1822</date>,  so the notebook might have lain unused in the household for a long time. What seems least likely is that 
                        someone would have subjected the manuscript to this treatment after <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> used the notebook for his poetry&#x2014;or, for <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s part, 
                        that he would have started his project several leaves into the notebook, leaving all those blank leaves to be exploited later.</p>
                    <p>Tipped in at the front, attached to the marbled fly leaf, <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName> added a sheet describing <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title>. Like his sheets tipped into the front of many <title type="manuscript" corresp="#JRREDBOOK">Red Books</title> 
                        and other major manuscripts, he pasted onto it a clipping from PJR describing the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title>, and commented on any additions or rebinding since <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>&#x02BC;s <date when="1891">1891</date> edition. 
                        In this case, where <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> summarized that  pp. 1&#x2013;21 are prepared for alphabetical index,  while  pp. 22&#x2013;23 contain quotations in <persName corresp="#MR">Mrs. J. J. Ruskin</persName>’s handwriting,  
                        and  pp. 25&#x2013;111, about a third of the book, were filled with prose and verse . . . with inserted drawings &#x2014;i.e., the so&#x2010;called <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">Account of a Tour on the Continent</title>&#x2014;<persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName> 
                        added the note,  most of the blank pages have since been removed &#x0026; the book replaced in its old cover.  This ranks among the more damaging decisions about the treatment 
                        of the early manuscripts. With blank leaves removed, we are prevented from seeing clearly where <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> might have left gaps in his fair&#x2010;copying, intending to insert a passage or 
                        a drawing later&#x2014;a practice that remains obvious in the extant arrangement. One wonders, too, whether the leaves were entirely blank; even a roughly penciled notation 
                        might have provided clues about <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s plan.</p>
                    <p>Reconstruction of the original manuscript is rendered uncertain, since one cannot be absolutely certain how many leaves were removed. 
                        <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>’s page counts in PJR accurately describe <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title> in its present condition. This means that <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> skipped over blank leaves when numbering the manuscript&#x2014;a practice 
                        consistent with his treatment of blank leaves in MS IVD&#x2014;and these unnumbered leaves would have been the  pages  removed by <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName>. Stubs do remain visible, 
                        but one cannot be confident that stubs would show for all the removed leaves, especially if the manuscript was removed and then rebound in its cover. 
                        In  Content  below, I have noted where a stub remains visible, which one may interpret as a leaf (i.e., two pages) that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> presumably intended to fill with writing or drawing. 
                        One must bear in mind, however, that not all stubs may be visible. The remaining stubs of the removed leaves should not be confused with stubs of a different paper&#x2014;paper 
                        that is not ruled, as the original paper is, and protruding slightly beyond the original marbled edges. These stubs appear to have been inserted as part of the rebinding process, 
                        to which <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName> alludes in his tipped&#x2010;in sheet. As irrelevant to the notebook <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> used, these rebinding stubs are not listed in  Content  below. 
                        Only the stubs are mentioned of paper that clearly belonged to the original notebook.</p>
                    
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="COLLATION">
                        <head type="subsection">Collation</head>
                        <p>In the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref>, 
                            the editors document that, as the contents of the &#x201C;<title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">Account</title>&#x201D; were collated in their time, a gallery of drawings followed the last page of extant fair&#x2010;copied text. 
                            Hanging a note to that effect at the end of the poem, <title type="poem" corresp="#JRHEIDELBERG">&#x201C;Now from the smiling afternoon&#x201D; [&#x201C;Heidelberg&#x201D;]</title>, 
                            the editors comment: &#x201C;In the MS. fair copy (ix.) two pages and a half are here left blank, and then follow 
                            the first four and a half lines of the prose passage . . . , the rest of which is supplied [by the editors] in the text from the draft in the earlier MS. (viii.).&#x201D; 
                            That is, following the end of the poem on 46v, a leaf 47r&#x2010;v is left blank, with the essay <title type="essay" corresp="#JRHEIDELBERGPROSE">&#x201C;Most beautiful are the paths&#x201D; [&#x201C;Heidelberg&#x201D;]</title> 
                            starting half&#x2010;way down on 48r, but breaking off midway in the first sentence of the essay, 
                            after the word &#x201C;sometimes&#x201D;. Here <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> stopped fair&#x2010;copying the &#x201C;Account&#x201D;, 
                            the editors supplying the remaining text of the work from rough draft in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title> and other sources. 
                            In <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title>, the editors go on, &#x201C;[t]he fair copy ends at this point, so far as writing is concerned, but seven page&#x2010;sketches are inserted: 
                            (1) A mountain gorge; (2) mountain heights, a castle on one; (3) a river between steep banks, snow mountains in the distance; 
                            (4) a mountain scene, ch&#x00E2;let in foreground; (5) <emph>a</emph>, a mountain scene, <emph>b</emph>, a lake with a house on piers islanded on it; 
                            (6) a lake&#x2010;side, with terraced gardens, hills behind; (7) aiguilles. These sketches belong to the later portion of the &#x201C;<title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">Tour</title>&#x201D;, 
                            of which the author did not make a fair copy.&#x201D; As discussed in the apparatus to the &#x201C;Account&#x201D; (<ref type="apparatus" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_apparatus.php#MAJORMS">Manuscripts</ref>), 
                            it is not possible to determine whether <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself assembled this gallery or another person did so when the manuscript was rebound.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="CONTENTS">
                    <head type="section">Contents</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi>
                    </p>
                    
                    <list xml:id="LIST" type="ordered">
                        <item n="a">Inscriptions by <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> and <persName corresp="#JAS">Joan Severn</persName> (2 front flyleaves).</item>
                        <item n="b">Tabbed and alphabetized pages (unnumbered leaf plus folios 1&#x2013;10r)</item>
                        <item n="c">Texts copied in <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s hand</item>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <item n="c.1"><ref type="apparatus" target="mr_advice_apparatus.php">Advice of the Mother of the Chevalier Bayard on His Leaving Home to Commence the Profession of Arms (10&#x2013;11r)</ref></item>
                                <item n="c.2"><ref type="apparatus" target="mr_chronicles_apparatus.php">I Chronicles 28:9 (11r)</ref></item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="d">Blank page (11v), followed by stub for one removed leaf.</item>
                        <item n="e"><ref type="apparatus" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_apparatus.php">Account of a Tour on the Continent</ref>, incomplete fair copy in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s copperplate hand with accompanying illustrations in imitation of engravings and lithographs.</item>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <item n="e.1"><ref type="figure" target="calais_fishermen_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCALAISFISHERMENMSIX">Calais Fishermen</title> [drawing] (13r)</ref></item>
                    
                    
                    
                    
                                <item n="e.2"><ref type="witness" target="calais_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRCALAIS">&#x201C;The sands are in the sunlight sleeping&#x201D; [&#x201C;Calais&#x201D;]</title> [poem] (13r&#x2013;13v)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.3"><ref type="figure" target="calais_fishermen_with_telescope_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCALAISFISHERMENWITHTELESCOPEMSIX">Calais Fishermen with Telescope</title> [drawing] (13v)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.4"><ref type="figure" target="calais_pier_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCALAISPIERMSIX">Calais Pier</title> [drawing] (14r)</ref></item> 
                                <item n="e.5"><ref type="witness" target="calais_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRCALAISPROSE">&#x201C;How much has been said of Calais&#x201D; [&#x201C;Calais&#x201D;]</title> [essay] (14r&#x2013;15r)</ref></item> 
                                <item n="e.6"><ref type="figure" target="calais_square_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCALAISQUAREMSIX">Calais Square</title> [drawing] (15r).</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.7"><ref type="figure" target="cassel_hill_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCASSELHILLMSIX">Cassel Hill</title> [drawing] (15v)</ref></item>  
                                <item n="e.8"><ref type="witness" target="cassel_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRCASSEL">&#x201C;The way was long and yet twas sweet&#x201D; [&#x201C;Cassel&#x201D;]</title> [poem] (15v&#x2013;16v)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.9"><ref type="figure" target="cassel_saint_omer_corpus_christi_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCASSELSAINTOMERCORPUSCHRISTIMSIX">Saint Omer Corpus Christi</title> [drawing] (16v).</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.10"><ref type="figure" target="cassel_windmills_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCASSELWINDMILLSMSIX">Cassel Windmills</title> [drawing] (17r)</ref></item> 
                                <item n="e.11"><ref type="witness" target="cassel_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRCASSELPROSE">&#x201C;When shall we get up this hill, this interminable hill&#x201D; [&#x201C;Cassel&#x201D;]</title> [essay] (17r&#x2013;18r)</ref></item> 
                                <item n="e.12"><ref type="figure" target="cassel_market_square_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCASSELMARKETSQUAREMSIX">Cassel Market Square</title> [drawing] (18r)</ref>.</item>
                                <item n="e.13"><ref type="figure" target="lille_street_with_wagon_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRLILLESTREETMSIX">Lille Street with Wagon</title> [drawing] (18v)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.14"><ref type="witness" target="lille_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRLILLE">&#x201C;Oh red the blushing east awoke&#x201D; [&#x201C;Lille&#x201D;]</title> [poem] (18v&#x2013;19v)</ref>; no drawing at end of poem, but small space available (19v).</item>
                                <item n="e.15"><ref type="figure" target="lille_battlement_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRLILLEBATTLEMENTMSIX">Lille Battlement</title> [drawing] (Note that the <title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Library Edition</title> gives the impression that this drawing closes the poem, when in fact it heads the prose section) (20r)</ref></item> 
                                <item n="e.16"><ref type="witness" target="lille_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRLILLEPROSE">&#x201C;Passeport, Monsieur, s&#x02BC;il vous plait&#x201D; [&#x201C;Lille&#x201D;]</title> [essay] (19r&#x2013;19v)</ref>; no drawing at end of prose section, but small space available (20v).</item>
                                <item n="e.17">No drawing at head of poem, but space definitely left for that purpose (20r);  <ref type="witness" target="brussels_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRBRUSSELS">&#x0201C;The racking clouds were fleeting fast&#x0201D; [&#x0201C;Brussels&#x0201D;]</title> [poem] (21r&#x2013;22v)</ref></item> 
                                <item n="e.18"><ref type="figure" target="brussels_wayside_shrine_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRBRUSSELSWAYSIDEMSIX">Brussels Wayside Shrine</title> [drawing] (22v)</ref>.</item>
                                <item n="e.19">Stub (between 22v and 23r).</item>
                                <item n="e.20"><ref type="figure" target="brussels_waterloo_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRBRUSSELSWATERLOOMSIX">Brussels Waterloo</title> [drawing] (23r)</ref></item> 
                                <item n="e.21"><ref type="witness" target="brussels_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRBRUSSELSPROSE">&#x0201C;Brussels is a lovely, a queenlike city&#x0201D; [&#x0201C;Brussels&#x0201D;]</title> [essay] (24r&#x2013;25r)</ref>, no drawing at end of prose section, but ample space available (25r).</item>
                                <item n="e.22">No drawing at head of poem, but space definitely left for that purpose (24v);  <ref type="witness" target="the_meuse_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMEUSE">&#x0201C;The sky was clear, the morn way gay&#x0201D; [&#x0201C;The Meuse&#x0201D;]</title> [poem] (25v&#x2013;26v)</ref></item> 
                                <item n="e.23"><ref type="figure" target="the_meuse_river_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRTHEMEUSERIVERMSIX">The Meuse River</title> [drawing], positioned between last two lines of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMEUSE">The Meuse</title> (poem) and beginning of prose section (26v)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.24"><ref type="witness" target="the_meuse_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRTHEMEUSEPROSE">&#x0201C;How lightly the waves of the broad Meuse crisped&#x0201D; [&#x0201C;The Meuse&#x0201D;]</title> [essay] (26v&#x2013;27r)</ref>; drawing, not at end of prose passage on 26v, where a small space is available, but pasted broadside and taking up whole of 27r (<title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Works</title>, 2:350 n. 2, first drawing listed).</item>
                                <item n="e.25">Blank page (27v);</item>
                                <item n="e.26"><ref type="figure" target="aix_la_chapelle_cathedral_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRAIXLACHAPELLECATHEDRALMSIX">Aix La Chapelle Cathedral</title> [drawing] (29r)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.27"><ref type="witness" target="aix_la_chapelle_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRAIXLACHAPELLE">&#x0201C;Hast ever heard of the peace of Aix La Chapelle&#x0201D; [&#x0201C;Aix La Chapelle&#x0201D;]</title> [essay] (29v&#x2013;31r)</ref>.</item>
                                <item n="e.28">Nearly full&#x2010;page blank space definitely left for drawing, following last few words of  <title type="essay" corresp="#JRAIXLACHAPELLE">Aix la Chapelle</title>  (prose) and preceding the two opening lines of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCOLOGNE">Cologne</title>  (31r)</item>  
                                <item n="e.29"><ref type="witness" target="cologne_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRCOLOGNE">&#x0201C;The noon was past, the sun was low&#x0201D; [&#x0201C;Cologne&#x0201D;]</title> [poem]</ref> (31r&#x2013;32r, with the deliberately erased gap described in <title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Works</title>, 2:351 n. 2).</item>
                                <item n="e.30"><ref type="figure" target="cologne_bayenturm_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRCOLOGNEBAYENTURMMSIX">Cologne Bayenturm</title> [drawing]</ref>, between last line only of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCOLOGNE">Cologne</title>  (poem) and beginning of prose section (<title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Works</title>, 2:351 n. 3) (32r)</item>
                                <item n="e.31"><ref type="witness" target="cologne_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRCOLOGNEPROSE">&#x0201C;And this is the birthplace of Rubens&#x0201D; [&#x0201C;Cologne&#x0201D;]</title> [essay]</ref> (31r&#x2013;34v); no drawing following prose section, but a small space available (33v). One of these leaves (31r) has at some point been cut away from its stub; then, the loose leaf cut horizontally between the drawing and the prose at the bottom; and, finally, the two pieces have been taped back into place again, reattached to the stub. The piece with the drawing has  &#x0201C;B&#x0201D;  written at the side. See 38r&#x2010;v, below.</item>
                                <item n="e.32">Stub (between 34r and 34v).</item>
                                <item n="e.33">No drawing, although large space definitely allowed (34v);  <ref type="witness" target="andernacht_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRANDERNACHT">&#x201C;We have wound a weary way&#x201D; [&#x201C;Andernacht&#x201D;]</title> (35r&#x2013;35v)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.34"><ref type="figure" target="andernacht_tower_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRANDERNACHTTOWERMSIX">Andernacht Tower</title> [drawing] </ref>, at top of page following poem and preceding prose, which is described in <title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Works</title> as somewhat detached from the poem, but which certainly depicts <name type="building" corresp="#ANDERNACHROUNDTOWER">Andernach tower</name> (<title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Works</title>, 2:354 n. 2) (36r)</item>
                                <item n="e.35"><ref type="witness" target="andernacht_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRANDERNACHTPROSE">&#x201C;What is it that makes the very heart leap within you&#x201D; [&#x201C;Andernacht&#x201D;]</title> [essay] (36r&#x2013;37v)</ref>; no drawing at end of prose section, but ample space available (37v).</item>
                                <item n="e.36"><ref type="figure" target="ehrenbreitstein_fortress_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JREHRENBREITSTEINFORTRESSMSIX">Ehrenbreitstein Fortress</title> [drawing] (38r)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.37"><ref type="witness" target="ehrenbreitstein_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JREHRENBREITSTEIN">&#x201C;Oh warmly down the sunbeams fell&#x201D; [&#x201C;Ehrenbreitstein&#x201D;]</title> [poem] (38r&#x2013;40v)</ref></item>
                                <item n="e.38"><ref type="figure" target="ehrenbreitstein_river_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JREHRENBREITSTEINRIVERMSIX">Ehrenbreitstein River Scene</title></ref> (40v). One leaf (38r&#x2010;v) has been removed from its stub and then reattached with tape. Since the tape is the same as that used to reattach 32r&#x2010;v, and since this entire leaf is reproduced in <title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Works</title>, one suspects that the leaf was detached so it could be photographed for the <title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Library Edition</title>. It is equally possible, however, that the editors took advantage of an existing separation.</item>
                                <item n="e.39">No drawing, although nearly full&#x2010;page space definitely allowed (41r); <ref type="witness" target="ehrenbreitstein_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JREHRENBREITSTEINPROSE">&#x201C;It is said that French will carry you over all Europe&#x201D; [&#x201C;Ehrenbreitstein&#x201D;]</title> [essay] (41r&#x2013;42r)</ref>; no drawing at end of prose passage, and insufficient space available for one (41r).</item>
                                <item n="e.40">No drawing, although space definitely allowed (42v); <ref type="witness" target="st_goar_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRSTGOAR">&#x201C;We past a rock, whose bare front ever&#x201D; [&#x201C;St. Goar&#x201D;]</title> [poem] (42v&#x2013;43r)</ref>; no drawing at end of poem, but small space available (43r).</item>
                                <item n="e.41">No drawing, although space definitely allowed (43r); <ref type="witness" target="st_goar_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRSTGOARPROSE">&#x201C;St Goar is the least and sweetest place on all the Rhine&#x201D; [&#x201C;St. Goar&#x201D;]</title> [essay] (43v&#x2013;44r)</ref>; no drawing at end of prose passage, and only a very small space available (44r).</item>
                                <item n="e.42"><ref type="figure" corresp="heidelberg_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRHEIDELBERGDRAWINGMSIX">Heidelberg Drawing</title> [drawing]</ref> (<title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Works</title>, 2:360 n. 1, cited erroneously as following poem on <title type="poem" corresp="#JRSTGOAR">St. Goar</title>) (44v)</item>
                                <item n="e.43"><ref type="witness" target="heidelberg_poem_msix.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRHEIDELBERG">&#x201C;Now from the smiling afternoon&#x201D; [&#x201C;Heidelberg&#x201D;]</title> [poem] (44v&#x2013;47v)</ref>; no drawing, but space allowed on two&#x2010;page spread (46v&#x2013;47r, on each page of which the poetry extends only halfway down, lines 65&#x2013;76 on 46v, and lines 77&#x2013;86 on 47r); no drawing, and no space available, at end of poem (46v).</item>
                                <item n="e.44">Blank leaf (48r&#x2013;48v); no drawing, although space definitely allowed (49r)</item>
                                <item n="e.45"><ref type="witness" target="heidelberg_prose_msix.php"><title type="essay" corresp="#JRHEIDELBERGPROSE">&#x201C;Most beautiful are the paths&#x201D; [&#x201C;Heidelberg&#x201D;]</title> [essay]</ref> (49r).</item>
                                <item n="e.46">Blank page (49v).</item>
                                <item n="e.47">Stub (between 49v and 50r).</item>
                                <item n="e.48"><ref type="figure" corresp="mountain_gorge_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRMOUNTAINGORGEMSIX">Mountain Gorge Drawing</title>, pasted in the middle of the page (50r)</ref>.</item>
                                <item n="e.49">Blank page (50v).</item>
                                <item n="e.50"><ref type="figure" corresp="balstall_drawing_msix.php"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRBALSTALLMSIX">Balstall Drawing</title></ref>, pasted in middle of page  (50r).</item>
                                <item n="e.51">Blank page (51v).</item>
                                <item n="e.52"><ref type="figure" corresp="river_drawing_msix"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRRIVERMSIX">River Drawing</title></ref>, pasted broadside in middle of page (51r).</item>
                                <item n="e.53">Blank page (52v).</item>
                                <item n="e.54"><ref type="figure" corresp="mountain_chalet_drawing_msix"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRMOUNTAINCHALETMSIX">Mountain Scene with Chalet Drawing</title> (52r)</ref>.</item>
                                <item n="e.55">Blank page (53v).</item>
                                <item n="e.56"><ref type="figure" corresp="mountain_boulder_drawing_msix"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRMOUNTAINBOULDERMSIX">Mountain Scene with Boulder Drawing</title></ref><ref type="figure" corresp="lake_building_on_piers_drawing_msix"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRLAKEWITHBUILDINGONPIERSMSIX">Lake Scene with Building on Piers Drawing</title></ref> (54r), no space available for text.</item>
                                <item n="e.57">Blank page (54v).</item>
                                <item n="e.58">Stub (between 54v and 55r).</item>
                                <item n="e.59"><ref type="figure" corresp="lakeside_with_terraced_villa_drawing_msix"><title type="artwork" corresp="#JRLAKESIDEWITHTERRACEDVILLAMSIX">Lakeside with Terraced Villa</title></ref>, pasted in middle of page (Works, 2:364 n. 1 [no. 6]) (55r).</item>
                                <item n="e.60">Blank page (55v).</item>
                                <item n="e.61">Drawing, pasted in middle of page (Works, 2:364 n. 1 [no. 7]) (56r).</item>
                                <item n="e.62">Blank pages (56v&#x2013;75r).</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>Date of manuscript’s composition <date notBefore="1833" notAfter="1834">1833&#x2013;34</date>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <!--The Discussion section may contain all or only some of the following subsections.-->
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Hand</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Composition &#x0026; Sources</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Domestic Scene</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>