<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject MANUSCRIPT followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "msi_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "msi_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_manuscript_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Manuscript</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="MJF">Madeline J Felps</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>            
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">Title of Manuscript</head>
                <!--A manuscript apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>MS VI</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="LOCATION">
                    <head type="section">Location</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>Princeton (cataloged as  Ruskin MS.--Poems ).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="PROVENANCE">
                    <head type="section">Provenance</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>Sotheby’s 1931.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DESCRIPTION">
                    <head type="section">Description</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.
                        In the time since <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> described the manuscript, its  reddish marbled paper covers  have disappeared, replaced by a dark red leather 
                        or roan binding, 32.5 × 11.5 cm, with  Ruskin MS.--Poems  impressed in gilt on the spine and cover. Arrangements for this binding would have 
                        been made by <persName corresp="#AW">Alexander Wedderburn</persName>, since the  limp roan  described in <title type="catalog_auction" corresp="#SOTHEBYCAT1930">Sotheby Cat.</title> <date when="1931">1931</date>
                        and the  red leather  mentioned in <title type="catalog_auction" corresp="#GOODSPEEDCATALOGUE">Goodspeed, Cat.</title>, must refer to the same binding.
                        The original notebook was purchased, not handmade, with marbled edges and pre-ruled paper, watermarked  J Wh[at(?)]man 1829.
                    </p>
                    <!--The subsection that follows, Collation, is common to all manuscript apparatuses and was, accordingly, assigned an xml:id by
                        the Ruskin Project Team during work on the "First Twenty."-->
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="COLLATION">
                        <head type="subsection">Collation</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="CONTENTS">
                    <head type="section">Contents</head>
                    <!--Typically, this section will begin:-->
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <!--and continue with a list, which may group items according to type (e.g. prose, poetry) or other similiarity. Note: drawings
                        may be included as items in this list.-->
                    <list xml:id="LIST" type="ordered">
                        <item n="a">Item belonging to Group A.</item>
                        <item n="b.1">First item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.2">Second item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.3">Third item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="c">Item belonging to Group C.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Body paragraph.
                        Collation
                        Because <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> is a rough-draft notebook, the sequence of its contents reveals their rough order of composition. 
                        This evidence is obscured in places by 
                        folios having been torn out, destroying many drafts both of poems known from copies elsewhere and of pieces that apparently existed only here. Fortunately, 
                        there remains in the back of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> own index, giving us the sequence 
                        and at least the titles of the lost entries. The mutilation had already occurred 
                        when <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> first described the manuscript for <!--Find out who PJR is-->PJR, and evidence suggests that <persName corresp="JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                        himself tore out the pages--or at least that the destruction, if not
                        by him, occurred during the notebook’s use. Interpretation of the index involves some speculation, since <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> renumbered some
                        pages after some folios were torn 
                        out, and, later, someone else also took a hand to numbering pages; however, the use of the notebook can be broadly reconstructed as follows. The first 57 pages 
                        are missing (as <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> also remarks, although he errs in listing only one other  page  as missing elsewhere in the book: 
                        there are, in fact, three other missing
                        folios, as discussed below). The next pages 58-85 were accurately numbered by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>, though with even numbers unconventionally
                        assigned to rectos. The versos were
                        likely odd-numbered from the beginning, since page 57 is the last missing--i.e., the folio, pp. 56-57. Following p. 85 (a verso), two folios (pp. 86-87 and 88-89) 
                        were completely torn out, leaving stubs to attest to their former existence. With their removal, two works were irrevocably lost--according to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> index,  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRRUSTICINLONDON">Rustic in London</title>
                        [p.] 87  (no. 120), and  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRHEAT">Heat</title> [p.] 88  (no. 121). Possibly the draft of some portion of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> [p.] 88  was lost, as well (see below). Clearly, these two 
                        folios were removed during the notebook’s use, since the index lists the extant poem  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>  (no. 129) on page 91 (a verso), a number at which one can arrive only 
                        by counting the two missing folios that fell just before the folio with  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>. The index entry for  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>  reads in full as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title> 91 86,  with  86  lined 
                        up with a column consistent with other entries. This mystery may be solved two ways: As one possibility,  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>  or a related poem may originally have been drafted
                        on the first of the two missing folios (the former pp. 86-87), and that earlier draft or related poem has simply been lost. This possibility is supported by the extant
                        poem opening with  "The second day past oer and gloomy night,"  as if an earlier poem had described
                        the first day. As a second possibility, both of the index numbers 
                        referred to the same poem, but <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> corrected  91  to  86  after tearing out the two folios. Two problems arise from this explanation.
                        First, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> had to err, since
                        the poem occurs, according to revised numbering, on the verso, page 87, not on the recto, page 86. Second,  86  appears to be the earlier index entry, not one added as
                        a correction. Thus, the former possibility is easier to accept, but <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> has befuddled explanation by tearing away approximately a 
                        quarter-page from the top of the 
                        folio with the extant  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>,  thus losing any page numbers he might have written. What is certain is that, prior to the notebook’s mutilation, the extant poem  
                        <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>  had been indexed for p. 91; and, following the notebook’s mutilation, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> new (visible) numbering starts on the page after 
                        <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title> --i.e., the new page 88,
                        formerly (presumably) page 92. By tearing away the top of the folio holding the extant  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>,  <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>
                        also destroyed most of the first stanza of the intriguing no. 122 
                        from its recto and, from its verso, something that preceded the fragment no. 128 ( tis not the proper measure ). On the next recto following this mutilated folio, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName>
                        revised page numbering is visible, pp. 88-89. The index gives as its last two page numbers for  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  (though more was to be written, if not indexed, in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title>)  88  and 
                        92.  These entries present a puzzle similar to that for  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>.  The newly numbered pp. 88 and 92 do hold  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> --the former even entitled  <title type="book" corresp="#JRITERIAD_BK$">Iteriad Book 4th</title>  and 
                        starting with line 27. That p. 88, however, according to the old numbering, would have been p. 92, and the old p. 88, now removed, might well have contained  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERAID">Iteriad</title>  
                        draft--in fact, there are very good reasons to believe it did (see note, no. 91).Thus, while definite conclusions cannot be drawn, probabilities suggest that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> stopped
                        his indexing not long after he mutilated the notebook, and that all his index numbers refer, therefore, to his earlier numbering. That is, an earlier version of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title> 
                        (probably describing the  first day ) once existed on the missing p. 86; some  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  draft was lost with the removed p. 88; not long before removing pp. 86-89, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> had
                        indexed his latest  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  draft as  92  and, after the removal of 86-89, he renumbered that same p. 92 on the
                        page itself as p. 88. The extant folio, pp. 88-89 (new numbering),
                        following the torn folio holding  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>,  would formerly have been p. 92; but it is numbered  88  with no sign
                        of a prior erasure. It appears, then, that when <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> reached 
                        about this point--the composition of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>,  4:27-68--he for some reason tore out the two missing folios, started
                        his new page numbering, and halted his indexing for  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>.
                        (Alternatively, the mutilation and renumbering could conceivably have occurred somewhat later, when <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> reached about three hundred 
                        lines into book 4. This possibility will be 
                        discussed below.) This means that poems indexed as falling on pages after this watershed had already been drafted; otherwise, their index entries would refer to the new page
                        numbering, and this theory seems borne out by the disposition of the remaining pages. Following the newly numbered pp. 88-89, yet another folio has been removed, what would have 
                        been pp. 90-91, according to the new numbering. A remaining stub attests to the folio’s existence and shows that it once held  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  draft on the recto--at least, line 95 of book 4,
                        a line continuous with 4:69-94 at the bottom of p. 89. The next existing folio was numbered 90-91. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> index mentions  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRDEARTEPOETICA">De arte poetica</title> [p.] 94  (no. 130), a title that is nowhere 
                        extant in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title>. If one counts pages, including all three missing folios, prior to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> renumbering (i.e., when the second-day  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title>  poem was correctly indexed as p. 91), one 
                        will arrive at pp. 94-95 for the third missing folio. Thus,  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRDEARTEPOETICA">De arte poetica</title>  was lost with this folio, and it likely existed prior to the new page numbering--i.e., prior to the 
                        composition of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  4:27ff., which <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> reached about <date notBefore="1831-06-21" notAfter="1831-09-22">summer 1831</date>  (see note to no. 91), or perhaps somewhat later when he had reached 300 lines into book 4 (see below). A 
                        fragment of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRDEARTEPOETICA">De arte poetica</title>  may, nonetheless, have been retained. At the top of the recto following the third missing folio--i.e., on what would formerly have been p. 95, now numbered
                        p. 90--a fragment appears to have been carried over from the previous page (two stanzas extant, the first of which is incomplete). The subject of this fragment, no. 131, is consistent 
                        with  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRDEARTEPOETICA">De arte poetica</title>,  no. 130, and the two may be the same poem. A few other index entries point to the old numbering, <date notAfter="1831-07-22">before midsummer</date>:  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRBED">Bed</title> [p.] 102,   <title type="poem" corresp="#JRETERNALHILLS">Eternal hills</title> [p.] 103,
                        and  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRFUN">Fun</title> [p.] 103.  These poems--the former two untitled in draft (nos. 133-34), and the latter entitled  different style  in draft but with a refrain  
                        Fun fun &#x0026;c  (no. 136)--now fall on pp. 96-97, a folio that would have been numbered pp. 102-3 prior to removal of all three missing folios. Thus, these three poems, too, 
                        likely preexisted the composition of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  4:27ff. or 4:300ff., when the missing folios were removed. This means that these poems should not regarded as composed sequentially 
                        with the draft of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  presently surrounding them but that they were composed earlier and the  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  draft wrapped around them. This arrangement may be confirmed by the appearance
                        of the manuscript: on p. 96 (i.e., formerly, p. 102)  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  4:247-61 extends from the top of the page down to the beginning of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRBED">Bed</title>,  which runs to the bottom of the page. At the top 
                        of p. 97 (i.e., formerly, p. 103), <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> squeezed in just one line of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>,  4:262, before  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRETERNALHILLS">Eternal Hills</title>  and  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRFUN">Fun</title>  take up the remainder of the page; then  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  recommences 
                        with 4:263ff. on the next page. Another index entry,  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRWHEREISJOY">Joy, where is</title> [p.] 97  (no. 132), can be made to correspond with the poem itself only by counting all three missing folios. 
                        It presently falls on p. 91; thus, it probably predates the  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  draft surrounding it--4:101ff. that follows it, and  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCOMINGDOWNUPONAMBLESIDE">Coming down upon Ambleside</title>  (4:383-402) that precedes it (see below).
                        The passage  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCOMINGDOWNUPONAMBLESIDE">Coming down upon Ambleside</title>  is responsible for the suggestion, already mentioned, that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> mutilation and renumbering of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> may have occurred somewhat later than the 
                        composition of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  4:27-68. The  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCOMINGDOWNUPONAMBLESIDE">Ambleside</title>  passage, which is placed (and perhaps written) out of sequence in the notebook, is cross-referenced by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> own note later on,  
                        FROM LINE 375 TO LINE 401 AT PAGE NINETY SIX ; since  page ninety six  refers to the old numbering, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> may not have yet removed the missing folios before composing book 4 into the 300s.
                        Unfortunately, the pages holding these shorter poems composed earlier than their surrounding  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  draft do not show erasure of a former page numbering. The page with  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRWHEREISJOY">Where Is Joy</title>  (no. 132)
                        is unnumbered; only the recto of that folio is numbered (the new p. 90). The same is true of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRETERNALHILLS">Eternal Hills</title>  and  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRFUN">Fun</title>,  whose page (a verso) is unnumbered, with its recto numbered (the new p. 96).
                        The latter page is the location of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRBED">Bed</title>,  but there is no sign of an erasure of the former p. 102 (as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRBED">Bed</title>  is indexed) beneath the new p. 96. One can only assume that, with the earlier 
                        numbering system, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> either indexed these poems by counting his pages, without marking the pages themselves, or wrote the numbers on the pages themselves in erasable pencil.
                        The composition of book 4 of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  (new p. 88 and following) is complex; full discussion will be found in the note to no. 91. It may be generally remarked here that this part 
                        of the manuscript is given over to partly drafting, partly schematizing line arrangements of draft from elsewhere. Thus, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> is by now, perhaps, starting to fair-copy  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> 
                        in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVII">MS VII</title>. This task may partly account for the removal of the three missing folios from <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title>. If so, one wonders why <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> did not mutilate <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> after having completely finished 
                        the draft of book 4, rather than toward the onset of its composition.
                        Starting with the first page of his new system (p. 88, holding  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  4:27-67), and not counting removed folios, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> numbered rectos only with even numbers through page 100 
                        (only failing to indicate the new p. 94, which is unnumbered). On the last of these pages,  100  is written over top of an erroneous  99,  and another hand has also numbered this
                        latter page as 100 in pencil. This new hand numbers the next recto in pencil as 101 and continues, 101-35. Since p. 135 falls on an endpaper that does not appear part of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName>
                        original notebook, this hand must be later--probably <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn's</persName>, after the manuscript acquired its present binding.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                    Content	
                    <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> falls into fairly distinct sections. In their sequence of appearance, the contents are as follows:
                    a) The sequence of the titles in the missing part of the manuscript can be reconstructed as nos. 70 (p. 6), 71 (p. 8), 
                    73 (p. 10), 74 (p. 12), 75 (p. 13), 76 (p. 21), 77(?) (p. 25, see no. 77), 
                    92 (p. 28), 93 (p. 29), 94 (p. 30), 95 (p. 31), 91 (p. 32; this is bk. 3, indexed under both  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRSKIDDAW1891">Skiddaw</title>  and  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> ), 
                    96 (p. 37), 77(?) (p. 39, see no. 77), 97 (p. 40), 100 (p. 46), 101 (p. 47), 102 (p. 48), 91 (p. 48, some portion,
                    presumably of book 3 or beginning of book 1), 103 (p. 49), 104 (p. 51), 105 (p. 51), 106 (no p. no., but see no. 106),
                    107 (p. 52), 91 (p. 54, some portion presumably of bk. 1).
                    b) In the extant portion of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title>, from p. 58, the roughly continuous record of poetry composition continues. Extant 
                    are drafts of books 1, 2, and 4 of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>,  no. 91, which are listed as follows, broken down into their parts and 
                    interspersed with shorter poems, to show their sequence: no. 91 (pp. 58-74; bk. 1:176-518, and bk. 2: 1-400; probably 
                    listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> 54  in index), 109 (p. 75, confirmed by index,  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRPOESIE">Poesie</title> 75 ), 
                        110 (pp. 75-76, listed  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRWIND">Wind</title> 76  in index), 91 (p. 76; bk. 2:401-26; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> 76  in index), 111 (pp. 77-78, listed  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRWANTOFSUBJECT">Want of subject</title> 77  in index), 112 (p. 78; 
                        listed  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTODASHHOWLING">To dash howling</title>  without page no. in index, unless the  79  for following entry, no. 114, is incorrectly meant to cover no. 112, as well), 113 (p. 78; through third 
                        stanza, line 5, followed by  Contd on p 81 ; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRFEMININEGENDER">Feminine Gender</title> 78  in index), 114 (p. 79; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRDOCTORS">Doctors</title> 79  in index), 91 (p. 79; bk. 2:659-67; entitled 
                        Conclusion of Book 2 <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  on p. 79; not listed in index), 115 (pp. 79-80; not listed in index, owing either to oversight or to later insertion), 116 (p. 80; partial 
                        draft, i.e., five lines not identical but closely related to later occurence of poem), 91 (p. 80; bk. 2:668-83; not listed in index, almost certainly owing to later 
                        insertion), 113 (p. 81; remaining 4 lines of stanza 3), 116 (p. 81; full draft; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRLIFE">Life</title> 81  in index), 91 (p. 81, beneath rule at bottom of page; bk. 2:684-88; 
                        not listed in index), 91 (p. 82; bk. 2:427-69; listed in index as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> 82 ), 91 (p. 82, beneath rule at bottom of page; bk. 2:689-92; not listed in index), 91 (p. 
                        83; bk. 2:470-513; continuation of index listing  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> 82 ), 91 (p. 83, beneath rule at bottom of page; bk. 2:693-94; not listed in index), 91 (p. 84; bk. 2:514-38;
                        continuation of index listing  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> 82 ), 117 (pp. 84-85; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRDAYOFJOY">Day of joy</title> 84  in index), 119 (p. 85; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRMARINERSSONG">Mariners song</title> 85  in index), [120-21 (indexed 
                        as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRRUSTICINLONDON">Rustic in london</title> 87  and  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRHEAT">Heat</title> 88 ), and a portion of 91 (probably bk. 2:539-658 and bk. 4:1-26, and possibly indexed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> 88 ), now lost with removed folios, 
                        i.e., old pp. 86-89], 122 (unnumbered partially torn folio, i.e., old p. 90; no identifiable listing in index), 123 (unnumbered partially torn folio, i.e., old p. 90; 
                        listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTEMPEST">Tempest</title> 90  in index), 128 (unnumbered partially torn folio, i.e., old p. 91; no identifiable listing in index), 129 (unnumbered partially torn folio--i.e., 
                        old p. 91--and continuing onto following folio, new p. 88; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCREATION">Creation</title> 91 86  in index), 91 (new p. 88; bk. 4:27-67; possibly listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title> 92,  i.e., old 
                        p. 92, in index), 91 (unnumbered verso of new p. 88, i.e., new p. 89; bk. 4:68), 73 (p. 88v, i.e., new p. 89; unfinished revision, indexed only by its earlier version  
                        <title type="poem" corresp="#JRDEATH">Death</title> 10 ), 91 (p. 88v, i.e., new p. 89; bk. 4:69-94; not indexed), [130 (indexed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRDEARTEPOETICA">De arte poetica</title> 94 ), and 91 (4:95, probably 95-100; not indexed), lost with 
                        removed folio, i.e. old pp. 94-95], 131 (new p. 90; possibly a remainder of no. 130; not otherwise indexed), 91 (new p. 90; variant, unpublished conclusion to bk. 4),
                        91 (new pp. 90-91; bk. 4:383-408; entitled here  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCOMINGDOWNUPONAMBLESIDE">Coming down upon Ambleside</title>  and lines unnumbered; not indexed), 132 (new pp. 91-92; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRWHEREISJOY">Joy, where is</title> 97  in 
                        index, i.e., old p. 97), 91 (new pp. 92-96; bk. 4:101-261; not indexed), 133 (new p. 96; listed in index as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRBED">Bed</title> 102,  i.e., old p. 102), 91 (new p. 97; bk. 4:262;
                        not indexed), 134 (new p. 97; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRETERNALHILLS">Eternal hills</title> 103  in index, i.e., old p. 103), 136 (new p. 97; listed as  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRFUN">Fun</title> 103  in index, i.e., old p. 103), 91 (new p. 
                        98; bk. 4:264-326 [these lines numbered differently in the draft--i.e., 248-313--than in their final fair copy, whose numbering is cited here, for the sake of clarity;
                        some of these lines indicated in this draft only by their opening words or by a note referring to where they will be found in some other manuscript]), 91 (new pp. 99-100r,
                        100v, and pp. 101-5 by later hand; 4:327-696 [numbered differently in this draft--i.e., 314-704--than their final numbering in fair copy; at line 382 (i.e., <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> line 
                        376), there is a note to pick up lines 383-408 from earlier in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title>:  from line 375 to line 401 at page ninety six --i.e., old p. 96, now new p. 90 with the section 
                        <title type="poem" corresp="#JRCOMINGDOWNUPONAMBLESIDE">Coming down upon Ambleside</title> ), 91 (pp. 107-8 in new hand;  Notes  to  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>,  book 1, scored through in draft).
                    c) Pp. 130-32: index to <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title>. The index was constructed by listing letters of the alphabet equally spaced down the page; then the titles were entered in the spaces under 
                    the headings. This was done in ink, while in pencil on these pages and the following folio, 133-34, are some multiplication and addition exercises. These exercises accord
                    with the lessons starting in <date when="1831">1831</date> that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> is known to taken from <persName corresp="#JROWBOTHAM">Mr. Rowbotham</persName> ( sums are advancing in very good style,  <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> announced in <date when="1832-01">January 1832</date>,  addition
                    subtraction multiplication and division,  but he thought Rowbotham’s instruction made up of  disagreeable et ceteras  and to be  a dry, and entertainmentless thing  [RFL 
                    258, 268, and see 261 n. 11].) Also on p. 134 is a fragment of verse,  "The [gem(?)] Oh [gemini(?) how monstrous pretty tale / Ah what a deal of trouble authors ye / Ye 
                    ladies Wayward fancie for to hit--." 
                    d) Probably after the index was started on page 130, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> used the preceding p. 129, working upside down and in the opposite direction to the rest of the book, for
                    nos. 87, 88, and 90 (no. 90 dated <date when="1830-09-10">10 September 1830</date>). No. 90 continues from p. 129 backwards to page 126.
                    e) Various items are scattered throughout pages remaining in the space between c-d at the back of the manuscript and a-b coming from the front. Reading from the back,
                    and upside down to text coming from front of book: On p. 124, a four-stanza poem,  <title type="poem" corresp="#ANDREWSELIZABRAVEHUSSAR">The Brave Hussar</title>.  This is copied, not in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> hand, but possibly <persName corresp="#JJR">John James's</persName>; 
                    in any case, the poem is signed by, or attributed to,  <persName corresp="#EAO">Eliza Andrews</persName> --probably the daughter of <persName corresp="#EA">Edward Andrews</persName>, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> tutor, who had a child by this name.
                    On p. 123, a four-line fragment ( "I think that the elements are contramacious / Such a huge disposition they showed for to splash us / For if we did but wish on some 
                    day to go out / That day they were sure to kick up such a rout" ). This is headed   <title type="book" corresp="#JRITERIAD_BK3">3rd book</title>,  no doubt referring to  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>.  The passage is scored through, and apparently 
                    it was not ultimately used.
                        On pp. 110-11, rough pen-and-ink sketches for the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">Account of a Tour of the Continent</title>, <date when="1833">1833</date>, no. 180. The first shows a Swiss cottage and bridge, and the drawing is 
                        captioned  No. 1. Head [i.e., at the head of a poem or prose selection of no. 180, as fair-copied and illustrated in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title>]. The Swiss Cottages.  Alongside this drawing
                        is one of a gothic fountain, captioned  No 2. Tail. Swiss Cottages.  Following these is a rocky, narrow path alongside a cliff, with a horse and rider proceeding toward 
                        a distant town; captioned,  No. 1. Splugen. Head.  Enclosed in rules, between the first two and the third drawings, is a note (but no sketches) for  No 3 head, William 
                        tell from boys own book  and  No 4. tail. Tells tower at Altorf.  On the opposite page (p. 111), <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> drew a precipitous waterfall from high crags, captioned  Perhaps.
                        No. 2. Tail. The descent.  Alongside this, another sketch (including stone arches) is not captioned and too fragmentary for identification.
                        f) Much later in <date when="1838">1838</date>(?), <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> used remaining blank spaces to compose no. 270. This essay begins on p. 112 and goes forward to p. 125 (working around the <persName corresp="#EAO">Eliza Andrews</persName>
                        poem and  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  fragment in e); then, obstructed by no. 90 in d, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> continued the essay on available blank pages 106, 108-9, 111. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> numbered these pages in 
                        sequence, 1-18.</p>
                        
                        
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>
                    Date of composition <date notBefore="1830-01-01" notAfter="1831-09-22">January 1830 through fall 1831</date>; <date notBefore="1833-01-01" notAfter="1834-12-31">1833-34</date>; <date when="1838">1838</date>(?).
                    Contrary to earlier assumptions (see Dearden, ed., Iteriad, 22), this manuscript probably was not used during the <date notBefore="1830-06-21" notAfter="1830-09-22">summer tour of 1830</date>, since poems associated 
                    with that tour (nos. 78-82, 84, and 85[?]) are not listed in <persName corresp="JR">Ruskin's</persName> index to <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> (see  Content,  a, below); however, the manuscript may have accompanied
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> on the <date notBefore="1831-06-21" notAfter="1831-09-22">summer tour of 1831</date> (see no. 91). </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>
                    As <persName corresp="WGC">Collingwood</persName> remarks, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> is a rough-copy book for  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  and for shorter poems, many of them copied into <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>. Unlike <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>, in which poems were fair-copied
                    in an order regardless of their dates of composition, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> reveals a compositional sequence of poems--some lost with the removal of folios. The sequence starts with
                    <title type="poem" corresp="#JRVESUVIUS">Vesuvius</title>,  which is the earliest item listed in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> index. Since  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRVESUVIUS">Vesuvius</title>  can be independently dated as <date notBefore="1830-02-01" notAfter="1830-02-28">February 1830</date>, and some other titles in the index can 
                    also be dated from other sources, conjectural dates can be assigned to pieces based on their relative positions in the manuscript.
                    Dates can be provisionally given even to titles of lost pieces, since their former positions are recorded in the index. Of course, we cannot be certain that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                    drafted the lost poems seriatim in the notebook, any more than we can assume that the extant poems form an undeviating sequence--and, as explained in  Description 
                    above and in no. 91, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> did at times skip backwards and fill unused spaces. In broad outline, however, the titles of lost poems indicate interests that absorbed
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> from <date notBefore="1830-01-01" notAfter="1831-02-28">early 1830 to late February</date> or <date notBefore="1830-01-01" notAfter="1831-03-15">early March 1831</date>, the period covered in the lost portion of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title>.
                    Throughout the notebook, shorter poems were interspersed with draft of  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>,  no. 91. The index tells us that  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  itself started life as a shorter poem,
                    <title type="book" corresp="#JRITERIAD_BK1">The Ascent of Skiddaw</title>,  which would later become book 3 (see no. 91). The index cites p. 32 both for  <title type="book" corresp="#JRITERIAD_BK1">Skiddaw</title>  and for the first of a series of pages for  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>.
                    <title type="book" corresp="#JRITERIAD_BK1">Skiddaw</title>  was drafted, judging by its indexed position, starting in <date notBefore="1830-12-15" notAfter="1830-12-31">late December 1830</date> or <date notBefore="1831-01-01" notAfter="1831-01-15">early January 1831</date>, just following the lost piece  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRREVOLUTION">Revolution</title>.  In <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVII">MS VII</title> 
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> says he started  <title type="poem" corresp="#JRITERIAD">Iteriad</title>  on <date when="1830-11-28">November 28, 1830</date>, either referring to <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> and offsetting these calculations by just a month or referring to draft in another 
                    manuscript, now lost. </p>
                    <!--The Discussion section may contain all or only some of the following subsections.-->
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Hand</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Composition &#x0026; Sources</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Domestic Scene</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>