<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "the_steam_engine_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;Of rocks first and of caverns now I sing&#x201D;</head>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>MS III.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>March 9 (or summer 1830?). Misdated 1828 (and first line misquoted) in Works, 2:536.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>In a letter of March 10, 1829, Ruskin refers to completing a red book, MS III, 
                        by gathering together several poems: “I am putting in the shipwreck altogether 
                        and the adventures of an ant &c” (RFL, 192; see nos. 38 and 49, and see note to no. 46). 
                        In MS III, several poems, including these lines, are dated 9 March 1829, the day before Ruskin’s promise to John James. 
                        The poems, in the sequential order they appear in MS III (not necessarily reflecting order of composition), are nos. 47, 28, 48-51, 38, 52-55, 39. 
                        Throughout the group, Ruskin distributed “March 9th 1829,” “March 1829,” or just “9th 1829.”
                        This flurry of fair-copying must have been instigated by Margaret’s complaint to John James on March 4: 
                        “If you think of writing John would you impress on him the propriety of not beginning too eagerly and becoming careless towards the end of his works as he calls them  I think in a letter from you it would have great weight.” On March 10, John James complied with the remark to John, “You have been at your Works with great Spirit & they commence so well that the end rather disappoints that is if they get to an end” (RFL, 187, 192). Ruskin appears to have outmaneuvered his mother and forestalled criticism, however, by already completing MS III on March 9; or, at least, he created the fiction of having done so, by gathering together poems written at widely different times, composing some new ones, and peppering the little anthology with the March 9 date. He then tried to turn the issue into a joke in a letter of March 10: “I believe my discourse has a conclusion, and a beginning too,” though his manner may not be analyzable in “the learned terms of Rhetoric” (RFL, 193).
                        The copying date of March 9 is to some extent a fiction designed to forestall, on paper if not in actuality, his father’s censure of March 10. The later poems in this group, at least, could have been composed and copied no earlier than March 13 (see no. 53). Still, Ruskin was able to compose and copy very rapidly. As he remarks in his father’s 1829 birthday letter, “the last year of my life was the happiest . . . because I have had more to do than I could do without all possible cramming and ramming and wishing days were longer and sheets of paper broader” (RFL, 200). Archly, he rounded out the section with a series of “fragments,” nos. 51-55, some new and some abstracted from older poems. When the March 9 group of smaller poems were entered, Ruskin followed with the resumption of “The Monastery” (see no. 46).
                        For some of these poems, earlier composition dates can be established. The remainder are arranged here, under 9 March 1829, for want of a better evidence. No. 47, the first in the group, presents a special problem. Its subject is “Matlock’s rocks . . . white as snow,” but Ruskin’s opportunity to explore the mines and caverns around Matlock appears not to have come until summer 1830 (TLC, 32-33, 51-56). If he did visit Derbyshire before the 1830 tour, this poem is the sole manuscript evidence. In Praeterita, Ruskin associates Matlock with 1829; but the autobiography’s dates are not reliable (see TLC, 67 n. 33), and Ruskin might well have derived that date from no. 47.
                        More likely, no. 47 reflects Ruskin’s preparation for his 1830 geological pursuits with research in some guidebook, illustration, or description. As Michael Brooks mentions, although not in connection with no. 47, Maria Edgeworth’s Harry and Lucy pay a geological visit to Matlock, which might have absorbed Ruskin (“Love and Possession in a Victorian Household: The Example of the Ruskins,” in The Victorian Family: Structure and Stress, ed. Anthony S. Wohl [New York: St. Martin’s, 1978], pp. 91-92). Likewise, in no. 56 Ruskin drew on a literary source for geology, and possibly at about the same time he composed no. 47 (no. 56 unfortunately presents dating enigmas of its own).
                        The alternative is to date no. 47 as summer 1830 or after, when Ruskin is known to have visited Matlock. Physical evidence shows this to be possible, since the lines are positioned at the beginning of the 9 March 1829 group, following a blank page, and therefore could have been inserted later. (The lines also wrap around a drawing of a mountain landscape and castle, but that only tells us that the drawing probably predates the poem.) Still, the notation “9th 1829” is clearly applied to no. 47, and by 1830 Ruskin would no longer have any reason to falsify the date his little anthology.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                            <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                            <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TEXTUALNOTE">
                    <head type="section">Textual Note</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>