<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <fileDesc xml:id="saltzburg_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;Saltzburg&#x201d;</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus" subtype="work">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="WITNESSES">
          			<head type="section">Witnesses</head>
          			<list>
          			    <item><ref type="apparatus" subtype="manuscript" target="msviii_apparatus.php"><hi rend="bold"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS VIII</title></hi></ref>
          			        <list>
                        <item><ref type="witness" target="saltzburg_msviii.php">&#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;</ref></item>
          			        </list>
          			    </item>
          			    <item><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold"><title type="annual" corresp="#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</title></hi></hi></ref>
          			            <list>
                        <item><ref type="witness" target="saltzburg_fo.php">&#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;</ref></item>
          			            </list>
                </item>
                </list>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Untitled in draft. When a revised version was published in the literary annual, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="friendships_offering_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref> 
                        (see <ref type="internal" target="COMPPUB">Composition and Publication</ref>), 
                        the poem first exhibited its title, &#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;; however, this title must have been determined by that of the steel engraving, 
                        which the poem was commissioned to accompany.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Ekphrastic and topographical poem.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>Draft contained in <ref type="apparatus" subtype="manuscript" target="msviii_apparatus.php">MS VIII</ref> 
                        (see <ref type="apparatus" subtype="manuscript" target="msviii_apparatus#LISTB2.php">Contents, list <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.2</ref>).</p>
                    <p>Facsimiles by permission of <title type="archive" corresp="#BEINECKERUSKINCOLLECTION">John Ruskin Collection</title>, General Collection, <orgName corresp="#BEINECKE">Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</orgName>, <orgName corresp="#YALE">Yale University</orgName>. Transcriptions of texts and commentary &#x00A9; <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Composed probably between May and July 1834, in time for submission deadline in August. 
                        As discussed in Hanson, "Ruskin in the 1830s", W. H. Collingwood assumed incorrectly that Ruskin composed this poem during a visit to Salzburg in 1835.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>Published in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; and Winter&#x02BC;s Wreath . . . for MDCCCXXXV</hi></ref>, 317&#x2013;19).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>In "Ruskin in the 1830s", Hanson argues that Collingwood wrongly assumed that Ruskin would have composed a topographical poem only about a place he had actually seen, 
                        and that therefore Ruskin must have received his commission from Thomas Pringle, the editor of Friendship's Offering, while visiting Salzburg during the family tour of 1835. 
                        Not noly would this alleged timing of the commission have been impossible; the underlying assumption is false as well. The commission, and Ruskin's poem itself, 
                        should not be understood in context of "truth to nature", but of the print culture of the annuals. Ruskin, like many other contributors to the annuals, 
                        responded to an engraving of a scene, not to the experience of the place itself.</p>
                    <p>It can be added to this argument that, in assigning this commission to the young writer, Pringle replicated an assignment he had given to himself as editor of the Friendship's Offering for 1830. 
                        That volume also featured an engraving after William Purser, the artist of <hi rend="italic">Saltzburg</hi>. 
                        Entitled <title type="artwork" corresp="#PURSERSPOLETO"><hi rend="italic">Spoleto</hi></title> and engraved by Thomas Jeavons (1795-1867), 
                        the plate appears to have been Purser's first work for the annual, and Pringle gave himself the task of writing the accompanying letterpress. 
                        (Pringle would not have commissioned the drawing to pair with a pre-existing poem, since he never traveled on the Continent, and had no other reason to write about this comparatively obscure destination in Italy, 
                        to which Mariana Starke in the 1820s devoted only a brief paragraph in describing the route from Rome to Florence, and to which William Brockedon drew attention 
                        in the 1830s mainly for the picturesque approach to Spoleto and the surrounding picturesque countryside [Starke, Travels in Europe [1828], 411; 
                        Brockedon, Traveller's Guide to Italy [1835], 144; 
                        Brockedon, Road-Book from London to Naples [1835], 130). 
                        Pringle's speaker meditates on a future visit, not a past one: "'Twere sweet, methinks, ere life hath passed away, / To spend one long, reflective summer's day" 
                        [<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1830"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; A Literary Album . . . for MDCCCXXX</hi></ref>, 109 facing page, 111; and see 
                        Eustace, A Classical Tour through Italy, 1:177-79].)</p>
                    <p>In the plate, Purser renders the scene on a plan similar to the composition of <hi rend="italic">Saltzburg</hi>. Spoleto is viewed from a distant, central vantage 
                        in the countryside above the town, its major monuments picked out in the middle ground, and with foreground figures in local costume orienting the spectator's gaze into the prospect. 
                        As the ekphrastic author, Pringle makes no pretence of being a traveler other than from his armchair, prefacing his poem with a substantial extract about the ancient history of Spoleto--its fame 
                        for repulsing an attack by Hannibal during his invasion of Rome, and the "barbarous antiquity" of its Gothic monuments--taken from 
                        A Classical Tour through Italy (1813) by Rev. John Chetwode Eustace (1761-1815). 
                        Pringle swerves from this dry annotation, however; and in keeping with the governing sentiments of the literary annuals--friendship and memory--he introduces 
                        observations on Spoleto from an unpublished travel journal lent "by the author of the 'The Pleasures of Memory'", Samuel Rogers,<!-- bio note --> 
                        "extracted, by his kind indulgence, from his travelling notebook". Rogers's jottings, much briefer than the extract from Eustace's published account, 
                        "will probably be esteemed by most readers [as] more interesting than pages of further details from more ordinary tourists", the narrator predicts. 
                        The observations are a revised version of a passage in what was later published as The Italian Journal of Samuel Rogers:</p>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <div type="essay">
                                <p>Spoleto, with its walls and turrets, soon appeared on the mountain side. . . . . The gate of Hannibal. . . . . The gigantic aqueduct crossing a deep and unfathomable chasm. . . . 
                                    Saw it by moonlight; and its vastness and entireness, connecting us at once with some mighty and unknown people, affected me deeply.</p>
                                <p>(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1830"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; A Literary Album . . . for MDCCCXXX</hi></ref>, 109; 
                                    and see The Italian Journal of Samuel Rogers, ed. Hale, 205) </p>
                            </div>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>In the poem following these prose extracts, then, the reader is to understand the speaker as meditating on the scene depicted in the plate 
                        in the light of expressive memories shared with him by Rogers. But while the speaker imagines himself beyond the engraved scene,
                        inhabiting the actual place and, like Rogers by moonlight, "mus[ing] o'er all that links thee [Spoleto] to the past" as "the wan moon gleamed high o'er rock and tower", 
                        in the end the poet humbles his efforts. Compared with what Rogers himself might have made of these materials, 
                        "Enough for me if he [Rogers] its [this poem's] tone commend, / Whom 'tis a pride and grace to call my Friend". 
                        For both poet and reader, a friendship's offering is not meant to be ambitious: "this rustic lay" is merely "Framed for the passing purpose of a day"
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1830"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; A Literary Album . . . for MDCCCXXX</hi></ref>, 111).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>