<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <fileDesc xml:id="saltzburg_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;Saltzburg&#x201d;</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus" subtype="work">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="WITNESSES">
          			<head type="section">Witnesses</head>
          			<list>
          			    <item><ref type="apparatus" subtype="manuscript" target="msviii_apparatus.php"><hi rend="bold"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS VIII</title></hi></ref>
          			        <list>
                        <item><ref type="witness" target="saltzburg_msviii.php">&#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;</ref></item>
          			        </list>
          			    </item>
          			    <item><ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold"><title type="annual" corresp="#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</title></hi></hi></ref>
          			            <list>
                        <item><ref type="witness" target="saltzburg_fo.php">&#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;</ref></item>
          			            </list>
                </item>
                </list>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Untitled in draft. When a revised version was published in the literary annual, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="friendships_offering_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref> 
                        (see <ref type="internal" target="COMPPUB">Composition and Publication</ref>), 
                        the poem first exhibited its title, &#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;; however, this title must have been determined by that of the steel engraving, 
                        which the poem was commissioned to accompany.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Ekphrastic and topographical poem.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>Draft contained in <ref type="apparatus" subtype="manuscript" target="msviii_apparatus.php">MS VIII</ref> 
                        (see <ref type="apparatus" subtype="manuscript" target="msviii_apparatus#LISTB2.php">Contents, list <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.2</ref>).</p>
                    <p>Facsimiles by permission of <title type="archive" corresp="#BEINECKERUSKINCOLLECTION">John Ruskin Collection</title>, General Collection, <orgName corresp="#BEINECKE">Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</orgName>, <orgName corresp="#YALE">Yale University</orgName>. Transcriptions of texts and commentary &#x00A9; <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Composed probably between May and July 1834, in time for submission deadline in August. 
                        As discussed in Hanson, "Ruskin in the 1830s", W. H. Collingwood assumed incorrectly that Ruskin composed this poem during a visit to Salzburg in 1835.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>Published in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; and Winter&#x02BC;s Wreath . . . for MDCCCXXXV</hi></ref>, 317&#x2013;19).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>In "Ruskin in the 1830s", Hanson argues that Collingwood wrongly assumed that Ruskin would have composed a topographical poem only about a place he had actually seen, 
                        and that therefore Ruskin must have received his commission for "Saltzburg" from Thomas Pringle, the editor of Friendship's Offering, while visiting Salzburg during the family tour of 1835. 
                        Not only would this alleged timing of the commission have been impossible for a text that must have been submitted for publication one year earlier; 
                        the underlying assumption is faulty, as well, Ruskin being fully immersed in the print culture of illustrated travel writing. The commission, and Ruskin's poem itself, 
                        should not be understood in context of Ruskin's aesthetics of "truth to nature" a decade later, but of his practical introduction to ekphrastic writing for the annuals. 
                        Like many other contributors to the annuals, Ruskin was commissioned to respond creatively to an engraving of a foreign scene, not to the experience of the place itself.</p>
                    <p>It can be added to this argument that, in assigning this commission to the young writer, Pringle replicated an assignment he had given to himself as editor of Friendship's Offering for 1830. 
                        That volume also featured an engraving after William Purser, the artist of <hi rend="italic">Saltzburg</hi>. 
                        Entitled <title type="artwork" corresp="#PURSERSPOLETO"><hi rend="italic">Spoleto</hi></title> and engraved by Thomas Jeavons (1795-1867), 
                        the plate appears to have been the first appearance of Purser's work in the annual, and Pringle gave himself the task of writing the accompanying text. 
                        (Pringle himself never visited the Continent, much less Spoleto, which was not well known to English travelers. 
                        In the 1820s, Mariana Starke devoted only a brief paragraph to the town in describing the route from Rome to Florence. 
                        In the 1830s, William Brockedon drew attention to the town's picturesque approach and surrounding countryside. See Starke, Travels in Europe [1828], 411; 
                        Brockedon, Traveller's Guide to Italy [1835], 144; 
                        Brockedon, Road-Book from London to Naples [1835], 130. 
                        Even Purser probably lacked first-hand experience of the scene, having based his drawing on "a sketch by Captain [Robert] Melville Grindlay", 
                        who had connections with Smith, Elder.  See Chatterjee, Rober Melville; 
                        and see <!-- bio note-->Smith, Elder &#x0026; Company for its connections with the East India Company.) 
                        </p>
                    <p>In the plate, Purser renders the scene on a plan similar to the composition of <hi rend="italic">Saltzburg</hi>. Spoleto is viewed from a distant, central vantage 
                        in the countryside above the town, its major monuments picked out in the middle ground. In the foreground, figures in local costume orient the spectator's gaze into the prospect. 
                        Pringle's accompanying text makes no pretence of being a traveler other than from his armchair. As a preface to a poem, "Spoleto", 
                        he fills the space adjacent to the engraving with a prose extract from a travel account, 
                        A Classical Tour through Italy (1813) by Rev. John Chetwode Eustace (1761-1815), which summarizes the triumph of ancient Spoleto over Hannibal's invading army, 
                        and highlights major monuments of the town today.</p>
                    <p>Pringle swerves from this dry annotation, however, to introduce what "will probably be esteemed by most readers [as] more interesting than pages of further details from more ordinary tourists"--some 
                        observations on Spoleto from an unpublished travel journal lent by Samuel Rogers.<!-- bio note --> 
                        Although much briefer and less informative than the extract from Eustace's published account, 
                        Rogers's jottings are in keeping with the governing sentiments of the literary annuals--friendship and memory. 
                        "[B]y his kind indulgence", the "author of the 'The Pleasures of Memory'" has shared his reminiscences of Spoleto, 
                        which turn out to be a curtailed and revised version of a passage that would later appear in The Italian Journal of Samuel Rogers:</p>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <div type="essay">
                                <p>Spoleto, with its walls and turrets, soon appeared on the mountain side. . . . . The gate of Hannibal. . . . . The gigantic aqueduct crossing a deep and unfathomable chasm. . . . 
                                    Saw it by moonlight; and its vastness and entireness, connecting us at once with some mighty and unknown people, affected me deeply.</p><lb/>
                                <p>(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1830"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; A Literary Album . . . for MDCCCXXX</hi></ref>, 109; 
                                    and see The Italian Journal of Samuel Rogers, ed. Hale, 205) </p>
                            </div>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>Pringle abridges the passage in order to feature the final and more poetic closing sentence--a poetic evocation of the scene by moonlight, with a meditation on history. 
                        In the poem following these prose extracts, then, the reader is to understand the speaker as meditating on the scene depicted in the plate, 
                        but in the light of expressive memories that have been shared with him by Rogers. From one "Whom 'tis a pride and grace to call my Friend"--the concluding line of the poem--the 
                        quotation lends romance to the vedute and prosy history, which would otherwise fail to be integrated as a friendship's offering.</p>
                    <p>One can speculate that, four years later, when Pringle had another plate by Purser, Saltzburg, to assign to a writer for the upcoming volume for 1835, 
                        he chose Ruskin in spite of the youth's lack of professional experience, 
                        in part because the editor was impressed by the youth's ability to match words with pictures, but also because behind the scene he could dedicate the assignment as an act of friendship. 
                        Since it was at about this time that Pringle arranged for Ruskin to be introduced to Samuel Rogers, 
                        and escorted him to Rogers's St. James Place residence 
                        (Hanson, Ruskin in the 1830s, 000; Samuel Rogers), 
                        it is more probable that Pringle would have invested the "Saltzburg" commission with greater significance than the mere happenstance that W. G. Collingwood supposes--that 
                        "[i]t happened that Mr. Pringle had a plate of Salzburg which he wanted to print in order to make up the volume of Friendship's Offering for the next Christmas" 
                        (Life and Work of John Ruskin, 1:52). Rather, in conferring such an impressive commission on a fifteen-year-old first-time contributor, 
                        Pringle would have shown his regard for the Ruskin family, and formalized his role of mentor and friend to the young poet, just as Rogers had condescended to Pringle. 
                        A tribute to an elder and greater poet occupies the entirety of Pringle's conclusion of his poem on Spoleto, framing the ekphrasis 
                        as an offering to a lasting poet from the pages of an ephemeral publication, "Framed for the passing purpose of a day" in the calendar of an annual, by a "rustic" Scots poet:</p>
                        <floatingText>
                            <body>
                                <div type="poem">
                                    <lg>
                                        <l>So rose the scene [of Spoleto] on Rogers' classic eye</l>
                                        <l>And thus, embalmed in words that ne'er could die,</l>
                                        <l>Its touching image had remained enshrined,</l>
                                        <l>Had <hi rend="italic">he</hi> to verse transferred it from his mind.</l>
                                        <l>Far other fate awaits this rustic lay,</l>
                                        <l>Framed for the passing purpose of a day:</l>
                                        <l>Enough for me if he its tone commend</l>
                                        <l>Whom 'tis a pride and grace to call my Friend.</l>
                                    </lg>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <p>(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1830"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; A Literary Album . . . for MDCCCXXX</hi></ref>, 111).</p>
                                </div>
                            </body>
                        </floatingText>
                    <p>Lines from Pringle's "Spoleto" are possibly echoed by Ruskin in "Saltzburg".</p>
                        <p>The extract first highlights the town's fame for repulsing an attack by Hannibal's army, following the Cathaginian victory over Rome, a continuing source of local pride which is mentioned in all guidebooks. 
                        The passage then scans the town's major monuments, using a strategy that may have been instructive to Ruskin. As a Roman Catholic priest, 
                        Eustace dwells on the Gothic cathedral, of course admiring its beauty in contrast with lighting its lurid fascination as Ruskin does; 
                        however, the passage also presents views of the cathedral that are invisible in the plate, such as details from its interior, 
                        and the prospect looking outward from its terrace. This accidental juxtaposition of conflicting viewpoints may have given; the "barbarous antiquity" of its castle 
                        (see Eustace, A Classical Tour through Italy, 1:177-79). </p>
                    <p>Forsyth 3d ed, 1824, 2:94; Lalande 6:247-50</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>