<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Education</title>
                <title type="sub">Essay</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head type="title">Education</head>
                <p>This essay presents an overview of John Ruskin's education, and the essay will be continually revised as the ERM archive expands. 
                    For detailed discussion of topics mentioned here, follow hyperlinks to notes and to the appartuses of works and of manuscripts.</p>
                <div type="section" xml:id="PRACTICALEDUCATION">
                    <head type="section">Practical Education</head>
                    <p>In MS I (1826&#x2013;27), MS II, and MS IIIA, John Ruskin&#x02BC;s prose and poetry reflect aspects of the methods advocated 
                        by associates of the Lunar Society, such as Erasmus Darwin, R. L. and Maria Edgeworth, and Barbauld. The Edgeworths' jointly written Practical Education epitomizes. . . 
                        While Ruskin copies verbatim stretches of Joyce, he also adapts the dialogues to his own circumstances at Herne Hill, 
                        showing that his parents encouraged him to form habits of inquiry and development of his own faculties (Simon 50-56). 
                        (Telling that the adaptation revolves around mother, and copying around father?). 
                        In MS IV he strives to explain the workings of machinery. Sandford and Merton his favorite book.
                    </p>
                    <p>That Margaret Ruskin had John and his cousin Mary study a portion of Adam Smith's theory of moral sentiments shows that the family accepted, at least in broad terms, 
                        the psychology founded by Locke and elaborated by the associationism of David Hartley (see Simon 45-46, 50). . . .</p>
                    <p>While the earliest manuscripts suggest that Ruskin was submerged in the experimental methods of the Lunar circle, 
                        Ruskin's engagement with such works falls off rapidly. There is no other imitation of a poem by Erasmus Darwin. The catalog poetry? 
                        In the year 1826, when Ruskin composed his poetry and prose most recognizably influenced by the educationists, their Utilitarian successors, 
                        were leading a Radical attack on the interests of the aristocracy and Established Church, 
                        as represented by James Mill's scathing article of that year in the Westminster Review (Simon74-79). and Ruskin's tutor, the Reverend Edward Andrews, attended the Dissenter academy at Hoxton, but by his time the Dissenting academies had shifted 
                        in the wake of post-revolutionary opposition to Reform, and reflected less interest in scientific investigation and more entrenched clerical training 
                        for their respective sects (Simon 69).</p>
                    <p>May be easy to see why, in that practical education was meant to train boys for industrial entrepreneurship (Simon 37), 
                        whereas Ruskin was destined for the traditional universities and Established connections. Bentham likewise advocated a vocational emphasis in education (Simon 80). 
                        Ruskin does retain his interest in science and experimental observation (Loudon), but nothing can be less utilitarian than the taste for picturesque that overtakes his poetry; 
                        and there's no suggestion of Benthamite regimentation of learning activities that J. S. Mill reservedly advocated in his autobiography.
                        In the second
                        (1828&#x2013;29), this plan is suffused first with the Romantic coloring of
                        history, and then with Christian theology&#x2014;the religious teaching itself
                        markedly historical, with its initial emphasis on Old Testament stories.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>