<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in <hi rend="italic">Title of Printed Work</hi> (Date)</title>
                <!--The xml:ids for author and editor below should include the first, middle, and last initials of the author and the editor, respectively.-->
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#APW">Author of Printed Work</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#EPW">Editor of Printed Work</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Poems of John Ruskin</title>
                        <title type="sub">Volume I: Poems Written in Boyhood, 1826-1835</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1891">1891</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">xxiii</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Simple Prose. Delete this <div/> if not used.-->
            <div type="prose">
                <head type="title">Title of Prose Piece</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter">Title of Chapter</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296809_Verso_03"/>
                    <p>The begninning of the 16 chapter of <title type="Scripture">Leviticus</title>  Last <persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> day, <!--Should I tag Leviticus as a person or as a book-->
                    <lb/>we were considering the importance of observing sacrificial 
                    <lb/>institutions and the example afforded us by <persName corresp="#NADAB">Nadab</persName>, and <persName corresp="#ABIHU">Abihu</persName>
                    <lb/>-To day, our attention is to be directed to the circumstances
                    <lb/>which occurred in the approach of the priest to the holy place.
                    <lb/>after the death of <persName corresp="#NADAB">Nadab</persName> and <persName corresp="#ABIHU">Abihu</persName>. We take up this subject, 
                    <lb/>both as a continuation of the thread of the narrative. <!--Cannot tell if thread is the correct word in the manuscript-->
                    <lb/>and as a farther exemplification of the general character of
                    <lb/>the subject, and evidence of its relation to the atonement of
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#LORD">Christ</persName>  Some may ask, why do we heap up evidence upon evidence.
                    <lb/>to prove what was never doubted  But we answer,  that there may
                    <lb/>be moments of weakness when doubts will thrust themselves upon 
                    <lb/>us in spite of our faith, and a chain of weighty evidence may
                    <lb/>be found exceedingly valuable. Besides the face that this succeeding
                    <lb/>evidence is given to us in the <title type="book" corresp="#BIBLE">Bible</title>, is sufficient to show us that
                    <lb/>it was necessary to inquire into it, it must be useful, or it would
                    <lb/>not have been given to us.</p>
                    <p>Having - thus considered sacrifices first as to their general intention,
                    <lb/>then as applied to the consecration and ministratino of the priest,
                    <lb/>to the atonement for the congregation, for an individual, and for
                    <lb/>the ruler of the people, We have now to consider the manner in which
                    <lb/>the priest was to minister, once in the year, to atone for
                    <lb/>the unknown sins of the congregation not only unwittingly
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA3451_296809_Recto_4"/>
                    <lb/>committed, but unknown, even at the time of atonement  The year
                    <lb/>is supposed to have passed by and the offences committed in that year.
                    <lb/>through ignorance, but afterwards known or recollected, have been atoned
                    <lb/>for, not a moment past after they came to the knowledge of the guilty
                    <lb/>person. before atonement was made for them. But besides thesem there
                    <lb/>might, there must, have been other sins, committed by the congregation,
                    <lb/>of which they not only became guilt through ignorance, but had never
                    <lb/>afterwards discovered, and even at the time of atonement, were not 
                    <lb/>certain, that they had ever committed the sin for which they were 
                    <lb/>atoning, it was only a strong supposition. still, these unknown sins 
                    <lb/>must be expiated. once in the year and that on the part of every individual
                    <lb/>in the congregation  Some may think, that these unknown offenses might
                    <lb/>have been freely pardoned. that sacrifice need not have been again introduced
                    <lb/>here, they had atoned for all known sins, the people could scarcely 
                    <lb/>be said to have disobeyed commands which they knew not, some may think
                    <lb/>this was too much severity and strictness But no, it is not inquired how
                    <lb/>they sinned, but whether. they sinned. Sacrifice is the groundwork of
                    <lb/>atonement and atonement is the groundwork of pardon.</p>
                    <p>Now, in the particulars of this great, and solemn atonement,
                    <lb/>we see that there were two atonements to be offered. 1.st
                    <lb/>for - the priest himself, alone, and not for the general 
                    <lb/>sin of the whole congregation, but for the sin of every 
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296809_Verso_04"/>   
                    <lb/>congregation, but for the sin of every particular person, that is, every person in the whole 
                    <lb/>congregation was not atoned for separately. but the 
                    <lb/>whole ceremony was shut up to the high priest to signify,
                    <lb/>that every individual of the congregation, must be singly 
                    <lb/>atoned for.</p>
                    <p>1st. For the priest himself, The high priest was in the 
                    <lb/>first place, to take a yound bullock, for a sin offering
                    <lb/>for himself alone. We cannot but suppose, that they high 
                    <lb/>priest from so continually sacrificing, and atoning for 
                    <lb/>sin, was particularly alive to its nature, and manner of
                    <lb/>approach, so that sin could scarcely lurk in him, without
                    <lb/>his knowledge. or after discovering for he knew how 
                    <lb/>important it was to keep free from it, and to obey the 
                    <lb/>commands of the Law, and likewise the high priest must, 
                    <lb/>without doubt, have been acquainted with the minutest 
                    <lb/>tittle of those commands, so that he could hardly sin 
                    <lb/>through ignorance, and the fault committed through 
                    <lb/>negligence, or forgetfulness, must have been afterwards 
                    <lb/>discovered, and atoned for. Yet, in spite of all. this, in
                    <lb/>spite of the almost impossibility of the priests committing
                    <lb/>unknown sin, sacrifice must be made for him, and for him. 
                    <lb/>not as - an individual of the congregation, but for him first,
                    <lb/>and alone, that he might be made perfectly pure, before he
                    <lb/>offered the sacrifice for the people  It is useless to think
                    <lb/>of pardon without the intervention of atonement, and sacrifice.</p>
                    <p>2. For the congregation. Now. as we before said, the priest was
                    <lb/>here a representative of the people of <placeName corresp="#ISRAEL">Israel</placeName>. and. that they might
                    <lb/>be more fully and perfectly represented, all was shut up to him, 
                    <lb/>there were no other priests, not even his sons, to
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296809_Recto_5"/>    
                    <lb/>minister with him. and it is likewise a very singular manner, in which he offered.
                    <lb/>He received two goats from the congregation and one of these he slew,
                    <lb/>for the expiation, while the other escaped, to show the forgiveness <!--Cannot tell if other is the correct word in the manuscript-->
                    <lb/>of unknown guilt thus expiated, The character of individuals is here
                    <lb/>counted as no thing, and pardon is here certainly not granted for
                    <lb/>confession of sin, not for repentance, for that cannot be confessed
                    <lb/>which is not known, neither can it be repented of, except in a 
                    <lb/>general way, but the pardon was granted for expiation of sin by 
                    <lb/>sacrifice, and we therefore see, that here also we remain shut up
                    <lb/>to sacrifice as the only way to escape from the punishment of sin.</p>
                    <p>In the 16 verse, we are told, that atonement must for the tabernacle,
                    <lb/>likewise, because it was unclean. Now, it was not defiled by the 
                    <lb/>touch of any particular individual, but because it was constantly 
                    <lb/>in the midst of an unclean congregation, and the altar must also
                    <lb/>be purified. Now incense is here represented, as offered to the 
                    <lb/>, as<persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> a token of <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">Gods</name> acceptance of the sacrifice  The <persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> smelt
                    <lb/>a sweet savour, The perfume of the incense devoted the sweetness of
                    <lb/>the sacrifice and expiation of sin. and the cloud of incense covered
                    <lb/>the mercy seat, when the priest offered sacrifice. to prevent his
                    <lb/>attention being disturbed by the symbolical presence of the <persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> between
                    <lb/>the cherubims, and to prevent idle curiosity being excited and restrain
                    <lb/>all wandering thoughts, because the least deviation from the established
                    <lb/>rule of sacrifice. was punished with death, it was a penalty attached to
                    <lb/>the minutest error. And thus by the incense rising and enveloping by 
                    <lb/>the holy place. the priest was undisturbed, and lefte to contemplate 
                    <lb/>the efficacy of the atonement, which
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296809_Verso_05"/> 
                    <lb/>he was engaged in presenting,and the sacrifice was offered only once in the year, in order to impart
                    <lb/>to it, a greater solemnity and to impress on every individual the 
                    <lb/>vast importance of a full and perfect expiation of unknown sin.</p>
                    <p>The next circumstance which we have to consider, is, that the priest
                    <lb/>in this one particular atonement, was entirely to forget the dignity
                    <lb/>of his character, he was not to remember that he was the high priest,
                    <lb/>and in order to this, he was not to be dressed in his sacrificial robes,
                    <lb/>The breastplate on whose twelve stones were graven the names of the 
                    <lb/>tribes of <placeName corresp="#ISRAEL">Israel</placeName>, and the mitre, and the ephod, were all to be laid aside,
                    <lb/>he was to be dressed only in simple linen garments, to show his humility
                    <lb/>before <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>, but after he had finished sacrificing, and had come out from
                    <lb/>the most holy into the holy placem he was to put on his sacrificial robes,
                    <lb/>before he came out to bless the people. before he came out to tell them
                    <lb/>that this most solemn atonement had been offered, &#x0026; had been offered
                    <lb/>with success. If we reflect that death was the penalty of the slightest
                    <lb/>deviation, and that not only of the priest, but that as the sacrifice would
                    <lb/>in such a case certainly not be accepted, the wrath of <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> might be poured 
                    <lb/>forth upon the whole congregation of <placeName corresp="#ISRAEL">Israel</placeName> on account of their unexpiated
                    <lb/>sin we cannot but feel that it must a deeply interesting and solemn, for the
                    <lb/>gathered multitude to have behold their priest entering alone into the holy
                    <lb/>place. to atone for the sins which they knew not ? if they had committed,
                    <lb/>and being doubtful if the agitation which the mind of the priest must in such
                    <lb/>circumstances have been under, might not cause him to commit some error slight
                    <lb/>in the estimation of man, but to which a dreadful penalty was attached by the
                    <lb/><name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">Almighty</name>, and which might cause the rejection of their atonement and then to
                    <lb/>hear the sound of the priests bells in the holy place after he had come out from</p>
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296809_Recto_6"/>
                    <p>the most holy, after having been in such intimate contact with <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>, it must have been
                    <lb/>a glad sound to the ears of that assembled multitude of doubting and ignorant sinners,
                    <lb/>for it told them that the atonement which they had offered was accepted, and pardon
                    <lb/>granted them, and the remission of their sins.</p>
                    <p>Now, as we have previously pointed out the intention of this. Mosaic economy, and the
                    <lb/>manner of its shadowing forth the sacrifice of <persName corresp="#LORD">Jesus</persName>, &#x0026; as to day we have seen
                    <lb/>how the slightest deviation from this law was punished with death, and how completely
                    <lb/>the Israelites were shut up to their - doctrine of atonement by shedding of blood, it
                    <lb/>follows that we are equally shut up to the doctrine of salvation through the blood of 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#LORD">Christ</persName>. and the great question must then suggest itself. have we indeed come to this 
                    <lb/>all powerful <persName corresp="#LORD">Redeemer</persName>. There were three things connected with the ancient expiation of
                    <lb/>sin, there was, 1st atonement. 2nd pardon. and 3rd Blessing. Now we know, that there 
                    <lb/>can be no effectual groundwork of pardon, or blessing, that is not laid in his atonement,
                    <lb/>for vindication on the ground of innocent intention, is, we have seen, utterly out of 
                    <lb/>the question, much less then on account of innocence. Let us not then say in our hearts,
                    <lb/>we have injured no man, we have defrounded no man, we believe in <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>, we have nothing to
                    <lb/>fear. The priest did not - do this, he did not advance one step without sacrifice, he
                    <lb/>ackknowledges &#x0026; atones for guilt, but he does not plead innocence, for, had he 
                    <lb/>done so, he would have been departing from the plan which <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> has universally laid down
                    <lb/>of salvation.</p>
                    <p>Let us then finally remember, that <persName corresp="#LORD">Christ</persName> is at present our high priest and that he has
                    <lb/>done more than the priest of the Jews, inasmuch, as besides offering the atonement which
                    <lb/>he has made with his own blood, he has also met the punishment, allotted to our sin and 
                    <lb/>presents us with the assurance that our <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> is one, who will be always gracious</p> <!--Cannot tell if gracious is the correct word in the manuscript-->
                    
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                </div>     
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
