<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in <hi rend="italic">Title of Printed Work</hi> (Date)</title>
                <!--The xml:ids for author and editor below should include the first, middle, and last initials of the author and the editor, respectively.-->
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#APW">Author of Printed Work</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#EPW">Editor of Printed Work</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#SEM">Sarah Elizabeth Montelepre</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Poems of John Ruskin</title>
                        <title type="sub">Volume I: Poems Written in Boyhood, 1826-1835</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1891">1891</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">xxiii</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Simple Prose. Delete this <div/> if not used.-->
            <div type="prose">
                <head type="title">Sermon X</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <pb facs="MS Sermon 005a"/>
                    <head type="chapter">The law of sacrifice.</head>
                    <p>The 1st chapter of <title type="scripture" corresp="#LEVITICUS">Leviticus</title>, from the
                    <lb/>beginning.  I think that in the re&#x2010;
                    <lb/>marks on the law of <persName corresp="#MOSES">Moses</persName>; which
                    <lb/>are to employ us to obey., it is better to
                    <lb/>enter upon <title type="scripture" corresp="#LEVITICUS">Leviticus</title>, as the book which
                    <lb/>contains more specifically the details
                    <lb/>of the law of sacrifice, which is the
                    <lb/>very foundation of the Mosaic econ
                    <lb/>omy.  We shall first <del rend="strikethrough">fir</del> consider
                    <lb/>the doctrine of atonement here, &#x0026; then
                    <lb/>follow it up to its antitype, the death
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>.  Now this is a real form 
                    <lb/>of sacrifice, and a simple form.  It is
                    <lb/>not for a confimation of testimony
                    <lb/>nor announcement, nor instruction
                    <pb facs="MS Sermon 005a"/>
                    <lb/>to be communicated.  The priest takes the
                    <lb/>sacrifice in silence, in the open court before
                    <lb/>the tabernacle, where the altar for sac
                    <lb/>rifice was placed. he slays and sprin
                    <lb/>kles the blood round about upon the
                    <lb/>altar.  Now there is nothing here, that
                    <lb/>would lead us to infer any thing
                    <lb/>more, than a simple form of sac&#x2010;
                    <lb/>rifice.  But. in the 4 verse, we are in
                    <lb/>formed, that the man laid his hand
                    <lb/>on the head of the burntoffering and
                    <lb/>it was accepted for him to make
                    <lb/>atonement for him.  Now, nothing can
                    <lb/>be more clear, than that we have here
                    <lb/>a sinner laying his hand on the head of
                    <lb/>the sacrifice, in order to communicate
                    <lb/>the load of his sins and his wickedness
                    <lb/>to the animal  The victim was then
                    <lb/>substituted for him, it bore his punish
                    <lb/>ment, and was accepted for him
                    <lb/>to make atonement for him.  Can
                    <lb/>anything be clearer, than that this
                    <lb/>was merely a scene of sacrifice and of
                    <lb/>atonement.</p>
                    <lb/><p>But we have also another intimat&#x2010;
                    <lb/>tion.  The sacrifice must be appropri&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ate.  Every victim or any victim that
                    <lb/>the man might choose to give, would
                    <lb/>not suffice.  It must be pure, chosen
                    <lb/>out of the flock, a male without ble
                    <lb/>mish, or it will not be accepted
                    <lb/>And the last intimation is, that the
                    <lb/>sacrifice must be offered, of the mans
                    <lb/>own voluntary will.  There was no le&#x2010;
                    <lb/>gal authority that could compel the
                    <lb/>man to bring the sacrifice, he was only
                    <lb/>in case that he withheld it debarred
                    <lb/>from certain religious privileges, which
                    <lb/>were withheld by <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> from him who
                    <lb/>sacrificed not, but he was compelled
                    <lb/>to sacrifice no farther than by being
                    <lb/>threatened with <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>s high displeas&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ure, if he refused.  It is through
                    <lb/>these three points that I wish to fol&#x2010;
                    <lb/>low up the shadow of sacrifice to its 
                    <lb/>substance, <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>.</p>
                    <lb/><p>For. the law was raised up, in order
                    <lb/>to throw forward a shadow to another
                    <lb/>economy which other economy, was,
                    <lb/>we see shadowed forth by sacrifice &#x0026;
                    <lb/>this is explained in the beginning of the
                    <lb/>10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> chapter, of <title type="scripture" corresp="#HEBREWS">Hebrews</title>, where it is said
                    <lb/>that the law, having a shadow of good
                    <lb/>things to come and not the very image
                    <lb/>of those things, can never with sacrifi
                    <lb/>ces, make the comers thereunto perfect &#x0026;
                    <lb/>and it goes on to say that the blood of
                    <lb/>it goes on to say that the blood of
                    <lb/>bulls and goats can never take away <add type="runover" place="below"><space quantity="29" unit="chars"/>(sin</add></p>
                    <pb facs="MS Sermon 006a"/>
                    <lb/><p>Now, if it is impossible, that blood can
                    <lb/>take away sin, can we suppose, that
                    <lb/>these momentous ordinances, were on
                    <lb/>ly for show, for ceremony,  Can <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> in
                    <lb/>stitute any thing of no moral worth
                    <lb/>certainly not.  Then as the law threw
                    <lb/>forward a shadow to another economy
                    <lb/>these sacrifices must be to intimate
                    <lb/>that sacrifice is necessary in the other
                    <lb/>economy and sacrifice, which shall
                    <lb/>be capable of taking away all sin.  Now
                    <lb/>if in the <title type="scripture" corresp="#GOSPEL">Gospel</title> this sacrifice of anim<!--rest of "animals?-->
                    <lb/>is done away with, and yet we know
                    <lb/>that we must have sacrifices of some
                    <lb/>sort, we are shut up to the death of
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>, as the very essence of atonemen<!--t?-->
                    <lb/>The law sacrifices derived their value
                    <lb/>only because they referred to the gos
                    <lb/>pel and if this be correct, the view
                    <lb/>which we have taked of them, must be referred to <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>.</p>
                    <lb/><p>In the first place, <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName> has some
                    <lb/>times been erroneously held up, as a
                    <lb/>mere martyr to truth, and it has
                    <lb/>been affirmed, that he died only to
                    <lb/>confirm the truth of his tetimonies
                    <lb/>and not to take away our sin.  Bu<!--t?-->
                    <lb/>he confirmed the truth of his testimony
                    <lb/>by miracles, not by his death, he died
                    <lb/>as a sacrifice, for his death alone could
                    <lb/>not have confirmed <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> his truth
                    <lb/>Pagans have died for their religion
                    <lb/>yet that does not prove the truth
                    <lb/>of Pagnism.  Mahametans have died
                    <lb/>for their religion yet that does
                    <lb/>not prove the truth of Moham&#x2010;
                    <lb/>medanism.  Atheists have died for
                    <lb/>their no religion, yet that does not
                    <lb/>prove that <!--???--> there is no <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>.  Their
                    <lb/>death proves only thier attachment
                    <lb/>to their system, not the truth of that
                    <lb/>system.  The word of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> in no place
                    <lb/>brings forward the death of <persName corresp="#STEPHEN">Stephen</persName>
                    <lb/>as an evidence of the truth of Chris&#x2010;
                    <lb/>tianity.  The death of <del rend="strikethrough">Stephe</del> <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>
                    <lb/>must then be regarded, not as a
                    <lb/>confirmation of his testimony, but as
                    <lb/>a sacrifice for the ungodly.</p>
                    <lb/><p>Again, as the law is a shadow of
                    <lb/>good things to come, and as sacrifice
                    <lb/>is the foundation of the law we have
                    <lb/>a stiking proof of the efficacy of the
                    <lb/>atonement of<persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>.  Now the victim
                        <!--something scrawled between these lines-->
                    <lb/>to be presented in the old law, was
                    <lb/>to be appropriate, and we find that
                    <pb facs="MS Sermon 006a"/>
                    <lb/>the <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Saviour</persName> was thus fitting for the a
                    <lb/>tonement he had to make.  He had
                    <lb/>to take upon himself the burde of the
                    <lb/>world, and he was able to do so, he had
                    <lb/>to take away moral guilts, which no cre<!--a?-->
                    <lb/>ture could do, and a creature victim
                    <lb/>would therefore have been rejected; he
                    <lb/>was able to do this also.  We should re
                    <lb/>member that when we wish to offer
                    <lb/>to the <persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName> a sacrifice for our
                    <lb/>sins, we have to consider of what value
                    <lb/>the victim will appear to his eyes.  Now
                    <lb/>could any creature have value in the
                    <lb/>sight of the <persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName>.  Are not the
                    <lb/>highest of them the mere result of
                    <lb/>his fiat, from the least even unto
                    <lb/>the greatest of them they requite the
                    <lb/>same effort of powe to create them;
                    <lb/>the crawling reptile, and the most ex
                    <lb/>alted archangel, are equally valueless
                    <lb/>as a sacrifice in the sight of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, bec
                    <lb/>ause he could speak a world of such
                    <lb/>beings into existence in a moment.  All
                    <lb/>things are valued by their scarcity &#x0026;
                    <lb/>there is no value whatever attached to
                    <lb/>that which is in rich abundance&#x2010;
                    <lb/>gold is valued because it<!--looks like he missed crossing the 't' twice--> is scarce, but the
                    <lb/>rock in which it is found is not
                    <lb/>valued, because it is plentiful.  As <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>
                    <lb/>therefore can call every creature in&#2010;
                    <lb/>to existence with equal facility no crea
                    <lb/>ture can be of value in his eyes and
                    <lb/>we are compelled to seek a sacrifice
                    <lb/>beyond creatures, which sacrifice must
                    <lb/>be <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>.  And his death could not
                    <lb/>be held up, unless he were the son of
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>  He must be <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, or he could not
                    <lb/>meet the character of the dispensation
                    <lb/>There is likewise another characteristic
                    <lb/>the man must do it of his own free
                    <lb/>will, and this finally gives us the whole
                    <lb/>character of the new testament dispen
                    <lb/>sation.  For the sacrifice of <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName> is
                    <lb/>not one to which authority can press
                    <lb/>us, nor with which we can be com
                    <lb/>pelled to connect ourselves.  We must
                    <lb/>have our mind enlightened by the
                    <lb/>demonstrations of the spirit and the po&#x2010;
                    <lb/>wer of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>.  There must be enlighten&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ing, before we can lay hold on the sac
                    <lb/>rifice of <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>.  Now the next question
                    <lb/>which must necessarily o<!--??-->ccur to us,
                    <lb/>is, have we done this, and have we done
                    <lb/>it of our free will  For it will not
                    <lb/>suffice if we have only been induced to
                    <pb facs="MS Sermon 007a"/>
                    <lb/>confess <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName> by the influence of our
                    <lb/>relations, Influence, or custom are not
                    <lb/>our own free will.  And unless we are
                    <lb/>found voluntarily resting on the new tes
                    <lb/>timent atonement, we are as guilty as
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#NADAB">Nadab</persName> and <persName corresp="#ABIHU">Abihu</persName>, we offer strange fire be
                    <lb/>fore the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> and we must take heed,
                    <lb/>lest their punishment should also light
                    <lb/>upon us.  we are as much guilty of us<!--??-->
                    <lb/>ery of the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName>, as that man would have
                    <lb/>been, who should have brought the vic
                    <lb/>tim to <persName corresp="#MOSES">Moses</persName>, not of his own free will.
                    <lb/>Now, is not this a solemn thing, to lay
                    <lb/>our hand on the sacrifice of <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName> which
                    <lb/>if we do of our own free will, we shall
                    <lb/>be found in the presence of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> accep&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ting the offering which he has valued
                    <lb/>because it was not that of a creature
                    <lb/>he invites us to draw near and rest on
                    <lb/>this atonement, the substance of the shad
                    <lb/>ow of the Mosaic dispensation, which
                    <lb/>if we do we shall be washed from 
                    <lb/>all our sins and made white in the blood
                    <lb/>of the lamb.</p>
                
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>