<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Work</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="subtype">
                <head type="title">Title of Note</head>
                <p><note n="2" place="botwin"
                    resp="DCH#">Prideaux&#x02BC;s criticism of <ref type="bibliography"
                        target="bibliography.php#EARLYEDITIONS">Slater&#x02BC;s <hi
                            rend="italic">Early Editions</hi></ref>, that it ranked the
                                significance of modern first editions too much according to their
                                market value, appears justified. As a guide for comprehensive
                                collecting, <ref type="bibliography"
                                    target="bibliography.php#EARLYEDITIONS">Slater&#x02BC;s
                                    book</ref> is eccentric. For example, in the chapter on
                                <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>, <persName
                                    corresp="#JHS">Slater</persName> mentions in passing a number of
                                &#x201C;publications which for one reason or another it has been
                                thought undesirable to describe in full,&#x201D; generally because
                                of &#x201C;the unimportance of the items from the collector&#x02BC;s
                                standpoint.&#x201D; Among these, he lists the <date when="1868"
                                    >1868</date> pamphlet of &#x201C;Leoni,&#x201D; which he notes
                                as rare (and which he presumably did not recognize to be a forgery).
                                Nonetheless, in the list of <persName corresp="#JR"
                                    >Ruskin</persName> publications that he does formally describe,
                                he includes the <hi rend="italic">Salsette and Elephanta</hi>
                                <!--needs to be linked to archive work when available--> pamphlet,
                                the <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS1850"
                                    ><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1850)</ref>, and the <ref
                                        type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891"><hi
                                            rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</ref>. While <persName
                                                corresp="#JHS">Slater</persName> may have omitted the
                                &#x201C;Leoni&#x201D; pamphlet merely on the grounds of having
                                &#x201C;not been able to meet with&#x201D; a copy, his caveats do
                                not explain the &#x201C;unimportance,&#x201D; in his view, of the
                                other <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> pamphlets he omits
                                (<ref type="bibliography"
                                    target="bibliography.php#EARLYEDITIONS">Slater, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Early Editions</hi></ref>, 219, 221&#x2013;22,
                                226, 247&#x2013;48, 219).</note>.</p>
                
                <p>Here, the reviewer mourns the &#x201C;pathetic sight&#x201D; of the child &#x201C;immersed&#x201D; in &#x201C;days
                and nights&#x201D; of &#x201C;labours&#x201D; over &#x201C;its <placeName corresp="#FRANCE">French</placeName> exercises, its <placeName corresp="#GERMANY">German</placeName> exercises, its
                <placeName corresp="#ITALY">Italian</placeName> exercises, its <placeName corresp="#GREECE">Greek</placeName> exercises, its Latin exercises, its lessons in
                music, drawing, arithmetic, geography, and all the rest of it.&#x201D; <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">Britain</placeName>, in this
                argument, becomes a green space, where &#x201C;in every meadow and lane in <placeName corresp="#ENGLAND">England</placeName>,&#x201D;
                childhood&#x02BC;s &#x201C;true and only schoolmistress, Nature,&#x201D; cries out for the child to
                read fairy tales &#x201C;under the waving trees.&#x201D; Correspondingly, &#x201C;infant literature&#x201D;
                (here, literature for children, not by them) is an essentialist experience,
                belonging to <persName corresp="#WW">Wordsworth&#x02BC;s</persName> &#x201C;literature of power&#x201D;: &#x201C;it is impossible to
                calculate how enormous in moulding the mind is the power of infant literature.
                It is not merely that what we read in childhood we never forget, but that it
                becomes part of our very being&#x201D; .(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LITERARYGOSSIPDEC76">&#x201C;Mrs. Browning&#x02BC;s Earlier Poems&#x201D;,</ref> 722).</p>
                
                <p>The admission appears to beg the question of his own culpability on the same grounds that he pleaded against <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName>&#x2014;that the personal wishes of &#x201C;writers of eminence&#x201D; and their families were being 
                    ignored. Even if <persName corresp="#RB">Browning</persName> genuinely believed <persName corresp="#PBS">Shelley&#x02BC;s</persName> early poetry to be unworthy, 
                    his testimony gives the appearance of his having acted in bad faith compared to <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName>, who at least professed to admire <persName corresp="EBB">Barrett Browning&#x02BC;s</persName> early poems. 
                    Despite this weakness arising in cross&#x2010;examination, <persName corresp="#EBB">Browning&#x02BC;s</persName> testimony succeeded in framing the terms for the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi>&#x02BC;s final word on the conflict. In comments appended 
                    to a (largely favorable) review of a compilation of Waltoniana compiled by the <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName><!--TPD: "the" Shepherd?-->, the journal reacted to the jury&#x02BC;s decision in <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> favor by listing what the journal editors interpreted 
                    as <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> self&#x2010;confessed infringements and concluded: &#x201C;It will be a lasting benefit to literature when it comes to be universally recognized that no desire to &#x2018;provide <hi rend="italic">caviare</hi> 
                    for a few students&#x2019; can excuse the defiance of the wishes of a great writer with respect to his own poems or those of his wife&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REVIEWWALTONIANA">Unsigned review of <hi rend="italic">Waltoniana</hi></ref>, 786).
                    <persName corresp="#RB">Browning</persName> also revisited an argument that the journal 
                    had conceded could not be sustained on strictly legal grounds (&#x201C;were it a question of tables or chairs, <persName corresp="#RB">Mr. Browning</persName> could defend the wishes of his wife; but in the case of poems, 
                    our wise laws give him no remedy&#x201D; [<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LITERARYGOSSIPNOV76">&#x201C;Literary Gossip&#x201D;</ref>, 25 November 1876, 690]), and he ignores the journal&#x02BC;s 
                    new argument&#x2014;on grounds of national, rather than personal interest&#x2014;that the journal pressed in its <date when="1877-12">December 1877</date> review of the reprint (although the writer deftly clings to personal claims, 
                    alongside wider ones, by remarking that, &#x201C;even if the volume of <date when="1826">1826</date> had been reprinted by the only man who has any right to reprint it&#x2014;<persName corresp="#RB">Mr. Browning</persName>&#x2014;we could scarcely . . . have approved the undertaking&#x201D; 
                    owing to the poems&#x02BC; lack of merit 
                    [<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REVIEWBARRETTBROWNINGEARLIERPOEMS1878">Unsigned review of <hi rend="italic">The Earlier Poems of Elizabeth Barrett Browning</hi></ref>, 766]). 
                    Perhaps by shifting back to claims of personal interest, <persName corresp="#RB">Browning</persName> fatally bared himself to contradictions exposed by the prosecution. 
                </p>
                
                
                <p>In <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> difficulties with modern writers and the public press, two sets of contradictions appear to be in play that bear on <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>&#x02BC;s concerns 
                    with nineteenth&#x2010;century children&#x02BC;s writing. 
                    One set of contradictions, which relates to the status of juvenilia in the editing and canonization of eminent Victorian writers, the uses of juvenilia in biography and autobiography of those writers, 
                    and the context of 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.php">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>, 
                    is the clash between the efforts of pioneering scholars and editors 
                    of modern literature like <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> to represent an author&#x02BC;s corpus genetically and comprehensively 
                    and the authority claimed by many Victorian writers to erase genetic evidence and vest legitimacy solely in a later, revised canon. On the evidence of <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> versus the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi>, 
                    in the final third of the century this conflict was playing out in terms of national and of private interests&#x2014;terms that themselves were not necessarily compatible. 
                    The second set of contradictions revolves around the figure of the precocious child. 
                    Again, in the contradiction is played out in terms of national versus private interests, with the former leading the journal to a negative view of the precocious child whose &#x201C;economy of Nature&#x201D; 
                    must be mechanistically managed to prove beneficial to the nation, whereas <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> advances a positive view of precocity with the aid of an organic, developmental metaphor of Romantic imagination in nature. 
                    A further contradiction is that the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi>, even while pursuing its feud with <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName>, could swerve to admiring and validating the authority of youthful imagination 
                    by using a paradigm that appears compatible with <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> rhetoric in his editions of juvenilia&#x2014;the paradigm, drawn from <persName corresp="#WW">Wordsworth&#x02BC;s</persName> &#x201C;Immotality Ode,&#x201D; of childhood as a lost, divine state of being.</p>
                <p></p>
                <p>A survey of <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> publications shows that he shared this essentialist, nostalgically sentimental view of the resources of childhood, despite also justifying his reprints of juvenilia 
                    with an organic, developmental view of the great writer&#x02BC;s youth. 
                    In his editions of <persName corresp="#WBP">Blake&#x02BC;s</persName> <hi rend="italic">Poetical Sketches</hi> (<date when="1868">1868</date>) and 
                    <hi rend="italic">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (<date when="1866">1866</date>, <date when="1868">1868</date>, <date when="1874">1874</date>),<note><persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> publisher for the <persName corresp="#WBP">Blake</persName> editions, <persName corresp="#BMP">Basil Montagu </persName>, 
                        was the son of <persName corresp="#WBP">William</persName>, who published the first regular typographical edition of <persName corresp="#WBP">Blake&#x02BC;s</persName> <hi rend="italic">Songs</hi>; 
                        the son restarted his father&#x02BC;s publishing business in <date when="1858">1858</date> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#">Keynes, <hi rend="italic">William </hi></ref>, 35, 42).</note> 
                    <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> assumes a view of juvenile literature similar to that in the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi>&#x02BC;s review of the the Lambs&#x02BC; <hi rend="italic">Poetry for Children</hi>.
                    He dotes on how the poems &#x201C;will be cherished by children for their purity and simplicity, and by grown&#x2010;up
                    men and women for the deeper meanings which always underlie the most simple of them:&#x2014;&#x2018;Thoughts that do often lie too deep for tears.&#x2019; 
                    There is something sublime in the spirit of childlike innocence and Christian rebuke of worldliness and hardheartedness that pervades these productions. 
                    [<persName corresp="#WBP">Blake</persName>] sums up all the commandments under the precept, &#x2018;Little children, love one another. For love is the fulfilling of the law. He that loveth not, knoweth not God; 
                    for God is love&#x2019;&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BLAKESONGS1866">Blake, <hi rend="italic">Songs</hi>, ed. Shepherd</ref>, xi).</p>
                <p>In one of <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> own compositions, a presentation poem for a little girl, &#x201C;To <placeName corresp="#FLORENCE">Florence</placeName> at <placeName corresp="#HASLEMERE">Haslemere</placeName>, with <persName corresp="#WBP">Blake&#x02BC;s</persName> &#x2018;Songs of Innocence,&#x2019;&#x201D; 
                    he invokes an essentialist view of <placeName corresp="#ENGLAND">English</placeName> childhood, again like the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi> reviewer&#x02BC;s, of imaginative experience shaded in green lanes:</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div type="poem">
                            <lg type="stanza">
                                <l>Accept, dear child, these songs of one whose Muse</l>
                                <l>For happy children piped her sweetest lays,</l>
                                <l>Nor deem&#x02BC;d their suffrages her lightest praise</l>
                                <l>Who hold Heaven&#x02BC;s kingdom as their proper dues.</l>
                                <l>And wilt thou with the lyric gift refuse</l>
                                <l>His thanks, whose drooping spirits thou couldst raise</l>
                                <l>By airy gestures, graceful as a fay&#x02BC;s</l>
                                <l>Dancing at eve in shady avenues?</l>
                                <l>With rapt delight I see you ponder long</l>
                                <l>The gentle words of one so pure of blame,</l>
                                <l>Who loved the right, who scorn&#x02BC;d and loathed the wrong</l>
                            </lg>
                            <p>(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SHEPHERDPOEMS">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">Translations from Charles Baudelaire, with a Few Original Poems</hi></ref>, 89)</p>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>Other poems by <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> on childhood concern children&#x02BC;s reading and writing; another presentation to <placeName corresp="#FLORENCE">Florence</placeName>, this time of <persName corresp="#CRK">Kingsley&#x02BC;s</persName> 
                    <hi rend="italic">Water Babies</hi>; and valentine poems. One poem, &#x201C;To <persName corresp="#WTW">W. T. Waite</persName>, with a Juvenile Poem,&#x201D; was apparently written to accompany one of <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> own juvenile poems, 
                    presented to the barrister who defended him in the trial contesting republication of the <persName corresp="#EBB">Barrett Browning</persName> juvenilia. The poem begins:</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div type="poem">
                            <lg type="stanza">
                                <l>Waite, while for loftier efforts I prepare,</l>
                                <l>Here with the first&#x2010;fruits unto thee I come,</l>
                                <l>And bring thee, chosen friend of childhood, some</l>
                                <l>Slight tribute to thy worth and goodness rare.</l>
                            </lg>
                            <p>(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SHEPHERDPOEMS">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">Translations from Charles Baudelaire, with a Few Original Poems</hi></ref>, 56)</p>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>Thus, <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> mildly presented himself as a modern author whose juvenilia merits regard. (Whether <persName corresp="#WTW">Waite&#x02BC;s</persName> status as a &#x201C;chosen friend of childhood&#x201D; refers to a shared boyhood with <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> himself, 
                    or to his championship of <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> as an editor of juvenilia, or both, is unknown.)<note>For <persName corresp="#WTW">Waite&#x02BC;s</persName> cross&#x2010;examination of <persName corresp="#RB">Robert Browning</persName> on behalf of <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> as plaintiff in &#x201C;Shepherd v. Francis,&#x201D; 
                        see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BROWNINGSTESTIMONY">Honan, &#x201C;Browning&#x02BC;s Testimony&#x201D;</ref>.</note></p>
                
                <p>Finally, the question most often raised about <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName>, when he is mentioned at all in literary history, is whether to see him as a drunk and opportunistic hack or as a pioneering professional 
                    of nineteenth&#x2010;century bibliography. The question is not very relevant to our concerns in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>, except to remark that the question, in how it is typically framed, misses a
                    point crucial to understanding the context for publishing eminent authors&#x02BC; juvenilia at the fin de si&#x00E8;cle&#x2014;namely, that the atmosphere in which editors and bibliographers like <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> worked was 
                    inherently ambiguous, the quality of the facsimile editions and &#x201C;reprints&#x201D; that they produced being disconcertingly staked on their close mimickry 
                    of the originals. <persName corresp="#WDP">W. D. Paden</persName> argues that <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> reputation fell victim to that very ambiguity, in that <persName corresp="#TJW">Thomas J. Wise</persName>, who most masterfully exploited the murkiness of the book trade of the era, 
                    strategically set up <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> as a fall guy for the <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName>/<persName corresp="#RBF">Forman</persName> forgeries should they come to require a decoy&#x2014;as <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> did eventually use the conveniently deceased <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName>, when need arose 
                    (<persName corresp="#WDP">Paden</persName>, &#x201C;<persName corresp="#ALT">Tennyson&#x02BC;s</persName> <hi rend="italic">The Lover&#x02BC;s Tale</hi>, <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName>, and <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName>,&#x201D; 144&#x2013;45). <persName corresp="#JC">Carter</persName> and <persName corresp="#MSS">Sadleir</persName> incorporated <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> into their narratives 
                    of how disinterested modern bibliography arose from the intellectually compromised collecting of the late&#x2010;nineteenth century: <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName>, not dishonorable in that development, as they see it, 
                    was an honest and industrious compiler of checklists 
                    (<persName corresp="#JC">Carter</persName>, Taste and Technique in Book&#x2010;Collecting, 23; 
                    <persName corresp="#MSS">Sadleir</persName>, &#x201C;Development of Bibliographical Study,&#x201D; 149).
                    Indeed, there is no evidence that <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> ever committed forgery; and works like his <hi rend="italic">Tennysoniana</hi>, while scarcely profound, 
                    present a serious effort at criticism, reaching beyond biographical platitudes to examine subject matter,
                    compare the poetic language of earlier and later works, point out patterns of revision, and research critical reception. At the same time, 
                    in his &#x201C;reprints&#x201D; he repeatedly and defiantly treaded close to piracy 
                    (see, e.g., <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#TENNYSONSHEPHERDWISE">Paden, &#x201C;Tennyson&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">The Lover&#x02BC;s Tale</hi>, Shepherd, and Wise,&#x201D; 112&#x2013;13, 119&#x2013;20</ref>).
                    <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd&#x02BC;s</persName> career in the <date notBefore="1860" notAfter="1869">1860s</date>&#x2013;<date notBefore="1880" notAfter="1889">80s</date> reflects the shifting combinations of opportunism, exacting scholarship, and sentiment 
                    that contextualized <persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> and <persName corresp="#GA">George Allen&#x02BC;s</persName> editing of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> juvenilia in the <date notBefore="1890" notAfter="1899">1890s</date>.</p>
                
                <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                        <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                        <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Body paragraph.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>