<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="boyhood_books_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Ruskin's Boyhood Books</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">Books Used by Ruskin in His Youth</head>
                <p>The aim of this note is not to attempt an exhaustive listing of books that Ruskin read or consulted in his youth. 
                    Information about Ruskin's reading and its influences is available throughout ERM, 
                    in the apparatuses and glosses of works that contain specific allusions to and borrowings from publications to which he was exposed. 
                    Especially influential authors and published sources, moreover, are discussed in notes of their own. 
                    This information can be accessed using the site's search engine.</p>
                
                <p>The purpose of the present note is, rather, to centralize <ref type="internal" target="#RESOURCES">Resources</ref> for researching the Ruskin family reading, 
                    by extending and enhancing existing research sources. Included are <ref type="internal" target="#ANNUALLISTS">Lists of Annual Book Purchases by the Ruskin Family</ref>, 
                    and <ref type="internal" target="#DESCRIPTIONS">Physical Descriptions of Some Books Used by Ruskin in Youth</ref>. 
                    These resources build on the enumerative bibliographies compiled by Van Akin Burd in The Ruskin Family Letters 
                    (i.e., lists of annual book purchases drawn from John James Ruskin's Account Book, RF MS 28, 1827&#x2013;45); 
                    and by James S. Dearden in The Library of John Ruskin. Those sources remain a starting point for all investigations of the Ruskin family reading. 
                    The resources are prefaced by some remarks, <ref type="internal" target="#RESEARCHING">On Researching Ruskin's Reading in His Youth</ref>.</p>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="RESEARCHING">
                    <head type="section">On Researching Ruskin's Reading in His Youth</head>
                    
                    <p>Regarding the Ruskin family's ownership or consultation of a given title at a given time, a measure of uncertainty will always be attached to 
                        documentable evidence of its presence in the family library--or for that matter, to the absence of such evidence. 
                        For example, the fact that John James purchased a book designed for youth does not necessarily mean it was intended for John; 
                        some purchases may have been intended as gifts for John's cousin, especially for 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_mary_note.php"><persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName> (1815&#x2013;49)</ref>, 
                        who lived with the Ruskin family from 1828 to her marriage in 1848. While James S. Dearden comments about the family library that 
                        "the books owned by all three Ruskins must be considered to be part of 'Ruskin's Library' because he ultimately inherited his parents' possessions, 
                        as well as having the use of them during their lifetimes", one wonders how far the availability, much less the inheritance, 
                        extended in the case of Mary's books. Dearden is right to conclude with the caveat that, 
                        "although Ruskin's lifetime's library was much greater than it was at any <hi rend="italic">one</hi> time, 
                        we do not know its total extent" (Library of John Ruskin, xv, xxiv). The most valuable evidence that ERM can contribute to the question of Ruskin's reading lies 
                        in the edited texts, which can reveal lexical traces of readings that may have left no material trace in the family record.</p>
                    
                    <p>As Dearden remarks, in adulthood Ruskin "was essentially . . . a book-buyer rather than a book borrower or library user" 
                        (Library of John Ruskin, xix), a habit that appears to have been inherited from his father, 
                        who was generous with books for his family's education and entertainment. Still, there is no way of knowing 
                        whether publications that left their influence in the early manuscripts were borrowed or owned, 
                        if otherwise unrecorded as part of the family library in the 1820s-30s. For example, 
                        Felicia Hemans was sufficiently admired for Ruskin to have transcribed her poem, The Sound of the Sea (1826) in MS IVB, 
                        probably based on the text as published in the New Monthly Magazine. He also adapted passages from Hemans's poem, 
                        The Restoration of the Works of Art to Italy, published by Murray in 1816, for use in his own poem, Saltzburg. 
                        Yet Mrs. Hemans is curiously absent from records of the Ruskins' book ownership, 
                        apart from poems included in literary annuals that the Ruskins are known to have owned. 
                        How other publications by Hemans passed through their hands will probably remain a mystery.</p>
                    
                    <p>Borrowing could have provided the means for Margaret Ruskin to control what books entered the house. 
                        She appears to refer to borrowing, for example, when she writes to Jahn James about the novel, 
                        The Fool of Quality (1766-72) by Henry Brooke (1703-83). Since she "did not like" the novel, 
                        she "got the first volume merely to read the History of the three little fishes to John". 
                        In this instance, Margaret's renewed encounter with the novel led to "the Almighty open[ing] the understanding", 
                        and she decided to "read it together" with John James. Perhaps only then was the full work acquired for the household, 
                        perhaps in the abridgement of the novel by John Wesley 
                        (Margaret to John James Ruskin, 15 May 1826, RFL 145; Dearden, The Library of John Ruskin, 51 [no. 336]; 
                        see Peace, "Sentimentality in the Service of Methodism").</p>
                    
                    <p>On travels, the Ruskins supplemented books they brought with them by tapping resources along the way; for example, 
                        during the tour of Switzerland in 1833, when John fell ill, his father and cousin Mary cheered him up by finding 
                        "some English books from a library" along with "2 or 3 volumes of Gagliani's Magazine"--that is, 
                        one of the periodicals issued by Librairie Galignani, the Paris-based English-language publisher, bookseller, and circulating library, 
                        which published two monthly journals, the <hi rend="italic">Repertory</hi> (ca. 1807-25), and 
                        <hi rend="italic">Galignani's Monthly Review and Magazine</hi> (ca. 1822-25), 
                        as well as a daily, the <hi rend="italic">Messenger</hi> (ca.1814-1904). 
                        Galignani also published a series, <hi rend="italic">Standard Modern Novels and Romances</hi>, 
                        which supplied English travelers and expatriates with contemporary British poetry and prose. 
                        The editions were issued in duodecimo, a size convenient for travel, but printed using excellent type and engravings, 
                        and edited for correct and complete text--in some cases, text more complete and reliable than what could be found in London editions. 
                        As piracies, the volumes were priced significantly cheaper than corresponding London editions, 
                        and sold in paper-covered boards--volumes that could be shared among travelers at a hotel and left behind for others' enjoyment. 
                        Ruskin did retain from boyhood one of Galignani's outstanding volumes in the series 
                        (possibly obtained from a London seller rather than from abroad)--<hi rend="italic">The Complete Poetical Works of Coleridge, Shelley, and Keats</hi> (1829), 
                        an edition that, at the time of publication, was superior to any British edition of Percy Shelley, 
                        and the only edition of Keats available in collected form 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48"><title type="transcript" corresp="#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson, 1833</title></ref>, 106; 
                        Barber, "Galignani's and the Publication of English Books in France", 269, 284, 272-74;
                        Dearden, The Library of John Ruskin, 76 [no. 556]).</p>
                    
                    <p>Besides the possibility that books were borrowed, another kind of caveat should be applied to Ruskin's retrospective accounts of his boyhood reading. 
                        The authors and titles he mentions in the opening chapters of Praeterta are not untrue to his early reading, 
                        but his account of how both loving and resisting certain books has charmed readers 
                        into fixating on a short list of titles that is potentially misleading. First, the list is highly selective--contrasting, 
                        for dramatic effect, the enforced Sunday reading of John Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress and Daniel Defoe's Robinson Crusoe 
                        with weekday "reading of my own election" of Walter Scott's novels and Homer (Alexander Pope's translation of the Iliad)--but 
                        the <ref type="internal" target="#DESCRIPTIONS">Physical Descriptions of Some Books Used by Ruskin in Youth</ref> shows how these 
                        classics were mixed with works, both secular and Sabbatarian, that now seem much more ephemeral. Second, Ruskin's retrospection 
                        flattenes these readings in time, suggesting that his study even of favored works was both simultaneous and compartmentalized. 
                        ERM along with the Ruskin Family Letters shows that the Ruskins, no less than other middle-class families, attempted to follow 
                        the program of graduated, age-appropriate reading for children as recommended by educationists like the Barbaulds and Edgeworths. 
                        Ruskin's writings in ERM also reflect his tendency, however, to buck the program, by reading texts above his years 
                        (e.g., Joyce's Scientific Dialogues, which he copied verbatim in "Harry and Lucy . . . Vol I", but which are too advanced for that context). 
                        Moreover, Ruskin and his mother shared weekday reading, in which the religious influences were likely more powerful and memorable to him 
                        (e.g., the White Lady as a protector of Protestanism in Walter Scott's The Monastery) than the Sunday sermons he attempted to copy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="RESOURCES">
                    <head type="section">Resources</head>
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="ANNUALLISTS">
                        <head type="subsection">Lists of Annual Book Purchases by the Ruskin Family</head>
                    
                    <p>In The Ruskin Family Letters, Van Akin Burd transcribes John James's brief notations of authors and/or titles that he 
                        purchased each month of every year, from 1827 through 1845, in his Account Book. In the ledger, 
                        book purchases are included among many other miscellaneous items on the pages devoted to "Sundries" for each year. 
                        Because John James notes the amounts spent, Burd is able in many cases to identify the authors/titles 
                        with specific editions available at the time from publishers at those prices. Burd's transcriptions and annotations are very reliable, 
                        but should nonetheless be revisited and compared against the manuscript of the Account Book, 
                        since John James's entries are sometimes ambiguous. Where appropriate, original entries in Account Book are referenced throughout ERM. 
                        Here, for convenience of reference, are listed the page numbers in Ruskin Family Letters of Burd's transcribed lists, 
                        along with the corresponding pages of "Sundries" in the Account Book. Here also are expansions and suggested corrections of Burd's lists.</p>
                        
                    <p>Burd omitted one year of sundry book purchases, those for 1830, from Ruskin Family Letters, 
                        presumably because no letters are extant from that year, thus giving no occasion for annotation. 
                        Dearden has incorporated the 1830 purchases into the alphabetized entries in The Library of John Ruskin; however, 
                        since John James's book lists organized chronologically by year form a helpful comparison 
                        with the discussions of dating works and manuscripts in ERM, the 1830 book list is compiled in its entirety, 
                        cross-referenced with entries in The Library of John Ruskin. This list and others from 1827-45 will be updated 
                        as new information comes to light. More speculatively, annual lists are also compiled 
                        for years prior to the start of John James's Account Book in 1827. These identifications are ongoing.</p>
                    
                    <p>Some names are transcribed from John James's "Sundries" that may or may not refer to books or authors. 
                        John James often listed names of vendors as shorthand for the wares they supplied, 
                        as well as naming recipients of gifts or purchases. In many cases, it is mere speculation whether a proper name 
                        refers to purchase of a book or of some other kind of item, and these names are flagged as "unidentified". 
                        Yet the occurence of some names can sometimes be aligned with other information to identify book titles and authors 
                        at least tentatively. Again, these identifications are ongoing.</p>
                    
                    <p><list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">Books purchased in 1827
                            <list>
                                <item>Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters [hereafter, RFL], 168 n. 1</item>
                                <item>John James Ruskin, Account Book (RF MS 28, 1827&#x2013;45) [hereafter, Account Book], 2r</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="2">Books purchased in 1828
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 188 n. 4</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 6r</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="3">Books purchased in 1829
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 187-88 n. 4</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 12r</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="4">Books purchased in 1830
                            <list>
                                <item>Account Book, 17r
                                    <list>
                                <item>January
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Jones 16/8 (unidentified)</item>
                                        <item>St. Pierre 10/ (possibly a work by Jacques-Henri Bernardin de Saint-Pierre; earliest purchase cited by Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, is a copy of Paul et Virginie, bought in 1840 [28, no. 194]</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>February
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Burrell 42/ (unidentified)</item>
                                        <item>Museums 10/ (unidentified)</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>April
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Newspaper &#x00A3;1.5/</item>
                                        <item>West 4/</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>May
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Horace 9/6 (edition unidentified)</item>
                                        <item>Cowpers &#x00A3;1./ (possibly William Cowper, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [1811], cited by Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 82 [no. 614], or another work by the poet)</item>
                                        <item>Greek 11/ (unidentified)</item>
                                        <item>Colours John 34/ (watercolors for John?)</item>
                                        <item>Every day Book 38/ (possibly William Hone [1780-1842], <hi rend="italic">The Every-day Book; or, the Guide to the Year</hi>, illustrated by George Cruikshank et al. [first published 1825, revised annually?])</item>
                                        <item>Rutter &#x00A3;8.7/. (unidentified)</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>June
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Newspaper &#x00A3;1.4/4</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>August
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Newspaper 22/9</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>December
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Tam O&#x02BC;Shanter 10/ (see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 58 [no. 399], which does not specify an edition; 
                                            possibly Robert Burns, <hi rend="italic">Tam O&#x02BC;Shanter, a Tale; to which are added Observations on the Statues of Tam O&#x02BC;Shanter and Souter Johnny, now Exhibiting . . .</hi> [London: John Murray, 1829], 
                                            compiled along with occasional poems to commemorate these sculptures by the self-taught Scottish stone carver, <persName corresp="#JTHOM">James Thom</persName> (1802-50), 
                                            whose statues toured Glasgow, Edinburgh, and London in 1829; see Gibson, Bibliography of Robert Burns, 147-48)</item>
                                        <item>Tales Grand 10/6 (an edition of Walter Scott, Tales of a Grandfather, of which the fourth series was published in December 1830; 
                                            see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 310 [no. 2435])</item>
                                        <item>Clark 10/6 (possibly John Clarke, An Introduction to the Making of Latin; see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 73 [no. 530])</item>
                                        <item>Latin Gr 30/ (possibly a Latin grammar or a Latin-Greek dictionary)</item>
                                        <item>Parnell 9/6 (Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, identifies as Sir Henry Parnell, On Financial Reform (p. 250 [no. 1957])</item>
                                        <item>Nat<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 15/ (possibly John Claudius Loudon, Magazine of Natural History)</item>
                                        <item>Greek Test<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> &#x00A3;2.2 (i.e., Greek Testament; see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 39 [no. 237])</item>
                                        <item>2 Anacreons 30/ (i.e., two editions of Anacreon; see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 11 [no. 55])</item>
                                        <item>Northcote 10/6 (possibly Hazlitt, Conversations with James Northcote RA, published at this price by Colburn in 1830; 
                                            see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 152 [no.1207], which does not connect a copy with this notation in the Account Book)</item> 
                                        <item>Loudon 21/ (possibly a work by John Claudius Loudon; see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 208, which does not connect any copies with this notation in the Account Book)</item>
                                        <item>Scott 12/ (possibly a work by Walter Scott; Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 306-11, connects no copies with this notation)</item>
                                    </list></item></list></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="5">Books purchased in 1831
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 229-30 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 19v-20r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="6">Books purchased in 1832
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 260 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 24v-25r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="7">Books purchased in 1833
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 286 n. 1</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 29v-30r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="8">Books purchased in 1834
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 286 n. 1</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 34v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="9">Books purchased in 1835
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 300-301 n. 12</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 39v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="10">Books purchased in 1836
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 393-94 n. 1</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 44v-45r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="11">Books purchased in 1837
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 413 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 49v-50r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="12">Books purchased in 1838
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 489-90 n. 8</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 54v-55r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="13">Books purchased in 1839
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 563-64 n. 7</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 59v-60r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="14">Books purchased in 1840
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 636 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 64v-65r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="15">Books purchased in 1841
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 685 n. 4</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 69v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="16">Books purchased in 1842
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 726 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 74v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="17">Books purchased in 1843
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 744-46 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 79v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="18">Books purchased in 1844
                            <list>
                                <item>Account Book, 85v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="19">Books purchased in 1845
                            <list>
                                <item>Account Book, 90v</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list></p>
                    </div>
                
                <div type="subsection" xml:id="DESCRIPTIONS">
                    <head type="subsection">Physical Descriptions of Some Books Used by Ruskin in Youth</head>
                
                <div type="sub-subsection">
                    <head type="sub-subsection">Books held by the Beinecke Library, Yale University</head>
                    <p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1" xml:id="FAIRYTALES"><title type="binding_slipcase" corresp="#FAIRYTALESSHARPCOLL">Fairy Tales</title> [title on binding; three separately published items bound together].
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Provenance:</hi> Sharp. Viljoen. Bookplate of John Ruskin, type 2 (Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, xcv-xcvi).</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Location:</hi> Beinecke Library, New Haven, Conn.; call no. 2000 1638.</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item xml:id="FAIRYTALESDISCUSSION"><hi rend="italic">Documentation and discussion:</hi> For the three items in the binding, see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 
                                    13 [no. 74], 19 [no. 115], 321 [no. 2527], respectively. 
                                    The responsibility for and circumstances of binding these three items as "Fairy Tales" are unknown. 
                                    This title on the spine applies most legitimately to the first of the items, Mother Bunch's Fairy Tales, 
                                    whereas the other two items belong only marginally, each containing just one or two stories that feature a fairy or fantastical events. 
                                    Regardless of the consistency of the collection, however, an implicit rationale becomes apparent by comparing the contents of another bound collection, 
                                    <ref type="internal" target="#WIDOWDISCUSSION"><title type="binding_slipcase" corresp="#WIDOWOFROSENEATHCOMP">[The Widow of Roseneath etc.]</title></ref>, 
                                    which appears to be a complementary volume.<lb/><lb/>
                                    
                                    Besides their contents, the three items in "Fairy Tales" also notably have in common their publication by J. Lumsden and Son of Glasgow. 
                                    Now highly regarded among collectors, Lumsden's children's books are distinguished by 
                                    "a certain trimness (primness one might almost call it) in the covers, the quality of the paper used, 
                                    the excellent type-face, the occasional use of coloured inks for text and illustrations, 
                                    usually bistre or sanguine, occasionally green, and a few hand-coloured illustrations". 
                                    In their own time, however, the books were apparently little known outside of Scotland; 
                                    and even in their own country, they were not widely popular, because their prices were considered 
                                    rather dear, even at two pence or six pence per copy--cheaper and less elegant chapbooks by this publisher 
                                    being more commonly found 
                                    (Roscoe and Brimmell, James Lumsden and Son of Glasgow, xi, xiii)
                                    <lb/><lb/>
                                    
                                    The Lumsden firm produced children's books ca. 1790-1850, but seldom printed dates on title pages 
                                    (Roscoe and Brimmell, James Lumsden and Son of Glasgow, xv). The three books bound together here are all undated. 
                                    Dearden, without explanation, dates them tentatively as 1814, presumably because that date is the lower limit 
                                    suggested by Roscoe and Brimmell in each of their analytical descriptions of of these books, as follows.
                                </item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item n="1"><title type="anthology" corresp="#MOTHERBUNCHSFAIRYTALES">Mother Bunch&#x02BC;s &#x007C; Fairy Tales. &#x007C; 
                                    Published for the &#x007C; Amusement &#x007C; of all those &#x007C; Little Masters and Misses &#x007C; who, &#x007C; 
                                    by Duty to their Parents, and Obedience &#x007C; to their Superiors, &#x007C; Aim at Becoming &#x007C; 
                                    Great Lords and Ladies.</title> &#x007C; Embellished with Engravings. &#x007C; Glasgow: &#x007C; Published by J. Lumsden and Son. &#x007C; 
                                    [Price Sixpence.]
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi> Most of the stories in this anthology originated in fairy tales by 
                                            Marie-Catherine Le Jumel de Barneville, Comtesse d&#x02BC;Aulnoy (ca. 1650-1705), written for the sophisticated Paris literary salons 
                                            in the age of Louis XIV. The texts translated into English from Countess d'Aulnoy's originals have a complex history. 
                                            Ruskin's copy matches the bibliographical description of an edition published ca. 1817 by the firm J. Lumsden and Son 
                                            (Roscoe and Brimmell, James Lumsden and Son of Glasgow, 68-69 [no. 102]; 
                                            see <ref type="internal" target="#FAIRYTALESDISCUSSION">Fairy Tales: Documentation and Discussion</ref>). 
                                            The Lumsden edition was a piracy and abridgement of an English edition 
                                            published in 1802 and 1817 by the London publisher of children's books, John Harris; 
                                            and the Harris editions were in turn based on editions (ca. 1773-99) published by the firm of John Newbery 
                                            (Blamires, "From Madame d&#x02BC;Aulnoy to Mother Bunch", 75; and see 
                                            Moon, John Harris's Books for Youth, 72 [nos. 470-71).<lb/><lb/>
                                            
                                            Newbery originated the title, Mother Bunch's Fairy Tales, and adapted an earlier English translation 
                                            (1721, reprinted frequently through 1817, and including tales by other French salon writers). 
                                            This early eighteenth-century English translation, according to David Blamires, 
                                            was faithful to the original, sophisticated French tales and intended for adult readers. 
                                            The Newbery edition and its descendents simplified the texts for child readers, 
                                            and reassigned the authorship from Madame d'Aulnoy to the fictitious Mother Bunch, 
                                            an English folklore figure whom children could imagine as a storyteller 
                                            similar to Mother Goose. Through these successive adaptations of the English texts 
                                            by Newbery, Harris, and Lumsden for an audience of middle-class children--as well as 
                                            through issues of individual tales in chapbook form for a working-class audience--the 
                                            French salon fairy tales came be regarded as English and traditional 
                                            (Blamires, "From Madame d&#x02BC;Aulnoy to Mother Bunch", 75-78).<lb/><lb/>
                                            
                                            In the subtitle, first applied by Newbery and carried through the adaptations by Harris and Lumsden, 
                                            the specification that the tales were meant to amuse "little masters and misses" signals that the tales 
                                            were meant for younger children. For Newbery in the eighteenth century, the purpose of such books was 
                                            to teach children basic reading, as compared with books designated for "young gentlemen and ladies", 
                                            which contained "lessons of life" (Townsend, "John Newbery and Tom Telescope", 82-83). 
                                        
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item n="2"><title type="anthology" corresp="#SOBERSIDESCHRISTMASTALES">Christmas &#x007C; Tales &#x007C; For the Instruction &#x007C; of &#x007C; 
                                    Good Boys and Girls,</title> &#x007C; by &#x007C; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Solomon Sobersides. &#x007C; Embellished with Engravings &#x007C; 
                                    Glasgow. &#x007C; Published by J. Lumsden &#x0026; Son. &#x007C; &#x0026; Sold by Stoddart &#x0026; Craggs. Hull &#x007C; Price Sixpence
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi> The copy is consistent with a bibliographical description in 
                                            Roscoe and Brimmell, James Lumsden and Son of Glasgow, 44 (no. 57), which cites a watermark date of 1814.<lb/><lb/>
                                            
                                            As pointed out in the "Introductory Essay" on the copy in the Hockliffe Archive, 
                                            the tales have no connection with Christmas, despite the anthology's title, which presumably was a marketing ploy 
                                            The text, which in some copies includes a description of the Seven Wonders of the World, 
                                            was apparently based on a collection first published in London, ca. 1780 
                                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SOBERSIDESCHRISTMASTALESHOCKLIFFE"><title type="archive" corresp="#SOBERSIDESCHRISTMASTALESHOCKLIFFE">&#x201C;Stories before 1850. 0220: Anon. [&#x2018;Solomon Sobersides&#x2019;], Christmas Tales&#x201D;</title></ref>).<lb/><lb/> 
                                            
                                            The first story in the collection opens with commentary on the neglect of religion and morality in childhood education, 
                                            but the stories in themselves do little to redress this supposed failing. The collection is miscellaneous, 
                                            some tales teaching prudent and moral conduct, some adopting an oriental flavor, and only a few entailing magic or fairies. 
                                            Two of the latter sort feature dervises (i.e., dervishes), who reward hospitality with magical riches, but retract the reward and punish 
                                            characters who overstep boundaries owing to greed or excess curiosity.<lb/><lb/>
                                            
                                            The frontispiece contains an emblem of a child choosing between folly and wisdom, 
                                            which may have contributed to Ruskin's own use of visual emblems, such as 
                                            <ref type="figure" target="heights_of_wisdom_drawing_msi.php">&#x201C;Heights of Wisdom, Depth of Fools&#x201D; [Miscellaneous Drawing, MS I]</ref>.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item n="3"><title type="anthology" corresp="#SELECTIONOFSTORIES">A &#x007C; Selection of Stories; &#x007C; containing the history &#x007C; of the &#x007C; Two Sisters, &#x007C; The Fisherman, &#x007C; 
                                    The King and Fairy Ring, &#x007C; and &#x007C; Honesty Rewarded.</title> &#x007C; Embellished with copperplates. &#x007C; Glasgow, &#x007C; 
                                    Published and sold by J. Lumsden &#x0026; Son. &#x007C; Price Sixpence.
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi> The copy is consistent with a bibliographical description in 
                                            Roscoe and Brimmell, James Lumsden and Son of Glasgow, 78-79 (no. 118), which cites watermarks of 1814 and 1816.<lb/><lb/>
                                            
                                            The collection consists of moral tales enjoining contentment with one's lot, prudence, and trust in God's providence. 
                                            (Roscoe and Brimmell remark that "The Two Sisters" is not the story of that title by Mrs. Sherwood.)
                                            Only "The King and Fairy Ring" qualifies as a fairy story.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="2" xml:id="WIDOW"><title type="binding_slipcase" corresp="#WIDOWOFROSENEATHCOMP">[The Widow of Roseneath etc.]</title> [description of binding to come; eight separately titled published items bound together].<!-- DCH TO REVISE-->
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Provenance:</hi> Sharp. Viljoen. Bookplate of John Ruskin, type 2 (Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, xcv-xcvi).</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Location: Beinecke Library, New Haven, Conn.; call no.:</hi> 2000 1641.</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item xml:id="WIDOWDISCUSSION"><hi rend="italic">Documentation and discussion:</hi> For the eight items in the binding, see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 
                                    respectively 14 [no. 77], 12 [no. 67], 13 [no, 70], 13 [no. 69], 227 [no. 1775], 345 [no. 2736], 315 [no 2475], 23 [no. 151]. 
                                    The responsibility for binding these items together is unknown. A rationale, if not the specific occasion for the collection 
                                    can be inferred, however, if the binding of these eight items was made in concert with the binding of <ref type="internal" target="#FAIRYTALESDISCUSSION">Fairy Tales</ref>. 
                                    As compared with the latter, the items collected here share an emphasis on "cautionary" tales (to draw on the subtitle of The Cowslip). 
                                    Since the early nineteenth century, such Romantic writers as Charles Lamb, S. T. Coleridge, and William Wordsworth 
                                    had polemically argued in favor of appealing to children's imagination with fairy tales as opposed to training their reason and morals 
                                    with "instructive" and "cautionary" tales and dialogues by the "cursed Barbauld Crew", as Lamb anathematized this group largely of women writers. 
                                    In our time, critics have exposed the politics underpinning these divisions, but in the late nineteenth or early twentieth century, 
                                    which was probably when a number of Ruskin's childhood books were divided between these two collections, the reputation of 
                                    Anna Laetitia Barbauld had been disassociated from her politics and reduced to bland high-mindedness--a "valuation" 
                                    of this writing that suggests, as William McCarthy complains, "that it entirely lacked humor, irony, or wit" 
                                    (McCarthy, &#x201C;&#x2018;A High&#x2010;Minded Christian Lady&#x2019;&#x201D;, 179; and see 
                                    Clarke, &#x201C;&#x2018;The Cursed Barbauld Crew&#x2019;&#x201D;, 91-93). 
                                    Such a valuation was perhaps implicitly placed on these eight items by binding them together.<lb/><lb/>
                                    
                                    The reductive valuation would not have been Ruskin's, but it seems unlikely that he could have been responsible for binding this collection 
                                    since, as noted in the following descritions, he annotated some of the items separately, 
                                    bequeathing them to Joan Severn and her children. One of the annotations is dated "1889", and another "1889-1890", 
                                    clues that the binding was ordered after 1890 by someone other than Ruskin--perhaps by Joan Severn--since by that time, 
                                    Ruskin himself would not have been in a mental state to take such an initiative.
                                    
                                    
                                </item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item n="1"><title type="book" corresp="#ANONWIDOWOFROSENEATH">The &#x007C; Widow of Roseneath; &#x007C; A &#x007C; Lesson of Piety: &#x007C; Affectionately &#x007C; 
                                    Dedicated to the Young.</title> &#x007C; Glasgow: &#x007C; Printed for Chalmers &#x0026; Collins; &#x007C; Waugh &#x0026; Innes, 
                                    W. Oliphant, and W. Whyte &#x0026; Co. Edinburgh; &#x007C; R. M. Tims, Dublin; &#x007C; J. Nisbet, W. Whittemore, 
                                    and F. Westley, London. &#x007C; 1822.&#x007C;
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi> The tale relates the fate of a Scottish widow who, reduced in circumstances by the death of her husband, 
                                            must part with her two sons. One son emigrates to America and prospers, and the other son resorts to crime. 
                                            As "A Lesson of Piety Affectionately Dedicated to the Young", the tale may well have been acquired 
                                            to help John contemplate the consequences of the death of his <!-- LINK to Richadson NOTES THROUGHOUT-->Uncle Patrick in Perth, Scotland, in 1824, 
                                            and its effect on his Aunt Jessie and his cousins.<lb/><lb/>
                                            
                                            The Ruskins regularly traveled to Perth, until John's Aunt Jessie died in 1828.
                                            By the time of her death, Jessie had lost six of her ten children, two of whom were especially dear as companions 
                                            to Ruskin in his childhood--James, who lived with the Ruskins at Herne Hill after his father's death, 
                                            and who himself died in 1826; and Jessie, who died in 1827. The four surviving children--three sons 
                                            and the daughter, Mary, who lived with the Ruskins until her marriage--were 
                                            generously supported by John James. Just so, in The Widow of Roseneath, the successful son is supported 
                                            in America by his uncle, a kindly and prudent merchant. The book might even have been shared between 
                                            John and his cousins living at Herne Hill who depended on John James's charity. 
                                            For a plot summary of the tale and brief commentary from an 1823 review, see 
                                            <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="widow_of_roseneath_note.php#WIDOW">Anonymous, <title type="book" corresp="#ANONWIDOWOFROSENEATH"><hi rend="italic">The Widow of Roseneath</hi> (1822)</title></ref>.<lb/><lb/>
                                            
                                            At a later time, Ruskin wrote on the frontispiece and title page: "New and Old mine my beloved Joanna and her children. SABRINA". 
                                            He refers to his cousin Joan Agnew Severn and her children. Sabrina was . . .
                                        
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            
                                <item n="2"><title type="book" corresp="#ANONHISTORYOFJOSIAHRUMBOLD">Sketches &#x007C; of &#x007C; the &#x007C; History &#x007C; of Mr &#x007C; Josiah Rumbold &#x007C; and &#x007C; 
                                    His Family.</title> &#x007C; Intended for the Benefit of &#x007C; Sabbath Evening School. &#x007C; Founded on Facts. &#x007C; 
                                    Second Edition. &#x007C; Edinburgh: &#x007C; Printed by William Aitchison, &#x007C; for A. Johnstone, Gran-Market; &#x007C; 
                                    and Sold by M. Ogle, Glasgow; and W. Whittimore, 62, &#x007C; Paternoster Row, London. &#x007C; 1820.</item>
                                
                                <item n="3"><title type="book" corresp="#ANONNICOLGRAY">Nicol Gray: &#x007C; or, &#x007C; Scenes in the Country. &#x007C; A Tale &#x007C; for the Cottar's Ingle Neuk.</title> &#x007C; 
                                    "Let not ambition mock their useful toil, &#x007C; Their homely joys and destiny obscure; &#x007C; Nor grandeur hear with a 
                                    disdainful smile, &#x007C; The short and simple annals of the poor." &#x007C; Edinburgh: &#x007C; Printed for Alexander Johnstone, &#x007C; 
                                    West Bow; &#x007C; Chalmers and Collins, and Lang, Glasgow; &#x007C;and Whittemore, London. &#x007C; 1823.
                                    <list>
                                        <item>The tale contains Scottish dialect. In periodicals, the work is found among listings of Sabbath School "reward books for young persons" by Waugh &#x02BC; Innes, 
                                            where attributed to the "author of 'Jacob Newman'". The author was also responsible for The Run-away; or, I Would Be a Sailor: A Narrative, 
                                            </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item n="4"><title type="book" corresp="#ANONMEMOIROFANOLDSOLDIER">Memoir &#x007C; of &#x007C; An Old Soldier.</title> &#x007C; Written &#x007C; for the Instruction of Youth. &#x007C; 
                                    Edinburgh: &#x007C; Printed for Alexander Johnstone, &#x007C; West Bow; &#x007C; Ogle, Chalmers and Collins, and Lang, &#x007C; 
                                    Glasgow; and Whittemore, London. &#x007C; 1823.</item>
                                <item n="5"><title type="book" corresp="BURNSACTIVEGOODNESS">Active Goodness &#x007C; Beautifully Exemplified, &#x007C; in the &#x007C; 
                                    Life and Labours &#x007C; of the &#x007C;&#x007C; Rev. Thomas Gouge, A.M.</title> &#x007C; By a Minister of the Church of Scotland. 
                                    &#x007C; Glasgow: &#x007C; Printed for Chalmers &#x0026; Collins; &#x007C; 
                                    Waugh &#x0026; Innes, William Oliphant, and W. Whyte &#x0026; Co. &#x007C; 
                                    Edinburgh; &#x007C; R. M. Tims, Dublin; &#x007C; J. Nisbet, W. Whittemore, J. Offer, and F. Westley, London. &#x007C; 1822.
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi> The author is identified as the Rev. Robert Burns (1789-1869), Minister of St. George's, Paisley, 
                                            in the second edition (1825), and in <persName corresp="#RFBURNS">Burns</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#BURNSLIFEANDTIMES">Life and Times of the Rev. Robert Burns by the Rev. R. F. Burns</title>, 120. 
                                            Thomas Gouge (1605-81) was an English clergyman who, although ejected from his living for nonconformist sympathies, 
                                            continued to preach and was revered for his "active goodness"--his extensive good works of practical Christianity. 
                                            His collected works were published in Kilmarnock in 1815.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item n="6">The &#x007C; Cowslip; &#x007C; or, &#x007C; More Cautionary Stories, &#x007C; in Verse. &#x007C; by the Author of that Much-Admired &#x007C; 
                                    Little Work Entitled &#x007C; the Daisy. &#x007C; the Seventh Edition. &#x007C; London: &#x007C; Printed for J. Harris and Son, &#x007C; 
                                    Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard; and Baldwin, Cradock, and Joy, &#x007C; Paternoster-Row. &#x007C; 1820.
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi> The author is Elizabeth Turner (1775-1846); Ruskin's copy matches the bibliographical description in 
                                            Moon, John Harris's Books for Youth, 129 (no. 932 [7]). 
                                            The "more cautionary stories" constituting The Cowslip were first published by Harris in 1811, following the 
                                            "cautionary stories in verse adapted to the ideas of children from four to eight years old" constituting 
                                            The Daisy, first published in 1807. The Daisy was originally "illustrated with thirty engravings on copper-plate", 
                                            but The Cowslip was illustrated with thirty woodcuts, which formed headpieces to the poems 
                                            (Moon, John Harris's Books for Youth, 129 [nos. 933 (1), 932 (1)]).<lb/><lb/>
                                            
                                            In Ruskin's copy, the signature was written by his father, as Ruskin notes in a later hand, perhaps because he was too young to have 
                                            signed the copy for himself when first presented with the book. The primitiveness of drawings scattered throughout the book 
                                            suggest a very early age. In a later hand, it appears that Ruskin re-dedicated the book to "My Joanna, and her children" on "New Years Day. 1889". 
                                            Later, he wrote "Deeper and deeper still. / 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> April 1889-1890"; also a date, "<hi rend="underline">1822</hi>" underlined, 
                                            and the comment, "<hi rend="underline">Now</hi> in Heaven".
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item n="7">A &#x007C; Drive in the Coach &#x007C; through the &#x007C; Streets of London. &#x007C; 
                                    A Story founded on Fact. &#x007C; By Mrs. Sherwood, &#x007C; Author of "Little Henry and his Bearer," &#x0026;c. &#x0026;c. &#x007C; &#x007C; 
                                    Seventh Edition. &#x007C; Wellington, <placeName corresp="#SHROPSHIRE">Salop</placeName>: &#x007C; printed by and for F. Houlston and Son. &#x007C; 
                                    And sold by &#x007C; Scatcherd and Letterman, Ave-Maria Lane, London. &#x007C; 1822. &#x007C; [Entered at Stationer's Hall.]
                                    <list>
                                        <item>During a drive through London with her mother, a "self-pleasing" girl is allowed to write down what she would like to buy 
                                            at each shop they pass. When they encounter a coffin-maker's establishment, representing the end of all worldly pleasures, 
                                            the girl of course balks at adding that item to her list. Her mother instead buys the girl a bible, 
                                            so she can learn to contemplate death without fear.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item n="8">Hymns in Prose &#x007C; for &#x007C; Children. &#x007C; by the Author of &#x007C; Lessons for Children. &#x007C; 
                                    Twenty-Second Edition, &#x007C; Much Enlarged. &#x007C; I will praise God with my voice, though I am &#x007C; but a little child. &#x007C; 
                                    London: &#x007C; Printed for Baldwin, Cradock, and Joy, &#x007C; Paternoster-Row; &#x007C; and R. Hunter, Successor to J. Johnson, &#x007C; 
                                    St Paul's Church-Yard. &#x007C; 1821.
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    </p>
                <!--
                <p>John Aiken and Anna Laetitia Barbauld, <hi rend="italic">Evenings at Home</hi></p>
                <p>A copy with a Brantwood bookplate now at the Beinecke Library, Yale University,
                    New Haven, Conn., may survive from Ruskin boyhood: <hi rend="italic">Evenings at Home; / or the /
                        Juvenile Budget Opened. / consisting of / a Variety of Miscellaneous Pieces /
                        for the / Instruction and Amusement / of / Young Persons / by Dr. Aiken and Mrs.
                        Barbauld / London / Printed and Published by J. F. Dove, / St. John Square.</hi></p>
                <p>The copy contains marginalia in Ruskin&#x02BC;s mature hand, especially the
                    pages containing the twenty&#x2010;first evening, which is connected with mineralogy
                    (Viljoen, Ruskin&#x02BC;s Backgrounds 8). Scrawls on the front endpaper may
                    be Ruskin&#x02BC;s from childhood: one of these scrawls Helen Gill Viljoen
                    read as a &#x201C;J&#x201D;, and she declared this to be Ruskin&#x02BC;s earliest extant
                    signature (where does she say so? not in Backgrounds where she assigns earliest
                    signature to Frank&#x2014;maybe she thought better of it Correction needed here?).</p>
                <p>See Anna Laetitia Barbauld, and, in connection with her
                    influence, &#x201C;The Needless Alarm&#x201D;: Discusssion.</p>
                <p>Maria Edgeworth, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy Concluded&#x201D;; although owned by Ruskin, may or may
                    not have been his boyhood copy.</p>
                <p>Maria Edgeworth, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy Concluded&#x201D; (Ruskin&#x02BC;s copy)</p>
                <p> A copy owned by Ruskin with a Brantwood bookplate was acquired by Sharp
                    (Viljoen, Ruskin&#x02BC; Backgrounds, 7). Sharp gave his collection to Helen Gill
                    Viljoen, who in turn, in dividing her collection between libraries, gave the
                    Ruskin books in her possession to the Beinecke Library, Yale
                    University, New Haven, Conn., where this copy of &#x201C;Harry and Lucy Concluded&#x201D;
                    remains.</p>
                <p>The copy is a first (1825) edition Entry needed here.</p>
                <p>It is unclear whether this copy is the one that Ruskin used in childhood. The
                    binding is tight and the pages clean, as compared with Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    boyhood copy of Edgeworth, Frank, which Entry needed here and which contains marginalia in
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s boyhood as well as mature hands. All Correction needed here? the marginalia in
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s &#x201C;Harry and Lucy Concluded&#x201D; is in Ruskin&#x02BC;s mature
                    hand; however, a crude geometrical drawing on the back endpaper of volume 4 may
                    date from boyhood Correction needed here?.</p>
                <p>Maria Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi> (Ruskin&#x02BC;s copy)</p>
                <p>A copy owned by Ruskin with a Brantwood bookplate was acquired by Sharp (Viljoen,
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s Backgrounds, 6). Sharp gave his collection to Helen Gill Viljoen, who in
                    turn, in dividing her collection between libraries, gave the Ruskin
                    books in her possession to the Beinecke Library, Yale University, New Haven,
                    Conn., where this copy of <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi> remains.</p>
                <p>The copy is a first (1822) edition in three volumes Entry needed here.</p>
                <p>The volumes, which have had heavy use Entry needed here, contain marginalia in the hand
                    of one of his parents and in Ruskin&#x02BC;s&#x2014;both his boyhood
                    and mature hands. The first volume has an inscription, &#x201C;John
                    Ruskin,&#x201D; on the first flyleaf (recto), which Viljoen identifies as
                    the hand of John James Ruskin; then, on a blank page which follows [i.e., the
                    second flyleaf, recto], [is] Ruskin&#x02BC;s earliest known signature Correction needed here?, a
                    pencilled one Ruskin apparently copied, in a most childish scrawl, from the name
                    as written in ink by his Father (ibid.). Entry needed here
                    Whether this is indeed Ruskin earliest extant signature cannot be determined,
                    but the cursive script, which Ruskin did not generally adopt before Entry needed here, is
                    indeed very labored.</p>
                <p>The endpapers (Entry needed here) of volume 1 also contain Frank drawing, untitled no. 1,
                    and Frank drawing, untitled no. 2.</p>
                <p>Daniel Defoe, <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi>, allegedly a two&#x2013;volume 1812 edition of
                    <hi rend="italic">The Life and Surprising Adventures of Robinson Crusoe</hi> (Ruskin Family Letters 150
                    n. 4).</p>
                <p>Genlis RFL 168</p>
                <p>Colley's point that Foxe and Bunyan "went through a new and much wider period of fame and [were] interpreted in a far more aggressively patriotic fashion in the eighteenth century and after" (p. 25)</p>-->
                </div>
                
                <div type="sub-subsection">
                    <head type="sub-subsection">Untraced Books</head>
                    <p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">Children in the Wood; Sinbad the Sailor: In 1823, to mollify John during an illness, Margaret Ruskin 
                            was "obliged to buy I don't know how many books". Worried that John James might duplicate a purchase, 
                            she recommended he bring home these traditional tales (Margaret to John James Ruskin, 11 March 1823, RFL 126-27 and see 127l no. 1).
                        </item>
                        <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                        <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                    </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>