<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="boyhood_books_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Ruskin's Boyhood Books</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">Books Used by Ruskin in His Youth</head>
                <p>The aim of this note is not to attempt an exhaustive listing of books that Ruskin read or consulted in his youth. 
                    Throughout ERM, information about the influences of Ruskin's reading is available 
                    in the apparatuses and glosses of works that contain specific allusions to and borrowings from publications to which he was exposed. 
                    Moreover, especially influential authors and published sources are discussed in notes of their own. 
                    This information may be searched by keyword, and relevant biographical and contextual notes are also linked below. 
                    The purpose of the present note, rather, is to centralize various information nowhere else referenced in the archive, 
                    particularly information about material features and marginalia of books that survive 
                    allegedly from the Ruskin family library. (Provenance is not certain in all cases.) Such features are too detailed to have been included 
                    in the enumerative bibliographies compiled by Van Akin Burd (i.e., his transcriptions in Ruskin Family Letters of annual book purchases noted in 
                    John James Ruskin's Account Book, RF MS 28, 1827&#x2013;45); 
                    and by James S. Dearden (The Library of John Ruskin). Those sources remain a starting point for all investigations of the Ruskin family reading.</p>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Researching Ruskin's Reading</head>
                    
                    <p>Regarding the Ruskin family's ownership or consultation of a given title at a given time, of course only so much can be inferred from 
                        documentable evidence of its presence in the family library--or for that matter, from the absence of such evidence. 
                        For example, some of John James's purchases of books designed for youths may have been meant less for John than for his cousin, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_mary_note.php"><persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName> (1815&#x2013;49)</ref>, 
                        who lived with the Ruskin family from 1828 to her marriage in 1848. While Dearden comments about the family library, 
                        "the books owned by all three Ruskins must be considered to be part of 'Ruskin's Library' because he ultimately inherited his parents' possessions, 
                        as well as having the use of them during their lifetimes", that availability for use, much less the inheritance, 
                        may or may not have included Mary Richardson's books. Dearden is right to conclude with a caveat that, 
                        "although Ruskin's lifetime's library was much greater than it was at any <hi rend="italic">one</hi> time, 
                        we do not know its total extent" (Library of John Ruskin, xv, xxiv). ERM is occasionally able to extend the known scope of the Ruskin library, or at least the Ruskins' known acquaintance with certain books, 
                        by pointing to the probable influence of publications that may otherwise have left no material trace in the family record.</p>
                    
                    <p>Dearden's view is well taken, too, that in adulthood Ruskin "was essentially . . . a book-buyer rather than a book borrower or library user" 
                        (Library of John Ruskin, xix). Ruskin seems to have inherited this habit from his father, 
                        who was generous with books for his family's education and entertainment. The possibility of borrowing cannot be dismissed, however. 
                        On travels, the Ruskins supplemented books they brought with them by tapping resources along the way, 
                        such as the tour of Switzerland in 1833, when John James and Mary Richardson cheered up John, who had taken ill, 
                        by finding him "some English books from a library" along with "2 or 3 volumes of Gagliani's Magazine" 
                        (i.e., probably one of the periodicals issued by Librairie Galignani, 
                        the Paris-based English-language publisher, bookseller, and circulating library, which published a monthly, 
                        the Repertory of English Literature [begun 1808], and a daily, Gaglinani's Messenger [begun 1814])
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48"><title type="transcript" corresp="#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson, 1833</title></ref>, 106). 
                        At home, Margaret Ruskin was watchful over what books entered the house, particularly during John's youth, 
                        and it is possible that borrowing formed part of her scheme for surveillance. For example, she appears to refer to borrowing 
                        when she writes to Jahn James about the novel, The Fool of Quality (1766-72) by Henry Brooke (1703-83): 
                        she "got the first volume merely to read the History of the three little fishes to John", since she otherwise "did not like" the book 
                        (Margaret to John James Ruskin, 15 May 1826, RFL 145). (In this case, "the Almighty open[ed] the understanding" in her renewed encounter with the novel, 
                        committing her to "read it together" with John James, perhaps in John Wesley's abridgement of the novel.)</p>
                    <p>For books that can be detected through lexical traces in the early manuscripts, but that are otherwise unrecorded as part of the physical Ruskin family library, 
                        it is of course impossible to know whether such a volume was owned or borrowed. An example is Felicia Hemans's 
                        ...., which, because of the portion of the text incorporated into Ruskin's poem, Saltzburg, 
                        must have originated in the revised edition of Hemans's poem published by .... 
                        (see "Saltzburg").
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>A caveat should also be applied to Ruskin's own account of his boyhood reading in Praeterita. 
                        While the authors and titles he identifies are not untrue to his early reading, his account of reading that was both beloved and resisted has charmed readers 
                        into fixating on a short list of titles that is potentially misleading. The selectiveness 
                        of the list--for example, the specific contrast of enforced Sunday reading of John Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress and Daniel Defoe's Robinson Crusoe 
                        with weekday "reading of my own election" of Walter Scott's novels and Homer (Alexander Pope's translation of the Iliad)--is 
                        well calculated to establish the autobiography's gently comic, ironic tone, but also lends a retrospective aura to these books. 
                        The problem is not just that, for the sake of irony, Ruskin is highly selective in the books he treats as influential; 
                        the foreshortening of the narrative also gives the impression that Ruskin's study of these books was both simultaneous and compartmentalized. 
                        While it is true that Sabbatarianism had the effect of compartmentalizing family reading, an effect of random simultaneity 
                        in the consumption of books was controlled to an extent by educationists like the Barbaulds and Edgeworths, 
                        who persuaded countless early Victorian parents to follow a graduated program of age-appropriate reading for their children. 
                        But even given these broad cultural influences over programs of childhood reading, one must still take account of Ruskin's 
                        sometimes eccentric and resistant response to the program. The early manuscripts and the family letters reveal that he did not always restrict himself 
                        to age-appropriate reading (Joyce's Scientific Dialogues, which he copied verbatim in Harry and Lucy, Vol. 1, 
                        was far beyond his seven years); and religious influence was as powerful in some weekday reading 
                        (Walter Scott's The Monastery), while Sunday services led by Ruskin's tutor, the Reverend Edward Andrews, 
                        were far from devoid of sophisticated secular culture.</p>
                    
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Resources</head>
                    
                    <p>In Library of John Ruskin, Dearden helpfully annotates his entries with provenance and other information; 
                        and in Ruskin Family Letters, Burd connects John James's brief notations of authors/titles and amounts spent 
                        with editions that were available at the time from publishers at those prices. Burd's transcriptions should nonetheless 
                        be compared against the manuscript of the Account Book, since John James's entries are sometimes ambiguous, 
                        warranting additional scrutiny. Where appropriate, the Account Book is referenced throughout ERM. 
                        Here below, for convenience of reference, are listed the page numbers of Burd's transcriptions of book lists, 
                        along with the corresponding pages of John James's lists of "Sundries" in the Account Book, 
                        which is how he caregorized books along with other non-perishable household items, subdivided by month (and often even days) of purchase.</p>
                    
                    <p>In addition to page numbers, this list also gathers information that has escaped attention elsewhere. 
                        One year of sundry book purchases, those for 1830, was omitted by Burd in Ruskin Family Letters, 
                        presumably because no letters are extant from that year, thus giving no occasion for annotation. 
                        Dearden has incorporated the 1830 purchases into the alphabetized entries in The Library of John Ruskin, 
                        but since book lists organized chronologically by year, as in Ruskin Family Letters, can form a helpful comparison 
                        with the discussions of dating works and manuscripts in ERM, John James's 1830 book list is compiled in its entirety, 
                        cross-referenced with entries in Dearden. For this and other years, if new information comes to light about John James's 
                        book listings in "Sundries", it is folded into the list. These identifications are ongoing.</p>
                        
                        <p>Some names are transcribed below from John James's "Sundries" that may or may not refer to books or authors. 
                            John James often listed names of vendors as shorthand for the wares they supplied, 
                            as well as naming recipients of gifts or purchases; in many of these cases, it is mere speculation whether a name 
                            refers to purchase of a book or of some other kind of item. Yet the occurence of some names can sometimes be aligned with other information 
                            to identify at least tentatively book titles and authors otherwise associated with the early Ruskin family library. 
                            These names are noted as "unidentified" along with salient information. Again, these identifications are ongoing.</p>
                    
                    <p><list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">Books purchased in 1827
                            <list>
                                <item>Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters [hereafter, RFL], 168 n. 1</item>
                                <item>John James Ruskin, Account Book (RF MS 28, 1827&#x2013;45) [hereafter, Account Book], 2r</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="2">Books purchased in 1828
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 188 n. 4</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 6r</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="3">Books purchased in 1829
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 187-88 n. 4</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 12r</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="4">Books purchased in 1830
                            <list>
                                <item>Account Book, 17r
                                    <list>
                                <item>January
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Jones 16/8 (unidentified)</item>
                                        <item>St. Pierre 10/ (possibly a work by Jacques-Henri Bernardin de Saint-Pierre; earliest purchase cited by Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, is a copy of Paul et Virginie, bought in 1840 [28, no. 194]</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>February
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Burrell 42/ (unidentified)</item>
                                        <item>Museums 10/ (unidentified)</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>April
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Newspaper &#x00A3;1.5/</item>
                                        <item>West 4/</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>May
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Horace 9/6 (edition unidentified)</item>
                                        <item>Cowpers &#x00A3;1./ (possibly William Cowper, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [1811], cited by Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 82 [no. 614], or another work by the poet)</item>
                                        <item>Greek 11/ (unidentified)</item>
                                        <item>Colours John 34/ (watercolors for John?)</item>
                                        <item>Every day Book 38/ (possibly William Hone [1780-1842], <hi rend="italic">The Every-day Book; or, the Guide to the Year</hi>, illustrated by George Cruikshank et al. [first published 1825, revised annually?])</item>
                                        <item>Rutter &#x00A3;8.7/. (unidentified)</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>June
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Newspaper &#x00A3;1.4/4</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>August
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Newspaper 22/9</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>December
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Tam O&#x02BC;Shanter 10/ (see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 58 [no. 399], which does not specify an edition; 
                                            possibly Robert Burns, <hi rend="italic">Tam O&#x02BC;Shanter, a Tale; to which are added Observations on the Statues of Tam O&#x02BC;Shanter and Souter Johnny, now Exhibiting . . .</hi> [London: John Murray, 1829], 
                                            compiled along with occasional poems to commemorate these sculptures by the self-taught Scottish stone carver, <persName corresp="#JTHOM">James Thom</persName> (1802-50), 
                                            whose statues toured Glasgow, Edinburgh, and London in 1829; see Gibson, Bibliography of Robert Burns, 147-48)</item>
                                        <item>Tales Grand 10/6 (an edition of Walter Scott, Tales of a Grandfather, of which the fourth series was published in December 1830; 
                                            see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 310 [no. 2435])</item>
                                        <item>Clark 10/6 (possibly John Clarke, An Introduction to the Making of Latin; see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 73 [no. 530])</item>
                                        <item>Latin Gr 30/ (possibly a Latin grammar or a Latin-Greek dictionary)</item>
                                        <item>Parnell 9/6 (Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, identifies as Sir Henry Parnell, On Financial Reform (p. 250 [no. 1957])</item>
                                        <item>Nat<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 15/ (possibly John Claudius Loudon, Magazine of Natural History)</item>
                                        <item>Greek Test<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> &#x00A3;2.2 (i.e., Greek Testament; see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 39 [no. 237])</item>
                                        <item>2 Anacreons 30/ (i.e., two editions of Anacreon; see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 11 [no. 55])</item>
                                        <item>Northcote 10/6 (possibly Hazlitt, Conversations with James Northcote RA, published at this price by Colburn in 1830; 
                                            see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 152 [no.1207], which does not connect a copy with this notation in the Account Book)</item> 
                                        <item>Loudon 21/ (possibly a work by John Claudius Loudon; see Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 208, which does not connect any copies with this notation in the Account Book)</item>
                                        <item>Scott 12/ (possibly a work by Walter Scott; Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 306-11, connects no copies with this notation)</item>
                                    </list></item></list></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="5">Books purchased in 1831
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 229-30 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 19v-20r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item n="6">Books purchased in 1832
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 260 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 24v-25r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="7">Books purchased in 1833
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 286 n. 1</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 29v-30r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="8">Books purchased in 1834
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 286 n. 1</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 34v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="9">Books purchased in 1835
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 300-301 n. 12</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 39v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="10">Books purchased in 1836
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 393-94 n. 1</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 44v-45r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="11">Books purchased in 1837
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 413 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 49v-50r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="12">Books purchased in 1838
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 489-90 n. 8</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 54v-55r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="13">Books purchased in 1839
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 563-64 n. 7</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 59v-60r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="14">Books purchased in 1840
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 636 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 64v-65r</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="15">Books purchased in 1841
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 685 n. 4</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 69v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="16">Books purchased in 1842
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 726 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 74v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="17">Books purchased in 1843
                            <list>
                                <item>RFL, 744-46 n. 2</item>
                                <item>Account Book, 79v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="18">Books purchased in 1844
                            <list>
                                <item>Account Book, 85v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                        <item n="19">Books purchased in 1845
                            <list>
                                <item>Account Book, 90v</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item></item>
                    </list></p>
                </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Physical Descriptions of Some Books Used by Ruskin in Youth</head>
                
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head type="subsection">Books held by the Beinecke Library, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.</head>
                    <p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1"><title type="composite" corresp="#FAIRYTALESSHARPCOLL">Fairy Tales</title> (title on binding).
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Provenance:</hi> Sharp. Bookplate of John Ruskin.</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Beinecke call no.:</hi> 2000 1638</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Documentation:</hi> xxx</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <item>Three separately published items bound together
                                    <list>
                                        <item><title type="book" corresp="#MOTHERBUNCHSFAIRYTALES"><hi rend="italic">Mother Bunch's Fairy Tales</hi></title></item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        
                        
                        
                    </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <!--
                <p>John Aiken and Anna Laetitia Barbauld, <hi rend="italic">Evenings at Home</hi></p>
                <p>A copy with a Brantwood bookplate now at the Beinecke Library, Yale University,
                    New Haven, Conn., may survive from Ruskin boyhood: <hi rend="italic">Evenings at Home; / or the /
                        Juvenile Budget Opened. / consisting of / a Variety of Miscellaneous Pieces /
                        for the / Instruction and Amusement / of / Young Persons / by Dr. Aiken and Mrs.
                        Barbauld / London / Printed and Published by J. F. Dove, / St. John Square.</hi></p>
                <p>The copy contains marginalia in Ruskin&#x02BC;s mature hand, especially the
                    pages containing the twenty&#x2010;first evening, which is connected with mineralogy
                    (Viljoen, Ruskin&#x02BC;s Backgrounds 8). Scrawls on the front endpaper may
                    be Ruskin&#x02BC;s from childhood: one of these scrawls Helen Gill Viljoen
                    read as a &#x201C;J&#x201D;, and she declared this to be Ruskin&#x02BC;s earliest extant
                    signature (where does she say so? not in Backgrounds where she assigns earliest
                    signature to Frank&#x2014;maybe she thought better of it Correction needed here?).</p>
                <p>See Anna Laetitia Barbauld, and, in connection with her
                    influence, &#x201C;The Needless Alarm&#x201D;: Discusssion.</p>
                <p>Maria Edgeworth, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy Concluded&#x201D;; although owned by Ruskin, may or may
                    not have been his boyhood copy.</p>
                <p>Maria Edgeworth, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy Concluded&#x201D; (Ruskin&#x02BC;s copy)</p>
                <p> A copy owned by Ruskin with a Brantwood bookplate was acquired by Sharp
                    (Viljoen, Ruskin&#x02BC; Backgrounds, 7). Sharp gave his collection to Helen Gill
                    Viljoen, who in turn, in dividing her collection between libraries, gave the
                    Ruskin books in her possession to the Beinecke Library, Yale
                    University, New Haven, Conn., where this copy of &#x201C;Harry and Lucy Concluded&#x201D;
                    remains.</p>
                <p>The copy is a first (1825) edition Entry needed here.</p>
                <p>It is unclear whether this copy is the one that Ruskin used in childhood. The
                    binding is tight and the pages clean, as compared with Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    boyhood copy of Edgeworth, Frank, which Entry needed here and which contains marginalia in
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s boyhood as well as mature hands. All Correction needed here? the marginalia in
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s &#x201C;Harry and Lucy Concluded&#x201D; is in Ruskin&#x02BC;s mature
                    hand; however, a crude geometrical drawing on the back endpaper of volume 4 may
                    date from boyhood Correction needed here?.</p>
                <p>Maria Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi> (Ruskin&#x02BC;s copy)</p>
                <p>A copy owned by Ruskin with a Brantwood bookplate was acquired by Sharp (Viljoen,
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s Backgrounds, 6). Sharp gave his collection to Helen Gill Viljoen, who in
                    turn, in dividing her collection between libraries, gave the Ruskin
                    books in her possession to the Beinecke Library, Yale University, New Haven,
                    Conn., where this copy of <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi> remains.</p>
                <p>The copy is a first (1822) edition in three volumes Entry needed here.</p>
                <p>The volumes, which have had heavy use Entry needed here, contain marginalia in the hand
                    of one of his parents and in Ruskin&#x02BC;s&#x2014;both his boyhood
                    and mature hands. The first volume has an inscription, &#x201C;John
                    Ruskin,&#x201D; on the first flyleaf (recto), which Viljoen identifies as
                    the hand of John James Ruskin; then, on a blank page which follows [i.e., the
                    second flyleaf, recto], [is] Ruskin&#x02BC;s earliest known signature Correction needed here?, a
                    pencilled one Ruskin apparently copied, in a most childish scrawl, from the name
                    as written in ink by his Father (ibid.). Entry needed here
                    Whether this is indeed Ruskin earliest extant signature cannot be determined,
                    but the cursive script, which Ruskin did not generally adopt before Entry needed here, is
                    indeed very labored.</p>
                <p>The endpapers (Entry needed here) of volume 1 also contain Frank drawing, untitled no. 1,
                    and Frank drawing, untitled no. 2.</p>
                <p>Daniel Defoe, <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi>, allegedly a two&#x2013;volume 1812 edition of
                    <hi rend="italic">The Life and Surprising Adventures of Robinson Crusoe</hi> (Ruskin Family Letters 150
                    n. 4).</p>
                <p>Genlis RFL 168</p>
                <p>Colley's point that Foxe and Bunyan "went through a new and much wider period of fame and [were] interpreted in a far more aggressively patriotic fashion in the eighteenth century and after" (p. 25)</p>-->
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Untraced Books</head>
                    <p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">Children in the Wood; Sinbad the Sailor: In 1823, to mollify John during an illness, Margaret Ruskin 
                            was "obliged to buy I don't know how many books". Worried that John James might duplicate a purchase, 
                            she recommended he bring home these traditional tales (Margaret to John James Ruskin, 11 March 1823, RFL 126-27 and see 127l no. 1).
                        </item>
                        <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                        <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                    </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>