<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="evangelical_magazine_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Evangelical Magazine</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#IB">Isabella Bairnsfather</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text><!-- 1. root element, the beginning of a  nested structures: text, body, and div -->
        <!-- 2. In an XML document, there can be only one root element. A "well-formed" XML document is one that observes 
            this basic grammar common to all XML documents. In a TEI XML document, that single root is almost always <text>.
            
            An XML document that begins with <text> is thus said to be "valid" according to the particular set of elements 
            and rules established by the Text Encoding Initiative consortium, a TEI-XML document.
            
        The set of elements and their hierarchy is established in your XML editor by a schema, which instructs your editor to operate by the
        -->
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="bibliographical">
                <!-- 3. Build a nested structure: element: head; element: title; attribute: periodical -->
           <head type="title">The Evangelical Magazine</head>              
             <div n="1">
                <head type="section">The Ruskins' and Evangelical Magazine</head>
                <p>In a letter of 3 March 1823 to <name type="person" corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</name>,
                    <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret Ruskin</persName> mentions receiving this publication 
                    (Ruskin Family Letters, ed. Burd, 121). Her remark does not make clear when the Ruskins' subscription began, 
                    but it might be significant that, with the 1823 issues, the magazine initiated volume 1 of a new series.</p>
                <!-- 4. divs can be nested inside divs; divs can carry attributes. 
            Try adding a div after the first paragraph, so we can create a subsection entitled "Founding of the Evangelical Magazine"--> 
                
                <!-- 5. then we can add an identifier xml:id to the section head so we can point to it -->
                 <p><title type="periodical">The Evangelical Magazine</title> was founded in 1793 as a nondenominational voice of evangelical culture 
                     embracing <orgName corresp="EVANGELICALANGLICANISM">Anglican Evangelicalism</orgName>, Old Dissent, and New Dissent (Altbolz, Religious Press in Britain, 45). 
                    That spirit of pan-evangelical catholicity of opinion and mission was reaffirmed at the start of the new series in 1823, 
                    but the position was being tested. A "Retrospect" published in the first issue of the new series admitted to the emergence of rival denominational publications 
                    on both the Anglican Evangelical and Congregational sides. In fact, the editorship of the Evangelical Magazine itself 
                    became dominated by Congregationalists, just as that sect prevailed within the organization that the magazine most prominently represented, 
                    the <orgName corresp="LMS">London Missionary Society (LMS).</orgName>
                     ("Retrospect of the Former Series of the Evangelical Magazine", 1; 
                     <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ALTHOLZRELIGIOUSPRESS"><persName corresp="JLA">Altholz</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#ALTHOLZRELIGIOUSPRESS">Religious Press in Britain</title></ref>, 46).</p>
             <div n="2">
                 <head type="subsection"></head>
                <p>So much of each issue was given over to news and formal reports of LMS activity that the Ruskins' (or at least Margaret's) 
                    regular reading of the <title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG">Evangelical Magazine</title> implies a strong interest in missionary work. 
                    The reports included lists of charitable contributions to the LMS, which, as Sujit Sivasundaram argues, 
                    inspired readers with a collective experience of evangelical zeal. The lists comprised both large and small donations, 
                    even so modest as used copies of the Evangelical Magazine to be sent to missionaries abroad, 
                    who duly reported back with their gratitude for fresh reading to relieve the tedium of their missions. 
                    Readers therefore felt they played a part in a worldwide evangelistic effort 
                    ("The Periodical as Barometer", 43-48).</p>
                
                 <p>Such outreach was characteristic of the <orgName corresp="#LMS">LMS's</orgName> larger effort in print culture, 
                     which <persName corresp="#AJOHNSTON">Anna Johnston</persName> describes as the construction of "a reading audience through its canny manipulation 
                    of textual and media technologies, a readership that would unite religious Britons in a common cause 
                    despite differences of class, region, gender, and age" (<ref type="bibiliography" target="bibliography.php#JOHNSTONMISSIONARYPUBLISHING">"British Missionary Publishing"</ref>, 30). 
                    The young John Ruskin was captured by the excitement, as evidenced by <!--title needed-->, 
                    which appears to record a speech or sermon at a meeting of a missionary society. 
                    Ruskin was also vulnerable to the appeal of missionary celebrity, as shown by his starstruck enthusiasm 
                    for the poetry and journals of <persName corresp= "#RHBC">Reginald Heber</persName>, Bishop of <placeName corresp= "#CALUCUTTA">Calcutta.</placeName><!-- note on Heber? --></p>
                
                <p>Besides reporting on the missionary activities of LMS, the Evangelical Magazine addressed other interests that probably engaged the Ruskin family. 
                    Each issue contained a section of poetry, albeit strictly pious in subject matter; and the January issue routinely 
                    printed poems for the New Year, which may have influenced Ruskin's custom of composing a <!--note-->New Year's ode to be fair-copied 
                    and presented to his father on New Year's Eve. Feature articles mainly concerned religious topics but 
                    occasionally encompassed other areas of knowledge, such as natural history. 
                    A section of book reviews and brief notices of religious publications, including pious works for children, 
                    evidently informed the elder Ruskins' choice of some books for John, since some notices correspond to books 
                    that he is known to have owned (see, e.g., <!--Roseneath-->. Among the most prominent features in each issue 
                    were lengthy obituaries and biographies of celebrated clergy, embellished by an engraved portrait of a clergyman, 
                    which supplied the sole graphic interest in each issue, apart from the engraved banner. 
                    These biographies exposed the reader to peoples, landscapes, and customs of cultures around the world, 
                    albeit filtered through the perception of missionaries.</p>
                </div> 
              </div>
           </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>