<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="evangelical_magazine_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main"></title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="bibliographical">
                <head type="title"><title type="periodical" corresp="#EVANGELICALMAG"><hi rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine</hi></title></head>                
                
                <p>In a letter of 3 March 1823 to John James Ruskin,
                    Margaret Ruskin mentions receiving this publication 
                    (Ruskin Family Letters, ed. Burd, 121). Her remark does not make clear when she began her subscription; 
                    notably, however, with the 1823 issues, the magazine initiated volume 1 of a new series, 
                    having begun publication in 1793.</p>
                <p>Regular reading of the Evangelical Magazine necessarily entailed an interest in missionary work,
                    since a significant portion of each issue was devoted to reporting missionary news 
                    and especially to promoting the efforts of the London Missionary Society (LMS). 
                    The magazine supported other interests, as well, which would have engaged the Ruskin family, including 
                    poetry; articles primarily on religious topics but encompassing other areas of knowledge, such as natural history; 
                    reviews and notices of religious publications; obituaries and biographies of celebrated clergy, 
                    embellished by an engraved portrait of a clergyman in each issue; and as an effect of missionary news, 
                    exposure to peoples, landscapes, and customs of cultures around the world--an exposure that was of course 
                    filtered through the perception of the missionaries reporting on their experiences.</p>
                <p>Doctrinally, the magazine claimed a pan-evangelical catholicity of non-affiliation. 
                    This position became difficult to maintain: a "Retrospect" published at the start of the new series 
                    admitted to the emergence of rival publications specific to denominations; and 
                    like the LMS it represented, the magazine became increasingly centered in Congregationalism 
                    ("Retrospect of the Former Series of the Evangelical Magazine", 1; 
                    Altholz, ???). 
                    Nonetheless, as Sujit Sivasundaram argues, the magazine offered readers a collective experience of evangelical zeal and meditation; 
                    and by reporting on charitable contributions to the LMS, from small donations such as used copies of the magazine to be sent to missionaries abroad, 
                    to more substantial cash donations, readers felt they participated in a worldwide evangelistic effort 
                    ("The Periodical as Barometer", 43-48). In the outreach for charitable support, the magazine formed but one part 
                    of what Anna Johnston describes as the LMS's construction of "a reading audience through its canny manipulation 
                    of textual and media technologies, a readership that would unite religious Britons in a common cause 
                    despite differences of class, region, gender, and age" ("British Missionary Publishing", 30).
                    
                
                    
                    
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>