<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="history_of_bibliography_and_editing_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">History of Bibliography and Editing of the Early Manuscripts</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="bibliographical">
                <head type="title">History of the Bibliography and Editing of the Early Ruskin Manuscripts</head>
                <p>The editorial rationale of <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> is grounded in the history of editing <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s early writing. 
                    This history began in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s lifetime, first with the anthologizing of his poems in <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1850_note.php"><title type="book" corresp="#POEMS1850"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1850)</title></ref>, 
                    selected and edited by <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> and <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="harrison_w_h_note.php">W. H. Harrison (ca. 1792&#x2013;1878)</ref>. 
                    The history was resumed toward the end of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s life, with the more extensive selection and scholarly editing of his poems 
                    in <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1891_note.php"><title type="book" corresp="#POEMS1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</title></ref> by 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="collingwood_w_g_note.php"><persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood</persName> (<date notBefore="1854" notAfter="1932">1854&#x2013;1932</date>)</ref>. 
                    <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>&#x02BC;s editing of the poems was absorbed and extended in the second volume of the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref>, edited by 
                    by <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="wedderburn_note.php"><persName corresp="#AW">Alexander Wedderburn</persName> (<date notBefore="1854" notAfter="1931">1854&#x2013;1931</date>)</ref> and 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="cook_e_t_note.php"><persName corresp="#ETC">E. T. Cook</persName> (1857&#x2013;1919)</ref>. That volume was paired one devoted to early prose, 
                    the first volume of the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref>&#x2014;a 
                    project that <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> originally contemplated as a scholarly edition complementing the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1891_note.php"><title type="book" corresp="#POEMS1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</title></ref>, 
                    but that was ultimately preempted by <persName corresp="#ETC">Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName>&#x02BC;s volume, 
                    in which they for most part merely gathered together texts that <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="allen_george_note.php"><persName corresp="#GA">George Allen</persName> (<date notBefore="1849" notAfter="1907">1849&#x2013;1907</date>)</ref> had previously published as collectors&#x02BC; items in the <date notBefore="1890" notAfter="1899">1890s</date>.
                    Through these two stages separated by a half century, the history of editing the early <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> was shaped by two overlapping constituencies&#x2014;one 
                    an almost private and familial enterprise in preserving the first phase of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s career as a writer, 
                    and the second a public activity of late Victorian book collecting, which sponsored a peculiar interest in the juvenilia and youthful writing of modern British authors.</p>

                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">John James Ruskin, W. H. Harrison, and Poems (1850)</head>
                    <p>In the late 1840s, Ruskin's father, John James Ruskin, compiled the earliest known bibliography of Ruskin, 
                        the <ref type="apparatus" target="published_poems_1830-46_note.php">List of Published Poems, 1830&#x2013;46</ref> in <ref type="apparatus" target="msiv_apparatus.php">MS IV</ref>. 
                        Presumably, John James compiled the list prepatory to editing 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1850_note.php"><title type="book" corresp="#POEMS1850"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> by &#x201C;J.R.&#x201D; (1850)</title></ref> with the assistance of his friend, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="harrison_w_h_note.php"><persName>W. H. Harrison</persName></ref>. 
                        Ruskin's own part, if any, in compiling this list is unknown.</p>
                        
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Richard Herne Shepherd and Collectors&#x02BC; Bibliographies of the 1870s&#x2013;90s</head>
                    <p>Information about Ruskin's first major bibliographer is divided between the biographical note on 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="shepherd_r_h_note.php">Richard Herne Shepherd (1840&#x2013;95)</ref>; 
                        the bibliographical note on his achievement, 
                        the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="bibliography_of_ruskin_shepherd_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Bibliography of Ruskin</hi> (1878&#x2013;81)</ref>; 
                        and the contextual note on the cultural phenomenon in which he worked, and which he helped to create, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.php">The Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>. 
                        The present discussion summarizes Shepherd's aims and ideals, which were solely bibliographical in practice. 
                        He never edited a Ruskin text, early or otherwise, although he was perhaps headed in the direction of reprinting fugitive pieces by Ruskin that he recovered from the public press, 
                        when he was co-opted in that project by Ruskin himself, who praised Shepherd for his effort, but who appointed Alexander Wedderburn to the task of helping assemble the collections, 
                        <hi rend="italic">Arrows of the Chase</hi> (1880) and <hi rend="italic">On the Old Road</hi> (1885).
                    </p> 
                    <p><persName corresp="#RHC">Shepherd</persName>&#x02BC;s bibliographies of Ruskin and of other modern authors amounted to little more than handlists, 
                        rather than constituting descriptive or analytical bibliography in a present&#x2010;day sense. Nonetheless, Shepherd is significant for aiming 
                        at an unprecedented exhaustiveness in chronologically listing of modern authors' published works. 
                        Moreover, in his "reprints" of little-known works by modern authors--often forgotten juvenilia or youthful publications--he 
                        stood by a principle of scrupulous accuracy of text, sometimes even reproducing the material conditions of the originally published text in a typographical facsimile. 
                        On both counts of exhaustiveness and accuracy, he was ridiculed and accused of base motives by powerful men. 
                        His insistence on "historical" accuracy of copytext was treated as pedantry by 
                        William Michael Rossetti and D. G. Rossetti, who were contemptuous of Shepherd's criticism of their editing of Blake's texts, 
                        which was in fact free-handed to the point of rewriting; and 
                        Shepherd's reprints of fugitive works by modern authors were denounced by 
                        Alfred Tennyson and Robert Browning as mere opportunistic piracy.  
                        Yet, while Tennyson took Shepherd to court and prevailed in forcing the editor to withdraw a reprint of an early Tennyson poem, 
                        Shepherd, nothing daunted, ultimately triumphed in a libel suit against the journal, the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi>, 
                        which overreached in attacking the editor for motives of dishonest gain and literary "vampirism." In this battle, Shepherd's lawyer confounded 
                        the testimony of Robert Browning, who appeared in court to support the defendant's denunciation of Shepherd's character for reprinting out-of-copyright juvenilia by the late 
                        Elizabeth Barrett Browning.
                    </p>
                    <p>Shepherd's principled stands tended to be grander than the theoretical writing and practical editing that he actually produced, 
                        and his motives in resurrecting and reprinting early published writing by modern authors (which sometimes had lapsed from copyright control by the author, 
                        but sometimes were only very doubtfully open to Shepherd's appropriation) probably could not bear very close scrutiny. 
                        Nonetheless, at stake in his editorial principles were nothing less than unprecedented standards of accuracy in editing modern texts, 
                        and the right of access by students of literature to texts and states of text over which some authors and their literary executors 
                        claimed absolute, and perhaps unreasonable control. For these stands, 
                        Shepherd was eventually awarded due honor as a pioneer of the bibliography and editing of modern texts. 
                        Deborah Dorfman acknowledges that Shepherd's editions of Blake achieved the greatest fidelity to historically justifiable copytext of his era 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#DORFMANBLAKE"><hi rend="italic">Blake in the Nineteenth Century</hi></ref>, 110-14); 
                        and the "New Bibliographers" of the 1930s, such as Michael Sadleir, Graham Pollard, and John Carter, 
                        credited Shepherd's Ruskin bibliography as heading a stream of serious and comprehensive modern-author bibliographies that poured almost annually
                        as aids to scholarship and book collecting from the 1870s through the First World War 
                        (Sadleir, &#x201C;Development of Bibliographical Study&#x201D; 148&#x2013;49).<!-- DCH: give ref --> Carter lauded 
                        Shepherd&#x02BC;s thoroughness and accuracy as 
                        providing &#x201C;a target of completeness at which previously desultory
                        collectors would be encouraged to aim,&#x201D; although Carter was also 
                        wary of a late-Victorian trend, which he traced to Shepherd's fledgling efforts in the 1870s, of describing &#x201C;the most trifling pamphlet . . . as
                        carefully and as impressively as its author&#x02BC;s
                        masterpiece&#x201D;&#x2014;a development in modern-author bibliography that erupted into controversy in the 1890s 
                        as the so-called "first edition mania." From the standpoint of the New Bibliographers, this "fashion" in collecting at best led to distasteful 
                        "sentimentality" in modern-author collecting, and at worst supplied an opening for exploitation of an overheated rare-book market by the forgers, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="wise_t_j_note.php">Thomas J. Wise (1859&#x2013;1937)</ref> 
                        and <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="forman_h_buxton_note.php">H. Buxton Forman (1842&#x2013;1917)</ref>, 
                        who specialized in faking pamphlet publications by modern authors 
                        (Carter, Taste and Technique in Book&#x2010;Collecting 23 <!--Correction needed here?-->, 28; Hanson, "Sentiment and Materiality in Late-Victorian Book Collecting," 00; 
                        and see The Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries; Forgery and Piracy).<!-- DCH: give refs -->
                    </p>
                    <p>For puposes of ERM, the greatest relevance of the controversies surrounding Shepherd's scholarship lies in how they played out specifically with reference 
                        to editing and publishing the juvenilia of modern authors. Shepherd typically justified his reprints of authors' early writing on the grounds that they provided materials 
                        for studying &#x201C;&#x2018;the growth of a Poet&#x02BC;s mind&#x2019;&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#TENNYSONIANA">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">Tennysoniana</hi></ref>, v); for Shepherd's critics, however, 
                        the seeming Wordsworthianism of this formulation was contradicted for by the textual accuracy--indeed, the facsimile-like typographic reproduction--on 
                        which Shepherd insisted in his reprints. Owing to the consequent immediacy of confrontation with the youthful author that the reader experiences in these reproductions, 
                        the child&#x02BC;s genius is not recollected in Wordsworthian fashion, and translated 
                        through the medium of the poet&#x02BC;s mature inscription of spots of time. 
                        Such unmediated authority awarded to a child writer drew an intensely negative reaction from the chief poetry critic for the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi>, 
                        <persName corresp="#TWD">Theodore Watts&#x2010;Dunton</persName>. In attacking Shepherd's professional character--Watts&#x2010;Dunton's review of Shepherd's reprint 
                        of the Barrett Browning juvenilia contributed largely to prompting Shepherd's 
                        libel suit against the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi>--the critic reacted disproportionately to the perception of Shepherd's alleged chicanery, 
                        and revealed that much of the outrage surrounded the authority that Shepherd vested in the child writer.
                    </p>
                    <p>Granted, Watts-Dunton, along with Algernon Swinburne 
                        and some other members of the later Pre-Raphaelite circle, was willing to award a positive critical assessment to modern juvenilia by 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="brown_oliver_madox_note.php">Oliver Madox Brown (1855&#x2013;74)</ref>, who had died young 
                        like <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="chatterton_thomas_note.php"><persName>Thomas Chatterton</persName> (<date notBefore="1752" notAfter="1770">1752&#x2010;70</date>)</ref>, 
                        and to the youthful productions of <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="wells_charles_jeremiah_note.php">Charles Jeremiah Wells (1800&#x2013;1879)</ref>, 
                        whose career as a writer seemed confined to an early, precocious achievement. It was common to credit Brown's writing with "power" 
                        (whether credited sincerely or in deference to Oliver's doting father, the painter Ford Madox Brown [1821-93]), 
                        although Watts-Dunton insisted that Oliver's precocity was "very likely unique" 
                        (quoted in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FREDEMANBROWN">Fredeman, &#x201C;Pre&#x2010;Raphaelite Novelist Manqu&#x00E9;&#x201D;</ref>, 31, and see 27-34). 
                        Swinburne responded to this modern juvenilia more in keeping with Shepherd's poetics, 
                        which used natural imagery of "budding" talent and new growth in valuing a direct and visceral response to unmediated childhood "genius"--a response that 
                        Shepherd offered as a benefit to the jaded adult reader, but that Swinburne offered as a boon to a reader of the same age as the child writer.
                    </p> 
                    <p>Despite this positive critical space set aside within the Pre-Raphaelite circle for Brown and Wells, the child writer in the abstract presented to Watts-Dunton, 
                        not an unmediated, natural genius, but a "precocious smartness" that was merely imitative. Owing to the child writer's tendency to ape  
                        (in Watts-Dunton's opinion) the most sentimental or otherwise fatuous literary models, the oversight of the nation's literary history was endangered 
                        by a license given to "early printing" by immature writers. 
                        Combined with the lack of dignity bestowed on childhood imagination by Wordsworthian recollection in tranquility, 
                        the child writer's upstart presence in print struck Watts-Dunton as a rebellion to be put down. 
                        More specifically, <persName corresp="#TWD">Watts&#x2010;Dunton,</persName> belittled the child writer in terms that paralleled 
                        those that he and other by the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi> critics used to ostracize Shepherd from professional letters. 
                        <persName corresp="#RHS">Shepherd</persName> was treated as rebelliously disrespectful of authors' authority over their canon, 
                        and yet as insufferably pedantic in his insistence on bibliographical thoroughness and textual accuracy,
                        and even as subhumanly parasitical in feeding on the corpus of the author. Just so, 
                        the child writer was perceived as threatening to disrupt control by the adult Wordsworthian &#x201C;literature of power,&#x201D; 
                        which was thought to enoble, if also quell, the child's spirit, 
                        and yet the precocious writer was dismissed as prone slavishly to imitate the most objectionable literary models. 
                        The child author and the child author's editor were both too insistent on origins and not original enough 
                        (see <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="shepherd_r_h_note.php">Richard Herne Shepherd [1840&#x2013;95]</ref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>This fault line of exposing intense ideological work surrounding the figure of the precocious child. . . .</p>
                    <p>Certainly, Shepherd relished the chase for minutiae, as witnessed by his
                        extraordinary keenness in ferreting out early Ruskin, and by his triumphant find
                        of Charles Lamb&#x02BC;s lost Poetry for Children (Shepherd,
                        &#x201C;Discovery&#x201D;). His industry appears especially remarkable
                        if one puts oneself in mind of Ruskin studies prior to the Library
                        Edition&#x2014;prior even to Ruskin&#x02BC;s Praeterita, in which the
                        author unintentionally alerted collectors to rarities through reminiscing about
                        his boyhood poetry publications. (Conceivably, Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                        reminiscences in chapter <!--Entry needed here.--> about publishing in the annuals could have been
                        prodded by bibliographers&#x02BC; research of the
                        1870s&#x2013;80s.) In the Bibliography of Ruskin, Shepherd annotates some entries describing the early
                        publications with quotations by Ruskin identifying his authorship, but these
                        quotations cannot have been easy to unearth, let alone the early publications
                        themselves.</p>
                    <p>For example, no. 1 in the Bibliography&#x2014;the two 1834 essays published
                        in The Magazine of Natural History, &#x201C;Enquiries on the Causes of the
                        Colour of the Water of the Rhine,&#x201D; and &#x201C;Facts and
                        Considerations on the Strata of Mont Blanc&#x201D;&#x2014;is glossed
                        by a remark from the so&#x2010;called Instructions in Use of the
                        Rudimentary Series for the Drawing Schools at Oxford (1872): &#x201C;Mr.
                        Loudon was the first literary patron who sent words of mine to be actually set
                        up in print, in his Magazine of Natural History, when I was sixteen&#x201D;
                        (see Ruskin, Works 21:243n). Not only was the remark obscure, printed as a
                        footnote in the Instructions; the pamphlet itself had never been issued for
                        sale, having been printed solely for students at the Oxford Drawing Schools.</p>
                    <p>Similarly, no. 5 in the Bibliography, the 1834 The Poetry of Architecture, is
                        annotated with a nugget from Ruskin&#x02BC;s 1878 essay on W. H. Harrison,
                        &#x201C;My First Editor: An Autobiographical Reminiscence&#x201D;:
                        &#x201C;the series of essays written about this time for the Architectural
                        Magazine, under the signature of Kata Phusin, contain sentences nearly as well
                        put together as any I have done since&#x201D; (see Ruskin, Works 34:97).
                        While Ruskin&#x02BC;s essay on Harrison became familiar to Ruskin readers
                        when reprinted in 1885 in On the Old Road, in 1878 Shepherd could have found it
                        only in its original place of publication&#x2014;as a preface to W. H.
                        Harrison, &#x201C;Notes and Reminiscences,&#x201D; recently published
                        in the Dublin University Magazine.</p>
                    <p>One wonders, therefore, whether the publication of Harrison&#x02BC;s
                        reminiscences served as an impetus for bibliographers&#x02BC; busy activity
                        after 1878, particularly. Besides Shepherd&#x02BC;s multiple editions of
                        his bibliography, for example, there appeared in 1879  &#x201C;John Ruskin: A
                        Bibliographical Biography&#x201D; by William Axon, which begins by
                        reprinting the poem&#x201C;Glenfarg&#x201D; from Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                        text given in Queen of the Air (18<!--Entry needed here.-->) along with two pieces from Poems (1850).
                        That Axon notes the latter as a &#x201C;very rare volume,&#x201D; and
                        as containing poems that &#x201C;had appeared in Friendship&#x02BC;s
                        Offering and other annuals,&#x201D; suggests the inspiration of
                        Harrison&#x02BC;s reminiscences as well as of the collecting culture that
                        was driving these bibliographical researchers (Axon, &#x201C;Bibliographical
                        Biography&#x201D; 156, and see 155&#x2013;58). (What Shepherd, Axon,
                        and other bibliographers and collectors gleaned from Harrison, &#x201C;Notes
                        and Reminiscences&#x201D; would, however, have depended less on Harrison,
                        who is very reticent about the Ruskins, and more on Ruskin in his introduction,
                        who supplied more clues about early publications; see note on W. H. Harrison.) </p>
                    <p>In Ruskin studies, that stream brought two more Ruskin bibliographies shortly
                        following Shepherd&#x02BC;s (Axon, &#x201C;Bibliographical
                        Biography&#x201D; [1879], Shepherd&#x02BC;s preface to the
                        Bibliography of Ruskin, published the same year in the first <!--Correction needed here?--> edition,
                        suggests that he had been working for years: &#x201C;the materials . . .
                        have taken many years . . . and much anxious labour&#x201D; to collect and
                        arrange; and that &#x201C;no entry . . . [was] made at
                        second&#x2010;hand&#x201D; but &#x201C;always with the actual
                        book, pamphlet, magazine, or journal&#x201D; at hand (4th ed., p. vii). The
                        statement might, however, apply to the collectors, whose help Shepherd
                        acknowledges in supplying him with materials. This long list of collectors,
                        whatever the immediate impetus in compiling the bibliography, suggests that the
                        audience for Ruskin bibliography was fairly substantial, at least among a circle
                        of collectors. The list acknowledges the help of librarians and of the
                        publisher, George Allen, as one would expect; others on the list must have been
                        collectors and enthusiasts.</p>
                    <p> Before Thomas J. Wise collaborated with James P. Smart to compile the Complete
                        Bibliography of . . . Ruskin (1889&#x2013;93), in which Wise inserted
                        descriptions of the forged pamphlets that he and H. Buxton Forman leaked into
                        the market, Richard Herne Shepherd assembled the Bibliography of Ruskin
                        (1878&#x2013;81). Shepherd also prepared bibliographies of several other
                        modern authors. A precursor to Forman in pioneering scholarly bibliography of
                        modern authors, Shepherd is credited with prescience of the new collecting by
                        Carter,Taste and Technique in Book&#x2010;Collecting (24). Shepherd also
                        industriously sought out and edited early writing by modern authors, as well as
                        their writing for children. He unearthed and edited juvenilia and youthful work
                        by Blake, Tennyson, Barrett Browning, Longfellow, and Thackeray, as well as then
                        little known writing about and for children by Blake and Lamb.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">W. G. Collingwood and the Editing of <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</head>
                    <p>The first systematic survey and description of the early <hi rend="italic">manuscripts</hi>--as distinct from a survey of the early <hi rend="italic">works</hi>, 
                    which John James Ruskin and W. H. Harrison had undertaken--was 
                    the &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems,&#x201D; which W. G. Collingwood compiled for 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1891_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</ref>. For this edition, 
                    Collingwood had access to a collection of early manuscripts at Brantwood, as indicated by his opening remark of the &#x201C;Preliminary Note&#x201D;: 
                    &#x201C;The early writings of Mr. Ruskin were carefully preserved by his parents&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:262; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:???).<!-- reference needed --> 
                    Apart from what Collingwood describes in the &#x201C;Preliminary Note&#x201D; itself, 
                    no exact list is known of what the collection of &#x201C;early writings of Mr. Ruskin&#x201D; at Brantwood consisted of--or, 
                    what may be a somewhat different matter, what he had access to. 
                    That there existed a distinct collection appears indicated by an 18 July 1880 comment in one of Ruskin's diaries: 
                    &#x201C;Drawer of Precious things examined, and all my Fathers and Mother’s things put with my childish books.&#x2014;upper shelf of Bible compartment of Bookcase.&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFMS13">MS 13</ref>, 13r).
                    By the phrase &#x201C;childish books,&#x201D; Ruskin may have referred to printed books--the books he read as a boy 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="boyhood_books_note.php">Ruskin's Boyhood Books</ref>)--rather than the bound notebooks and other papers that Collingwood 
                    surveyed and described a decade later in &#x201C;Preliminary Note.&#x201D; 
                    It appears clear, however, that there existed a collection that defined for Collingwood &#x201C;the early writings of Mr. Ruskin,&#x201D; 
                    and that, whatever its specific contents at a given time at Brantwood, Ruskin thought of it as a family collection of 
                    &#x201C;Precious things&#x201D; belonging alongside &#x201C;all my Fathers and Mother’s things.&#x201D;
                    (Detailed reconstructions of how this collection evolved in Ruskin's lifetime are attempted in 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_herne_hill_note.php">Provenance of the Early Manuscripts at Herne Hill</ref> and                         
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_brantwood_note.php">Provenance of the Early Manuscripts at Denmark Hill and Brantwood</ref>.)</p>
                <p>Because Collingwood was at this time interested only in the poetry, his &#x201C;Preliminary Note&#x201D; excludes early manuscripts that contained exclusively prose. 
                    Presumably, these lay among the other manuscripts in the family archive, 
                    and Collingwood would have described them, had he carried forward with his plan to prepare an edition of early prose to complement the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891).<!-- REFERENCE NEEDED --> Twelve years later, in the Library Edition, the omissions were made good by Cook and Wedderburn, 
                    who reprinted Collingwood's &#x201C;Preliminary Note,&#x201D; 
                    but expanded it with bracketed insertions of additional entries to form 
                    &#x201C;Notes on the Original MSS. of the Poems  [Revised and Completed from the Edition of 1891].&#x201D; <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> observes this
                    tradition of carrying forward and elaborating the system of identifying and naming manuscripts as first established by Collingwood and continued by Cook and Wedderburn, 
                    albeit (it is hoped) more exactingly than the earlier editors 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="title_citation_for_major_mss_note.xml">System of Title Citation for Manuscripts</ref>). 
                    In its encoding and editorial design, <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> aspires to greater thoughtfulness and flexibility in representing Ruskin's restless 
                    anthologizing, whereby every work was potentially a part of a collection, and every collection potentially subsumed under a still larger collection. 
                    To represent this anthologizing calls for preserving a tension between <hi rend="italic">work</hi> and <hi rend="italic">manuscript</hi>, 
                    which tended to be blunted by Collingwood's system of naming manuscripts, which emphasized the separateness of the bound notebooks. 
                    XML/TEI encoding imposes limitations of its own, however, and one acknowledges the earlier editors' best intentions, even as he strive to improve on their system 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology</ref>).
                </p>
                
                
                
                <p>The orientation to Ruskin&#x02BC;s early works in both periods of editing
                    can be described as aesthetic, in the sense described in Shillingsburg,
                    Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age, but with a more historical orientation
                    developing in Poems (1891) and the Library Edition. That is, as editors, John
                    James Ruskin, Harrison, and even Collingwood to a large extent, produced single,
                    eclectic texts, rather than attending to the historical interest of separate,
                    monolithic variant texts. To arrive at these eclectic texts, the editors freely
                    divided authority between themselves and Ruskin, to an extent that it is now
                    difficult to determine whether they based a given choice either on reasoning
                    through the authority of Ruskin&#x02BC;s own competing variants, or simply
                    on what appealed to them. Collingwood felt free to punctuate, entitle, and
                    otherwise regularize according to his notions of how a well&#x2010;edited
                    work should appear. Aesthetic judgments also reigned over selection of works to
                    print from the manuscripts, in some cases even inventing works that Ruskin
                    surely never intended, by combining of unconnected texts.<!--Entry needed here.--> [Give examples.]</p>
                <p> At the same time, Collingwood certainly intended an approach in Poems (1891)
                    that was more historical and documentary than that taken in the unabashedly
                    nostalgic project of the Poems (1850), and he was supported by fellow
                    bibliographers who assured an approach as comprehensive and systematic in the
                    treatment of printed works as he careful in the treatment of early manuscripts.
                    (Bibliographers outside the Ruskin circle at Brantwood of course had no access
                    to manuscripts, those sales beginning after the first major bibliographies and
                    the Library Edition were undertaken: see Provenance.) The Library Edition
                    intensified the documentary approach in general, being more forthcoming with
                    manuscript and printed variants than late Victorian editions generally were <!--Entry needed here.-->
                    [document]. Respecting Ruskin&#x02BC;s early works, however, the Library
                    Edition relied heavily on Collingwood and Allen&#x02BC;s
                    existing publications, hence incorporating their largely aesthetic choices, if
                    in some instances extending the documentary aspect&#x2014;for example, by
                    supplementing Collingwood&#x02BC;s descriptive bibliography and chronology
                    of the poetry manuscripts with a much needed, similar apparatus for the early
                    prose manuscripts.</p>
                <p>The orientation of these first editors can also be described in
                    Shillingsburg&#x02BC;s sense of sociological, although they were far more
                    themselves a part of the sociological phenomenon they addressed than critical of
                    it. In the case of the first period, Ruskin&#x02BC;s father and the editor,
                    W. H. Harrison, produced a privately printed edition intended for family and
                    close friends. The audience shared a view of the young Ruskin as <!--Entry needed here.-->. Their
                    approach can be regarded as sociological, albeit unconsciously so, in that they
                    were producing an edition that was both culmination and testament of their
                    partnership in producing Ruskin&#x02BC;s texts. The Ruskin that was
                    published in the gift annuals was, like all such cases of authorship more or
                    less, a joint effort of author, editor, publisher, and often artist, and Poems
                    (1850) commemorates that partnership. If the project was nostalgic,
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s refusal to participate must have forced at least some
                    self&#x2010;awareness onto the editors.</p>
                <p>The second period is also sociologically oriented, although catering to quite
                    different, public motives than the private ones that engaged John James Ruskin
                    and Harrison. Early bibliographers such as Shepherd, Smart, and Wise, publishers
                    such as Allen, and even reasonably scholarly editors such as Collingwood were
                    caught up in a broader social phenomenon of book collecting. Of course, these
                    producers and collectors were driven in part by devotion to Ruskin and his
                    ideas, often passionately so; however, the passion could be also in part be
                    expressed, and perhaps sometimes overtaken, by an acquisitive fever for
                    collecting modern authors, compiling their bibliographies, and participating in
                    societies dedicated to them. Again, as in the first period of editing, the
                    distinction is ambiguous between an edition that treats text as a sociological
                    phenomenon and that is itself a part of that phenomenon. Wise&#x02BC;s
                    forgered publications of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early poems require some
                    consciousness on the forger&#x02BC;s part of the sociology of collecting
                    that he was pandering to (see Forgery and Piracy).</p>
                <p>The present note presents an overview of these projects of the 1840s and
                    1870s&#x2013;90s. In addition, see, in connection with the first stage, the
                    notes on <!--Entry needed here.-->. In connection with the second stage, see the notes on Collecting
                    of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries; Forgery
                    and Piracy; <!--Correction needed here?--> (Ruskin Societies); <!--Correction needed here?--> (Ruskin Bibliography).</p>
                </div>
                
                <div>
            
            
                <p>and a checklist by the American, William Sloane Kennedy, attached to one of his
                    Ruskin anthologies <!--Correction needed here?--> [1885]). Ruskin bibliography was then settled for a time
                    by Thomas J. Wise and James P. Smart with Wise and Smart, Complete Bibliography
                    of <!--Entry needed here.--> Ruskin (1889&#x2013;93; see), and then more authoritatively by E.
                    T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn with the Library Edition&#x2014;the
                    bibliographies in each of the individual volumes and in the Bibliography volume
                    (1912?).</p>
                <p>An interest in juvenilia and youthful writing in particular arose in part from
                    the new zeal for collecting modern authors as comprehensively as possible (see
                    collecting of modern authors, including their juvenilia). This comprehensive
                    collecting interest was spurred as well by modern author societies. W. E. A.
                    Axon produced his brief 1879 bibliography (Axon, &#x201C;Bibliographical
                    Biography&#x201D;) for the Manchester Literary Club <!--Entry needed here.-->. </p>
                <p>The interest in juvenilia and youthful writing cannot be ascribed solely to
                    collecting, however, for modern author societies show extensive inquiry into the
                    subject, even apart from the relatively select group of modern writers who
                    typically formed the subject of these societies. The interest is shown in
                    individual bibliographers, too, like Shepherd and Axon, suggesting that they
                    were not merely supporting the others&#x02BC; taste as collectors and
                    society members in their research (see Richard Herne Shepherd and W. E. A.
                    Axon).</p>
                <p>For Carter, such thorough bibliography was a laudable development, providing
                    &#x201C;a target of completeness at which previously desultory collectors
                    would be encouraged to aim&#x201D;; again, however, Carter the professional
                    is suspicious of describing &#x201C;the most trifling pamphlet . . . as
                    carefully and as impressively as its author&#x02BC;s
                    masterpiece,&#x201D; and he sees an opening for the later forgeries (23<!--Correction needed here?-->,
                    28). Certainly, Shepherd relished the chase for minutiae, as witnessed by his
                    extraordinary keenness in ferreting out early Ruskin for the bibliography, or by
                    his triumphant find of Charles Lamb&#x02BC;s lost Poetry for Children
                    (Shepherd, &#x201C;Discovery&#x201D;).</p>
                <p><!--Entry needed here.--> Writing of the paradox of the childless siblings, Charles and Mary Lamb, as
                    writers for children, Shepherd <!--Entry needed here.-->.</p>
                <p>Although exonerated by later scholars from the charge of forgery that Wise
                    attempted to shift onto him, Shepherd, an intriguingly ambiguous personality,
                    appears an early key figure in the intersection of Ruskin bibliography, editing
                    and collecting modern authors, and the interest in childhood and juvenilia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="section"><hi rend="caps">Approaches to Bibliography and Editing of the Early Manuscripts</hi></head>
                <p>A more public story that John James certainly helped to promote by his selections
                    for the Poems of 1850&#x2014;which were taken mainly from the publications
                    in sentimental gift annuals, such as Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering, of 1835
                    and afterward&#x2014;was that Ruskin&#x02BC;s greatest power as a poet
                    was realized through his adolescent and unrequited first love, for Adèle
                    Domecq.<note n="1" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    See E. T. Cook&#x02BC;s introduction to the volume of
                    poems in the Library Edition, esp. Works, 2:xx&#x2013;xxiii; and Wendell Stacy
                    Johnson, &#x201C;Memory, Landscape, Love: John Ruskin&#x02BC;s Poetry and Poetic
                    Criticism,&#x201D; Victorian Poetry 19 (1981): 19&#x2013;34.</note> Putting aside the
                    merits of this view purely as a critical judgment, the story was initially
                    served by noncritical suggestions. Besides the spice added by
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s self&#x2010;mocking account in Praeterita of how he
                    wooed Adèle with Byronic melodrama, the texts themselves became enhanced by
                    collectors&#x02BC; acquisitiveness. By the end of the century, the Poems of
                    1850 had become an almost legendary &#x201C;Rara Avis of Ruskin
                    literature,&#x201D; commanding higher prices than any other editions of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s work (Wise, 1:17; &#x201C;Ruskin&#x02BC;s Poems
                    1850,&#x201D; 153). T. J. Wise capitalized on the situation, choosing as
                    the first of his Ruskin forgeries an &#x201C;1868&#x201D; (i.e., ca.
                    1889&#x2013;90) reprinting of the 1835&#x2013;36 Byronic tale Leoni
                    (&#x201C;Wise and Ruskin II,&#x201D; 170&#x2013;71). Wise
                    cleverly exploited the circumstances of Ruskin, in Praeterita, having singled
                    out Leoni as an example of his blandishments to Adèle, and of the market having
                    bestowed such expensive rarity and an aura of romance on the 1850 Poems (which
                    contained a song from Leoni) (see Wise, 1:147&#x2013;48; Works, 35:180).
                    Two years later, Wise continued to encourage and profit by the story of Ruskin
                    as lovesick poet by forging an &#x201C;1849&#x201D; Scythian Guest
                    (&#x201C;Wise and Ruskin II,&#x201D; 176&#x2013;78).</p>
                <p>Critics continue to be influenced by the story of how the child&#x02BC;s
                    garden at Herne Hill fell with Adèle&#x02BC;s invasion, and how Ruskin was
                    expelled from paradise to embark on a Shelleyan quest of unobtainable love.
                    While there is some truth to the romance, the poems excluded from
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s 1891 Poems and the Library Edition reveal that imagery
                    commonly associated with the Adèle poems first arose much earlier, in poetry
                    probing Ruskin&#x02BC;s anxious and problematic love for his mother.
                    Figures of drowning in a maternal ocean, drawn from Byron, occur obsessively in
                    the poetry of 1831&#x2013;33, long before Ruskin caused weird cries to
                    issue from shadowy waters in writing about Adèle. However one chooses to
                    interpret the fact, Ruskin&#x02BC;s romance of Venice must be approached as
                    rooted at least as profoundly in these earlier fragments about drowning in a
                    maternal &#x201C;ocean&#x02BC;s breast&#x201D; as in the poems
                    probing Adèle&#x02BC;s betrayal and loss.</p>
                <p>This and other corrections to prevailing myths have been prevented by the
                    pervasive errors and questionable decisions in the bibliography and textual
                    transmission of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early writing. The first attempt at a
                    comprehensive bibliography specifically of the early writing was
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s descriptive bibliography compiled for his 1891 edition
                    of Ruskin&#x02BC;s Poems (PJR). Collingwood&#x02BC;s
                    &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&#x201D;
                    (PJR, 1:262&#x2013;68) described many of the major manuscripts of the
                    juvenilia, namely, the notebooks in which Ruskin drafted and
                    fair&#x2010;copied his first poems. Courageous in undertaking the
                    description of very complicated manuscripts, and correct in many of his
                    interpretations, Collingwood nonetheless misdated the entirety of one notebook
                    (MS II) and many sections of others; misinterpreted the compositional sequences
                    within several notebooks; and, since he was interested only in the poetry,
                    omitted description of most of the prose manuscripts.</p>
                <p>Even more momentously for the future understanding of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early
                    compositional practices, Collingwood made an editorial decision&#x2014;one
                    that has gone entirely unnoticed, so far as I know, much less
                    questioned&#x2014;to print &#x201C;only such [childhood] verses as are
                    of sufficient completeness to stand alone.&#x201D; He adds that this
                    decision was governed by &#x201C;the instructions which have been given
                    him,&#x201D; failing to specify the source (PJR, 1:270). We may never know
                    whether those instructions were imparted by Ruskin or by someone close to him.
                    Given Ruskin&#x02BC;s sardonic view in Praeterita of the
                    &#x201C;unfinished folly&#x201D; of an early production, left
                    &#x201C;in Joanie [Severn]&#x02BC;s care, that none but friends may
                    see it&#x201D; (Works, 35:81), such a caveat would have been characteristic
                    of the elderly writer, as well as of his circle. In Fiction, Fair and Foul
                    (1880, 1881), Ruskin had attacked Wordsworth&#x02BC;s
                    &#x201C;disciples&#x201D; for advancing the poet&#x02BC;s
                    &#x201C;unfinished verse, and uncorrected fancy . . . into places of
                    authority.&#x201D; According to Ruskin, such unauthorized printings of
                    fragments were meant to &#x201C;give countenance to the popular national
                    prejudices from the infection of which . . . [the disciples] themselves
                    sprang&#x201D; (Works, 34:350). Whatever &#x201C;national
                    prejudices&#x201D; Ruskin had in mind&#x2014;and he rails against
                    several &#x201C;infections&#x201D; of the modern literary market in
                    Fiction, Fair and Foul <note n="2" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">As
                    Wordsworth&#x02BC;s &#x201C;unfinished verse,&#x201D; Ruskin
                    may have been thinking of The Prelude. By
                    Wordsworth&#x02BC;s &#x201C;disciples,&#x201D; he may have
                    meant Matthew Arnold, but certainly the Wordsworth Society, of which he was
                    a member. Linda Austin argues that Ruskin&#x02BC;s equivocal
                    detractions from Wordsworth in the Wordsworth versus Byron debate of the
                    1880s were most strongly animated by what Ruskin regarded as the Lake
                    poet&#x02BC;s violation of appropriate social distance between writer
                    and audience (The Practical Ruskin: Economics and Audience in the Late Work
                    [Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1991],
                    145&#x2013;68).</note>&#x2014;his animus may well have resulted in
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s &#x201C;instructions.&#x201D; The
                    consequence was the exclusion of dozens of fragments from the early editions,
                    especially those fragments that the editors
                    considered &#x201C;morbid&#x201D; and
                    &#x201C;bloodthirsty&#x201D; (Works, 2:279 n. 1). When recovered,
                    correctly dated, and compared against events recounted in the family letters
                    (RFL), many of these rejected poems will be found to contain
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s response to his mother&#x02BC;s attempts
                    to &#x201C;stop his rhyming&#x201D; and to other psychological
                    disturbances that the elder Ruskin probably preferred to forget. One impression
                    that arises from reading the suppressed early Ruskin is of an occasionally more
                    obstreperous, rebellious, and even manipulative youth than the obedient, if
                    high&#x2010;spirited, child of Praeterita.</p>
                <p>Nowadays, our prejudices, including my
                    own&#x2014;&#x201C;infections,&#x201D; Ruskin would call
                    them&#x2014;tend to favor fragmentation and perhaps even
                    &#x201C;morbidity.&#x201D; For recent Ruskin criticism, completeness
                    and closure would be considered precisely the most misleading criteria for
                    selection. Critical focus has turned to Ruskin&#x02BC;s deliberately
                    open&#x2010;ended forms and the psychodynamics of incompletion in Fors
                    Clavigera and Praeterita. It is ironic that, while recent criticism is shifting
                    attention to the late work, away from the earlier Ruskin, the new approaches
                    would find support in a more accurate and comprehensive scholarship of the early
                    manuscripts. I would not want readers to take the poems in this edition, which
                    tend to support more recent readings of Ruskin, as necessarily more
                    representative of Ruskin&#x02BC;s youthful writing than the poems chosen
                    for Collingwood&#x02BC;s Poems and the Library Edition.
                    &#x201C;Calamities,&#x201D; as Ruskin said, were &#x201C;equally
                    dominant&#x201D; with the &#x201C;blessings.&#x201D; But the
                    earlier editors&#x02BC; exclusions are unacceptable for objective
                    bibliography and for editing, however interesting and worthy of debate their
                    reasons for their suppressions may remain.</p>
                <p>Also unacceptable is Collingwood&#x02BC;s extension of the preference for
                    completed verse to his editorial treatment of what he did select. Collingwood
                    invariably imparted the appearance of greater polish and completion to the
                    poetry than the manuscripts warrant. Through his extensive repunctuation,
                    revision of diction, rearrangements and omissions of lines, retitling, even the
                    patching together of unrelated fragments to invent whole poems that Ruskin never
                    imagined, Collingwood imparted a seemliness that is only somewhat legitimized by
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s own scrupulous attention to fair&#x2010;copy
                    presentation in some of the original manuscripts.<note n="3" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Emerson is one of the few critics to recognize the formal poetic gains in reading
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s poems in the original, without the early
                    editors&#x02BC; meddling niceties; see her discussion
                    of &#x201C;When furious up from mines the water pours&#x201D; (no.
                    5) in RGI, 24&#x2013;28. Otherwise, except for quoting from a few
                    previously unpublished poems, Emerson generally accepts the published texts
                    and chronologies.</note> To return to the example of &#x201C;Skiddaw and
                    Derwent Water,&#x201D; Collingwood departed from his usual policy and
                    published the poem&#x02BC;s rough&#x2010;copy (MS II) version in PJR,
                    only because, I believe, the fair copy was unavailable to him at the time. He
                    claims not to have &#x201C;mended&#x201D; the &#x201C;childish and
                    almost illegible scribble,&#x201D; &#x201C;except by omission of
                    incomplete parts&#x201D; (PJR, 1:270). Putting aside his disclaimer about
                    emendation, which is simply false, just as his description of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s illegibility is exaggerated, what most closely bears on
                    editorial policy is the decision to omit &#x201C;incomplete
                    parts.&#x201D; Here is a good example of Collingwood&#x02BC;s policy
                    guiding even what he saw, much less how he acted on what he saw, for there are
                    no incomplete parts in Ruskin&#x02BC;s draft. The draft was
                    fair&#x2010;copied substantially as Ruskin first wrote it, saving slight
                    word changes. There are only parts that appeared to Collingwood insufficiently
                    polished.</p>
                <p> Plans for Library Edition (see Dearden, &#x201C;Library Edition of the Works
                    of John Ruskin,&#x201D; 54&#x2013;55). Prospectus (May 1902) for 30
                    volumes placed poems in vol. 1 or a later volume (<!--Entry needed here.-->). (Vol. 1 is called in
                    Prospectus &#x201C;Early Writings.&#x201D;) &#x201C;The Academy of
                    24 May 1902 [i.e., clarifying a confusion in the Prospectus <!--Correction needed here?-->] explained that
                    a separate volume would be devoted to the poems [i.e., separate from early
                    prose?]. If they had been included in volume 1 as originally intended, that
                    volume would have bulked to over 1000 pages&#x201D; (ibid., 54).</p>
                <p> Were there tensions about where the poems would go and how treated because of
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s disapproval of the Library Edition?</p>
                <p>In 1972, Dearden (&#x201C;Library Edition,&#x201D; 7) reported on an
                    India&#x2010;paper set of the Library Edition that exhibited special
                    treatment of the poems. At the time, the set was in the hands of C. C. Kohler,
                    bookseller, 141 High Street, Dorking, Surrey, which he described as:</p>
                <p>&#x201C;in the original sections, unsewn , preserved in original
                    boxes.&#x201D; Of the boxes themselves he writes, &#x201C;The boxes
                    would appear to have been made for the set though there is one curious point.
                    All of the boxes except that for Volume 2 have been made in blue paper covered
                    board. The box for Volume 2 is made of green cloth covered boards, much more
                    substantial. The labels on this box are exactly the same as all the other
                    labels.&#x201D; There are two labels on each box. On the spine: Ruskin / --
                    / Library Edition / - / India&#x2010;paper /Vol. / , and on the lid: The
                    Works of / John Ruskin / Library Edition / Volume - India Paper / . The volume
                    number has been entered by hand on each label.<note n="4" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Later, in &#x201C;Library Edition of the Works of John Ruskin&#x201D; (56),
                    Dearden added that the &#x201C;thinner paper&#x201D; of this issue
                    is not actually India&#x2010;paper. In both articles, Dearden points to
                    India&#x2010;paper sets (not Kohler&#x02BC;s) held by the
                    Ashmolean Museum and the British Library.</note></p>
                <p>In the next stage of editing the juvenilia, Collingwood&#x02BC;s policies
                    were carried over to Cook and Wedderburn&#x02BC;s Library Edition, forcing
                    those editors to strike an awkward and self&#x2010;contradictory pose
                    between the principle of exclusion they inherited from their precursor, on the
                    one hand, and the principle of inclusion governing their own edition, on the
                    other. &#x201C;From a considerable quantity of unpublished pieces [of
                    poetry] belonging to Ruskin&#x02BC;s childhood, scarcely anything further
                    has been taken. At least as much as was desirable was published during his
                    lifetime, and the scheme of the [Library] edition requires that all this should
                    be reprinted. In some cases, however, where editorial excisions were made in the
                    edition of 1891 [by Collingwood], passages have been restored from the
                    MSS&#x201D; (Works, 2:xvii, my emphasis).<note n="5" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    On Wedderburn and George Allen&#x02BC;s foundational
                    principle of inclusiveness governing the editing of the Library
                    Edition&#x2014;a principle opposed by Charles Eliot
                    Norton&#x2014;see James S. Dearden, &#x201C;The Library Edition of
                    the Works of John Ruskin,&#x201D; Book Collector 44, no. 1 (Spring
                    1995): 52&#x2013;53.</note> In their textual presentation, Cook and
                    Wedderburn were somewhat more scrupulous than Collingwood in distinguishing
                    between editor and author. &#x201C;Emendations made by the editor
                    [Collingwood] in 1891 have been retained where they are necessary for the sense;
                    these are included in square brackets. Other emendations introduced in that
                    edition have not been followed in the text, though they are mentioned in
                    footnotes. It seemed desirable in this edition to let the text appear as the
                    author wrote it.&#x201D; Cook and Wedderburn stopped short, however, of
                    providing &#x201C;any critical apparatus of manuscript
                    variants,&#x201D; because they did not think it &#x201C;worth while to
                    treat these early verses with more importance than they possess&#x201D;
                    (Works, 2:xxxvi). While it is true that some of Ruskin&#x02BC;s juvenile
                    writings insufficiently reward the labor of compiling textual variants, the
                    editors&#x02BC; dismissiveness has made it impossible to determine what
                    textual variants do repay examination and interpretation.</p>
                <p>Moreover, Cook and Wedderburn&#x02BC;s tampering with the texts was far more
                    invasive than they claim. For example, they did manage to overcome the prejudice
                    favoring Ruskin&#x02BC;s supposed analytic and scientific beginnings, and
                    located at least the 1830 Spiritual Times version of &#x201C;On Skiddaw and
                    Derwent Water.&#x201D; This printing was used as their main copytext,
                    relegating Ruskin&#x02BC;s original fair copy and its variants from
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s MS II rough&#x2010;copy version to a note. Still,
                    their printing contains no less than
                    one&#x2010;and&#x2010;a&#x2010;half dozen silent punctuation
                    variants from the original Spiritual Times version and changes the wording of
                    three lines. The other early poetry and prose in the first two volumes of the
                    Library Edition were subjected to similar emendations, sometimes significant,
                    sometimes probably not&#x2014;but almost always silent and inaccessible to
                    readers&#x02BC; assessments.</p>
                <p>Of course, in their treatment of &#x201C;On Skiddaw and Derwent
                    Water,&#x201D; Cook and Wedderburn missed altogether the 1829 publication
                    of &#x201C;Lines Written at the Lakes in Cumberland,&#x201D; an
                    understandable oversight in view of the evidence available to them. They might
                    have remarked, however, that significant revisions had been made to
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s original version in arriving at the Spiritual Times
                    versions. A pious concluding couplet was added in the published
                    &#x201C;Lines,&#x201D; and decorous revisions transformed the ending
                    of the 1830 &#x201C;On Skiddaw and Derwent Water,&#x201D; as well. The
                    sentiment in these revisions can be seen as contradictory to the spirit of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s original version. The friction caused by his revising
                    process (at the behest, I believe, of his parents and tutor) is probably
                    reflected in debates over worldly beauty versus religious asceticism carried on
                    in poems succeeding Ruskin&#x02BC;s MS II draft, &#x201C;These worldly
                    things are fair and beauteous too&#x201D; and &#x201C;We say that this
                    world is unhappy&#x201D; (nos. 58&#x2013;59). The debate seems to
                    culminate in &#x201C;If such the beauties of an earthly shore&#x201D;
                    (no. 60). The latter, truly almost illegible and scrawled draft almost certainly
                    represents Ruskin&#x02BC;s troubled attempt at revising his Lake District
                    poem for August 1829 publication. But these poems, nos. 58&#x2013;60, are
                    fragments, and so they were excluded from the Library Edition, just as they had
                    been banned from PJR. Again, throughout the poetry volume of the Library
                    Edition, as in this case of &#x201C;On Skiddaw and Derwent
                    Water&#x201D; and its related fragments, Cook and Wedderburn rarely
                    questioned Collingwood&#x02BC;s judgments about selection, just as they
                    carried on the practice of molding and polishing the texts&#x2014;policies
                    that, by their time, perhaps no longer required
                    explicit &#x201C;instructions.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Cook and Wedderburn did make significant contributions. Although they reprinted
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s 1891 &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS.
                    of the Poems&#x201D; in their 1903 volume of Poems, they expanded
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s descriptions of the notebooks with sequential lists of
                    the titles that the notebooks contain (Works, 2:529&#x2013;34), and later,
                    in the bibliography volume of the Library Edition, they added very slight
                    descriptions of the prose juvenilia that Collingwood had omitted (Works,
                    38:205&#x2013;6). Especially usefully, Cook and Wedderburn paired the
                    descriptive bibliography with a chronological list of the individual poems
                    contained in the notebooks, the &#x201C;Chronology of Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    Juvenilia&#x201D; (Works, 2:535&#x2013;41). A separate chronology is
                    essential since the specific dates of individual items in the notebooks can be
                    gathered from
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s &#x201C;Note&#x201D;&#x2014;even as
                    expanded in the Library Edition&#x2014;only with difficulty, if at all.
                    The &#x201C;Chronology&#x201D; excludes prose, however&#x2014;an
                    unhelpful decision, since prose works such as Ruskin&#x02BC;s Mineralogical
                    Dictionary, fictional tales, sermons, lesson exercises, and essays are
                    integrally connected to his poems. Prose and poetry must be chronologically
                    ordered together, since most of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early prose, like many of
                    the poems, was not dated by him, and so the only means to date such important
                    prose works as the childhood sermons&#x2014;unless they chance to be
                    mentioned in the family letters&#x2014;is to draw inferences from their
                    position in the notebooks relative to the poems.</p>
                <p>The most serious problem with the Library Edition
                    &#x201C;Chronology&#x201D; is its perpetuation of
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s errors in dating. When Cook and Wedderburn ventured to
                    dissent, they nearly always got it wrong, sometimes newly misdating a poem that
                    Collingwood had dated accurately. Their dates for prose works, in the few cases
                    where they hazarded them, were especially groundless, reliant on little more
                    than biographical and anecdotal guesswork. For example, they seriously misdated
                    the important Sermon Books on the basis of vague inferences drawn from
                    Praeterita, as Burd remarks in an article relaying Viljoen&#x02BC;s work on
                    the sermons (&#x201C;Ruskin&#x02BC;s Testament,&#x201D;
                    1&#x2013;3); and their datings of the essays and tales of the later 1830s,
                    dates that have always been taken for granted, turn out similarly to be based on
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s decidedly unreliable memories in the autobiography.</p>
                <p>The countless limitations of the Library Edition have been acknowledged, if not
                    always heeded in critical practice, since the 1950s, when Helen Gill Viljoen
                    inveighed against the competence of its editing (RSH, 1&#x2013;35). Hers
                    was the next major stage of editing the early Ruskin, although much of her
                    bibliographic labor remained unpublished in her lifetime, and it is still
                    available only in typescripts kept among the Helen Gill Viljoen Papers at the
                    Pierpont Morgan Library. Viljoen was the first and only previous scholar to
                    recognize the need for, and partially to undertake, a systematic revision of
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s and Cook and Wedderburn&#x02BC;s bibliographies
                    and chronology of the early manuscripts.</p>
                <p>Viljoen advanced exponentially what had already emerged as an almost peculiarly
                    American interest in Ruskin&#x02BC;s childhood writing and early family
                    history. The greatest of the English collectors, John Howard Whitehouse,
                    restricted his interest in the earlier Ruskin to the drawings&#x2014;one of
                    Whitehouse&#x02BC;s earliest acquisitions being Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    &#x201C;first&#x201D; sketchbook. In 1935 Whitehouse was apparently
                    offered only the remaining drawings, not the manuscripts, in the possession of
                    the Boston dealer Charles E. Goodspeed, although Goodspeed certainly still held
                    a great deal of Ruskin&#x02BC;s juvenilia from the 1931
                    Sotheby&#x02BC;s sale (RBB 38, 136&#x2013;39).<note n="6" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    In general, according to Dearden, Whitehouse&#x02BC;s
                    affections were focused more on the Ruskin drawings he collected than on the
                    manuscripts. As it chanced, in the sale of drawings to Whitehouse, Goodspeed
                    was able to restore a few leaves that had been removed from the early
                    sketchbook, MS VIIIA (James S. Dearden, &#x201C;The Ruskin Galleries at
                    Bembridge School, Isle of Wight,&#x201D; Bulletin of the John Rylands
                    Library 51, no. 2 [Spring 1969]: 318, 319).</note> By comparison, American
                    collectors took a notable interest in the Ruskin juvenilia from the earliest
                    availability of those manuscripts. Henry Huntington in San Marino, Pierpont
                    Morgan in New York, and William Bixby in St. Louis bought early Ruskin
                    manuscripts in the first decades of the century (although those magnates, of
                    course, focused primarily on the major manuscripts of Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    maturity). At the Sotheby sales of 1930&#x2013;31, juvenilia was acquired
                    for Yale directly; and the Yale collection eventually profited, as did the
                    Princeton library, by Charles Goodspeed&#x02BC;s eager bidding for the
                    juvenilia lots at Sotheby&#x02BC;s. Shortly before those sales, the
                    important Sermon Books were given outright to an American collector (albeit
                    Welsh&#x2013;born) by a Coniston resident, who apparently had only a
                    passing acquaintance with the collector (see &#x201C;Provenance of the Major
                    Manuscripts,&#x201D; Viljoen). Helen Viljoen was also a modestly active
                    buyer during the decades after the sales of 1930&#x2013;31.</p>
                <p> One can only speculate why English collectors left the early writings to
                    Americans. The trend is perplexing, since initial reports on the manuscript
                    juvenilia by its new American owners often reflected the language and
                    perspective of Collingwood&#x02BC;s Life and PJR, and Collingwood can
                    surely be credited with first stirring interest in the juvenilia.<note n="7" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    See, e.g., Kenneth G. Weihe, &#x201C;A Collection of
                    Ruskin Manuscripts,&#x201D; YULG 5, no. 3 (January 1931):
                    47&#x2013;49, which in places borrows phrases verbatim from
                    Collingwood, Life. Goodspeed&#x02BC;s fascination with
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s early handwriting is also probably influenced by
                    Collingwood (see, e.g., part 2, MS
                    IA, &#x201C;Provenance&#x201D;).</note> As I argued above (see also
                    my &#x201C;Self and Revision&#x201D;), strict control over the
                    selection and editing of the early writings can be traced to the attitudes of
                    Ruskin himself. Perhaps vestiges of these attitudes influenced English
                    collecting. Whitehouse&#x02BC;s connections with the elder
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s inner circle might explain why he troubled to acquire only
                    transcripts, and no originals, of the early manuscripts (RBB 143). The
                    transcripts had been prepared by Cook and Wedderburn for the Library Edition,
                    and perhaps Whitehouse regarded these to be as good as&#x2014;or, in
                    respect to editorial intervention, better than&#x2014;the manuscripts
                    themselves. Certainly, it is significant that the most outstanding exception to
                    the English willingness to let go of the earlier manuscripts was F. J. Sharp,
                    and Sharp worked entirely apart from the inner circle of English Ruskinians.
                    Subsequently, Sharp&#x02BC;s appreciation of the earlier Ruskin helped to
                    cement his association with Viljoen.</p>
                <p>With the dispersal of Ruskin&#x02BC;s manuscripts and library in the sales
                    of the 1930s, Viljoen could no longer enjoy the benefit, as she had done years
                    earlier in the Brantwood study, of working with so many of the manuscripts
                    within easy reach. But with the major collections of the early Ruskin
                    manuscripts now in America at Yale, Princeton, the Huntington, and the Pierpont
                    Morgan libraries (and the Morgan&#x02BC;s holdings would later become more
                    important with Viljoen&#x02BC;s own donations of Sharp&#x02BC;s and
                    her own Ruskin manuscripts), she was able to attack the problem of the
                    juvenilia, as English scholars could no longer so readily attempt. The resulting
                    document, Viljoen&#x02BC;s &#x201C;Dating MSS. of Boyhood,&#x201D;
                    was prepared as an appendix, first to her unpublished edition of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s childhood sermons, the so&#x2010;called Sermons on the
                    Pentateuch, and then to her unfinished biography of Ruskin (HGVP, boxes D.V,
                    E.IX).</p>
                <p>The &#x201C;Dating MSS. of Boyhood&#x201D; first revealed to me the
                    necessity of undertaking a systematic and comprehensive revision of the earlier
                    bibliographies. Viljoen&#x02BC;s scrupulous and often brilliant research
                    has inestimably aided my own, and I hope I have acknowledged throughout this
                    edition all the ways that my bibliographic arguments originated with her. I have
                    also found an invaluable resource in Viljoen&#x02BC;s transcriptions of
                    unpublished texts of juvenilia, included among her papers at the Morgan. Her
                    transcriptions must be checked against the originals, for Viljoen was a
                    surprisingly careless copyist; nonetheless, her notes provide an invaluable and
                    convenient guide to widely dispersed manuscripts.</p>
                <p>Even the &#x201C;Dating MSS. of Boyhood,&#x201D; however, has proved in
                    need of extensive revision and supplementation. First, Viljoen limited the
                    &#x201C;Dating MSS. of Boyhood&#x201D; to emending
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s descriptive bibliography. Juggling her document with
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s &#x201C;Note&#x201D; and with Cook and
                    Wedderburn&#x02BC;s revised &#x201C;Note&#x201D;
                    and &#x201C;Chronology&#x201D; is impossibly awkward. Previous
                    scholarship needs to be replaced by a single, comprehensive bibliography and
                    chronology. Second, more serious limitations in
                    Viljoen&#x02BC;s &#x201C;Dating MSS. of Boyhood&#x201D; arise from
                    her having committed errors of her own in dating nearly all the major
                    manuscripts that she chose to review. Third, while other papers among the
                    materials for her Ruskin biography testify to her thorough study of the
                    juvenilia, in &#x201C;Dating MSS. of Boyhood&#x201D; she deferred to
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s descriptions of several major manuscripts, which do in
                    fact require reexamination, and she was altogether unacquainted with at least one manuscript.<note n="8" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Viljoen could not have been unaware of an
                    early commonplace book kept jointly by father and son (MS IC; Bem MS 88),
                    since this formed part of the Adams bequest to the Bembridge Ruskin
                    Galleries (RBB 198). I do not know whether she actually visited the
                    Huntington collection (see RSH 194 n. 16).</note> Several other manuscripts,
                    which she deliberately omitted from her appendix, can be found transcribed in
                    papers among her working notes on the juvenilia (HGVP, box F), but these
                    manuscripts&#x02BC; descriptions are entrusted to Collingwood as a
                    &#x201C;reliable . . . guide through the maze of juvenilia analyzed in his
                    edition of the poems&#x201D; (&#x201C;Dating MSS. of
                    Boyhood,&#x201D; unnumbered cover page). Specifically, she does not discuss
                    what Cook and Wedderburn called MS IA (she lists as her IA what Cook and
                    Wedderburn label IB, but, since her general practice was to maintain earlier
                    designations, I take this to be an unintentional error), and she let stand
                    Collingwood&#x02BC;s descriptions of MSS V through XI. I find much to
                    question, however, in what Viljoen accepts from Collingwood; and, of the
                    manuscripts she does analyze in &#x201C;Dating MSS. of
                    Boyhood,&#x201D; I have found it necessary to revise, at least in part, her
                    datings of MSS IB (i.e., what she calls IA), II, IIA&#x2013;E, III, IIIA,
                    IVA, IVB, IVC, and IVD. Viljoen&#x02BC;s work is an inspiring and
                    invaluable resource, but by no means infallible.</p>
                <p>Critical and biographical interest in Ruskin&#x02BC;s early writings and
                    drawings started with Ruskin himself. He reprinted his earliest compositions in
                    Queen of the Air, Fors Clavigera, and Praeterita to illustrate the lifelong
                    consistency of his thought, pointing out to us the lasting importance of
                    studying his early and later writing together.<note n="9" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    In Queen of the Air, Ruskin &#x201C;risk[ed] whatever charge of folly may come on
                    me, for printing one of my many childish rhymes,&#x201D;
                    since &#x201C;the weak little rhyme&#x201D; powerfully
                    illustrated &#x201C;all that I ever could be, and all that I cannot
                    be&#x201D; (Works, 19:396). With autobiography continuing as a central
                    mode of argument&#x2014;especially in Fors Clavigera and in the
                    autobiography proper, Praeterita, which grew out of passages in
                    Fors&#x2014;Ruskin frequently points to his early writing for origins
                    of his temperament (see, e.g., Works, 35:51&#x2013;57).</note> Ruskin
                    also contributed to the myths and prohibitions that have misdirected, or at
                    least skewed, how and what portions of the early writing should be read. As we
                    approach the centenery of Ruskin&#x02BC;s death, many of those myths and
                    misdirections have been overcome by the exemplary editorial standards set by
                    Viljoen&#x02BC;s unpublished edition of the childhood sermons; Van Akin
                    Burd&#x02BC;s Ruskin Family Letters; James Dearden&#x02BC;s editions
                    of Iteriad and other juvenile poems, and Dearden&#x02BC;s many
                    bibliographic articles; and Dearden and Burd&#x02BC;s edition of the 1830
                    diary (TLC).<note n="10" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Dearden has occasionally rendered previously
                    unpublished poems available through the Bembridge School press, the
                    Yellowsands Press; these printings are listed where appropriate in part
                    1.</note> Among recent critics, Sheila Emerson (RGI), C. Stephen Finley
                    (NC), and John Dixon Hunt (WS) stand out for their recognition that what meets
                    the eye in the Library Edition should not be taken for granted, and for their
                    important insights gained by returning to the archives.<note n="11" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Finley (NC) grounds the study of Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    theology in the unpublished sermons written in boyhood. Among recent
                    biographers, John Dixon Hunt (WS) stands out for his use of the manuscript
                    juvenilia to cut through Ruskin&#x02BC;s later mythologizing of his
                    childhood. For Emerson, see n. 9 above. My own work using unpublished
                    juvenilia includes &#x201C;Ruskin&#x02BC;s Praeterita and Landscape
                    in Evangelical Children&#x02BC;s Education,&#x201D;
                    Nineteenth&#x2010;Century Literature 44, no. 1 (June 1989):
                    45&#x2013;66; &#x201C;Out of the Same Mouth Proceedeth Blessing
                    and Cursing: Ruskin as the &#x2018;Strange Disciple,&#x2019;&#x201D; Modern Philology 90, no. 3 (February
                    1993): 360&#x2013;80; &#x201C;The Psychology of
                    Fragmentation&#x201D;; and &#x201C;Self and
                    Revision.&#x201D;</note> These achievements, however, have been limited
                    to selected segments of the early Ruskin manuscripts. No bibliographic review of
                    the early manuscripts has been attempted since Viljoen&#x02BC;s, and no
                    review has been attempted comprehensively since Collingwood&#x02BC;s, and
                    Cook and Wedderburn&#x02BC;s. Consequently, scholarship has remained
                    haunted by the earlier editors&#x02BC; errors, omissions, and suppressions,
                    and this edition seeks to clear the way for a more thorough and accurate
                    understanding of Ruskin.</p>
                <p>Of the published poems, only a few exist in MS. Most of them have been
                    transcribed by Miss Allen from Mr. George Allen&#x02BC;s copy of
                    &#x201C;Poems. J. R.&#x201D; (STILL EXTANT? <!--Correction needed here?-->); privately printed, 1850;
                    now excessively rare. &#x201C;Salzburg,&#x201D;
                    &#x201C;Andernach,&#x201D; and &#x201C;St. Goar&#x201D; have
                    been taken from &#x201C;Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering&#x201D;
                    (1835)&#x2014;the copy inscribed &#x201C;To John Ruskin from the
                    Publishers.&#x201D; (STILL EXTANT? <!--Correction needed here?-->) Full account of the published poems has
                    been given by Mr. Thomas J. Wise in his &#x201C;Bibliography of the
                    Writings, &#x0026;c., of John Ruskin,&#x201D; part I, Sept. 1889 (printed
                    for subscribers only); of which I have gladly availed myself.</p>
                <p> Is there meaning in the fact that Norton chose early poems to publish in the
                    Atlantic Monthly, knowing he&#x02BC;d violate Wedderburn&#x02BC;s
                    attempted ban on publishing correspondence? (See Dearden, &#x201C;Library
                    Edition of the Works of John Ruskin,&#x201D; 59)</p>
                <p>Autobiographical writing about the childhood, which became the opening two
                    chapters of Praeterita, was published in Fors Clavigera in 1871 and 1874, but
                    these passages did not concern the juvenilia, published or unpublished.</p>
                <p>The first attempt to collect a portion of the youthful writing was Poems by J.R.,
                    a privately printed selection assembled in 1850 by Ruskin&#x02BC;s father,
                    John James Ruskin, with the help of the editor W. H. Harrison. Next, Ruskin
                    became his own editor, when he printed and commented on selected juvenile pieces
                    in Queen of the Air (1869), Fors, Praeterita, and other books. Finally, starting
                    in the 1890s, inspired by the interest in the juvenilia opened up by
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s autobiography, his secretary W. G. Collingwood, his
                    publisher, George Allen, and Cook and Wedderburn compiled editions of selected
                    works.</p>
                <p>Collingwood&#x02BC;s edition of the Poems (1891) was the first to be based
                    on a systematic attempt at manuscript bibliography, although his survey,
                    description, and dating of the manuscripts were limited to the poetry, excluding
                    prose. Cook and Wedderburn reprinted this edition as the core of the second
                    volume of the Library Edition, Poems (1903), extending the core with additional
                    poetry selections, some augmentation of the descriptive bibliography, and a
                    chronological list of the individual poems (but not prose) contained in the
                    major notebooks. Evidence exists that Collingwood also projected an edition of
                    the early prose to complement his edition of the Poems, but that project was
                    abandoned for unknown reasons. That project may be viewed as having been
                    partially realized by Cook and Wedderburn as the first volume of the Library
                    Edition, Early Prose Writings (1903), but that volume is a more slapdash affair
                    than what Collingwood is likely to have envisioned.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, throughout the 1890s, Ruskin&#x02BC;s publisher, George Allen,
                    had been bringing out expensively produced editions of neglected early
                    works&#x2014;The Poetry of Architecture (1893), Three Letters and an Essay
                    Found in His Tutor&#x02BC;s Desk (1893), and Letters to a College Friend
                    (1894). (The popular fairy tale The King of the Golden River had never gone out
                    of print.) Allen&#x02BC;s editions were reasonably careful but not
                    scholarly. His interests lay in producing fine editions; keeping Ruskin in
                    print; and preempting American publishers, who had proved equally resourceful at
                    unearthing forgotten early Ruskin.</p>
                <p>The Library Edition, which began appearing in 1903, was in its time viewed as
                    overzealous, and even imprudent, in presenting all Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    published writing and much of the unpublished, including draft material.<note n="12" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    James S. Dearden, &#x201C;The Library Edition of the
                    Works of John Ruskin,&#x201D; Book Collector 44, no. 1 (spring 1995):
                    52&#x2013;53.</note> In fact, to speak only of the first two volumes,
                    the edition was highly selective. Those volumes were compiled hastily because,
                    as revealed in Allen&#x02BC;s letters, the publisher was rushing the
                    editors in order to deliver introductory volumes to subscribers by a promised
                    date. It was merely to get the job done, therefore, that Cook and Wedderburn
                    relied heavily on Collingwood&#x02BC;s and Allen&#x02BC;s editions of
                    the 1890s to fill the first two volumes. True, the editors of the Library
                    Edition did trouble to bring to light some previously unpublished or long
                    unreprinted juvenilia, but what they added to Collingwood&#x02BC;s work was
                    laden with error. Their textual notes were haphazard and incomplete; they based
                    bibliographic details on Ruskin&#x02BC;s unconfirmed reminiscences in
                    Praeterita; and they neglected to devote the time and attention required to
                    decipher Ruskin&#x02BC;s complex juvenile notebooks. Because Ruskin used
                    these notebooks nonsequentially and intermittently over many years, their
                    contents are easily misdated and misconstrued. Collingwood was a far more
                    fastidious editor, yet even he misdated one entire notebook and large sections
                    of others. Collingwood&#x02BC;s successors merely took his conclusions for
                    granted while compounding the errors.</p>
                <p>Allen&#x02BC;s rushed schedule also encouraged Cook and Wedderburn to leave
                    in place Collingwood&#x02BC;s decision to treat poetry and prose separately
                    since that arrangement enabled them to construct the first two volumes of the
                    Library Edition from materials that lay ready to hand&#x2014;the first
                    volume, especially, being assembled from existing Allen publications. The
                    separation of prose and poetry, however, imposes a questionable distinction on
                    the interpretation of the manuscript notebooks and uncritically carries forward
                    the agenda of Ruskin&#x02BC;s father and W. H. Harrison in the Poems by
                    J.R. of 1850. This was a nostalgic project in resuscitating Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    abandoned career as a poet, which Ruskin himself resented as an implied
                    criticism of the critic he chose to become instead. Thirty&#x2010;five
                    years later in Praeterita, Ruskin got his revenge by constructing a tragicomic
                    narrative of his supposed failure in poetry (bound up with his ridiculous
                    failure as a lover, as he tells it), a story suffused with ambivalence about his
                    parents&#x02BC; influence on his emotional life. Ironically, the rare book
                    marketplace responded to the tale by driving up the price of the scarce Poems of
                    1850, a situation that T. J. Wise exploited by forging other, allegedly
                    forgotten printings of juvenilia. By the early 1900s, Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    editors had caught on to Wise (prodding Carter and Pollard&#x02BC;s later
                    full&#x2010;scale exposure), but they left in place the decision to treat
                    poetry and prose separately, without considering how such decisions were
                    involved in family conflicts over Ruskin&#x02BC;s vocation and his
                    self&#x2010;presentation as an author. These conflicts resurfaced in
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s late works, when his circle attempted to control his mental
                    illness by regulating controversial aspects of his
                    authorship&#x2014;control that Ruskin explicitly and angrily associated
                    with his parents&#x02BC; regulation of his writing in childhood and
                    youth.</p>
                <p>An example of how the editors played into the family psychological drama
                    symbolized by the editing of the early work was their preoccupation with
                    identifying Ruskin&#x02BC;s first publication. This
                    problem&#x2014;finally resolved as late as 1994, when J. S. Dearden
                    discovered a poem published in 1829<note n="13" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    James S. Dearden, &#x201C;John Ruskin&#x02BC;s First Published
                    Work,&#x201D; Book Collector 42, no. 2 (summer 1994):
                    299&#x2013;300.</note>&#x2014;was prompted by Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    story in Deucalion (1875&#x2013;83) that his first publication was an 1834
                    scientific paper.<note n="14" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    In the Catalogue of the Rudimentary Series
                    of drawings at the Oxford schools, and in Deucalion, Ruskin attributes his
                    first appearance in print to his two 1834 papers for Loudon&#x02BC;s
                    Magazine of Natural History (Works, 21:243, 26:275).</note>
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s story, although replete with a colorful anecdote about his
                    father&#x02BC;s pride in this publication, was pure wish fulfillment since,
                    for reasons that Emerson has explored, Ruskin preferred to have it known that he
                    had debuted as an empirical, not an imaginative, writer. Nonetheless, the
                    alleged memory was sufficient warrant to enshrine the 1834 paper as
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s &#x201C;first publication&#x201D; in a
                    bibliography by R. H. Shepherd (1878);<note n="15" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    Richard Horne Shepherd, The Bibliography of Ruskin: A Bibliographical List, Arranged
                    in Chronological Order of the Published Writings in Prose and Verse (New
                    York: John Wiley, 1878), 9. See also Thomas J. Wise and James P. Smart,
                    comps., A Complete Bibliography of the Writings in Prose and Verse of John
                    Ruskin, 2 vols. (1893; reprint, London: Dawsons, 1964), 1:302&#x2013;3,
                    2:111.</note> and the story about Ruskin&#x02BC;s development as at
                    heart a scientific writer remained so persuasive that
                    Collingwood&#x2014;after discovering a poem he recognized as having been
                    published prior to 1834, and even printing that poem (without comment) in the
                    1891 Poems&#x2014;maintained in his 1893 Life of John Ruskin that the
                    Master &#x201C;began his literary career&#x201D; as the
                    &#x201C;analytic John Ruskin . . . already an enfant terrible&#x201D;
                    of empirical prose argument.<note n="16" type="bibliographical" place="botwin" resp="#DCH">
                    W. G. Collingwood, The Life and Work of John Ruskin, 2 vols. (Boston: Houghton
                    Mifflin, 1893), 1: 57.</note> The fact that Ruskin first appeared publicly
                    as a poet, not a prose writer, was finally admitted in the Library Edition
                    (albeit attached to the wrong poem with the wrong date); nonetheless, that
                    edition persisted in giving priority to Early Prose Writings as volume 1, with
                    Poems following in second place.</p>
                <p>The selection of poems for the 1891 Poems and the Library Edition was likewise
                    influenced by late&#x2010;century biographical and autobiographical
                    considerations. According to an inconspicuous comment in the 1891 Poems,
                    Collingwood was instructed&#x2014;he does not say by whom&#x2014;to
                    publish &#x201C;only such verses as are of sufficient completeness to stand
                    alone.&#x201D; (270) A ban on fragments is a notably
                    un&#x2010;Ruskinian approach, in light of such inventions as Fors, with its
                    open&#x2010;ended, indefinitely expandable, and variable public letter. Yet
                    the caveat was followed to extremes by Collingwood, Cook, and Wedderburn, who
                    not only omitted fragments but also punctuated, rearranged, and reworded lines
                    of poetry and even combined unrelated stanzas, presumably to bestow greater
                    polish on the draft&#x2010;like, often open&#x2010;ended character of
                    the compositions.</p>
                <p>Another caveat constructing and constructed by the late&#x2010;century
                    presentation of Ruskin&#x02BC;s childhood was the exclusion of poems with
                    gothic, often violent imagery, which the editors of the Library Edition
                    pronounced &#x201C;morbid.&#x201D; 2:279 n. 1 To them, such writing
                    must have appeared to conflict with the image of the obedient child in the
                    garden that prevails in Praeterita. Since these &#x201C;morbid&#x201D;
                    earlier works were in most cases left unfinished, one is tempted to argue that,
                    in both their frequent representation of violence and their fragmentation in
                    itself, the poems must have issued from psychological disturbance. If so, it may
                    well have been the suggestion of psychological disturbance in the fragmentation,
                    more than the untidiness of fragments per se, that was decreed unfit for the
                    late&#x2010;century editions of the juvenilia. Similarly, Ruskin, when
                    writing his autobiography, was determined to suppress anger and
                    resentment&#x2014;disruptive emotions that did nonetheless ultimately
                    fragment and silence that book. The editions of juvenilia that followed imposed
                    the control that Ruskin himself was no longer able to master.</p>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>