<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">City of London</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-26">October 26, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">City of London</head>
                <p>In &#x201C;Harry and Lucy . . . Vol 1&#x201D; (chap. 1), when Mamma mentions that Papa has gone to the &#x201C;city&#x201D;, 
                    she refers to the &#x201C;general name for London within the gates and within the bars&#x201D; 
                    (Cunningham, <hi rend="italic">Hand-book of London</hi> 121). By the early
                    nineteenth century, the gates and bars had been removed, except for Temple Bar,
                    designed by Wren after the Great Fire.</p>
                <div>
                    <head type="section">Billiter Street and the Premises of Ruskin, Telford, and Domecq</head>
                    <p>For Walter Besant writing at the end of the nineteenth century, 
                        the district of the City where John James Ruskin worked was defined by the ancient boundaries of two gates, 
                        Aldgate in the east and Bishopsgate on the north. Leadenhall Market marked one of the district's oldest functions, 
                        while a more modern landmark was the headquarters of the East India Company. The district also contained the Jewish quarter 
                        (Besant, London City, 146). In Ruskin's youth, the East India House was the 1799 neoclassical structure, 
                        featuring an Ionic portico; and in the year of Ruskin's birth, James Mill began his career in the building, 
                        with his son, John Stuart, starting work there as a clerk four years later 
                        (Wheatley, London Past and Present, 2:2-3).</p>
                    <p>The business premises of Ruskin, Telford, and Domecq was located in Billiter Street, 
                        which runs between Leadenhall and Fenchurch Streets. Once called a lane, 
                        Billiter Street is very old, its structures having escaped the
                        Great Fire. By the eighteenth century, observers regarded the street's buildings as antiquated and "mean" 
                        except for those built in their own time in Billiter Square, on the west side of the street. 
                        Billiter Square square was considered &#x201C;airy&#x201D; and lined with &#x201C;good new brick buildings, 
                        very well inhabited&#x201D;, according to eighteenth-century sources quoted 
                        in the 1850 Hand-book of London, which also notes that, from the beginning of the nineteenth century, 
                        those residences were gradually converted to businesses 
                        (Cunningham, <hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book of London</hi>, 54; 
                        Besant, <hi rend="italic">London City</hi>, 150). 
                        One of these respectable buildings in Billiter Sreet was owned by Henry Telford, 
                        who became the sleeping partner in the firm of Ruskin, Telford, and Domecq 
                        (Hilton, John Ruskin: The Early Years, 6).</p>
                    <p>In the 1820s and 1830s, besides John James's firm, other import businesses were headquartered in the neighborhood, 
                        such as the large West India House, which operated the West India Docks 
                        (Chancellor, <hi rend="italic">Squares of London</hi> 385). For such companies, 
                        Billiter Street was convenient to the London Docks, which were situated east of the nearby Tower of London. 
                        A more auspicious neighbor for Ruskin's career was the shop of Smith, Elder, 
                        first located in Fenchurch Street, around the corner from Billiter Street, 
                        where the company supplied stationery to the East India Company, 
                        and later located in Cornhill, where the company went on to develop its publishing arm 
                        (see Smith, Elder, &#x0026; Company).</p>
                    <p>According to the 1891 updated edition of the Hand-book of London, 
                        toward the end of the nineteenth century Billiter Street became "very different" 
                        with the erection of "large and lofty piles of offices" and "a handsome avenue opened to Lime street", 
                        which runs parallel to Billiter Street (Wheatley, London Past and Present, 1:185).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="section">The London Docks</head>
                    <p>In &#x201C;Harry and Lucy . . . Vol. 1&#x201D;, Mamma remarks to Lucy that Papa has &#x201C;got to go to
                        . . . the city and then to the docks&#x201D; (chap. 1), and Ruskin later
                        includes an illustration, &#x201C;Harry’s Dock,&#x201D; [Plate] &#x201C;8,&#x201D; [&#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol.
                        1] <!--Correction needed here?-->. By the 1820s, when Ruskin was writing, 
                        new docks had been recently completed or were under construction to service the enormous increase in trade. 
                        Over the course of the eighteenth and early nineteebth centuries, rapidly growing congestion at the quays had became untenable, 
                        causing damage to ships, and creating conditions of lax control that resulted in huge losses due to thievery and smuggling. 
                        Consequently, the legislative and engineering feat of constructing new wetdocks within the first decade of the nineteenth century was celebrated as a
                        testimonial to England’s commercial might (though the new docks would soon be made obsolete by growing size of ships powered by steam). 
                        To manage trade with India, the new West India Docks were built in the Isle of Dogs, 
                        and the new East India docks arose at Blackwall. Closer to the City, 
                        the new London Docks were built at Wapping. As Ruskin was writing his first 
                        &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; volume, the St. Katherine Dock was under construction near the
                        Tower. It opened in 1828 (Marriott, Beyond the Tower, 96-103).</p>
                    <p>Initially, Ruskin, Telford and Domecq must have done business at the London Docks in
                        Wapping, opened in 1805, since it held a twenty-one-year monopoly on imports of tobacco, rice, wine and brandy,
                        other than the Indies trade (a monopoly that backfired during the Napoleonic Wars, when imports of wine were disturbed). 
                        When the monoply expired, and a free-trade legislature was disinclined to renew it, 
                        the case made for the openly competitive St. Katherine Dock was led, among others, by wine merchants 
                        who complained that the London Docks lacked adequate warehousing for the barrels that now crowded in shipments 
                        from the reopened Continent
                        (Broodbank, <hi rend="italic">History of the Port of London</hi>, 1:114, 140, 157).</p>
                    <p>John Marriott comments that the London docks, "more than any other feature of the industrial landscape", 
                        acquiried "extraordinary symbolic power" as representing "metropolitan modernization", 
                        yet "the vast body of casual labourers" unsteadily employed there "struck at the very heart of the social, moral and political 
                        concern exercising the minds of nineteenth-century middle-class observers in London, who . . . singled out the figure 
                        of the casual dockworker as the most degraded form of human existence"
                        (Beyond the Tower, 104, 107).
                        In Fors Clavigera, letter 12 (December 1871), 
                        Ruskin perhaps meant to invoke such an impression when referring to "the men at St. Catherine's Docks . . . under Tower Hill", 
                        who by implication rank among the lowest and most neglected of the "host of earth". Perhaps this reference was also personal, 
                        meant to include his own family among the "religious friends" he mocks in the letter as claiming to "'have nothing to do with it--you 
                        are very sorry for it--[but] . . . the power of England is coal'"
                        (Ruskin, Works, 27:206, 205, 204).
                    </p>
                    <!--<p>The appearance of warehouses was determined by &#x201C;requirements of structural
                        stability and fire protection,&#x201D; and remained consistent from the Great Fire of
                        the seventeenth century through the twentieth century. Materials were brick,
                        timber for floors, and tiles or slate for roofs, although cast iron was used for
                        columns and reinforcements from the early 1800s. Of interest for the Ruskin
                        firm, for wine and spirits at the London docks &#x201C;an important feature . . . was
                        the vaults . . . beneath quay level.&#x201D; These were wide barrel vaults resting on
                        stone or cast&#x2010;iron columns (Tucker, &#x201C;Warehouses in Dockland&#x201D; 22, 24, 26). </p>
                    <p>Transport from the city to the docks was at first by omnibus. River steamers were
                        in service by the mid&#x2010;1830s; and soon thereafter, rail lines, among the first in
                        the kingdom, ran to Greenwich and Blackwall (Pearsall, &#x201C;Dockland Transport&#x201D;
                        145&#x2013;46). For John James, the trip would not have been far from the premises of
                        Ruskin, Telford, and Domecq, which were housed in Billiter Street (see City of
                        London).</p>
                    <p>Shortly prior to these
                        developments, Thomas Pennant described Blackwall and Wapping as miles of
                        streets, &#x201C;inhabited by multitudes of seafaring men, alternate occupants of sea
                        and land: their floating tenements . . . before them. In fact, the whole river,
                        from the bridge, for a vast way, is covered with a double forest of masts, with
                        a narrow avenue in mid-channel&#x201D; (Pennant, <hi rend="italic">History of
                            London</hi> 2:56).</p>-->
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>