<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="HMT">Heidi M. Toloudis</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#HRB">Hannah R. Bourgeois</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-25">October 25, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="bibliographical">
                <head type="title"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</head>
                <!--START-->              <p><title type="book" corresp="JRPOEMS8D1891"><hi rend="italic">The Poems of John Ruskins</hi></title>, edited by <!-- refs to Allen and Collingwood biographical note as well as persName tags --><ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="collingwood_w_g_note.php"><persName corresp="WGC">W. G. Collingwood</persName></ref>, 
      was published by <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="allen_george_note.php"><persName corresp="GA">George Allen</persName></ref> in <date when="1891">1891</date>. The two&#x2010;volume edition was released in the two forms that, by then, 
      <persName corresp="GA">Allen</persName> had established on a plan that was profitable while remaining responsive to <persName corresp="JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s standards of quality in making books and ideas of fair trade in selling and distributing them. 
                    For modest consumers, <persName corresp="GA">Allen</persName> made the two volumes available for ten shillings net, in the sturdy and serviceable <!-- ref to note-->Uniform Edition. 
      For collectors, he produced a deluxe edition, lavishing his craftsman&#x02bc;s love for fine bookmaking on what his <date when="1900">1900</date> advertisement described as 
      &#x201c;a Large Edition, with 23 Illustrations in Photogravure from Drawings by the Author and Facsimiles of MSS. Medium 4to&#x201d;, priced at thirty shillings for the two volumes 
      (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#DAWSONPEOPLESRUSKIN"><persName corresp="PDAWSON">Dawson</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="DAWSONPEOPLESRUSKIN"><hi rend="italic">The People&#x02bc;s Ruskin, ii</hi></title></ref>). Even in the Uniform Edition, a few manuscript facsimiles were bound into volume 1, 
                    these embellishments evidently being deemed necessary to the reader&#x02bc;s experience of the boyhood poems, 
                    as well as to the reader&#x02bc;s witness of <!-- ref to note--> <persName corresp="JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s Handwriting, which was integral to <persName corresp="WGC">Collingwood</persName>&#x02bc;s arguments for dating the poems.</p>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Genesis of the Project</head>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">The Provocation of American Literary Piracy</head>
                        <p>Sporadic evidence suggests that plans for publication of the poems developed over a number of years. 
                            Presumably, from <persName corresp="JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s standpoint, his father&#x02bc;s private publication of <!-- ref to note plus title tag-->Poems by J. R. (1850) had brought to a close 
                            any perceived need for further collecting of the poem. Ironically, it was the existence of that private publication that, 
                            because of its rarity and growing interest as a collector&#x02bc;s item, prompted the American publisher 
                            <orgName corresp="JWILEY">John Wiley &#x0026; Sons</orgName> in <date when="1882">1882</date> to compile an unauthorized edition, 
                            <!-- title tag --><title type="book" corresp="JRPOEMS1886"><hi rend="italic">Poems by John Ruskin</hi></title> &#x201c;collected and edited&#x201d; 
                            by <persName corresp="JOWRIGHT">John Osborne Wright</persName> from texts originally published in the annuals. The wording of the title page was clearly designed 
                            to evoke the sought&#x2010;after Poems by <persName corresp="JR">J. R.</persName> &#x201c;collected | <date when="1850">1850</date>&#x201d;; and its preface highlighted the rising desirability of the <date when="1850">1850</date> volume 
                            in the rare&#x2010;book market, where &#x201c;copies have become virtually inaccessible except to the most rabid bibliomaniac, 
                            whose heavy purse enables him to successfully outbid competitors in the auction room and bookstore&#x201d;. 
                            A footnote pointed to the sale of copy in <placeName corresp="LONDON">London</placeName> two years earlier for 41 guineas 
                            <!-- biblioigraphy _-->(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRPOEM1886"><title type="book" corresp="JRPOEMS1886"><hi rend="italic">Poems by John Ruskin</hi></title>, ed. <persName corresp="JOWRIGHT">Osborne</persName></ref>, pp. i, iv). 
                            Certainly, the <persName corresp="JOWRIGHT">Osborne</persName> edition constituted a response the phenomenon of 
                            <!-- ref to note -->Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries. 
                            However disingenuously, <persName corresp="JOWRIGHT">Osborne</persName>&#x02bc;s preface conveys an impression that the edition was justified a public service, 
                            by bringing a rare and expensive resource within reach of the common reader.</p>
                        
                        <p><persName corresp="JR">Ruskin</persName> reacted aggressively to counter what he perceived as piracy, but his reaction was complicated by his ambivalence toward his early writings. 
                            Writing in <date when="1882">1882</date> to <persName corresp="AW">Alexander Wedderburn</persName>, he fumed&#x2014;less at piratical practices by American publishers and at the opportunistic reprint trade 
                            by English publishers, which increasingly worried <persName corresp="GA">George Allen</persName> (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#DAWSONGEORGEALLENOFSUNNYSIDE"><persName corresp="PDAWSON">Dawson</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="DAWSONGEORGEALLENOFSUNNYSIDE"><hi rend="italic">George Allen of Sunnyside</hi></title></ref>, 22, 25-26)&#x2014;and more at English law, 
                            half&#x2010;playfully holding Wedcderburn personally responsible for his profession as a barrister: &#x201c;what a beast British law is! 
                            I'm obliged to print these&#x2014;at least a lot out of&#x2014;these idiotisms&#x2014;because another fellow&#x2014;a blackguard&#x2014;called Wily! [punning on Wiley's name]&#x2014;has 
                            published them without my leave&#x2014;copyright of Friendships Offering being out! Theft &#x0026; libel in one!&#x201d; 
                            To Ruskin, literary piracy was mere theft, whether at home or abroad, another way in which authors were denied 
                            fair pay in the tangled system of book dealing, from which he had attempted to extricate his work by setting up Allen as his personal publisher. 
                            As Brian Maidment has argued, however, Ruskin's seemingly personalized complaints were more broadly polemical 
                            than the resigned reaction of some other British writers to American piracy 
                            (Maidment, "John Ruskin, George Allen, and American Pirated Books", 7-8). 
                            As Ruskin states in his letter, the Wiley edition presented a "libel" combined with a theft, 
                            meaning that he was embarrassed by inadequate copyright law that compelled him to protect his property as a writer, 
                            while disowning the quality of the poems as "idiotisms". With only seeming irrelevance, the letter goes on to call out Wedderburn 
                            for "your profession" for "mak[ing] <hi rend="underline">me</hi> pay 300 pounds for calling Whistler a coxcomb!"--referring 
                            to J. A. M. Whistler's 1878 libel case against Ruskin for the critic's disparaging comments about 
                            Nocturne in Black and Gold: The Falling Rocket (1875), a case in which the artist won 
                            only a pyrrhic victory of a farthing in damages, while the artist plaintiff and critic defendant had to split court costs 
                            (Ruskin to A. Wedderburn, 7 February 1882, in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ALSJRTOAW">Ruskin ALS to Alexander Dundas Ogilvy Wedderburn, 1874&#x2013;1888</ref>; 
                            an unknown hand docketed this letter "83" in pencil above Ruskin's "82" for the year).</p>
                        
                        <p>Ruskin's mercurial analogy equates the American painter's coxcomb "impudence" of "flinging a pot of paint in the public face" 
                            with the "blackguard" wiliness of the American publisher scooping up Ruskin's unprotected property and tossing it 
                            into an overheated book market, which its editor pretends to disparage while capitalizing on the exaggerated prices surrounding Ruskin's poems. 
                            Ruskin leaves unsaid whether it is the edition or the poems themselves that constitute a "libel" on his reputation. 
                            Would he have conceded the logic of Whistler's self-defense that the pricing of any portion of his work ought to be calibrated according to the artist's 
                            "knowledge of a lifetime"? Given the biographical approach that Collingwood would adopt in his preface to his own edition of the Poems, 
                            Whistler's argument seems supported by the value Collingwood places on juvenilia for its "peculiar interest" as a witness to "development" and "growth" 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:xix; 
                            <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:v).b</p>
                        
                        <p>George Allen persisted in the struggle against American piracy for fair legal protections, 
                            but Collingwood's edition played little part. Although published in the year of the International Copyright Act ("Chace Act"), 
                            the 1891 Poems did not profit by the agreement, which applied only to new works published after 1891. 
                            Nonetheless, Collingwood's edition was published in the U.S. legally, as part of the "Brantwood Edition" of Ruskin's works, 
                            which was produced under an agreement with the New York firm, Charles E. Merrill &#x0026; Co. While the 
                            Brantwood Edition did not prove very profitable, it did pay royalties to the author 
                            while upholding Ruskin's expectations for quality of bookmaking. This venture provided the foundation 
                            for Allen's subsequent attempts to arrive at mutually satisfactory terms with the Merrill Company 
                            for producing and marketing an "honest Ruskin" edition in the U.S., but which led only to suspicion and grievance on both sides 
                            (see Maidment, "John Ruskin, George Allen, and American Pirated Books").</p>
                        
                        <p>As Dearden remarks, each of the Brantwood Edition volumes carried an introduction by Charles Eliot Norton, 
                            with the sole exception of Poems (Dearden, "The Library Edition", 52). Probably, no prefatory remarks were needed, 
                            since Poems was a new work with an introduction of its own by Collingwood, as opposed to the older works making up 
                            most of the twenty-two volumes of the Brantwood Edition, which it was hoped would gain renewed value through Norton's commentary, 
                            helping to justify its price against competition by the cheap American piracies.</p>
                        
                        <p>According to Maidment, the first book by Ruskin that Allen succeeded in bringing out in full compliance with the strenuous regulations 
                            of the Chace Act was <title type="book" corresp="#JRVERONARIVERS"><hi rend="italic">Verona and Its Rivers</hi></title>, 
                            published in the U.S. and Britain simultaneously in 1893 ("John Ruskin, George Allen, and American Pirated Books", 15-16). 
                            While protection specifically under the Chace Act eluded the 1891 Poems, Allen and Merrill and Co. were at least able to use the inclusion of Collingwood's edition 
                            in the Brantwood Edition to help advertise the case for honesty in Ruskin publishing. In an August 1890 
                            full-page advertisement in the New York magazine The Critic, Merrill and Co. placed an "important announcement", which laid out the terms whereby it was to be understood that
                            "Ruskin's Works will hereafter be published in America by Messrs. CHARLES E. MERRILL &#x0026; CO., of New York, 
                            who will issue the only authorized editions":</p>
                            <floatingText>
                                    <body>
                                        <div type="prose">
                                            <p>In accordance with a contract with Mr. Ruskin's English publishers, . . . we have the pleasure of announcing 
                                                the publication of the Brantwood Edition of Ruskin's Works in 21 volumes. <hi rend="italic">This is the only 
                                                edition published in this country with Mr. Ruskin's consent, and from the sale of which he derives a profit.</hi> 
                                                The illustrations have been prepared under the author's personal supervision. and the type, paper and style of binding 
                                                are in accordance with his suggestions. Each of the prose works contains a special introduction by Prof. Charles Eliot Norton, 
                                                of Harvard College, explaining the purposes for, and the conditions under which it was writien. These introductions from the pen 
                                                of Mr. Ruskin's most intimate friend and most acute and sympathetic critic, many of them containing extracts from personal letters written 
                                                while the works were in preparation, give to this edition a rare and unique value. The two volumes of poetry written between the ages 
                                                of seven and twenty-six, with an appendix of later poems now first collected from original manuscript and printed sources, 
                                                are edited in chronological order, with notes biographical and critical, by Mr. Ruskin's secretary, William G. Collingwood, M.A. 
                                                The chronological arrangement of the poems--the author's age at the time of writing being printed at the top of each page--illustrates 
                                                in a most interesting manner the development of his mind and style. The two volumes of poems have been copyrighted in this country under the new law, 
                                                and the attention of the public is called to the fact that, by virtue of this copyright, we shall hereafter be 
                                                <hi rend="italic">the only publishers in this country able to supply Ruskin's works in a uniform style of binding</hi>. 
                                                This edition is intended to include what Mr. Ruskin and his literary advisers regard as the essential and permanent part of his writings.</p>
                                            <p>The unillustrated volumes, bound in dark green cloth, will be sent by mail, postpaid, on receipt of $1.50 each, 
                                                and the illustrated volumes for $2.75.</p>
                                            <p>All English editions of Ruskin now in print are kept in stock or will be imported at short notice.</p>
                                            <p>(The Critic 18, new ser., no. 548 [20 August 1892]: 102)</p>
                                        </div>
                                    </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        <p>The same issue carried a brief commentary claiming that "wily travellers" from Britain come to America to "buy the Wiley reprints" 
                            of "England's highly-prized but higher-priced Apostle of High Art", and return to "smuggle them into the right little, tight little island where the writer lived", 
                            since "'We can't afford to buy Ruskin at home, you know'". Emphasizing that "[o]ur laws permitted the American publisher 
                            to appropriate the work of any foreign author", and that "the Messrs. Wiley might have reprinted Mr. Ruskin's books as long as they liked 
                            without asking any one's consent", the writer nonetheless alleged that Wiley &#x0026; Sons "had tried to get the author's consent 
                            and had even sent him a check as a matter of business courtesy. But Mr. Ruskin withheld his approval and rejected the proffered payment" (pp. 94-95).</p>
                    </div>
                    <!--STOP-->
                </div>
                <div type="section"
                    >
                    <p>
                        
                         and 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="history_of_bibliography_and_editing_note.php">History of Bibliography and Editing of the Early Manuscripts</ref>). 
                    </p>
                    <p>Instigated by American edition. Letter to AW. American edition cites sale prices. Why reissued?</p>
                    <p>Collectors. See <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.php">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>. 
                        By the <date notBefore="1890" notAfter="1899">1890s</date>, the privately printed and distributed <date when="1850">1850</date> edition of the <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> had taken on a talismanic aura for rare book collectors, 
                        and <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> inevitably justified the purposes of the <date when="1891">1891</date> edition in part by appealing to the &#x201C;no idle curiosity . . .  that prompts the admirers 
                        of Mr. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s works to collect his boyish writings and to learn the story of his youth.&#x201D;. But he also denies playing to this audience, 
                        arguing that Ruskin is "misunderstood by the casual reader" etc. (v-vi).
                    </p>
                    <p>In his editorial rationale, <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>, admitted that the poems&#x02BC; &#x201C;author himself has never brought them forward,&#x201D; 
                        it being &#x201C;impossible for him to offer his own juvenile productions as examples of the lofty ideal he preached&#x201D; in his attempt to elevate 
                        &#x201C;the public taste in poetry as well as art&#x201D; (a half truth, since <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> did occasionally quote from his juvenilia, 
                        with precisely the purpose of showing that they adumbrated his ideals). <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>, however, was determined to shape the corpus 
                        of early writing in favor of the &#x201C;sonorous line and noble thought&#x201D;, the &#x201C;genuine feeling and fine, enthusiastic description&#x201D;. 
                        Without expurgating irony and fun, <persName corresp="#WGC">the editor</persName> felt obliged to present the consistency of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s 
                        &#x201D;ways, and aims, and attitude&#x201D;&#x2014;conditions that &#x201D;in his case, more than with&#x201D; other writers, were &#x201D;determined at an early age, 
                        and illustrated in his early writings. That is the recurrent burden of his autobiography:&#x2014;&#x2018;I find in myself nothing whatsoever <hi rend="italic">changed</hi>&#x2019;&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:xx&#x2013;xxi, xxviii, xx; and 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:vii, xv, vi; and see 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 35:00).</p>
                    <p>Although printed in the back of volume 1 like an appendix, the &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#POEMS8D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:261&#x2013;67; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#POEMS4D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:???) 
                        probably reflects in its title the accurate relation of the "Note" to the remainder of the edition. As a "preliminary" effort, the descriptive bibliography dates at least in part to 1889 or earlier, 
                        on the evidence of the binding history of MS XI. In the "Note," Collingwood describes MS XI as "an envelope containing loose papers," 
                        whereas in its present state this manuscript is bound in several volumes. These bindings originated in 1889 at the latest, although the physical and documentary evidence is obscured and somewhat muddled 
                        (see MS XI: Description). Thus, while Collingwood apparently failed to revise his "Note" to reflect ongoing efforts respecting the manuscripts' preservation and provenance--efforts that may 
                        have been beyond his ken (see Provenance of Early Manuscripts at Denmark Hill and Brantwood)--the "Note" does record a "preliminary" stage of the editorial project. And this makes sense, 
                        as the note's stated purpose is to justify the chronology that Collingwood used to arrange the edition: "After some study of these ancient Codices, . . . the Editor has been able to disentangle their contents 
                        and to arrange them in chronological order; which it may be worth while to note here, both for the assistance of future students, and in jusification of the hypothetical dates assigned to some of the poems" 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#POEMS8D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:???; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#POEMS4D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:261).</p>
                    <p>"I am happy in the permission to print this and other early unpublished prose writings in a companion volume to these Poems" (1:265).</p>
                    <p>Wise. In particular, <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> was indebted to the collector, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="wise_t_j_note.php">Thomas J. Wise (1859&#x2013;1937)</ref>, 
                        of whose &#x201C;full account of the published poems&#x201D; in the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="bibliography_of_ruskin_wise_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Complete Bibliography of . . . Ruskin</hi> (1889&#x2013;93)</ref> 
                        <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> &#x201C;gladly availed&#x201D; himself (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 
                        1:267; and <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 
                        1:268). <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> was therefore to some degree influenced by <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName>&#x02BC;s manipulation of the bibliographical record in favor of juvenile poems 
                        that <persName corresp="#TJW">Wise</persName> could forge in the form of &#x201C;rare&#x201D; pamphlets (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WISERUSKINI">Dearden, &#x201C;Wise and Ruskin I&#x201D;</ref>, 46&#x2013;47; 
                        and <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="forgery_and_piracy_note.php">Forgery and Piracy</ref>).</p>
                    <p>In this instance, <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> avows his responsibility&#x2014;&#x201C;the very few emendations I have presumed to make 
                        are marked by square brackets&#x201D;&#x2014;and while he tended to be much more casual than a twenty&#x2010;first&#x2010;century editor would be 
                        about what emendations needed flagging, we probably can safely assume that these aesthetic &#x201C;emendations&#x201D; were his, and not specifically authorized 
                        by the elderly <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>. In his notes and prefaces to the edition, <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> always refers 
                        to the author&#x02BC;s investment in the edition in the past tense, as having authorized the editor&#x02BC;s judgments but resigned his own responsibility, 
                        consistent with <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>&#x02BC;s general statement that closes his 
                        <title type="bibliography_text" corresp="#COLLINGWOODPREFATORYNOTESPLATES">&#x201C;Prefatory Notes on the Plates&#x201D;</title>: &#x201C;this publication 
                        is in no sense my own enterprise, . . . it had been long contemplated by <persName corresp="#JR">Mr. Ruskin</persName>, and . . . it was put into my hands 
                        in default of better, with instructions which I have endeavoured to carry out faithfully. But as the selection and arrangement have been left entirely to me, 
                        it is only just to the author that I should avow the responsibility&#x201D; (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:281, xi; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:282)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
