<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="provenance_american_research_libraries_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Ruskin Collecting by American Research Libraries in the Twentieth Century</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="contextual">
                <head type="title">Early Ruskin Manuscript Collecting by American Research Libraries</head>
                <p>Holdings of the early Ruskin manuscripts are concentrated American research institutions largely as an outcome of the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date></ref> and the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1931</date></ref>. 
                    The primary buyer at these sales for the American market was the Boston rare book dealer, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="goodspeed_charles_note.php"><persName corresp="#CG">Charles E. Goodspeed</persName> (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1950">1867&#x2013;1950</date>)</ref>, 
                    who sold in turn to Yale University Library and to Princeton University Library. 
                    Another participant stateside in the 1930 sale was the Yale English Department professor and Yale Library keeper of rare books, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="tinker_c_b_note.php"><persName corresp="#CBT">Chauncey Brewster Tinker</persName> (<date notBefore="1876" notAfter="1963">1876&#x2013;1963</date>)</ref>. 
                    although further research is required to clarify Tinker's role beyond serving as Yale's agent for purchasing from Goodspeed. 
                    At Princeton, a key figure in securing several of Goodspeed's acquisitions from the 1931 Sotheby's sale for the university library was 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="thorp_willard_note.php"><persName corresp="#WT">Willard Thorp</persName> (<date notBefore="1111" notAfter="1111">0000&#x2013;0000</date>)</ref>.</p>
                
                <p>At these institutions, collecting Ruskin in general, and the early manuscripts in particular, grew out of earlier trends in private collecting, 
                    which led to donations benefiting the libraries. At Yale between the World Wars, collecting of Ruskin and of much else was driven by Tinker, 
                    who advocated for building the library's special collections and encouraged their use by graduate students. Tinker generously opened his personal rare book 
                    and manuscript collection to students' use and persuaded his friend and fellow collector 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="adam_r_b_note.php">R. B. Adam II (1863&#x2013;1940)</ref> to make his collection available as well. 
                    Adam's collection was devoted primarily to Samuel Johnson and his circle, but he also inherited a Ruskin collection from his father, which he built 
                    into one of the most comprehensive print collections of Ruskin in America. Adam donated his Ruskin collection largely intact to Yale University Library in 1929, 
                    just one year previous to the Sotheby's 1930 sale, in which Yale took the opportunity to complement Adam's print collection of Ruskin 
                    with a wide range of manuscripts representative of Ruskin's career and diverse interests. At Princeton, nearly a decade later in 1939, Willard Thorp, 
                    who like Tinker was a professor in the English Department and an advocate for developing the university library's special collections, 
                    dealt with Goodspeed to acquire a representative manuscript collection of Ruskin drawn from acquisitions from the 1931 Sotheby's sale. 
                    Goodspeed's personal collection of printed Ruskin--"its scope . . . enlarged to include all the authorized editions of Ruskin and his biographies" 
                    comprising "more than five hundred volumes"--went to Wellesley College "principally in consideration of Ruskin's interest in the education of girls" 
                    and because his own daughters had graduated from Wellesley (Yankee Bookseller 265). 
                    Goodspeed made the initial donation in 1920 and continued adding to the collection throughout the 1930s and 1940s.</p>
                
                <p>The generation of American collectors represented by Goodspeed, Tinker, and Adam was guided in their Ruskin collecting by the phenomenon of 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.html">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>, 
                    which aspired to comprehensive acquisition of every printed item in the original published state by the modern author of the collector's choice. 
                    Ruskin collectors mirrored this ambition for comprehensiveness, from juvenilia to last words, with selections of drawings, letters, proof sheets and other materials; 
                    and the opportunity for collectors to enhance the scope of manuscript materials to complement print collections was exponentially raised by the two Sotheby's sales. 
                    The bibliographical details concerning those sales and their buyers (insofar as related to ERM) are described in 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date></ref> and the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1931</date></ref>. 
                    The present note discusses factors that influenced Ruskin collecting at particular institutions. The motives animating American libraries&#x02bc; acquisition 
                    of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> manuscript and rare&#x2010;book collections appear to have been tied as much to American aspirations in higher education and evolving ideas about the place of the library in campus life, 
                    as to distinterested investment in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s ideas, architectural or educational. Another, not insignificant factor affecting acquisitions by Ivy League universities 
                    was competition, Princeton envying Yale's larger library holdings, and both eyeing Harvard's vast resources--in the 1930s, the largest research collection 
                    among American universities.
                </p>
                
                <div>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="section">The Sterling Memorial Library and Ruskinian Architecture at Yale</head>
                        
                        <p>In 1930, at the time of Yale Library's acquisition of a Ruskin manuscript collection via Goodspeed's Book Shop 
                            (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php#YALE"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date>: <persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName>, the <date when="1930">1930</date> Acquisitions, and <orgName corresp="#YALEUNIVLIBRARY">Yale University Library</orgName></ref>), 
                            it would not have been lost on <persName corresp="#CBT">Chauncey Tinker</persName> that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> materials formed an appropriate acquisition at the time when the <orgName corresp="#YALEUNIVLIBRARY">Yale Library</orgName> 
                            was moving to the newly completed <placeName type="building" corresp="#STERLINGMEM">Sterling Memorial Building</placeName>. Architecturally, the structure wraps a Gothic cathedral&#x2010; and cloister&#x2010;like shell, 
                            which houses the reading and circulation spaces, around a setback skyscraper tower, containing the stacks and technical operations. 
                            In context of this project, a research collection of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> was perhaps considered appropriate, but not vital, 
                            to discussion about architectural style at <orgName corresp="#YALE">Yale</orgName>.</p>
                        
                        <p>The time was past when <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s ideas were realized directly in designs for Yale's campus buildings. 
                            Ruskinian Gothic flourished from <date when="1864">1864</date>, with P. B. Wight&#x02bc;s (<date notBefore="1838" notAfter="1925">1838&#x2013;1925</date>) design for the Street Fine Arts Building, 
                            through the mid&#x2010;1880s, with Russell Sturgis&#x02bc;s (<date notBefore="1836" notAfter="1909">1836&#x2013;1909</date>) work on Battell Chapel and other buildings. 
                            These men were <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> enthusiasts, and their understanding of his architectural and social ideas found supporters among the faculty 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LYNNBUILDINGYALE"><persName corresp="#CLYNN">Lynn</persName>, &#x201c;Building Yale and Razing It from the Civil War to the Great Depression&#x201d;</ref>, 110&#x2013;18). 
                            But by the <date notBefore="1920" notAfter="1939">1920s&#x2013;30s</date>, Victorian thinking about architecture was being displaced by Bauhaus; 
                            and while Gothic Revival persisted in Yale's campus development, just as "collegiate Gothic" thrived on American campuses elsewhere, 
                            which teachers like Tinker and their students must have connected with their readings in Ruskin, it is questionable 
                            whether Ruskin's ideas retained the force of an ideology for architects of American universities. 
                            According to <persName corresp="#PGOLDBERGER">Paul Goldberger</persName>, the designer of the <placeName type="building" corresp="#STERLINGMEM">Sterling Memorial Library</placeName>, 
                            James Gamble Rogers (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1947">1867&#x2013;1947</date>), was not prone to defend either its neo&#x2010;Gothic design or its skyscraper functionality on ideological grounds. 
                            Rogers&#x02bc;s buildings, Goldberger believes, did not aspire to &#x201c;the same kind of moral authority 
                            that <persName corresp="#AWNP">[Augustus Welby] Pugin&#x02bc;s</persName> or <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s Gothic possessed in the <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth century</date>&#x201d; 
                            and that Wight&#x02bc;s and Sturgis&#x02bc;s campus buildings articulated for <orgName corresp="#YALE">Yale</orgName> a half&#x2010;century earlier; Rogers sought, rather, 
                            &#x201c;to provide pleasure for the eye along with a casual, undemanding association with the past&#x201d; 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GOLDBERGERROGERS">&#x201c;James Gamble Rogers and the Shaping of Yale in the Twentieth Century&#x201d;</ref>, 272).</p>
                        
                        <p>At the same time, the <placeName type="building" corresp="#STERLINGMEM">Sterling building</placeName> epitomized what one historian has characterized as the &#x201c;golden age&#x201d; of the American university library (<date notBefore="1890" notAfter="1940">1890&#x2013;1940</date>), 
                            when free&#x2010;standing, architecturally imposing library buildings were erected at the geographical and intellectual heart of the university campus. 
                            Earlier, in the colonial era, college libraries occupied a single room in a multipurpose building; and then in the nineteenth century, 
                            larger colleges such as <orgName corresp="#YALE">Yale</orgName> constructed dedicated library buildings&#x2014;in either neoclassical or (modeled on the English universities) Gothic Revival styles&#x2014;which 
                            sat on the edge of campus and functioned more as glorified book repositories than as circulating libraries. Starting in the late nineteenth century, 
                            with the erection of vast and imposing library buildings, situated at the center of a revised campus plan, a new message was conveyed: 
                            &#x201c;educators considered these structures to be ennobling, uplifting students by providing them with opportunities for cultural improvement, 
                            whether by studying library books or the building that housed the books&#x201d; (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GYUREHEARTOFTHEUNIVERSITY"><persName corresp="#DAGYURE">Gyure</persName>, &#x201c;The Heart of the University&#x201d;</ref>, passim and 119). 
                            The architectural rhetoric mixed overwhelming cultural authority with individualistic aspiration and enfranchisement&#x2014;values 
                            that are combined in a challenging and disconcerting fashion in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s lectures about books and reading, <title type="book" corresp="#JRSESAME">Sesame and Lilies</title> (<date when="1865">1865</date>). 
                            During the golden age of American university library building, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s book servied as a universal school prize&#x2014;small presentation volumes, 
                            which were tricked out as decoratively within their means as the ornate buildings to which the prizes were meant to direct the grateful recipient.</p>
                        
                        <p>While James Gamble Rogers may have been no ideologue according to <persName corresp="#PGOLDBERGER">Goldberger</persName>, 
                            he did contend for maintaining &#x201c;religion, or at least a version of it, at the Yale center&#x201d;, according to another architectural historian; 
                            like other campus planners and library architects of his period, Rogers proposed &#x201c;creating a new kind of sacred space for the modern American university&#x2014;a 
                            cathedral library laden with quasi&#x2010;religious iconography&#x201d;. Not only did the <placeName type="building" corresp="#STERLINGMEM">Sterling</placeName>&#x02bc;s structural plan encase 
                            &#x201c;the functions of a modern library within the shell of a neo&#x2010;Gothic cathedral&#x201d;; the building&#x02bc;s elaborate decoration scheme of Gothic detail 
                            encompassed an extensive iconographic program, which was perceived as important enough to sacrifice 
                            &#x201c;six tiers of book stacks in order to fund more ornament&#x201d; in stone and wood carving, glass and mural painting, and other media 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GRUBIAKSTERLINGLIBRARY"><persName corresp="#MMGRUBIAK">Grubiak</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#GRUBIAKSTERLINGLIBRARY">&#x201C;Reassessing Yale&#x02BC;s Cathedral Orgy&#x201D;</title></ref>, 171, 174, 178). 
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s books on architecture were well&#x2010;known primers for reading iconographic programs, although the <placeName type="building" corresp="#STERLINGMEM">Sterling</placeName>&#x02bc;s scheme 
                            appears not to have incoporated a direct homage to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#STERLINGLIBRARY">&#x201c;The Sterling Memorial Library&#x201d;</ref>).</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="section">Ruskin and the Building of Special Collections at Princeton University</head>
                        
                        <p>As at Yale, the acquisition of a Ruskin collection at Princeton marked a period of library expansion (see 
                            <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php#PRINCETON"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1931</date>: <persName corresp="#CG">Goodspeed</persName> and <orgName corresp="#PRINCETONLIBRARY">Princeton University Library</orgName></ref>. 
                            However, the chachet of acquiring a Ruskin collection at this juncture was probably less significant for Princeton than for Yale 
                            since the pressing architectural problems were functional rather than aesthetic. Princeton already possessed a Ruskinian-influenced library building, 
                            the Chancellor Green Library (1872), designed in the Venetian polychromatic Gothic style 
                            by William Appleton Potter (1842-1909). The building's octagonal plan--centered on a panopticon-like reference desk, 
                            which was encircled by radiating shelves and reading desks--was responsive to librarians' thinking of the time, 
                            that services should be "tri-partitioned" into staff services, secure stacks, and patron reading areas. 
                            This facility was rapidly outgrown, so the Chancellor Green was extended in 1897, by being joined to the new Pyne Librry--a 
                            more practical rectangular building, designed by Potter in "collegiate" Tudor Gothic 
                            (Wodehouse, &#x201C;William Appleton Potter&#x201D;, 176, 184, 192; 
                            Kaser, <hi rend="italic">Evolution of the American Academic Library Building</hi>, 32-33).</p>
                        
                        <p>Even the combined Chancellor Green and Pyne buildings soon reached capacity, despite what was regarded as an embarrassingly modest pace of growth, 
                            compared to the mammoth collections held by Yale and Harvard. Moreover, the buildings were not designed to accommodate the flexibility and increased usage demanded 
                            by the pedagogical innovations that Woodrow Wilson introduced as president of the university in 1905--the preceptorial method of instruction--and 
                            that were further developed in 1923 as the "Four-Course" plan, which stressed independent and wide-ranging reading. 
                            In 1930, when Yale Library was moving to the new Sterling Building, Princeton took an important step toward addressing these limitations 
                            by organizing the Friends of Princeton University Library. While the Friends was at heart devoted more 
                            to amassing a competitive rare books and manuscript collection for the library than to advocating for brick-and-mortar issues, 
                            they nonetheless gravitated to a natural alliance with the bookish humanities and social sciences faculty, since, as James Axtell remarks, 
                            they expected their donations to be well cared for and used in an up-to-date special collections facility, 
                            as opposed to the dank storage and paltry exhibition space allowed by the Pyne 
                            (Axtell, &#x201C;The Making of the Princeton University Library&#x201D;, 507-10, 513, 521-23).</p>
                        
                        <p>The alignment of these forces is reflected in the funding for the Ruskin purchase from Goodspeed, 
                            which was secured "almost entirely by means of contributions" from the Friends organization, 
                            faculty in the Department of English and Department of Art, and alumni. Among the English Department faculty 
                            were <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="thorp_willard_note.php"><persName corresp="#WT">Willard Thorp</persName></ref>--well-known 
                            to the Frinds, although not a member, and a chief organizer of the Ruskin effort--and Charles Grosvenor Osgood (1871-1964), 
                            a Spenser scholar known for his interdisciplinary approach to literature 
                            (<persName corresp="#LHEYL">Heyl</persName>, <title type="periodical" corresp="#HEYLREPORT_1938-39">&#x201C;Report of the Librarian, for the Year Ending <date notBefore="1938-07-01" notAfter="1939-06-30">June 30, 1939&#x201D;</date></title>, 2; 
                            <title type="essay" corresp="#BIBLIA_1938-39">&#x201C;The Emergency Fund&#x201D;</title>, 34-35). 
                            Osgood had a long-standing interest in Ruskin, having once answered an invitation by the collector 
                            <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="adam_r_b_note.php">Robert B. Adam II</ref> to travel to Buffalo and lecture on the master</p>
                    </div>
                        
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>