<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="seaside_resorts_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Seaside Resorts</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="contextual">
                <head type="title">Seaside Resorts</head>
                <p>The Ruskins frequented seaside resorts during John Ruskin's youth, which coincided with a period of expansion for coastal settlements 
                    that could provide amenities for visitors seeking health and recreation through sea bathing. The growth in fashionable seaside resorts 
                    began in the eighteenth century as an extension of the established season for the inland spas such as Bath and Tunbridge Wells; 
                    and in the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries, the seaside resorts prospered by the incursion of the professional and well-to-do 
                    merchant classes, like the Ruskins, into these elite pleasures. As Londoners, the Ruskins patronized the resorts within easy reach 
                    along the southeast coast such as Sandgate and--especially attractive to the Ruskins--Hastings, 
                    which grew along with the wealth and sophisticaion of the metropolitan middle class 
                    (see Walton, The English Seaside Resort, 6-9, 20, 48). The Ruskins also took advantage of mineral springs at inland spas. 
                    Ruskin's cousin, ??? Ruskin, was a physician at Tunbridge Wells. Later, he was sent to take the cure at Leamington Spa, which,
                    according to Walton, was an exceptional late bloomer among Britain's many spas (Walton, 7).</p>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Health and Sea Bathing</head>
                    <p>In June 1819, Margaret Ruskin "rejoiced" that her husband, John James, was considering sea bathing, 
                        but she advised caution. He should &#x201C;try cautiously the sea&#x201D;, &#x201C;tak[ing] but one plunge 
                        come out instantly rub yourself perfectly dry and if you should feel no cold nor headake try it again 
                        at the interval of the day&#x201D;. If this experiment made him &#x201C;sensible of benefit&#x201D;, 
                        she urged him to &#x201C;stay [at] the seaside as long as business will permit&#x201D; in order to strengthen his health 
                        (Margaret to John James Ruskin, 23 June 1819, <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 95). 
                        Margaret's advice closely echoes text found in <title type="book" corresp="#BUCHANDOMESTICMEDICINE1791"><hi rend="italic">Domestic Medicine</hi></title> 
                        by the Edinburgh physician, William Buchan (1729-1805). First published in 1769 and revised continuously by Buchan through 1803, 
                        this home reference work remained widely popular in Britain and America for a century. 
                        (The book by Buchan that the Ruskins are documented as owning, 
                        <title type="book" corresp="BUCHANCOTTAGEPHYSICIAN">The Cottage Physician</title>, does not contain the text on sea bathing that Margaret quoted, and is not in fact by Buchan at all, 
                        but alleged to have been edited by "W. Buchan, M.D., and the members of a private medical society". First published in 1825, 
                        this manual consists of a farrago of medical advice excerpted from various publications. See 
                        Dearden, Library of John Ruskin, 55 [no. 369]; and Rosenberg, "Medical Text and Social Context", 22, 42.)</p>
                    
                    <p>In the chapter of <title type="book" corresp="#BUCHANDOMESTICMEDICINE1791"><hi rend="italic">Domestic Medicine</hi></title>, 
                        "Cautions concerning Cold Bathing, and Drinking the Mineral Waters",  Buchan concedes that 
                        "it is now fashionable for persons of all ranks to plunge into the sea, and drink the mineral waters", 
                        so he undertakes to provide "hints or cautions" since "many lives are lost, and numbers ruin their health" 
                        by "imprudent use" of these resources. Among those who "ought to be cautious in using the cold bath" and yet 
                        "who stand peculiarly in need of the bracing qualities of cold water" are "nervous" people, including 
                        "a great number of the male, and almost all the female inhabitants of great cities" Lest these urban denizens 
                        cause themselves harm, "[f]or them, . . . the best plan would be to accustom themselves to it [cold bathing] 
                        by the most pleasing and gentle degrees". The recommended method, which Margaret repeated to John James, was 
                        to take "one immersion at a time" and get "rubbed dry the moment" of coming "out of the water" and then 
                        "continue to take exercise for some time after". After this trial, immersions may be repeated 
                        only if the bather is not afflicted by "chilness, loss of appetite, listlessness, pain of the breast or bowels, 
                        a prostration of strength, or violent head-achs" 
                        (Buchan, Domestic Medicine, 633, 637, 639).</p>
                    
                    <p>Buchan had fewer reservations about exposing youths to sea water: "To young people, and particularly to children, 
                        cold bathing is of the last importance. Their lax fibres render its tonic powers peculiarly proper. It promotes their growth, 
                        increases their strength, and prevents a variety of diseases incident to childhood" 
                        (Domestic Medicine, 638). (Starting with the eighteenth edition [1803], the last edition revised by the author, 
                        these remarks were replaced by additional chapters on cold-bathing and on mineral waters; see Domestic Medicine [1805], xii, 576-77. 
                        Margaret Ruskin appears not to have consulted the later edition.)
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Ruskins at Seaside Resorts</head>
                    <p>Besides the salubriousness of seaside resorts, a characteristic that evidently factored into the Ruskins' choice among them 
                        was their respectability along with (or in spite of) their novelty. In 1819, John James made his trial of sea-bathing 
                        at Weymouth, doubtless in part because he happened to have business in Southampton 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 95). 
                        Weymouth also presented prestige, however, having been patronized by the court of George III. 
                        In the last decade of the eighteenth century, the king was prescribed sea bathing to guard against return of his madness. 
                        Weymouth was selected, as already settled with a lodge belonging to his brother, the Duke of Gloucester. 
                        The town was thus assured a place among the most fashionable resorts--a position that an 1815 guidebook to resorts and spas 
                        continued to claim for the post-Georgian period, because Charlotte, the popular Princess of Wales (1796-1817), 
                        spent a summer at Gloucester Lodge and had promised to return. (Instead, she was mourned by the nation by the time of John James's visit.) 
                        According to the guidebook, "within the last twenty or thirty years"--that is, since the advent of royal residence--Weymouth 
                        "was small and meanly built, but by rapid enlargements, and many elegant buildings, it has now become a very respectable place". 
                        By historical statistical measures of elite status among resorts in the first third of the century, Weymouth did rank high and grow fast 
                        (Feltham, Guide to All the Watering and Sea-Bathing Places, 490-91; Walton, The English Seaside Resort, 12, 77-78).</p>
                    
                    <p>The guidebook's invoking the patronage of Princess Charlotte may have been code for diassociating royal Weymouth 
                        from the moral stigma that clung to Brighton owing to its connection with Charlotte's prodigal father, George IV. 
                        The southern coastal resorts may, in any case, have presented the Ruskins with a journey too lengthy for a short summer holiday. 
                        Still, it is telling that for their first visit as a family they chose, from among the southeastern resorts, 
                        a comparatively small and unnoticed place, Sandgate. Even as late as the decades around the turn of the twentieth century,
                        Sandgate ranked one hundreth in population among the nation's resorts (Walton, The English Seaside Resort, 65).</p>
                    
                    <p>The holiday in Sandgate must have occurred in summer 1821, since in January 1822 Margaret looked back fondly on the excursion, 
                        which she framed in terms of homeliness--"I hope . . . we shall be permitted to enjoy our home and english comforts 
                        [in the coming months] and if we are to travel it may only be on such journey as our Sandgate one". 
                        Even John at age three considered Sandgate as the standard for what was "fine and . . . beautiful", comparing its pleasures 
                        favorably to the stone rolling and stick gathering to be had on Duppas Hill in Croydon 
                        (Margaret to John James Ruskin, 30 January 1822, 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 107, 108). 
                        At about the time of their visit, according to the Guide to All the Watering and Sea-Bathing Places, 
                        Sandgate was "a very pretty village", which had "suddenly and deservedly started into notice as a watering place". 
                        It could boast "neither a ball nor assembly room" like nearby Dover, Folkestone, or Hythe, but for the Ruskins 
                        the point probably was that "the lovers of dancing" would gravitate to those resorts, leaving them with the cliffs to walk, 
                        commanding a prospect of the French coast; an Elizabethan castle to admire, its fortress "lately . . . converted into a martello tower", 
                        a reminder of the British victory over Napoleonic France; a "good circulating library; and "lodgings . . . on reasonable terms" (p. 423).</p>
                    
                    <p>For what became the Ruskins' most favored resort, however, what was evidently wanted was a resort that combined 
                        quiet and respectability with somewhat grander pretensions.</p>
                        
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Hastings</head>
                        <p>With a severe glance directed presumably at Brighton, the local author of an 1804 guidebook to Hastings declared 
                            that "[o]ne circumstance must, above all others, render Hastings dear to those who have a regard to morality-—Vice 
                            has not yet erected her standard here;-—the numerous tribe of professional gamblers, unhappy profligates, 
                            and fashionable swindlers find employment and rapine elsewhere. Innocent recreational delight, card assemblies, 
                            billiards, riding, walking, reading, fishing, and other modes of pastime banish care from the mind, 
                            whilst the salubrity of the atmosphere impels disease from the body. The society of Hastings are gay without profligacy, 
                            and enjoy life without mingling in its debaucheries" 
                            (The Hastings Guide, 1-2).</p>
                        
                        <p>Quoting this pronouncement a decade later in 1815, the Guide to All the Watering and Sea-Bathing Places deemed the statement fitting, 
                            but presents Hastings as equivocally poised between decline from its prosperous past as a trading, fishing, and shipbuilding center and its ambition for its rebirth as a tourist resort. 
                            While acknowledging the town's strong suit in its impressive history and romantic landscape, this guidebook description harps on losses: 
                            "The present is a new town; the old one having been swallowed up by an inundation", and the coast continues to erode; 
                            Hastings "had formerly a good harbour", which has lain in ruin since Elizabethan times; "trade . . . is inconsiderable, 
                            compared to what it once enjoyed", though the boat builders continue to maintain a "high reputation"; with "only one inn, properly so called", 
                            "accommodations and attendance are frequently subjects of complaint". Yet Hastings "every year . . . seems to obtain fresh accessions of visitors", 
                            and development is underway: "the promenade lately obtained . . . is a great improvement" 
                            (Feldman, Guide to All the Watering and Sea-Bathing Places, 317, 318, 319, 320-21, 316). Whatever merit these judgments 
                            may have warranted, they at least reflect an ancient coastal town in the process of transforming its economy 
                            from traditional but declining maritime occupations to modern tourism servicing the rising middle class.</p>
                        
                        <p>This entrepreneurial activity may have been what intrigued the Ruskins--particularly John James--when they visited Hastings, probably for the first time in 1826. 
                            The 1820s was the peak decade for Hastings as a resort (Walton, The English Seaside Resort, 58). 
                            Taking advantage of the rising tide of fashion for seeking health and pleasure at the seaside, 
                            the town was turning to account its decayed advantages as a port and fishery, by offering a beachfront well adapted for bathing--a 
                            wide coastal frontage with a gentle declivity for easy access to the sea. The town could also parlay resources 
                            appealing to a broad range of tourist interests during the period. The area was rich with historical asssociations, 
                            and it presented landscape features of interest to seekers both of the picturesque and of natural history. 
                            Such variety and flexibility of touristic resourcees, Walton argues, gave seaside resorts an edge over the older inland spas, 
                            which had little besides their mineral springs to recommend them. Also unlike the traditional spas 
                            with their rigid social codes, the seaside resorts welcomed children (see The English Seaside Resort, 
                            106-7, 16-17, 42-43, 217).</p>
                        
                        <p>Promotion of the emerging resort industry is packaged together with the picturesque and historical appeal of Hastings in illustrated travel publications 
                            of the first two decades of the nineteenth century, which culminate in 1824 with an illustrated history, 
                            The History and Antiquities of the Town and Port of Hastings, by W. G. Moss (dates unknown). As "draughtsman to His Royal Highness the Duke of Cambridge", 
                            Moss created the topographical, architectural, and antiquarian drawings, and he was apparently also responsible for the text. 
                            The work was published by subscription, listing numerous royal subscribers, headed by George IV. 
                            The attention thus garnered may have helped Hastings to build a case for an elite clientele to frequent its seaside. 
                            Notwithstanding the declaration by the Hastings Guide that the town set itself apart from resorts harboring morally disreputable pleasures, 
                            Moss's stately work indicates how a bid for patronage by the Georgian aristocracy could be accommodated along with appeal to the evanglical middle class. 
                            As Walton remarks, the visiting public at the resorts was formed from a "complex pattern of demand", 
                            woven from "differing visiting publics, aristocratic and commercial . . . centered on the metropolis", and reflecting a 
                            "wide range of social attributes, attitudes and expectations, which could be subsumed under each [social] label", including 
                            "many shades of religious commitment" (The English Seaside Resort, 14). A spectrum of desirably polite society could be cultivated 
                            with the aid of an intelligent and appealing print and visual culture.</p>
                        
                        <p>In the preface to History and Antiquities, Moss characterizes himself as an invalid who came to Hastings for convalescence, and discovered 
                            a historical and picturesque treasure "heretofore . . . unnoticed and untouched" save by guidebooks. 
                            He scorns the guides' . . . , making an exception for the Hastings Guide "published a few years since", presumably referring to an edition of guide 
                            which contained an earlier state of Moss's designs, here engraved as outline drawings 
                            (Moss, History and Antiquities . . . of Hastings, xi-xii; Powell, Hastings Guide). After three chapters of 
                            military and ecclesiastical history, chapter four opens by describing the ride to Hastings, 
                            highlighting the "peculiarity and and favourableness of aspect and situation, which render it so well calculated for sea-bathing, 
                            and the restoration of health and convalescence", but taking notice also of the variety of attractions, 
                            such as the "fine walks and rides" that have brought an "influx" 
                            of "visitants and strangers" who have "contributed to . . . [the town's] rising consequence" (p. 123). 
                            The chapter opening is faced by a plate, Entrance from the London Road, featuring a tree-lined avenue leading to the town entrance--a 
                            more intimate view than the treatment of this subject in the 1803 edition of the Hastings Guide, which positions the viewer on the London Road 
                            from a higher vantage, overlooking the town to the sea beyond. In Moss's book, a panoramic prospect is presented from a different angle in the frontispiece, 
                            View from the Minnis Rock, but comparison with the plates in the earlier guidebook shows that the picturesque-worthy scenes were well established.
                            Similarly, both Moss's book and the 1803 Guide contain engravings of a "northwest view" of the castle ruins (see . . . "engraved for Barry's Hastings Guide)</p>
                        
                        <p>The landscape drawings were engraved by Robert Wallis (1794-1878), who was simultaneously building areputation 
                            based on his copper plates of scenes after J. M. W. Turner of other developing seaside resorts--Ramsgate (1824), and Folkestone (1825) 
                            (Hunnisett, Steel-engraved Book Illustration in England, 95). Even the earlier Hastings Guide(?) was "embellished by plates" 
                            (, 
                            however, setting the main focal points of picturesque interest, on which Moss likewise capitalizes--the view of Hastings from the battery, 
                            the view of Hastings from the London Road, 
                            the northwest view of the Hastings Castle ruins, a prospect of Pevensey Bay where William the Conqueror landed in 1066 (frontispiece, 41 opp, 49 opp, 75 opp
                            
                            
                            The society of Hastings are g'ay without profligacy, and enjoy life without mingling in its debaucheries.It was Hastings, however, that won the Ruskins' favor among the many resorts 
                            that beckoned to middle-class holiday makers in the first third of the century 
                            A town and port on the shore (or <hi rend="italic">rape</hi>) of Sussex. In the 1820s, the distance from London was 64 miles. 
                            [Pick up on tourism, Moss 123, 145-46] <!--Entry needed here.--> </p>
                        
                        <p>The vicinity was best known as the historical site of the Battle of Hastings,
                    which, in the language of an 1824 history of the town, &#x201C;changed the destinies .
                    . . of the nation, by annihilating the Saxon dynasty, and substituting that of
                    the Norman in its stead&#x201D; (Moss, <hi rend="italic">Hastings</hi> 1). When the
                    Ruskins visited in 1826, attractions would have included the castle ruins, of
                    which survived &#x201C;a few fragments . . . , presenting grotesque and fantastic
                    forms, from different points in which they may be viewed. The only remains now
                    [in 1824] in any degree perfect, are small portions of a round and square Tower,
                    with a part of the sally-port. Its site is on a rocky cliff on the westward of
                    the Town&#x201D; (Moss, <hi rend="italic">Hastings</hi> 60).</p>
                <p>Of ecclesiastical ruins, &#x201C;gloomy but interesting vestiges of monastic grandeur
                    remain[ed] . . . heighten[ing] the picturesque beauties of the local scenery.&#x201D;
                    The most prominent churches were All Saints, believed to stand &#x201C;in its original
                    state&#x201D; from the early fourteenth century; and St. Clements, parts of which also
                    dated to the fourteenth century (Moss, <hi rend="italic">Hastings</hi> 78, 97,
                    112). </p>
                <p>[Pick up on views, Moss 123-24, 126] <!--Entry needed here.-->. There was also a view of the town from the
                    site of a Roman encampment, on the hill east of the town.</p>
                <p> On the shore, there was a fort and a landing place (<hi rend="italic">stade</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">staithe</hi>), where Ruskin was probably diverted by
                    observing the bustle of related to shipping, fishing, and boat&#x2010;building, such as
                    watching vessels launched&#x2014;perhaps the model for Harry&#x02BC;s experiments with his toy
                    boat, or for the drawing &#x201C;Harry Seeing a Ship Launch,&#x201D; [Plate] <!--Entry needed here.--> &#x201C;6,&#x201D; [&#x201C;Harry and
                    Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1] (See &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1, <!--Entry needed here.-->).</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
                <!--In 1823, at the same time that the Ruskins showed so much delight in their seaside visits, William Cobbett, while admiring the beauty of Sandgate and Folkstone, 
                    was struck mainly by the area&#x02BC;s Mortello towers, defensive works that had been erected to guard against Napoleonic invasion. 
                    Cobbett railed against the costliness of &#x201C;these ridiculous things,&#x201D; thirty of which he counted stretching in a &#x201C;chain&#x201D; from Sandgate &#x201C;all the way to Hastings!&#x201D; 
                    For him, they represented the government&#x02BC;s extravagance that was &#x201C;sending some farmers to the workhouse and driving others to flee the country or to cut their throats!&#x201D; 
                    (Cobbett, <hi rend="italic">Rural Rides</hi>, September 3, 1 bibliog ref needed). The Ruskins are likely to have gazed on these structures with opposite feelings of patriotism.
                
                <ref type="works" target="harry_and_lucy_vol1_apparatus.html">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1,</ref> recounts a visit to <placeName>Hastings</placeName> 
                    ; and see also 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="tours_of_1822-25_note.html">Tours of 1822&#x2013;25</ref> and 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="tours_of_1826-27_note.html">Tours of 1826&#x2013;27</ref>).</p>-->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>