<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
       <fileDesc xml:id="strachen_anne_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Anne Strachan (ca. 1799-1871</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="HMT">Heidi M. Toloudis</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="biographical">
                <head type="title">Anne Strachan (<date notBefore="1799" notAfter="1871">ca. 1799&#x2013;1871</date>)</head>
                <p>In Praeterita, Ruskin characterizes the household servant Anne (or Ann or Anna) as "my father's nurse, and mine", 
                    paying tribute to her "natural gift and specialty . . . the service of a sick room". A life-long servant, 
                    she was thus "occupied" with "other people's good instead of her own", Ruskin writes, from "the age of fifteen to seventy-two" 
                    (Ruskin, Works, 35:30-31. a paragraph first published in letter 28 of Fors Clavigera in 1873, two years after Anne's death 
                    [Works, 27:517-18]).</p>
                
                <p>If Anne came into service at age fifteen--as "a bare-foot child", according to Georgiana Burne-Jones 
                    (Memorials of Edward Burne-Jones, 1:300)--then she would have begun work around 1814, 
                    and in a Ruskin household prior to that of John James and Margaret Ruskin, who were not married until 2 February 1818. 
                    W. G. Collingwood states that she "had come from the Edinburgh home" of John Thomas and Catherine Ruskin 
                    (Life of John Ruskin [1900], 26); however, Helen Viljoen realizes that in 1814 
                    the elder Ruskins--who were John James's parents and Margaret's aunt and uncle--were living in Perth, 
                    not Edinburgh, in the house known as Bowerswell. Viljoen connects these facts with Ruskin's implication in Praeterita 
                    that Anne was his father's nurse before she was his, and concludes that the girl must have helped 
                    with John James's convalescence at Bowerswell from typhoid. He came down with a fever while on the road to Perth in August 1813, 
                    and the disease kept him confined at Bowerswell until July 1814 (Ruskin's Scottish Heritage, 157, 246 n. 23; and see 
                    Catherine to John James Ruskin, 14 August 1813, and Margaret Cock to John James Ruskin, 
                    in Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 63-64, 67-70).</p>
                
                <p>It was Margaret who was sent to rescue John James when he fell ill on the way to Perth 
                    (Catherine to John James Ruskin, 14 August 1813 and 21 August 1813, in Burd, Ruskin Family Letters, 64, 66-67). In the ensuing months, 
                    she would have been stretched between her regular housekeeping duties and nursing John James, so it makes sense 
                    that a girl would have been hired to help in the house. The fifteen-year-old Anne presumably was inexperienced, 
                    not yet the servant who, according to Ruskin's testimonial, "was never quite in her glory unless some of us were ill" 
                    (Ruskin, Works, 35:39). But a mere girl's service may have been as much as the Ruskins could afford in their straitened circumstances. 
                    To reduce expenses, Catherine had pressed her husband to move from Edinburgh to the country, 
                    where household management could be confined to "Meggy [i.e., Margaret] my self and one servant" 
                    (Catherine to John James Ruskin, 15 March 1808, in Burd ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 23). They had already lived a year in the "retired" 
                    but "shabby" coastal town of Dysart before moving to Perth to be near the household of their daughter, John James's sister, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_jessie_note.php"><persName corresp="#JRP">Janet (&#x201c;Jessie&#x201d;) Richardson</persName> (<date notBefore="1783" notAfter="1828">1783&#x2013;1828</date>)</ref> and her husband, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_patrick_note.php"><persName corresp="#PR">Patrick Richardson</persName> (<date notBefore="1774" notAfter="1824">1774&#x2013;1824</date>)</ref>.</p>
                
                <p>Anne is not mentioned in surviving family correspondence, 1814-18; she first appears 
                    (assuming she is the "Anna" taking orders from Margaret) in the earliest surviving letter written by Margaret to John James 
                    following their marriage, when living at their Hunter Stree house in London. John was at this time a newborn 
                    (26 March 1819, in Burd, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi>, 92, 94 n. 6). But if Anne had been present in the background over the past five years, 
                    she was to some extent privy to the most dramatic events of her employers' lives. John James and Margaret had been betrothed since 1809, 
                    and the crisis of John James's near-lethal illness appears to have deepened their commitment, but now their union faced opposition by John Thomas. 
                    John James was convinced that the tension would bring about Margaret's death (see Margaret Cock to John James Ruskin, 12 July 1814; 
                    John James Ruskin to Margaret Cock, 22 March 1815 and 13 April 1815; 
                    and John James to Catherine and John Thomas Ruskin, 13 April 1815, in 
                    Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 67-77). 
                    Unexpectedly, in June 1815, John Thomas descended into madness. His son's emotions were divided between apprehension for his parents and relief for himself and Margaret. 
                    Writing to his mother, John James rejected recourse to a "public asylum" where his father would be subjected to "Surrounding Horrors", 
                    while recognizing that even "the strictest confinement" at home risked the "safety" and "health of the rest of the family". Writing to Margaret, 
                    he expressed compassion for his father's "frailties" but he could not resist interpreting his father's madness to their advantage 
                    as having rendered his father "in a manner dead to all of us", exonerating the family from "a place in his affections", and putting their 
                    "actions" beyond a hold even on John Thomas's "least interest" much less his control. John James also fretted over how public exposure "may injure me in business" 
                    (John James to Catherine Ruskin, 30 June 1815; and 
                    John James Ruskin to Margaret Cock, 3 July 1815, in Burd, ed. Ruskin Family Letters, 79, 80). 
                    As it turned out, release came by way of further calamity: in October 1817, Catherine Ruskin died suddenly, 
                    followed shortly by John Thomas's bloody suicide. At the time, Margaret was already in mourning for her own mother, 
                    Margaret Cock of Croydon. Throughout all this, John James was struggling to launch a new wine importing business in partnership with 
                    Pedro Domecq and Henry Telford, for his fateful journey north in 1813 had been prompted by his flight from the declining fortunes 
                    of his previous employer, Gordon, Murphy, &#x0026; Company (see the correspondence, 1812-17, in Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 53-88; 
                    and Hilton, John Ruskin: The Early Years, 6-8).</p>
                
                <p>As a young servant at Bowerswell, Anne shared the women's vantage on these events, which helps to explain a degree of intimacy 
                    between her and Margaret. One can only speculate, however, about the causes that underlay a prickliness in their relationship, 
                    which is treated as comedy in reminiscences by Ruskin and by Georgiana Burne-Jones, but with a strong suggestion 
                    that Anne was fiercely loyal to John James and John to the detriment of civility to Margaret and "a want of deference" toward her mistress that,
                    as Burne-Jones put it, "was certainly not the growth of the moment" 
                    (see Ruskin, Works, 35:31; G. Burne-Jones, Memorials of Edward Burne-Jones, 300-301). One can only speculate, too, 
                    about how Anne chose to manage her power by virtue of her presence at events that John James and Margaret presumably did not want divulged to John--at 
                    least in his youth. At any rate, the somewhat caricatured "white-haired, light-eyed, spare little figure, harsh and unattractive to our southern feeling" as perceived 
                    by Burne-Jones (Memorials of Burne-Jones, 300) was only in her twenties and early thirties when she accompanied John and his cousin Mary Richardson 
                    on many of their formative encounters at home and during travels in Britain and abroad.</p>
                
                <p> See <hi rend="italic">Tour to the Lakes</hi>, 6;</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>