<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="thorp_willard_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Willard Thorp </title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="biographical">
                <head type="title"><persName corresp="#WT">Willard Thorp</persName></head>
                <p>Thorp is significant to ERM because he was instrumential in establishing a research collection of Ruskin manuscripts, including juvenilia, 
                    at Princeton University Library. Ruskin collecting at Princeton mirrored that at Yale University Library, 
                    which was founded a decade earlier than Princeton's, in 1929-30, 
                    from a comprehensive print collection of first editions donated by 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="adam_r_b_note.php">R. B. Adam II (1863&#x2013;1940)</ref> 
                    and from a manuscript collection representative of Ruskin's career acquired under the direction of 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="tinker_c_b_note.php"><persName corresp="#CBT">Chauncey Brewster Tinker</persName> (<date notBefore="1876" notAfter="1963">1876&#x2013;1963</date>)</ref>. 
                    Both collections reflected a biographical approach that underpinned the trend of 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.html">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>, 
                    which committed collectors to assembling comprehensive runs of an author's first editions in their original condition, 
                    from juvenilia to last words; and both institutions were indebted not only to private collectors, who assembled that scope of Ruskin's vast print output, 
                    but also to the fortuitous occurrence of the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date></ref>, the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1931">1931</date></ref>, and the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_pictures_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Pictures and Drawings, <date when="1931">1931</date></ref>, 
                    which made available the full chronological scope and diversity of Ruskin's manuscripts and drawings. Acquisitions from those sales were made through the boldness and intelligence 
                    of the American dealer, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="goodspeed_charles_note.php"><persName corresp="#CG">Charles E. Goodspeed</persName> (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1950">1867&#x2013;1950</date>)</ref>--Princeton 
                    benefiting from Goodspeed's acquisitions primarily at the 1931 sale, as Yale had gained from the dealer's acquisitions primarily at the 1930 sale.</p>
                
                <p>Though Thorp's scholarly reputation was built primarily as an Americanist, when these developments in Ruskin collecting were unfolding in the 1920s and 1930s 
                    he was teaching Victorian and modern poetry. With a B.A. from Hamilton College and M.A. from Harvard, Thorp had taught at Smith College 1921-24, 
                    and then came to Princeton in 1925 for a Ph.D., which he completed in 1926 and joined the teaching staff of the English Department.
                    His Victorian poetry course grew popular for its approach using practical criticism, rather than a biographical method; 
                    and along with his dissertation director, Thomas Marc Parrott, he edited an anthology, 
                    <title type="book" corresp="#THORPPARROTTPOETRYOFTHETRANSITION"><hi rend="italic">Poetry of the Transition, <date notBefore="1850" notAfter="1914">1850&#x2013;1914</date></hi></title>, first published in 1932. 
                    He reached associate professor in 1939, the year of the Ruskin purchase 
                    (Robertson, "Remembering Professor Thorp", 128-29, 130-31).</p>
                
                <p>In 1930, when <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="tinker_c_b_note.php"><persName corresp="#CBT">Tinker</persName></ref> at Yale 
                    (likewise working on poetry at the time, publishing The Good Estate of Poetry in 1929) was recognized for his advocacy for building the library collections 
                    by being appointed keeper of rare books at the Sterling, Thorp as a young assistant professor of English was chosen to lend support to the newly formed 
                    Friends of the Princeton University Library. As Tinker scored the magnificent acquisitions from the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php"><orgName corresp="#SOTHEBYS">Sotheby&#x02BC;s</orgName> Sale of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Manuscripts and Library, <date when="1930">1930</date></ref>, 
                    Princeton announced its ambitions with the first issue of the Friends' newsletter, Biblia, with a list of "Desiderata" including "first editions" 
                    of Robert Browning, from the youthful Pauline of 1833 to a late publication of 1884--the wish list of the popular young instructor of Victorian poetry, 
                    whose tastes abided by the prevailing standard for collecting a run of "firsts" from early works to late ("Desiderata", 7). For the "Desiderata" of the second issue, 
                    Thorp followed up with a call for 1200 titles by 400 Victorian poets, which, not including the Browning firsts, he calculated could be acquired for $3500 
                    ("Desiderata", 6). The third issue featured a call by the chair of English, Dickson Q. Brown, justifying his faculty's need for 
                    "first editions of books of the seventeenth, eighteenth and nineteenth centuries", especially "copies of obscurer writings . . . which can be had only in contemporary editions" from the respective periods, 
                    and "which are of the utmost significance because of the light . . . they throw on the tastes and interests of a bygone generation from which some great masterpiece has emerged" 
                    ("Committee on Library Needs", 2). A sixteen-page supplement to the issue identified a "want-list" of hundreds of titles needed for competent undergraduate and graduate research in literary studies. 
                    Over the years, Thorp became a noted collector and donor himself, and he lent his influence to attract major collections such as the Morris L. Parrish collection of Victorian novels 
                    (Wainwright, "One of the First and the Best").
                    
                </p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>