<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <fileDesc xml:id="widow_of_roseneath_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Anonymous, <hi rend="italic">The Widow of Roseneath</hi> (1822)</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="subtype">
                <head type="title">Anonymous, <title type="book" corresp="#ANONWIDOWOFROSENEATH"><hi rend="italic">The Widow of Roseneath</hi></title> (1822)</head>
                <p>For bibliographical details describing this tale, see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="boyhood_books_note.php#WIDOW">Books Used by Ruskin in His Youth</ref>. 
                    Owned by the Ruskin family, it may have served--in the terms of its subtitle--as "A Lesson of Piety Affectionately Dedicated to the Young" 
                    for both Ruskin and his cousins who survived the deaths of <!-- LINK NOTES -->Patrick and Jessie Richardson of Perth. 
                    An 1823 review summarized the plot and commented as follows:</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div type="essay">
                            <p>Mrs. Stewart, who had lived in a respectable sphere of life in Scotland, becomes a widow ; 
                                and as her husband died insolvent, no rever sion is left for her and her two orphan children, 
                                Gilbert and Allan. She parts with most of her now useless furniture, and retires with her sons to a small cottage 
                                in Roseneath; “where seeking a solace to her griefs in works of piety and affection, she devoted herself diligently 
                                to the care of their instruction,” and in bringing them up in the ways of truth and goodness. Thus consoling herself 
                                in her misfor tunes under the influence of religion, and firmly believing that the God who overns the world 
                                never chastens un indly, she submits in pious resigna tion to his sovereign will. 
                                Years roll on, and the period arrives when it be comes necessary that her children should go forth 
                                to some employment in the world. Gilbert, her eldest son, a boy about fifteen years of age, is destined for America, 
                                in the employ of an affectionate uncle; and Allan, about fourteen, is to be apprenticed to a goldsmith in Greenock. 
                                They leave their widowed mother with ac cumulated anguish upon her wrinkled brow. They embark—the fond parent becomes 
                                inconsolable at her addition al bereavement—she revives;–but she no longer embraces them with maternal tenderness, 
                                for they are be yond her reach ; and all her concern is, how they will preserve those pious habits which she had endeavoured 
                                to impress upon their minds, and avoid the dread infection of temptation and 9f crime, to which it would be their t, 
                                to be exposed. They arrive at their looked-for homes; Allan at Sreenock, and Gilbert at New York. 
                                Gilbert's uncle meets him on the quay, and welcomes his young nephew to the shores of America: 
                                every thing looks auspicious. After spending *arly three years upon the beautiful *nks of the Hudson, 
                                and having *d himself high in the estimation of his kind relative and benefactor, 
                                by his attentive conduct and exemplary deportment, Mr. Stewart (the uncle) having some business to transact 
                                in Glasgow, determines to entrust his faithful nephew, Gilbert, with the im portant commission; 
                                at the same time appointing him to be the bearer of an invitation to his mother and brother Allan, 
                                to take up their abode in New York. Gilbert embarks with the pleasing intelligence;—he sets his feet once more 
                                on Scottish ground; he looks forward with anxious solici tude again to embrace his best of pa rents. 
                                As he approaches nearer home, he redoubles his eager steps—at last, his eye catches in the distance 
                                his wi dowed mother's dwelling—he presses onward—he beholds the cottage door, but sees not his parent 
                                upon her wonted seat. His heart beats high with doubt and suspense—every filial emotion is excited—scarcely 
                                a tiny vapour from the chimney tells that there is an in habitant within. He lightly raises the latch—he 
                                witnesses his mother once again in the weeds of her widowhood, but, insensible of his return, 
                                and wringing her hands in agony, and her eyes drowned in tears. He inquires the cause of such lamentation; 
                                the mother identifies his voice; she looks upward, and, in a compound parox ysm of ecstasy and grief, 
                                beholds her son Gilbert; but nature cannot sus tain the struggle. At length he ex torts the fact, 
                                that his brother Allan is incarcerated in a dungeon, and is to be tried on the morrow for forgery 
                                on the Greenock Bank. The widowed mother and her pious son repair with hurried steps to the prison-house, 
                                to catch one glance of their son and bro ther. She lies down to sleep; but the still darkness of midnight 
                                affords her no repose: images of terror, dun geons, gibbets, and executioners, rise in her feverish dreams; 
                                and the only balm to her racking mind is to call upon God to preserve his life; to in terpose his grace, 
                                and save his pre cious soul. They arrive in Glasgow, and behold the streets unusually crowded;—they witness 
                                the lords justiciary passing to the court-house. They hurry to the jail, and inquire for Allan Stewart; 
                                but admittance is denied them, as he is summoned to the bar, to be put first upon trial. 
                                With much urgent solicitation, they º a place in court; they immediately ſix their eyes upon the bar 
                                where the culprits stand; but no pri soner is there. They turn pale, and tremble—they shrink from every sound 
                                of the coming footsteps. Allan at last appears as the criminal between the liveried officers. 
                                The indictment is read; Allan pleads Not Guilty!— the trial proceeds—the evidence is unquestionable;—not 
                                even a mother's fondness can deny that the charge looks black against him. The verdict of the jury 
                                is unanimous and unhesi tating. The solemn word of “Guilty” is recorded. The judge pronounces the awful sentence; 
                                and implores him to pass the remainder of his time in genuine repentance and Christian meditation. 
                                They visit him in his gloomy abode, chained in ſetters. The interview is melting. Gilbert and his mother urgently intreat him 
                                to seek remission of his sins through the blood of the Saviour; and endea vour to dissipate, by the radiance of Christian faith, 
                                the fearful cloud of Allan's despair. Time rapidly ad vances—and poor Allan's life is draw ing to a close. 
                                Three sleepless nights remain, and the destined morning will arrive, when the heavens shall be clothed with sackcloth. 
                                Gilbert and his mother hasten once more to the dreary dungeon; and in unutterable anguish at the thought of Allan's speedy dissolution, 
                                endeavour to con sole him with the unspeakable com forts of religion; but powerful nature seems to invade, as it were, 
                                the still more powerful empire of religious trust. A pardon, however, unexpect edly arrives; Gilbert conveys the pleasing 
                                intelligence to his disconso late parent; but she cannot survive the past overwhelming shock; she closes her eyes in death, 
                                before her liberated son reaches her abode. Thus have we hastily glanced at the history of the pious widow of Rose neath, 
                                and with much pleasure we re commend it to the perusal of our readers.</p>
                            <p>We have already stated that it is a work of fiction; but it has none of the unmeaning and ungovern able incidents 
                                of an overdrawn ro mance, which has seldom any thing to recommend it but the delusions of a disordered or uncultivated mind— the 
                                visionary speculations of a fanci ful imagination—wild in its scenery —improbable in its situations—dis torted 
                                in its character—inconsistent with itself—and baneful in its ten dency;-but it is a work which bears 
                                so close an approximation to real life itself, as it is continually verified by our own daily observation, 
                                that it might well pass current as a narrative of fact, had not our author apprised us of the contrary.
                            </p>
                            <lb/>
                            <p>(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REVIEWANONWIDOWOFROSENEATH">Unsigned review of <hi rend="italic">The Widow of Roseneath</hi></ref>)</p>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>The Imperial Magazine was, according to William McCarthy, pro-Dissent, pro-Reform, and anti-slavery, addressed to a lower-middle-class readership. 
                    The magazine was a loyal admirer of <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="barbauld_anna_laetitia_note.php"><persName corresp="#ALB">Anna Letitia Barbauld</persName> (<date notBefore="1743" notAfter="1825">1743&#x2013;1825</date>)</ref> 
                    (McCarthy, &#x201C;&#x2018;A High&#x2010;Minded Christian Lady&#x2019;&#x201D;, 167).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>