<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="a_theme_apparatus">
        <fileDesc xml:id="a_theme_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">“A Theme”</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#EAH">YEva Hoffmann</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2019-12-04">December 4, 2019</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;A Theme&#x201D;</head>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Ruskin wrote the title &#x201C;a theme&#x201D; centered and on a line by itself above the text, just as he wrote the title 
                        <!-- ADD REF WHEN DETERMINED -->&#x201C;A sermon&#x201D; 
                        centered and on a line by itself above the brief text that immediately precedes &#x201C;a theme&#x201D; on the same page of MS II. 
                        In both cases, it appears that Ruskin positioned the title prior to the text as if he was naming a routine genre or exercise.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>If by <hi rend="italic">theme</hi> Ruskin means a written exercise.</p>
                    <p> <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> calls this piece <title type="sermon">“a theme”</title>, rather than a “sermon”, 
                        possibly because he did not hear the text in church. The discourse reads like notes on an address to a missionary society. 
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>’s handwriting is unusually illegible for this piece.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p><title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSII">MS II</title> .</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p><date notBefore="1829-02" notAfter="1829-03">February to March 1829</date>.</p>
                    <p>So dated by its position between <title type="sermon">A Sermon" ["beautiful allegory"]</title> and <title type="poem" corresp="#JRONSKIDDAWANDDERWENTWATER">On Skiddaw and Derwent Water"</title> in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSII">MS II</title> .</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>Previously unpublished.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    
                    
                    <p>While Ruskin's transcript contains too little detail to identify the specific occasion, 
                        the stir in the Ruskins' environment of worship in 1828 explains the kind of meeting he attended. 
                        On 14-16 May 1828, as documented at length by the Evangelical Magazine, to which the Ruskins subscribed, 
                        the London Missionary Society held its thirty-fourth annual meeting, commencing with a sermon preached by 
                        the Reverend Richard Alliott on the "Nature and Obligation of Christian Liberality". Based on Matthew 10, verse 8, 
                        "Freely ye have received, freely give", the argument explicated the Christian obligation of liberality as descending from the Apostles' 
                        endowment with "miraculous powers by the use of which they might bave enriched themselves" were it not that such use of their powers 
                        "was wholly inconsistent the chaaracter of . . . [Christ's] dispensation". Just so, Christians possess "the Gospel in our hands, 
                        conveying greater and better blessings;--for these we are indebted to the bounty of God, and it is according to his purpose that, 
                        that which we bave freely received, we should also freely communicate". If this sermon, or an address like it, was the occasion for Ruskin's theme, 
                        he might have picked up on the perorartion, which appealed to "<hi rend="italic">Philanthropists</hi>, as above all other means calculated to ameliorate and improve 
                        the condition of the most barbarous and wretched of the human race; and to Englishmen, as involving in its results the honour and prosperity of our own country,--the 
                        cause of Missions being considered as, indeed, the cause of our countr--of the world--of the salvation of men,--and of the glory of our great Creator" 
                        ("Surrey Chapel", 261-62).</p>
                    
                    <p>that recorded by Ruskin was the thirty-first anniversary of the Surrey Mission Society, 
                        which was celebrated on 9 April 1828 at "Dr. Andrews's Chapel, Walworth"--that is the Beresford Street Chapel, Walworth, 
                        built for the popular preacher by his parishioners. According to a report in the Evangelical Magazine, the society was 
                        "composed of Christians of various denominations, for the purpose of preaching the Gospel, establishing Schools", and 
                        "circulating the Scriptures and Religious Tracts in the villages of Surrey 
                        The 31st Anniversary of_this important Institution was held at Dr Andrews's Walworth on Wednesday April 9 in the morning at eleven o clock 
                        when the Rev Matthew Wilks read the 60th chapter Isaiah and offered up an appropriate prayer 
                        After which the Rev Rowland Hill preached an excellent sermon from 1 Timothy iv 12 
                        The Rev R Davis con with prayer The Societs met again in the evening when the Rev Rowland Hill was called to take the Chair 
                        The Rev G Rose opened the meeting with prayer after which the Rev T Jackson read the Report from wbich it appears 
                        that the Society continues its disinterested labours with success it has four Missionaries wbolly supported by it 
                        and several others receive assistance from its funds It has been the means of introthe ducing the Gospel into about 100 villages congregations 
                        
                        ducing the Gospel into about 100 villages where in some instances stated congregations and regular churches have been formed it has built eight chapels and has at this time many poor childreen under tuition in its schools The Committee regret that their are not equal to their expenditure and respectfully solicit from the friends of Redeenier in the county tbat pe cuniary aid without which it will be im possible for them to maintain the ground they now occupy whilst there are 
                        
                        yet whole districts where the light of the Gospel is not enjoyed The congregations on both parts of the day were very large and many found it good to be there The collections amounted to 531 besides a donation of 104 </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>