<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "the_steam_engine_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"The Constellations"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;The Constellations: Northern, Some of the Zodiac, and Some of the Southern&#x201D;</head>
                <!--An apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">MSS IA and III, RF T70</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">January (or January 1827?)</head>
                    <p>Undated fair copy in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>, 
                        where title written <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHECONSTELLATIONS">&#x201C;THE CONSTELLATIONS / NORTHERN, SOME OF THE ZODIAC AND / SOME OF THE SOUTHERN.&#x201D;</title>. 
                        Its placement after the second volume of <title type="lesson" corresp="#JRHARRYANDLUCYVOL2">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D;</title> 
                        and before <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHESUN">&#x201C;The Sun&#x201D;</title> suggests <date when="1828-01-01">New Year&#x02BC;s 1828</date>. 
                        Indeed, in the prose section of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> preceding the poem, 
                        <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> gives <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> 
                        a drawing of <name type="astronomical" corresp="#CHARLESSWAIN">Charles&#x02BC;s Wain</name> &#x201C;as an introduction to astronomy&#x201D;. 
                        Thus, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s editors are strictly correct in listing the poem under <date when="1827">1827</date>&#x2014;that is, 
                        composition in late <date when="1827">1827</date> for a <date when="1828-01-01">New Year&#x02BC;s 1828</date> presentation.</p>
                    <p>The editors seem to intend earlier <date when="1827">1827</date>, associating the poem with the rough draft of <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMONASTERY">&#x201C;The Monastery&#x201D;</title> 
                        in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>, which they misdate as <date when="1827">1827</date>. 
                        If they based their dating on harder evidence contained in the rough draft of <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHECONSTELLATIONS">&#x201C;Constellations&#x201D;</title> 
                        in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title> (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE"><title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE"><hi rend="italic">Works</hi></title></ref>, 2:535), 
                        their reasoning cannot be confirmed or denied, since a piece of that rough draft manuscript is now very likely missing.
                        The evidence in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> does hold open a possibility for an earlier date. 
                        As noted in nos. 1 and 4, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> seems habitually to have included his previous year&#x02BC;s presentation poems 
                        along with the most recent New Year&#x02BC;s gift in his <title type="lesson" corresp="#JRHARRYANDLUCY">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D;</title> books 
                        (e.g., in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> includes another older New Year&#x02BC;s poem, no. 4, in this group). 
                        Thus, <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHECONSTELLATIONS">&#x201C;The Constellations&#x201D;</title> could have existed as a New Year&#x02BC;s gift for <date when="1827">1827</date>, 
                        although no positive evidence supports the possibility.</p>
                    <p>If the poem is based on <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s actual observation of the sky, the alignment of heavenly bodies described at the beginning 
                        of the poem would not have been possible in <date when="1827">1827</date>, not even as late as December for a New Year&#x02BC;s composition. In that case,
                        the composition would have to be moved forward to <date notBefore="1828-04" notAfter="1828-05">April&#x2010;May 1828</date>, more in keeping with the occasion of <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName>&#x02BC;s birthday. 
                        See <ref type="internal" target="#DISCUSSION">Discussion</ref>.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition and Publication</head>
                    <p>Quoted in <title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE"><hi rend="italic">Works</hi></title>, 2:260 n. 1. 
                        Previously unpublished in entirety.</p>
                    <p>A separate presentation copy of the poem is represented at the <orgName corresp="#RUSKINLIBRARYLANCASTER">Ruskin Library</orgName> 
                        by a photograph of a manuscript, taken for the <title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE">Library Edition</title> but unused 
                        (RF T70; for its physical description, see part 2, MS IA, &#x201C;Contents,&#x201D; b). 
                        The location of the original manuscript is unknown, as are the occasion and date of its presentation, 
                        and its physical characteristics, other than its consisting of a single folded sheet. 
                        Entitled <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHECONSTELLATIONS">&#x201C;THE CONSTELLATIONS NORTHERN / SOME OF THE ZODIAC / AND SOME OF THE SOUTHERN&#x201D;</title>, 
                        the photograph shows a fair&#x2010;copy version predating the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> fair copy. 
                        It runs the full length of the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> version, 
                        but several lines are crossed out and revisions scrawled in the margins&#x2014;revisions that all appear in the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> version, 
                        excepting a word or two that were altered again for that final version. The revisions are written in an awkward longhand, 
                        unlike the tiny print lettering of the fair copy.
                        Presumably, the RF T70 revisions were made shortly before the <date notBefore="1827-09" notAfter="1828-04">late 1827&#x2014;early 1828</date> fair copy 
                        in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> (thus, incidentally, representing one of the earliest datable examples of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s longhand script). 
                        In fact, the RF T70 fair copy itself, and not just its revisions, may have only shortly predated the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> version. 
                        At line 53 of RF T70, the fair&#x2010;copy hand suddenly becomes larger and more careless, suggesting that, at this point, 
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> decided to sacrifice this fair copy to revision (see also textual note for line 54).
                        On the last page of the folded sheet (i.e., p. 4) in the photograph, revised lines of <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHECONSTELLATIONS">&#x201C;The Constellations&#x201D;</title> 
                        appear to be written over top of a lighter script of lines that I am unable to connect definitely with any extant fair&#x2010;copy juvenilia: 
                        &#x201C;[to(?)] heaven but / not [to(?)] hell [for when (?)] / they went to / place [I(?)] say [that then (?)] / they took quite / a different way / and . . .&#x201D; 
                        (the writing continues for four more, illegible lines). The scrawled draft suggests notes for a sermon, although it might represent attempted revision of 
                        <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHECONSTELLATIONS">&#x201C;The Constellations&#x201D;</title> since some lines were given a more pious cast in the final version 
                        (see, e.g., the textual notes for the lines &#x201C;The scales in which twas vainly said / The crime and virtues of men were weighed,&#x201D; and for the closing meditation on the superiority of virtue to knowledge). 
                        No surviving fair&#x2010;copy lines, however, even remotely match the faint draft.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="SOURCES">
                        <head type="subsection">Sources</head>
                    <p>Definitive evidence of one source of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s reading about the constellations is revealed in his <title type="lesson" corresp="#JRHARRYANDLUCYVOL2">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy . . . Vol 2&#x201D;</title>, 
                        where <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> offers to &#x201C;give . . . [<persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>] a drawing of <name type="astronomical" corresp="#CHARLESSWAIN">charles&#x02bc;s wain</name> 
                        as an introduction to astronomy&#x201D;. The drawing, which <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> illustrates with his own drawing in the text, reproduces a diagram in volume 2, 
                        &#x201C;Of Astronomy&#x201D;, of <persName corresp="#JJ">Jeremiah Joyce</persName>&#x02BC;s <title type="book" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES"><hi rend="italic">Scientific Dialogues</hi></title> (2:250 opp. [pl. 1, fig. 1]). 
                        In <persName corresp="#JJ">Joyce</persName>&#x02BC;s dialogue, the <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TUTORJJ">Tutor</persName> shows this diagram to his pupils, <persName type="fictional" corresp="#CHARLESJJ">Charles</persName> and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#JAMESJJ">James</persName>, just as <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> presents the drawing to <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>,
                        as a first step in learning &#x201C;&#x2018;how to distinguish the stars, and . . . call them by their proper names&#x2019;&#x201D;. 
                        He points out <name type="astronomical" corresp="#CHARLESSWAIN">Charles&#x02BC; Wain</name> in the night sky, and illustrates the formation with the diagram&#x2014;four stars forming a waggon, and three stars making the horses, 
                        all of them also forming part of a larger constellation, the <name type="astronomical" corresp="#URSAMAJOR">Great Bear</name>&#x2014;and he explains how these constellations can serve as a compass for finding one&#x02BC;s bearings at night, 
                        without the sun&#x02BC;s position to define the cardinal points. As a northern constellation, <name type="astronomical" corresp="#CHARLESSWAIN">Charles&#x02BC; Wain</name> is always visible on a clear night; 
                        and as the diagram shows, it can be used to point to the <name type="astronomical" corresp="#POLARIS">North Star (i.e., Polaris)</name> by tracing a line upward through the two stars forming the rear of the waggon. 
                        From this first point of reference, the <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TUTORJJ">Tutor</persName> proceeds to instruct <persName type="fictional" corresp="#CHARLESJJ">Charles</persName> and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#JAMESJJ">James</persName> in the names and locations of other stars, constellations, and planets 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES">coversation 2, <title type="lesson" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUESFIXEDSTARS">&#x201C;Of the Fixed Stars&#x201D;</title>, <title type="book" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES"><hi rend="italic">Scientific Dialogues</hi></title></ref>, 2:12&#x2013;18).</p>
                        <!-- START NEW TAGGING -->
                    <p>In Ruskin's reading, this episode in Joyce's dialogues formed a node of interlocking texts, for in Maria Edgeworth's Frank the Engineer 
                        marks passages on astronomy in Joyce's Scientific Dialogues where the youth can find information about astronomy. 
                        Frank himself recalls an episode in Thomas Day's Sandford and Merton, in which "Harry Sandford found his way out of the moor by the help of the pole star" 
                        (Edgeworth, Frank, 2:141, 140). In Sandford and Merton, this story is told in connection with a lesson, similar to the Tutor's in Scientific Dialogues, 
                        in which Day's tutor, Mr. Barlow, teaches Tommy to find Charles's Wain as Harry did, in order to find his way on a dark night. 
                        To remember the constellations, Tommy gets the idea of diagramming the stars on paper and carries on to conceive of a celestial globe, 
                        which Mr. Barlow later provides in the form of a paper-covered ball on which the boys record their observations of the constellations. 
                        These lessons convey practical knowledge, which saved Harry's life when lost on the moor, but also teach appreciation of natural beauty:</p>
                        <!-- use floating text -->
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. Barlow</hi>. Were there no other use, I should think there would be a very great pleasure 
                            in observing such a number of glorious, glittering bodies as are now above us. We sometimes run to see a procession of coaches, 
                            or a few people in fine clothes strutting about; we admire a large room that is painted, and ornamented, and gilded: 
                            but what is there in all these things to be compared with the sight of these luminous bodies that adorn every part of the sky?</p>
                        <p>(Day, The History of Sandford and Merton, 165, and see 162-69, 187-88)</p>
                        <!-- end floating text -->
                    <p><persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s poem, <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHECONSTELLATIONS">&#x201C;The Constellations&#x201D;</title>, 
                        corresponds to these methods of putting the constellations on paper. In context of Ruskin's own <title type="lesson" corresp="#JRHARRYANDLUCYVOL2">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy . . . Vol 2&#x201D;</title>, 
                        the poem effectively forms <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>&#x02BC;s &#x201C;introduction to astronomy&#x201D;; and in the context of his reading, 
                        the poem's seemingly mechanical exercise of listing the star clusters carries out the method, recommended by Mr. Barlow, of "remembering these stars 
                        [in Charles's Wain]" so that "you may very easily observe those which are next to them, and learn their names too, till you are acquainted with the whole face of the heavens" 
                        (Day, History of Sandford and Merton, 163). Just so, in Joyce's Scientific Dialogues, the <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TUTORJJ">Tutor</persName> instructs 
                        <persName type="fictional" corresp="#CHARLESJJ">Charles</persName> and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#JAMESJJ">James</persName> in the names and positions of the constellations.</p>
                        
                        <p>In his poem, Ruskin adopts the tactic of Day's and Joyce's tutors by starting from a prominent point of reference--in Ruskin's case, 
                            a planet, <name type="astronomical" corresp="#VENUSPLANET">Venus</name>, the so&#x2010;called Morning Star and Evening Star, and a wandering rather than a fixed star&#x2014;and 
                        he carries on to list the formations more or less in sequence, as do Tommy and Harry on their globe. 
                        <persName corresp="#JJ">Joyce</persName>&#x02BC;s <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TUTORJJ">Tutor</persName> leads his pupils on a somewhat more complicated path, 
                            starting from the diagram of <name type="astronomical" corresp="#CHARLESSWAIN">Charles&#x02BC;s Wain</name> and proceeding to a celestial globe, 
                            but moving rapidly to orient the constellations to the ecliptic and equator, and then teaching them to consult an <hi rend="italic">ephemeris</hi> 
                        or almanac of the longitudes and latitudes, times of rising and setting, and other information about the heavenly bodies 
                        (Joyce, Scientific Dialogues, "Of Astronomy", conversations 2-4, 2:12-47).</p>
                    </div>
                    <!-- END NEW TAGGING -->
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="REAL-LIFE">
                        <head type="subsection">Real-life Observations</head>
                    <p><persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> possibly built his simpler catalogue of constellations based on actual observation of <name type="astronomical" corresp="#VENUSPLANET">Venus</name>, 
                        just as <persName corresp="#JJ">Joyce</persName> initially situates his fictional characters observing the evening sky at the end of a lingering walk. 
                        According to a digital&#x2010;age ephemeris, <name type="astronomical" corresp="#VENUSPLANET">Venus</name> would have been visible from <placeName corresp="#LONDON">London</placeName> as an evening star, 
                        setting in the west and appearing close to <name type="astronomical" corresp="#ORION">Orion</name>&#x02BC;s belt, in <date notBefore="1828-04" notAfter="1828-05">April&#x2010;May 1828</date>. <name type="astronomical" corresp="#MARS">Mars</name> would not have been visible high in the sky precisely at that time, 
                        but would have risen from the east somewhat later, after <name type="astronomical" corresp="#VENUSPLANET">Venus</name> had set. This particular configuration of planets and constellations 
                        would not have appeared at any other time in <date when="1828">1828</date>, and not at all in <date when="1827">1827</date>. During those two months in <date when="1828">1828</date>&#x2014;the time when <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                        would have been composing poetry for <date when="1828-05-10">his father&#x02BC;s birthday</date>&#x2014;the northern constellations could be viewed circling counter&#x2010;clockwise overhead, 
                        in roughly the sequence listed in the poem&#x2014;<name type="astronomical" corresp="#URSAMAJOR">Ursa Major (the Great Bear)</name>, 
                        <name type="astronomical" corresp="#DRACO">Draco (the Dragon)</name>, <name type="astronomical" corresp="#CORONABOREALIS">Corona Borealis (the Crown)</name>, <name type="astronomical" corresp="#COMABERENICES">Coma Berenices (Berenice&#x02BC;s Hair)</name>. 
                        Beyond this point in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s list, the sequence is jumbled compared to what one would have seen in the sky, 
                        having to dart in different directions to find <name type="astonomical" corresp="#CYGNUS">Cygnus (the Swan)</name>; 
                        <name type="astronomical" corresp="#CHARLESSHEART">Charles&#x02BC;s Heart</name>, which is a star in <name type="astronomical" corresp="#CANESVENATICI">Canes Venatici (Hunting Dogs)</name>; and so on 
                        (<title type="website" corresp="#SKYANDTELESCOPE">Sky &#x0026; Telescope, Interactive Star Chart and Celestial Almanac</title>, accessed <date when="2022-03-20">20 March 2022</date>). 
                        Of course, if based on any actual observation at all, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s poem reflect experience mixed with information gleaned from a book or globe.</p>
                    <p>A distinct difference between <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s poem and <persName corresp="#JJ">Joyce</persName>&#x02BC;s dialogue is that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> is interested in the poetic images evoked by the mythic names, whereas 
                        <persName corresp="#JJ">Joyce</persName>&#x02BC;s <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TUTORJJ">Tutor</persName> and his scholars are dismissive of what they regard as largely humbug: &#x201C;<hi rend="italic">James</hi>. 
                        &#x2018;Why are the signs of the Zodiac called by the several names of <name type="astrological" corresp="#ARIES">Aries</name>, <name type="astrological" corresp="#TAURUS">Taurus</name>, <name type="astrological" corresp="#LEO">Leo</name>, &#x0026;c. 
                        I see no likeness in the heavens to Rams, or Bulls, or Lions, which are the English words for those Latin ones&#x2019;. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Tutor</hi>. &#x2018;Nor do I&#x2019;&#x201D; (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES">conversation 4, <title type="lesson" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUESEPHEMERIS">&#x201C;Of the Ephemeris&#x201D;</title>, <title type="book" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES"><hi rend="italic">Scientific Dialogues</hi></title></ref>, 2:36&#x2013;37).</p>
                    <p>One lesson that <persName corresp="#JJ">Joyce</persName>&#x02BC;s <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TUTORJJ">Tutor</persName> dwells on is the arbitrariness underlying the naming systems of astronomy. 
                        The imagined patterns in the sky, whereby the Greek ordered and named the constellations, were arbitrary constructions. As the <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TUTORJJ">Tutor</persName> emphasizes: 
                        &#x201C;&#x2018;The ancients, that they might the better distinguish and describe the stars, with regard to their situation in the heavens, 
                        divided them into constellations, that is, systems of stars, each system consisting of such stars as were near to each other, 
                        giving them the names of such men or things, as they fancied the space which they occupied in the heavens represented&#x2019;&#x201D;. 
                        <persName type="fictional" corresp="#CHARLESJJ">Charles</persName> takes the point: it is &#x201C;perfectly arbitrary, that one collection is called the <hi rend="italic">great bear</hi>, 
                        another <hi rend="italic">the dragon</hi>; a third <hi rend="italic">Hercules</hi>, and so on&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES">conversation 2, <title type="lesson" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUESFIXEDSTARS">&#x201C;Of the Fixed Stars&#x201D;</title>, in <persName corresp="#JJ">Joyce</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES"><hi rend="italic">Scientific Dialogues</hi></title></ref>, 2:13&#x2013;14). 
                        The arbitrariness of naming extends beyond the ancient constellations to modern systems: 
                        &#x201C;&#x2018;If you look on the [celestial] globe&#x2019;&#x201D;, the <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TUTORJJ">Tutor</persName> continues, &#x201C;&#x2018;you will observe, that . . . [lesser stars] are distinguished 
                        by the different letters of the Greek alphabet&#x2019;&#x201D;, which are also assigned arbitrarily 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES">conversation 3, <title type="lesson" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUESECLIPTIC">&#x201C;Of the Fixed Stars, and Ecliptic&#x201D;</title>, <title type="book" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES"><hi rend="italic">Scientific Dialogues</hi></title></ref>, 2:23).</p>
                    </div>
                    
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>