<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "the_steam_engine_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"The Constellations"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;The Constellations: Northern, Some of the Zodiac, and Some of the Southern&#x201D;</head>
                <!--An apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">MSS IA and III, RF T70</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">January (or January 1827?)</head>
                    <p>Undated fair copy in MS III, where title written “THE CONSTELLATIONS / NORTHERN, SOME OF THE ZODIAC AND / SOME OF THE SOUTHERN.” Its placement after the second volume of “Harry and Lucy” (no. 20) and before “The Sun” (no. 22) suggests New Year’s 1828; indeed, in the prose section of MS III preceding the poem, Harry gives Lucy a drawing of Charles’s Wain “as an introduction to astronomy.” Thus, Ruskin’s editors are strictly correct in listing the poem under 1827--that is, composition in late 1827 for a New Year’s 1828 presentation. However, the editors seem to intend earlier 1827, associating the poem with the rough draft of “The Monastery” in MS IA, which they misdate as 1827. If they based their dating on harder evidence contained in the rough draft of “Constellations” in MS IA (see Works, 2:535), their reasoning cannot be confirmed or denied, since a piece of that rough draft manuscript is now very likely missing (see part 2, MS IA, “Contents,” b).
                        The evidence in MS III does hold open a possibility for an earlier date. As noted in nos. 1 and 4, Ruskin seems habitually to have included his previous year’s presentation poems along with the most recent New Year’s gift in his “Harry and Lucy” books (e.g., in MS III, Ruskin includes another older New Year’s poem, no. 4, in this group). Thus, “The Constellations” could have existed as a New Year’s gift for 1827, although no positive evidence supports the possibility.
                        .</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>Quoted in Works, 2:260 n. 1. Previously unpublished in entirety.</p>
                    <p>A separate presentation copy of the poem is represented at the Ruskin Library by a photograph of a manuscript, taken for the Library Edition but unused (RF T70; for its physical description, see part 2, MS IA, “Contents,” b). The location of the original manuscript is unknown, as are the occasion and date of its presentation, and its physical characteristics, other than its consisting of a single folded sheet. Entitled “THE CONSTELLATIONS NORTHERN / SOME OF THE ZODIAC / AND SOME OF THE SOUTHERN,” the photograph shows a fair-copy version predating the MS III fair copy. It runs the full length of the MS III version, but several lines are crossed out and revisions scrawled in the margins--revisions that all appear in the MS III version, excepting a word or two that were altered again for that final version. The revisions are written in an awkward longhand, unlike the tiny print lettering of the fair copy.
                        Presumably, the RF T70 revisions were made shortly before the late 1827--early 1828 fair copy in MS III (thus, incidentally, representing one of the earliest datable examples of Ruskin’s longhand script). In fact, the RF T70 fair copy itself, and not just its revisions, may have only shortly predated the MS III version. At line 53 of RF T70, the fair-copy hand suddenly becomes larger and more careless, suggesting that, at this point, Ruskin decided to sacrifice this fair copy to revision (see also textual note for line 54).
                        On the last page of the folded sheet (i.e., p. 4) in the photograph, revised lines of “The Constellations” appear to be written over top of a lighter script of lines that I am unable to connect definitely with any extant fair-copy juvenilia: “[to(?)] heaven but / not [to(?)] hell [for when (?)] / they went to / place [I(?)] say [that then (?)] / they took quite / a different way / and . . .” (the writing continues for four more, illegible lines). The scrawled draft suggests notes for a sermon, although it might represent attempted revision of “The Constellations” since some lines were given a more pious cast in the final version (see, e.g., the textual notes for the lines “The scales in which twas vainly said / The crime and virtues of men were weighed,” and for the closing meditation on the superiority of virtue to knowledge). No surviving fair-copy lines, however, even remotely match the faint draft.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                            <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                            <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TEXTUALNOTE">
                    <head type="section">Textual Note</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>