<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <fileDesc xml:id="death_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Death"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#BDT">Brady Daniel Thomas</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>htts://erm.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;Title of Work&#x201D;</head>
                <!--An apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Title written “DEATH” in MSS IA and V.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>MSS IA, V, VI.</p>
                    <p>Among the papers in MS IA, a presentation copy of &#x201C;Death&#x201D; appears as if meant to accompany a presentation copy of the group, 
                        &#x201C;Vesuvius&#x201D;, &#x201C;Trafalgar", and "The Yew&#x201D;. However, the kinds of paper differ, and Ruskin’s March date in the MS V copy sets it apart 
                        from those others (see part 1, MS IA, “Content,” e). This date is consistent with evidence of the index to MS VI, 
                        which indicates that, in the section of the manuscript now torn away, the poem (probably its draft) fell between "&#x201C;Vesuvius&#x201D; and &#x201C;Trafalgar&#x201D; preceding it 
                        and &#x201C;Salamis&#x201D; and &#x201C;Ivanhoe&#x201D; following it.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>March 1830 and early fall 1831.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>Unpublished, but mentioned in Works, 2:279 n. 1.</p>
                    <p>The MS V version is longer by 21 lines than the MS IA version, although the latter appears to be a complete fair copy, with ample blank space left at the end of the poem. Added to the end of the poem in the MS V version is “a vision of delight,” the gathering of the dead babe’s and boy’s souls “round a throne of glory” in heaven, while death lies vanquished below. The MS IA version, by contrast, ends bleakly with the “silence of death.”
                        Also in MS VI, where, according to its index, Ruskin first drafted “Death,” he returned to the poem--probably in early fall 1831, judging by its position following “Creation--Second Day” and embedded between two portions of book 4 of “Iteriad” (ll. 27-68 and 69-94). Entitled “Death” here, as well, the poem recurs as a revision or new version, Ruskin rewriting or adding lines to the opening section that deals with a dead child and his mother. In draft, after this new section “I” comes a roman numeral “II,” with no follow-up, indicating that the revision or new version was abandoned.
                        It is possible that the MS VI version existed prior to the “Iteriad” draft surrounding it, so that it ought to be dated earlier than fall 1831. But several indicators suggest that Ruskin paused during composition of “Iteriad” book 4 to draft the revised lyric: (1) the ink and pen for the draft appear identical to “Iteriad” 4:27-68 preceding it; (2) immediately beneath the abandoned lyric, Ruskin drew a line and, with a new pen, entitled the succeeding draft of “Iteriad” 4:69ff. as “Iteriad Book 4th”--as if he were returning to that poem after a hiatus; and (3), the revision of the lyric does not appear in Ruskin’s index, whereas, with only one exception (no. 115), he consistently indexed shorter poems composed prior to “Iteriad,” book 4.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                            <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                            <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TEXTUALNOTE">
                    <head type="section">Textual Note</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>