<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <fileDesc xml:id="on_the_appearance_of_a_sudden_cloud_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">“On the Appearance of a Sudden Cloud of Yellow Fog Covering Everything with Darkness"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;On the Appearance of a Sudden Cloud of Yellow Fog Covering Everything with Darkness&#x201D;</head>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Poem.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>MS III.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Possibly composed after 13 November 1828; fair copied between 9-13 March 1829.</head>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition and Publication</head>
                    <p>Printed in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891"><title type="book" corresp="#POEMS4D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></title>, 1891]</ref>, 1:???&#x2013;??; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891"><title type="book" corresp="#POEMS8D1891"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891]</title></ref>, ?:???; 
                        PJR, 1:23-24; Works, 2:272.</p>
                    <p>Only a fair copy survives, which Ruskin copied in MS III as part of a group of poems that he dated 9 March 1829: see 
                        <ref type="apparatus" target="of_rocks_first_and_of_caverns_now_i_sing_apparatus#COMPPUB">"Of rocks first and of caverns now I sing": Composition and Publication</ref>.</p><!--WHY DID I SAY 9-13?-->
                    <p>Originally, W. G. Collingwood suggests, the poem “may have been written at any time during the winter of 1828-29” 
                        (PJR, 1:272). 
                        The poem was likely occasioned by a great fog of 13 November 1828; see Discussion.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>While complaints about London's excessive smoke from industrial and domestic fires became common starting in the seventeenth century, 
                        Christine Corton finds that the "true London fog as it came into being in the Victorian era" was marked by 
                        "yellow as a characteristic colour of [the] polluted air" and took "on a new character, thick, widespread, and prolonged". 
                        Typically caused by temperature inversion, the fogs began "increasing in frequency" in the early nineteenth century, 
                        and "became even more frequent during the 1820s, when occurrences were reported in 1820, 1821, 1822, 1826, 1828, and 1829, 
                        though none of them seems to have lasted more than a couple of days"--a duration that seems reflected in Ruskin's description 
                        of the sudden appearance of the yellow cloud, and its dispersal after a storm. As documentation of the 1828 event that Ruskin 
                        presumably was responding to, Corton cites a report of a fog in the Times for 13 November, 
                        as well as the observations of the meteorologist and chemist Luke Howard (1772-1864), who recorded an "extreme dense fog all day" on that date 
                        (Corton, London Fog 6, 9, 11, 337 n. 43; Howard, Climate of London, 3:302).</p>
                    
                    <p>The November 1828 fog was remarkable enough for Howard describe its phenomena at length:</p>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <div type="essay">
                                <p>The fog of Wednesday has seldom been exceeded in opacity in the metropolis and its neighbourhood. 
                                    It began to thicken very much about half past twelve o'clock, from which time, till near two, 
                                    the effect was most distressing, making the eyes smart, and almost suffocating those who were in the street, 
                                    particularly asthmatic persons. In the city all the bankers, and offices of different descriptions, 
                                    as well as the principal shops, were obliged to have lights. To see with any distinctness further than across the street was impossible; 
                                    all the narrow lanes, beyond the perspective of a few yards, were absolutely in a state of darkness, 
                                    and in the great thoroughfares, the hallooing of coachmen and drivers to avoid each other, 
                                    seemingly issuing from the opaque mass in which they were enveloped, was calculated to awaken all the caution of riders, 
                                    as well as of pedestrians who had to cross the streets. On the Thames, as on land, the tendency which fog has to enlarge distant objects, 
                                    was strikingly illustrated; the smallest vessels on their approach seemed magnified to thrice their usual dimensions. 
                                    St. Paul's had a prodigious effect through the mist, though neither that nor the monument were visible above the height of the houses. . . . 
                                    [The fog] cleared off a little about a quarter past two, but returned with all its density in the evening</p>
                                
                                <p>(Climate of London, 3:303).</p>
                            </div>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>

                    <p>Did Ruskin himself experience the fog in the city, or even at home in Camberwell? How far did the affected "neighbourhood" of the metropolis extend? 
                        It is possible that the suburbs were enveloped, as Howard quotes an 1816 report describing how, on the morning of 27 November, 
                        the "neighbourhood of Walworth and Camberwell" grew "so completely dark" with "fog, combined with smoke", 
                        that "coachmen . . . were obliged to get down and lead their horses with a lantern" (Climate of London, 2:313). 
                        Dickens, in Our Mutual Friend (1864-65), treats a "foggy day" as "grey" in "the surrounding country" of London, but turning "dark yellow" 
                        "at about the boundary line", and growing "browner, and then browner, until at the heart of the City . . . it was rusty-black"; however, 
                        in context of the novel, the deepening color and darkness form a metaphor (Dickens, Our Mutual Friend, 000 [bk. 3, chap. 1]; 
                        see Corton, London Fog, 65-66). 
                        The yellow color, which resulted from tars precipitating from low-combustion domestic fires, likely gave way to darker colors over lengthening time 
                        rather than decreasing proximity to the city, as later in the day fires were compounded by industry emitting darker tars, soot, and smoke 
                        (Novakov and Novakov, Chromatic Effects of Late Nineteenth-Century London Fog").</p>
                    
                    <p>Despite the vulnerability of the suburbs, fog was a metropolitan topic in poetry, notably in Byron's. 
                        While his relationship with London was ambivalent, as John Clubbe describes it, 
                        Byron found especially negative, albeit distinctly urban images to describe the fog. 
                        In The Vision of Judgement (1822), the sun struggles "to dispel / the fogs of London, through which, dimly beaconed, / 
                        The weathercocks are gilt some thrice a year, / If that the <hi rend="italic">summer</hi> is not too severe". 
                        In Manfred (1817), the songs of the destinies reverse the hopefulness 
                        of Wordsworth's sonnet "Composed upon Westminster Bridge, September 3, 1802" (1807), 
                        in which the "beauty of the morning" reveals "Ships, towers, domes, theatres, and temples" made "bright and glittering in the smokeless air", 
                        so that "the very houses seem asleep; / And all that mighty heart . . . lying still"; 
                        rather, in the view from the summit of the Jungfrau, "The city lies sleeping; / The morn, to deplore it, / May dawn on it weeping: / Sullenly, slowly, / 
                        The black plague flew o'er it-- / Thousands lie lowly". 
                        Wordsworth's sonnet is mocked again by the prospect of London's plague-cloud in canto 10 of Don Juan (1823). 
                        When Juan first sights the city from Shooter's Hill, the narrator describes 
                        "a wilderness of steeples peeping / On tiptoe through their sea coal canopy, / A huge, dun cupola, like a foolscap crown, / 
                        On a fool's head--and there is London Town!" 
                        (Wordsworth . . .
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BYRONWORKS"><persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#BYRONWORKS"><hi rend="italic">Complete Poetical Works</hi></title>, ed. McGann</ref>, 
                        ??:?? [stz. 55]; 4:79 [act 2, sc. 3, lines 34-39]; 5:462 [canto 10, stanza 82]; 
                        Clubbe, "Byron's London Revisited", 10-11, 15-17; and see Corton, London Fog, ).</p>
                    
                    <p>By comparison, Ruskin's poem is remarkable for its disassociation from London. It is concerned strictly with meteorological phenomena, 
                        except for the extended trope of warfare between the light and the darkness.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>