<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Vesuvius"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>htts://erm.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;Title of Work&#x201D;</head>
                <!--An apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>Title written “VESUVIUS” in MS V.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="GENRE">
                    <head type="section">Genre</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="MAJORMS">
                    <head type="section">Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>MS IA, MS V, [MS VI].</p>
                    <p>See MS IA, “Content,” e. 
                        According to the index of MS VI, the sixth page of the section of the manuscript now torn away contained a copy of “Vesuvius,” 
                        probably the rough draft, and it was followed two pages later by "Trafalgar". presentation copy, MS IA, “Content,” e.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Dated 1 February 1830 by Ruskin in MS V. 
                        For a possible February 8 presentation copy, MS IA, “Content,” e.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COMPPUB">
                    <head type="section">Composition &#x0026; Publication</head>
                    <p>Previously unpublished.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p>Ruskin's dating of the poem as February 1830 is in keeping with the publication of Friendship's Offering for 1830 
                        (marketed for the holiday season starting ca. November 1829), which contained a tale, “Il Vesuviano,” 
                        by the Reverend George Croly (see Works, 1:445). The tale was accompanied by a Turner engraving of Vesuvius, 
                        “the first piece of Turner I ever saw,” according to Ruskin in later years (Works, 13:428).</p>
                    
                    <p>Croly's story contains some slight details that Ruskin may have borrowed for his poem.</p>
                    
                    <p>Another possible source, as Helen Viljoen remarked (HGVP, box F.X), 
                        was Maria Edgeworth’s story “The Little Merchants” in The Parent’s Assistant. 
                        This tale would have interested the Ruskins for rewards bestowed on the honesty of a boy entrepreneur, Francisco, 
                        whose honorable actions lead to the discovery and cultivation of his artistic talents. 
                        In his climactic adventure, Francisco prudently removes his friends and family from the threat of Vesuvius’s eruption, 
                        and then, when the threat proves a dangerous reality, he heroically defends the property of an aristocratic patron from pillage. 
                        Francisco’s bravery is to be celebrated by an improvisatore “in a poem . . . on the late eruption of Mount Vesuvius,” 
                        but Ruskin’s poem does not fulfill this promise, his subject being the more ancient disaster of Herculaneum and Pompeii. 
                        Ruskin could have read about the ancient eruption in “The Little Merchants,” which includes an historical note on the event, 
                        and which sends Francisco into the cave of the excavated “subterraneous city” of Herculaneum to sketch the ruins 
                        (Edgeworth, Parent’s Assistant, 2:135, 105).</p>
                    
                    <p>Ruskin’s mother would have approved the Edgeworth story more than the other possible sources of this poem, 
                        the art and literature of the annuals. The Edgeworth stories were carefully written to “improve” the young reader morally, 
                        if not religiously. The annuals failed this test, when Margaret examined her son’s first Friendship’s Offering, 
                        a gift of his cousin Charles, who was employed by its publisher, Smith, Elder & Co.: 
                        “the plates are well done but they are not interesting  the tales are horrible enough  
                        the poetry very so I think  upon the whole it does not improve” 
                        (RFL, 208, letter of 31 October 1829, by which time the Friendship’s Offering for 1830 might have been published, 
                        although Burd’s note [RFL, 209 n. 6] fails to clarify reference to the annual volume for 1829, 
                        published in late 1828, or the one published in 1829, for 1830).</p>
                    <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                            <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                            <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="TEXTUALNOTE">
                    <head type="section">Textual Note</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>