<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <fileDesc xml:id="monastery_glosses_textual">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;The Monastery&#x201d;</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="BOOKSGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Text divisions and running heads (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi><persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s 
                    division of his poem into &#x201c;books&#x201d;, along with his imitation of running heads that change from one book to the next (at least until he abandons running heads altogether), 
                    does not correspond to the edition of <persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName>&#x02bc;s novel that was in the <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin library</persName>&#x2014;the 
                    <date when="1820">1820</date> first edition in three volumes, with the <placeName corresp="#LONDON">London</placeName> firm of <orgName corresp="#LONGMAN">Longman</orgName> allotted the lead position on the title page as managing publisher, 
                    and the <placeName corresp="#EDINBURGH">Edinburgh</placeName> firm of <orgName corresp="#CONSTABLEPUBLISHER">Constable</orgName> demoted to second place (see 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#DEARDENRUSKINLIBRARY"><persName corresp="#JSD">Dearden</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#DEARDENRUSKINLIBRARY"><hi rend="italic">The Library of John Ruskin</hi></title></ref>, 309 [nos. 2420&#x2013;21]; 
                    and on the rivalry of the two firms for control over <title type="book" corresp="#SCOTTMONASTERY"><hi rend="italic">The Monastery</hi></title>, see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FIELDINGMONASTERYESSAYONTHETEXT"><persName corresp="#PFIELDING">Fielding</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="FIELDINGMONASTERYESSAYONTHETEXT">&#x201c;Essay on the Text&#x201d;</title></ref>, 355&#x2013;64). 
                    The <orgName corresp="#LONGMAN">Longman</orgName> first edition divided the text into three volumes, each divided by chapters, with the chapter numbering starting anew with each volume. 
                    The running heads&#x2014;though set in small capitals, similarly to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s imitation in <ref type="apparatus" target="msiii_apparatus.php"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title></ref>&#x2014;are formed solely from the title of the novel 
                    and do not change with volumes and chapters. Finally, the page number is set on the same baseline as the running head, alternating right to left 
                    with recto and verso, and not centered beneath the running head as <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> devises.</p>
                    
                    <p>If <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> imitated any publication in particular, he apparently modeled his layout on a poem divided into books, 
                        and formatted with marginal line numbering. If so, the model was not from <persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName>&#x02bc;s poems, which are divided into cantos, not books; 
                        and <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s layout does not resemble that used by the <orgName corresp="#CONSTABLEPUBLISHER">Constable</orgName> firm and the printer, <persName corresp="#JAMESBALLANTYNE">James Ballantyne</persName>, 
                        which produced the editions owned by the Ruskins prior to 1830 (see 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#DEARDENRUSKINLIBRARY"><persName corresp="#JSD">Dearden</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#DEARDENRUSKINLIBRARY"><hi rend="italic">The Library of John Ruskin</hi></title></ref>, 306&#x2013;11 [nos. 2409, 2411, 2416, 2418, 2432]).</p></note> 
                    
                <note xml:id="UNKNOWNMARKGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Vertical mark (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>The 
                    purpose of this mark is unknown. It may be a deletion.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="INVERTEDSEMICOLONGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Inverted semicolon (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In 
                    this fair copy of <title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMONASTERY">&#x201c;The Monastery&#x201d;</title>, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> consistently forms a semicolon with the comma above the point.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="WRONGLINENUMBERGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Erroneous line number (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi><persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> omitted ten lines by writing 
                    <hi rend="italic">50</hi> where he should have written <hi rend="italic">40</hi>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="THEIRGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201c;their&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Misspelling for <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, which is spelled correctly in 
                    <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title> draft, <title type="manuscript" corresp="MSIAA1">&#x201c;come on good horse and let us see&#x201d;</title>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="MSIAA1VERSOGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201c;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#MTACKET">martin</persName> took his task as guide&#x201d; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>)&#x2014;</hi>The verso of the manuscript, <title type="manuscript" corresp="MSIAA1">&#x201c;come on good horse and let us see&#x201d;</title> 
                    (facsimile available of recto only), contains a line group starting &#x201c;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#MTACKET">martin</persName> took his task as guide&#x201d;, which, 
                    according to the sequence of lines as fair-copied in MS III, precedes the line group on the recto beginning &#x201c;come on good horse and let us see&#x201d;. 
                    In fact, the text of lines 14-62 (as numbered by Ruskin in the fair copy) loop around the two sides of the manuscript. Midway on the verso appear 
                    lines 20&#x2013;21, 14&#x2013;19, and 22&#x2013;25; the text continues with lines 26-59 on the recto; and the passage runs over to the verso again, 
                    with lines 60-62 at the top of the page, above the line group starting with lines 20-21.</p>
                    
                    <p>Physical characteristics of the manuscript lend themselves to an interpretation of the sequence of composition, but with significant uncertainty. 
                        The hand is Ruskin's cursive throughout, but on the verso, the medium is pencil, while on the recto the medium is ink. 
                        The sheet has been sheared and torn, resulting in lost portions of pencil text on the verso, while the ink text on the recto did not suffer from the tearing. 
                        Rather, on the recto, Ruskin appears to have fitted his writing to the margins that were left following the mutilation. 
                        Thus, it appears that the sheet was torn and reused after Ruskin wrote the lines in pencil on the verso, starting with lines 20-21; 
                        and then, after the mutilation, he wrote the ink text on the recto (see <ref type="apparatus" target="msia_apparatus.php">MS IA Apparatus</ref>).</p><!-- DCH: specify section of apparatus when ready -->
                    
                    <p>This reconstruction fails to account satisfactorily for the continuation of the text from the end of the recto, which is written in ink, 
                        to the three succeeding lines of text at the top of the verso, which are written to pencil. It is possible that this latter stage of composition was sequential, 
                        since the three lines are complete, unaffected by the tearing. On this evidence, Ruskin might be understood as composing the three lines sequentially, 
                        from the bottom of the ink verse on the recto. It seems odd, however, that Ruskin would have put down his pen at the bottom of the recto, 
                        and returned to pencil at the top of the verso. Would he have done so merely to remain in keeping the medium he had already used on that side of the sheet? 
                        As an alternative explanation, the ink text on the recto may be viewed as representing, not part of a continuous act of composition 
                        from the verso to the recto and back again to the verso; rather, the ink text may represent a discontinuous intervention--a copy or a new version of a witness, 
                        now lost, that had carried on from the text at the bottom verso of the surviving sheet. If the latter scenario is true, then the ink witness 
                        may be surviving evidence of even greater perplexity than what is shown by the compositional changes in the ink text itself (see subsequent textual gloss).</p>
                    
                    <p>In light of this uncertainty about what stages of composition may be represented by the ink and the pencil texts, respectively, 
                        the transcription is given in order
                    
                    <p>Owing to the mutilation of the sheet, to lines 20&#x2013;21 (i.e., &#x201c;so <persName type="fictional" corresp="#MTACKET">martin</persName> took his task as guide / 
                    and all the women did in him confide&#x201d;). Following this couplet, there occurs a horizontal rule followed by lines numbered 14&#x2013;19 and 22&#x2013;25 
                    by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> in the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> fair copy of book 3.</p>
                    
                    <p>The displacement of lines 21&#x2013;22 from the order in which they are found in fair copy cannot fully be explained 
                        owing to the damage to this manuscript. In the manuscript&#x02bc;s original state, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> may have indicated 
                        that lines 20&#x2013;21 were to be inserted in the place they occupy in fair copy, or he may have decided on this change 
                        during the process of fair copying. The former hypothesis might explain the presence of the horizontal rule 
                        in this passage of draft, a mark that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> used along with a metamark on the recto side of this manuscript 
                        to indicate that a verse line adjacent to the rule was to be inserted in another place.</p>
                    
                    </note>
    
                <note xml:id="OUTLETGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201c;let.&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Having divided <hi rend="italic">outlet</hi> with a line break for the sake of the rhyme, 
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> adds punctuation, perhaps in part to compensate for the confusion he introduces with the possibility of reading <hi rend="italic">let</hi> as a word, 
                    rather than as the second syllable of <hi rend="italic">outlet</hi>. At this stage in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s developing penmanship for fair&#x2010;copying, 
                    he rarely used punctuation as an ongoing rhetorical and grammatical feature, reserving punctuation marks as a separate overlay on the already fair&#x2010;copied text. 
                    See <ref type="apparatus" subtype="work" target="monastery_apparatus.php#COMPPUB1"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRTHEMONASTERY">&#x201c;The Monastery&#x201d;</title> Apparatus: Stage One of Composition, circa 1828</ref>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="EXEEDINGGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201c;exeeding&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Misspelling for <hi rend="italic">exceeding</hi>. 
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> had trouble with the word. In a rare instance in the early manuscripts of his visibly working out spelling, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> sounded out the syllables on the margin of the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title> sheet containing 
                    <title type="manuscript" corresp="MSIAA1">&#x201c;come on good horse and let us see&#x201d;</title>, writing first <hi rend="italic">eceede</hi>, 
                    then <hi rend="italic">exx</hi>, and finally and still incorrectly <hi rend="italic">exeeding</hi>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="AVENELSFATEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201c;but it was great avenels fate / . . . / to have a spirit in their line&#x201d; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>This 
                    passage underwent considerable revision in the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title> draft, <title type="manuscript" corresp="MSIAA1">&#x201c;come on good horse and let us see&#x201d;</title>. 
                    In <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>, the passage is interpreted in documentary XML markup as two substitutions, one simple and a second complex&#x2014;the latter subdivided into three actions. 
                    This note comments on possible interpretations of the sequence of those actions.</p>
                    
                    <p>In the first substitution, contained in the line &#x201c;but it was great <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate&#x201d;, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                        replaced a deleted word with &#x201c;great&#x201d;, which he wrote in the right margin. The deleted word is nearly illegible but appears to be &#x201c;gay&#x201d;.</p>
                    
                    <p>The second, more complex substitution involves several rejected and substituted lines. The sequence of this process of revision 
                        is open to at least three variable interpretations, though the documentary evidence of the component deletions and additions is clear, and 
                        can be subdivided into distinct actions, which lead clearly to the outcome in the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> fair&#x2010;copy passage of the <title type="poem" corresp="#JRMONASTERY">&#x201c;The Monastery&#x201d;</title>.</p>
                    
                    <p>Following &#x201c;but it was great <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate&#x201d;, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> composed two lines, 
                        &#x201c;to see things that nobody saw / except themselves, and would say pshaw&#x201d;. To obtain this account of the haunting of the <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">House of Avenel</orgName>, 
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> temporarily departed from the Halloween episode in <persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName>&#x02bc;s chapter 3 that he was mainly summarizing, in order to draw from a gossipy exchange 
                        between <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ELSPETGLENDINNING">Elspet Glendinning</persName> and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TTACKET">Tibb Tacket</persName> in chapter 4, in which <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TTACKET">Tibb</persName> boasts about spirits like the <persName type="fictional" corresp="#WHITELADY">White Maiden of Avenel</persName> that are peculiarly attached 
                        to &#x201c;&#x2018;great ancient families&#x2019;&#x201d; like the <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">Avenels</orgName>. From this exchange, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> borrowed dialogue that can be recognized, somewhat altered, 
                        in the couplet about &#x201c;<orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate&#x201d;: for example, <persName type="fictional" corresp="#TTACKET">Tibb</persName> observes that <persName type="fictional" corresp="#MARYAVENEL">Mary Avenel</persName>, having been born on Halloween, 
                        is able to &#x201c;&#x2018;see mair than ither folk&#x2019;&#x201d;; and the gruff &#x201c;pshaw&#x201d; is characteristic of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ELSPETGLENDINNING">Elspet</persName>, 
                        although in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s couplet the expression is suspended without a clear agent&#x2014;ambiguously applicable either to the <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">Avenel</orgName> family or to outsiders 
                        (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SCOTTMONASTERYFIELDING"><persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#SCOTTMONASTERY"><hi rend="italic">The Monastery</hi></title>, ed. <persName corresp="#PFIELDING">Fielding</persName></ref>, 
                        55&#x2013;56 [vol. 1, chap. 4]; and see also 40 [vol. 1, chap. 2]).</p>
                    
                    <p>The documentary evidence for next step in the process is open to multiple interpretations of the sequence of composition. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> may have composed the next couplet, 
                        &#x201c;so it was in this odd time / for a spirit haunted <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s line&#x201d;, with or without having made the deletion shown by strikethrough of the preceding couplet, 
                        &#x201c;to see things that nobody saw / except themselves, and would say pshaw&#x201d;. The two couplets read coherently in sequence if no lines are deleted&#x2014;&#x201c;but 
                        it was great <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate / to see things that nobody saw / except themselves, and would say pshaw / 
                        so it was in this odd time / for a spirit haunted <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenels</orgName> line&#x201d;. In fact, the flow is improved by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s insertion of &#x201c;and&#x201d; above the beginning of the line, 
                        &#x201c;so it was in this odd time&#x201d; (the conjunction appears also in the fair copy). But the second couplet also flows coherently, if awkwardly, 
                        from &#x201c;but it was great <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate&#x201d; with the intervening couplet omitted. Finally, a third possibility 
                        can be drawn from the deletion of the line, &#x201c;for a spirit haunted <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenels</orgName> line&#x201d;, in the manuscript: it is possible that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> never intended that line 
                        to form a couplet with the preceding line &#x201c;and so it was in this odd time&#x201d;; rather, the latter can be interpreted as a subtitution above the line, 
                        replacing &#x201c;for a spirit haunted <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenels</orgName> line&#x201d;. (While the interlinear spacing in the manuscript does not appear crowded, 
                        the line &#x201c;so it was in this odd time&#x201d; does appear compacted relative to the cursive hand in the other lines.)</p>
                    
                    <p>In the simplest reconstruction of the process, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> can be imagined as composing the two couplets following &#x201c;but it was great <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate&#x201d; 
                        without making any deletions. Then he deleted the first, second, and fourth lines of the two couplets, leaving just &#x201c;and so it was this odd time&#x201d;. 
                        As part of this change, he inserted an asterisk to serve as a metamark following &#x201c;but it was great <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate&#x201d;. 
                        The metamark directs the reader to a line near the bottom of the page, &#x201c;to have a spirit in their line&#x201d;, which is marked by corresponding asterisk, 
                        and set off by a horizontal rule. The metamark signals that this line is to be inserted following &#x201c;but it was great <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate&#x201d;, 
                        thus substituting for the three deleted lines, and forming a completed couplet with the remaining line, &#x201c;to have a spirit in their line&#x201d;. 
                        The resulting revised passage reads, as in the fair copy, &#x201c;but it was great <orgName type="fictional" corresp="#AVENEL">avenel</orgName>s fate / 
                        to have a spirit in their line / and so it was this odd time&#x201d;. This outcome involving the insertion of the substitute line, as directed by the metamark, 
                        unquestionably formed the final action of the change, regardless of the process of deletion and substitution that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> followed with respect to the preceding pair of couplets.</p></note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="AOGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201c;at ao&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Perhaps a misspelling of <hi rend="italic">so</hi>, 
                    or perhaps Scots dialect <hi rend="italic">ae</hi> for <hi rend="italic">one</hi> is intended, as in <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ELSPETGLENDINNING">Elspet Glendinning</persName>&#x02bc;s remark, 
                    &#x201c;I was mair beholden to ae Southron, and that was <persName type="fictional" corresp="#STAWARTHBOLTON">Stawarth Bolton</persName>&#x201d; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SCOTTMONASTERYFIELDING"><persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#SCOTTMONASTERY"><hi rend="italic">The Monastery</hi></title>, ed. <persName corresp="#PFIELDING">Fielding</persName></ref>, 
                    53 [vol. 1, chap. 4], 490).</p></note>
                
                
                
                    <note xml:id="TOOKHISTASKGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201c;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#MTACKET">martin</persName> took his task as guide&#x201d; 
                        (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>)&#x2014;</hi>With this line, the pencil draft on the verso 
                        of the manuscript, <title type="manuscript" corresp="MSIAA1">&#x201c;come on good horse and let us see&#x201d;</title>, 
                        skips backward from the preceding line numbered 62 by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> in the <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> fair copy of book 3 (i.e., &#x201c;but set off at . . . good rate&#x201d;) 
                        </note>

                <note xml:id="SERJEANTGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201c;serjeant&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Interlinearly 
                    and above this line, &#x201c;serjeant&#x201d; is written in pencil print. The hand appears to be <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s. Presumably, he was copying the word 
                    from <persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName>&#x02bc;s text in order to confirm its spelling, as he was attempting to write the word in longhand.</p></note>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>