<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in <hi rend="italic">Title of Printed Work</hi> (Date)</title>
                <!--The xml:ids for author and editor below should include the first, middle, and last initials of the author and the editor, respectively.-->
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#APW">Author of Printed Work</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#EPW">Editor of Printed Work</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#SEM">Sarah Elizabeth Montelepre</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Poems of John Ruskin</title>
                        <title type="sub">Volume I: Poems Written in Boyhood, 1826-1835</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1891">1891</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">xxiii</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Simple Prose. Delete this <div/> if not used.-->
            <div type="prose">
                <head type="title">Sermon VI</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Verso_2"/>
                    <head type="chapter">The lives of the Patriarchs</head>
                    <p>6 verse, of 1. <title type="scripture" corresp="#EXODUS">Exodus</title>.  And <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName> died,
                    <lb/>and all his brethren, and all that gene
                    <lb/>ration.  I have read these words, in
                    <lb/>order, that through them, I may be
                    <lb/>enabled to make some general rem
                    <lb/>arks, on the lives, the habits and the
                    <lb/>acts of the patriarchs, and these most
                    <lb/>certainly require attention, in order, to
                    <lb/>discover the amount of the privileges,
                    <lb/>which they enjoyed, and also, the uses,
                    <lb/>which they made of those privileges
                    <lb/>Now, the whole family of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, had
                    <lb/>formerly, and have now, clear statement,
                    <lb/>and evidences, capable of proving the per
                    <lb/>fect truth of those statements, but they
                    <lb/>neither had, nor have, such a clear,
                    <lb/>and certain application of the gospel, to
                    <lb/>individuals, as may be capable, of&#x2014;at
                    <lb/>once affording them assurance of their
                    <lb/>safety, and the peace, happiness, and
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Recto_3"/>
                    <lb/>security, consequent upon that assur&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ance.  Let us therefore consider, how.
                    <lb/>for the pledges and promises (of the
                    <lb/>truth of which no doubt could possib
                    <lb/>ly be entertained, inasmuch as this was
                    <lb/>a period, in which visions, and direct
                    <lb/>communications with <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, were, by
                    <lb/>no means uncommon) were, in fact
                    <lb/>redeemed to the ancient Patriarchs, &#x0026;
                    <lb/>in pursuance of this design, I should
                    <lb/>wish first to make a few remarks, upon
                    <lb/>the character of the blessings.  And we
                    <lb/>shall therefore refer to the twenty sixth
                    <lb/>Chapter of <title type="scripture" corresp="#GENESIS">Genesis</title>, in which at the third
                    <lb/>verse, we find the blessing pronounced by
                    <lb/>the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> upon <persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName>,.&#x201D;<!--or is it supposed to be: "&#x201C;"-->  Sojourn in this
                    <lb/>land, and I will be with thee, and will
                    <lb/>bless thee, for unto thee and to thy seed
                    <lb/>I will give all these countries and I
                    <lb/>will perform the oath which I swore
                    <lb/>unto <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> thy father, &#x0026;c. &#x2014;  We
                    <lb/>find, that this blessing was essen
                    <lb/>tially the same with that at first pro
                    <lb/>nounced upon <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, and which
                    <lb/>was transferred from father to son.
                    <lb/>by <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> himself.  It was again trans
                    <lb/>ferred from <persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName> to <persName corresp="#JACOB">Jacob</persName>, twenty&#x2010;se
                    <lb/>venth, chapter, 27 verse,  But still, there
                    <lb/>remains a very great indistinctness, &#x0026;
                    <lb/>generality, in the stating of all these
                    <lb/>blessings, which were transferred from
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#Abraham">Abraham</persName> to <persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName>, and from <persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName>,
                    <lb/>to <persName corresp="#JACOB">Jacob</persName>,  They are remarkable,  be&#x2010;
                    <lb/>cause they combine such a remarka
                    <lb/>ble degree of certainty, with so much
                    <lb/>generality.  They were so vague as to 
                    <lb/>leave ample reason for the patriarchs
                    <lb/>to exercise there faith and there was
                    <lb/>sufficient and certain evidence to af
                    <lb/>ford ground for that faith.  But when
                    <lb/>the faith however strong it might
                    <lb/>be, was only extended to the truth
                    <lb/>of the promises, and not to their ap
                    <lb/>preciation, it gave room for very great
                    <lb/>errors, as in the instance of <persName corresp="#ESAU">Esau</persName> and
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#JACOB">Jacob</persName>.  <persName corresp="#ESAU">Esau</persName> was the elder, and <persName corresp="#JACOB">Jacob</persName>
                    <lb/>the younger, but <persName corresp="#JACOB">Jacob</persName> was the favou
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Verso_3"/>
                    <lb/>rite of his mother, and the practised fraud
                    <lb/>to obtain for him a blessing of which, althoug<!--h?-->
                    <lb/>she knew the certain and positive truth
                    <lb/>yet the personal application of which
                    <lb/>she knew not.  We have however, many
                    <lb/>instances of the same feeling, throughout
                    <lb/>all the lives of the patriarchs, occasioned
                    <lb/>by this imperfect kind of faith, but this
                    <lb/>does not atall, excuse the proceeding.  At
                    <lb/>the present time, we know the certainty 
                    <lb/>of salvation through <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName> the certain 
                    <lb/>ty of general salvation is attested by suf
                    <lb/>ficient evidence, but still, it is dif
                    <lb/>ficult to apply it personally, to bring
                    <lb/>it home to ourselves, there we have 
                    <lb/>doubts, and fears, and faulterings, we be
                    <lb/>lieve, but we cannot apply, and we know
                    <lb/>but we cannot trust, It is this, which 
                    <lb/>causes us now, not to be sufficiently attach
                    <lb/>ed to the word of God, we hear of the word<!--???--> kingdom of 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, and we believe in its truth, and yet
                    <lb/>we will not exert ourselves in order to ob
                    <lb/>tain it.  I call your, own experience to
                    <lb/>witness that this is the fact although it 
                    <lb/>might <del rend="strikethrough">als</del> be inferred <del rend="strikethrough">fr</del> merely from the 
                    <lb/>nature of the human mind.  Let us es
                    <lb/>cape as much as possible from this kind of
                    <lb/>feeling which so frequently influenced the
                    <lb/>actions of the patriarchs, and let us en
                    <lb/>deavour to imitate their settled habits, not
                    <lb/>the incidental actions, which sometimes were
                    <lb/>contrary to those habits  But it may be
                    <lb/>asked if this state of mind exists now, 
                    <lb/>how can we escape from sin.  Now, the
                    <lb/>promises say. the blood of <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName> cleanseth 
                    <lb/>from all sin, and our only inquiry must
                    <lb/>be,  Have we accepted this blood, For the
                    <lb/>doubting state of mind must all be traced
                    <lb/>to unbelief  There must be some doubt of 
                    <lb/>the testimony of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, if we cannot make
                    <lb/>it ours.  There cannot be entire belief in the
                    <lb/>truth combined, with want of faith in per
                    <lb/>sonal application  But if, in some cases;
                    <lb/>we find this state of mind on the part 
                    <lb/>of the patriarchs, let us observe the particu
                    <lb/>lars of <del rend="strikethrough">part</del> some of the actions occaison
                    <lb/>ed by that doubt.  <persName corresp="#JACOB">Jacob</persName> was instruc&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ted to practise fraud, in order to obtain
                    <lb/>the blessing of a <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> who was altogether ho
                    <lb/>ly and just, <persName corresp="#REBEKAH">Rebecca</persName> must, have had a
                    <lb/>strange idea of the blessing of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, to sup
                    <lb/>pose that it was to be obtained in this 
                    <lb/>manner, We must suppose that she was
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Recto_4"/>
                    <lb/>either altogether ignorant of the attribut
                    <lb/>es of the <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> whose blessing she thus
                    <lb/>endeavoured to obtain, or else, that she 
                    <lb/>had at the time entirely forgotten them
                    <lb/>We would bring this before you, in order
                    <lb/>to show how persons may be led away 
                    <lb/>by their own views.  Can we say, that
                    <lb/>there is nothing done among us at the
                    <lb/>present day, which resembles this action
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#REBEKAH">Rebecca</persName>s.  <del rend="strikethrough">These d</del> In these days, as
                    <lb/>we have before said <del rend="strikethrough">?</del> men were freq
                    <lb/>uently in direct communion with the. 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName>, yet this did not <del rend="strikethough">hinder</del> pre
                    <lb/>vent these actions from taking place. &#x0026;,
                    <lb/>in the same way although we have seen
                    <lb/>the fulfilment of the promises yet this
                    <lb/>cannot prevent similar feelings.  I will not
                    <lb/>say what they may be, every one must&#x2010;
                    <lb/>know that within himself, And we see
                    <lb/>that although the fraud might be said to
                    <lb/>have obtained a partial blessing, yet it was
                    <lb/>attended with infinite misery, one torment
                    <lb/>ing circumstance succeeded another, and 
                    <lb/>at the end of his life he was obliged to
                    <lb/>confess, that &#x201C;Few and evil have been the
                    <lb/>days of my pilgrimage.  I am afraid that
                    <lb/>many parents at the present day, fol
                    <lb/>low the example of <persName corresp="#REBEKAH">Rebecca</persName> in endeavou
                    <lb/>ring to provide rather for the present good
                    <lb/>of their children, that for the future ben
                    <lb/>efit.  Perhaps they would be warned, if they 
                    <lb/>would consider the circumstances attendant
                    <lb/>upon the very partial blessings of which Re
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#REBEKAH">becca</persName><!--"Re" on previous line--> obtained for <persName corresp="#JACOB">Jacob</persName>.</p>
                    <lb/><p>Again.  We cannot dwell upon all the 
                    <lb/>circumstances of the life of <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName>, but it
                    <lb/>affords a sufficient number of instances of 
                    <lb/>the same feeling, We find in the first place
                    <lb/>providence permitting him to be carried in
                    <lb/>to <placeName corresp="#EGYPT">Egypt</placeName>, in order <del rend="strikethrough">that</del> to promote his fu
                    <lb/>ture good and then the famine compell&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ing his brethren, to go up into <placeName corresp="#EGYPT">Egypt</placeName> for corn
                    <lb/>and we must next consider what influ
                    <lb/>enced the conduct of <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName> toward his
                    <lb/>brethren, (neither excusing their wickedness,
                    <lb/>nor forgetting to distinguish the acts of Jo
                    <lb/>seph, from his habits) In the first place
                    <lb/>5 verse. of XLII chapter of <title type="scripture" corresp="#GENESIS">Genesis</title>, we are 
                    <lb/>told that <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName> knew his brethren but
                    <lb/>they knew not him. and this may be
                    <lb/>easily accounted for if we consider, that
                    <lb/>when <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName> was last seen by his 
                    <lb/>brethren, he was but a youth, and in
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Verso_4"/>
                    <lb/>consequence may be supposed to have alter
                    <lb/>ed much more, during the period of at least
                    <lb/>seven years which must since have elapsed &#x0026; 
                    <lb/>also the circumstance of <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName>Joseph were so com
                    <lb/>pletely altered as to render it difficult for
                    <lb/>his brethren to recognise him, while theirs
                    <lb/>remained exactly the same, But we find
                    <lb/>that although <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName> recognised them at 
                    <lb/>once, yet he said that they were spies,
                    <lb/>and then adopts a test, swearing, by the 
                    <lb/>life of Pharaoh<!--does this need a persName tag?-->, a profane and idolatrous
                    <lb/>oath that &#x201C;except your youngest brother 
                    <lb/>come hither ye shall not go forth hence
                    <lb/>Again, during a period of at least 
                    <lb/>9 years, although his father was within
                    <lb/>a very little distance, he made no inquiry
                    <lb/>after him, it was at least 9 years, for the 
                    <lb/>seven years of plenty had past away, and
                    <lb/>we find in the 6th verse of the 45 chapter
                    <lb/>For these two years hath the famine been
                    <lb/>in the land, Therefore without reckoning the 
                    <lb/>time which past between <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName>s first be
                    <lb/>ing sold into <placeName corresp="#EGYPT">Egypt</placeName>, and the commencement 
                    <lb/>of the years of plenty, and which may have
                    <lb/>been considerable, we find that during a 
                    <lb/>period of nine years he showed no anxiety
                    <lb/>about the welfare of his father and made 
                    <lb/>no inquiry after him. we might have
                    <lb/>expected that as soon as the famine com&#x2010;
                    <lb/>menced, he would <del rend="strikethrough">have</del> at least then
                    <lb/>have informed his father of his prosper
                    <lb/>ity and desired him to come to up into <placeName corresp="#EGYPT">Egypt</placeName> 
                    <lb/>in order that he might be able to assist 
                    <lb/>him, but we find him doing nothing 
                    <lb/>of the kind. This conduct was not worthy 
                    <lb/>of the rank to which he had attained al
                    <lb/>though it was most likely this elevation 
                    <lb/>which affected his principles and caused
                    <lb/>him to act in this manner.  I know  
                    <lb/>that the history of <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName> has been com&#x2010;
                    <lb/>monly held up in quite a different 
                    <lb/>light, It has been considered as an entertain
                    <lb/>ing tale, and an excellent example, while,
                    <lb/>on the contrary, the view which I have 
                    <lb/>taken <del rend="strikethrough">Joseph</del> of this subject appears to 
                    <lb/>bring down his actions from ideal to real,
                    <lb/>and to the common level of human nat
                    <lb/>ure. and we find that the effect which 
                    <lb/>it produced on his brothers was the same 
                    <lb/>as that with which it has struck me
                    <lb/>(5 verse of 50 chapter) And when <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName>s
                    <lb/>brethren saw that their father was dead they
                    <lb/>said &#x201C;<persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName> will peradventure hate us and
                    <lb/>will certainly requite us all the evil which
                    <lb/>we did unto him; They were more.
                    <lb/>struck with the incident than with 
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Recto_5"/>
                    <lb/>the habits, which was probably caused by their
                    <lb/>being as soon as they came into <placeName corresp="#EGYPT">Egypt</placeName>, sent
                    <lb/>into the Land of <placeName corresp="#GOSHEN">Goshen</placeName> were being at some
                    <lb/>distance from the court they could not
                    <lb/>have an opportunity of witnessing the hab
                    <lb/>its of <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName>.  The impression on <persName corresp="#JACOB">Jacob</persName> was, 
                    <lb/>we find, the same,.  Now I do not say this,
                    <lb/>in order to blot a character in other cir&#x2010;
                    <lb/>cumstances so fair, but in order to be enabled
                    <lb/>to derive benefit from it. Let us always 
                    <lb/>flee from pride with abhorrence. Pride
                    <lb/>was <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName>s bane, How much more con-
                    <lb/>sistent would it have been, had he sent
                    <lb/>to his fathers home, and communicated. 
                    <lb/>with him, informed him of his prosperity
                    <lb/>and invited him to share it.  But no, on 
                    <lb/>the contrary he adopted the practises of the
                    <lb/>Pagan court in ee<!--??--> which he was, and instead
                    <lb/>of producing any thing like the object which
                    <lb/>I think erroneously he is said to have
                    <lb/>had in view, namely to <del rend="strikethrough">com</del> soften his
                    <lb/>brethren and cause them to repent, he only
                    <lb/>made them fear him. And, had <persName corresp="#JOSEPH">Joseph</persName>
                    <lb/>previously been told of the conduct which
                    <lb/>he afterwards observed toward his breth
                    <lb/>ren he might have said like <persName corresp="#HAZAEL">Hazel</persName>
                    <lb/>to the <persName corresp="#ELISHA">prophet of Damascus</persName>, "Is thy ser
                    <lb/>vant a dog, that he should do this 
                    <lb/>thing.  Let us therefore never say, I can
                    <lb/>not, I will not do this, or that, but 
                    <lb/>let us cast ourselves entirely on the will
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, and thus endeavour to escape from 
                    <lb/>the short comings, and cling to the settled 
                    <lb/>and exemplary habits of which an example
                    <lb/>is so constantly and steadily held forth
                    <lb/>to us as a lamp unto our feet and a light
                    <lb/>unto our path in the various and remar
                    <lb/>kable events, or the holy and faithful Lives 
                    <lb/>of the Patriarchs.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>