<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="source_of_the_arveron_prose_glosses_contextual">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Source of the Arveron"</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#AEH">Aimee E. Harris</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2017-07-19">July 19, 2017</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="WALKTOTHESOURCE" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;It is thus that I look back upon our first walk at <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, 
                    to the <geogName corresp="#ARVERON">Source of the Arveron</geogName>&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <title type="book" corresp="#JRWORKSLE"><hi rend="italic">Works</hi></title> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi><geogName corresp="#ARVERON">The Arveyron</geogName>, 
                    a glacial tributary that rises from the <geogName corresp="#MERDEGLACE">Mer de Glace</geogName>, which in the nineteenth century extended to the village of <placeName corresp="#BOISBERNARD">Bois</placeName> and was there called the <geogName corresp="#GLACIERDESBOIS">Glacier du Bois</geogName>. 
                    On <date when="1833-08-14">14 August 1833</date>, the Ruskins set out from <placeName corresp="#GENEVA">Geneva</placeName> for the valley of <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamonix</placeName> (<placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, in their spelling), the final major excursion of their summer journey. 
                    They arrived in the village on <date when="1833-08-15">15 August</date> in rainy weather, prompting <persName corresp="#SALVADOR">Salvador</persName> to procure a loan of books, which included a set of 
                    <title type="book" corresp="#SAUSSUREVOYAGES"><hi rend="italic">Voyages dans les Alpes</hi></title> by <persName corresp="HBS">Horace&#x2010;B&#x00E9;n&#x00E9;dict de Saussure</persName>, 
                    a copy of which <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> would receive for his birthday in <date when="1834">1834</date> (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL">Burd, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 278, 280 n. 1). 
                    Shortly after arrival, <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName> and <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> ventured out on a walk to view the <geogName corresp="#ARVERON">source of the Arveyron</geogName>, 
                    while <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> and cousin <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary</persName> stayed behind at the inn. Their courier, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="salvador_note.php"><persName corresp="#SALVADOR">Salvador</persName></ref>, 
                    also remained behind, so it is likely that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and his father 
                    were attended by the youths whom John mentions as competing to lead them to the river&#x02BC;s source. 
                    Children also swarmed <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary</persName> and <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> when they set out (likewise without <persName corresp="#SALVADOR">Salvador</persName>, apparently) to catch up with <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName> and <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName>. 
                    The ladies walked alongside the <geogName corresp="#ARVERON">Arve</geogName> until they reached a village, where they were told the view lay another quarter&#x2010;hour&#x02BC;s walk ahead, so they decided to turn back, 
                    &#x201C;to the great regret of our little man&#x201D; who was guiding them &#x201C;and a number of children who continually kept saying that it was a fine sight well worth seeing, 
                    using many times the terms &#x2018;superbe, magnifique&#x2019; &#x0026;c &#x0026;c&#x201D;. Returned to the inn, <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary</persName> and <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> were soon reunited with <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName> and <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName>, 
                    who returned &#x201C;much pleased with the sight&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson, 1833</title></ref>, 128&#x2013;30).</p>
                    
                    <p>According to <persName corresp="#JM">John Murray III</persName> (<date notBefore="1808" notAfter="1892">1808&#x2013;92</date>), in his <date when="1838">1838</date> guidebook to <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Switzerland</placeName>, 
                        the excursion to the source of the <geogName corresp="#ARVERON">Arveyron</geogName> was &#x201C;a delightful walk of an hour, along the plain of the valley, 
                        crossing beautiful meadows, and a little forest.&#x201D; The so&#x2010;called source is an &#x201C;affluent of the <geogName corresp="#ARVE">Arve</geogName>&#x201D; that &#x201C;issues from below the vault of ice with which the <geogName corresp="#GALCIERDESBOIS">Glacier du Bois</geogName>, 
                    the <geogName corresp="#MERDEGLACE">Mer de Glace</geogName> terminates. . . . The vault of ice varies greatly in different seasons, and the author, at different times, has remarked a change 
                    of from 30 to 100 feet of height in the arch. It may be entered, but this is dangerous, and some have suffered for their temerity. . . . The danger is, that blocks 
                    of ice may detach themselves from the vault. . . . The scenery around the source is very grand, the deep blackness of the depth of vault, the bright and beautiful azure 
                    where the light is transmitted through the ice. The enormous rocks brought down by the glacier from the mountains above, here tumble over, 
                    and are deposited in the bed of the <geogName corresp="#ARVERON">Arve</geogName>. Here, too, the dark forest, and the broken trunks of pines, add to the wild character of the scene&#x201D;. 
                    Through this forest, a steeper and more difficult path also descended to the river&#x02BC;s glacier source, leading &#x201C;active and strong&#x201D; visitors who had set out first for the <geogName corresp="#MONTANVERT">Montanvert</geogName> 
                    to visit the river&#x02BC;s source before they returned to <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamonix village</placeName> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITERZERLAND1838"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 297).</p></note>

                <note xml:id="VARIETIESOFCHILDISHBEAUTY" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;What variaties of childish beauty we met with in that short walk, . . . all expecting a similar distinction, 
                    but who, finding the post of honour preoccupied, followed very gravely, en suite&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi><persName corresp="#FMT">Frances Trollope</persName> 
                    (<date notBefore="1769" notAfter="1863">1779&#x2013;1863</date>) similarly encountered child&#x2010;guides when touring <placeName corresp="#GERMANY">Germany</placeName>, where she 
                    &#x201C;constantly found that these little local urchins are excellent in that capacity [of tour guide]. They know every mysterious hole and cranny; 
                    and have a marvellous talent of helping out their words, in answer to our imperfect German inquiries, with most amusing and expressive grimaces.&#x201D; 
                    In <placeName corresp="#HEIDELBERG">Heidelberg</placeName>, as her family party was preparing to ascend the path to the castle, they found themselves &#x201C;accosted . . . by numberless little boys, 
                    who petitioned for the honour of serving us as guides amid the ruins. Their mode of address was very engaging; for they uniformly prefaced the request 
                    by presenting to each of us a pretty nosegay of freshly&#x2010;gathered flowers, out of the little baskets with which they were furnished, 
                    apparently as a sort of professional property. We selected a fine bright&#x2010;looking little fellow, who performed the office admirably; 
                    and, under his guidance, we now traversed the whole of this amazing fabric [of the castle ruins]&#x201D;.</p>
                    
                    <p>In one episode narrated by <persName corresp="#FMT">Trollope</persName>, the competition among the boys to proffer their services turned less than charming. 
                    Wishing to ascend the heights above the castle, the Trollope family chose a &#x201C;young rogue [who] testified his satisfaction, by every imaginable demonstration of glee. 
                    He smiled, he laughed, he bowed, as he scampered on before us; but, ere we had gone fifty yards, a boy, more than twice his age, presented himself, 
                    and, pushing aside the little one, began to chatter forth his own information, with an air of great importance. We wished to get rid of him, but it was impossible, 
                    and we proceeded with our double escort. On reaching the top of the ridge, . . . the little fellow stepped eagerly forward to point out the beautiful valley, 
                    and its bright clear brook. This was more than the senior could bear; and seizing upon his rival, with no gentle gripe, he thrust him rudely back. 
                    The gay smiles of the poor boy gave place to a burst of tears; whereupon I instantly found German enough to make my election clearly understood: 
                    &#x2018;Nein geld fur sie&#x2019;, was sufficient to make the elder stalk off, and my little man remained master the field. I never witnessed a prettier ebullition of happiness 
                    than this triumph produced. He has bowed his merry head every time I have looked at him; gathered every flower in our path to present to me; 
                    and, in short, made me feel exceedingly well pleased with myself for having protected the weak against the strong&#x201D;.
                    The episode is summed up in a genre scene amid the sublime landscape: &#x201C;My little guide sat on a neighbouring stone, with his elbow resting on his knee; 
                    looking down upon the river, and its boats, the town, and its castles, with an air of most happy idleness&#x201D;  
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#TROLLOPEBELGIUM"><persName corresp="#FMT">Trollope</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#TROLLOPEBELGIUM"><hi rend="italic">Belgium and Western Germany in 1833</hi></title></ref>, 280, 265&#x2013;66, 280&#x2013;81, 279).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="MONTANVERT" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold"><placeName corresp="#MONTANVERT">The Montanvert</placeName> (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>; <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> [<date when="1903">1903</date>])&#x2014;</hi>An 
                    elevated viewpoint overlooking the <geogName corresp="#MERDEGLACE">Mer de Glace</geogName>, the confluence of three glaciers that in the eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries 
                    advanced into the edge of the valley of <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamounix</placeName>. A path led from the village to the top of the <placeName corresp="#MONTANVERT">Montanvert</placeName>. 
                    For the Ruskins&#x02BC; excursion to this scenic outlook, see the poem, <ref type="witness" target="chamouni_poem_msvii.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRCHAMOUNI">&#x201C;Chamouni&#x201D;</title></ref> and glosses.</p></note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>