<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="andrews_edward_note.xml">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Edward Andrews (1787-1841)</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-25">October 25, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">Edward Andrews (1787&#x2013;1841)</head>
                <p>Andrews was a popular Dissenting (Congregationalist) clergyman, whose preaching the Ruskins attended starting ca. 1826, 
                    and who tutored Ruskin in classical languages starting in 1829 until ca. 1833-34.</p>
                <p>In a biography of <persName corresp="#EAP">Andrews's daughter, Emily</persName> (1824-62)--who married <persName corresp="#CKDP">Coventry Patmore</persName> (1823-96), 
                    and who modeled the archetypal domestic virtues of the Victorian wife and mother for Patmore's poem, 
                    <hi rend="italic">The Angel in the House</hi> (1854-62)--<persName corresp="#IA">Ian Anstruther</persName> 
                    presents the Reverend Andrews as combining evangelical seriousness with a robust appreciation of the arts. 
                    Descended from a learned and sophisticated Essex family, he followed his father and grandfather into the Nonconformist clergy, 
                    studying at <orgName corresp="#HOXTONACAD">Hoxton Theological College</orgName>, and then at <orgName corresp="#GLASGOWUNIV">Glasgow University</orgName> (the latter a Scottish connection 
                    that would have recommended him to the Ruskins' favor) 
                    (<ref type="bibiography" target="bibliography.php#ANSTRUTHERCOVENTRYPATMORESANGEL"><hi rend="italic">Coventry Patmore's Angel</hi></ref>, 9, 12). 
                    According to <persName corresp="#EPH">Edwin Paxton Hood</persName> (1820-85), a Congregational minister and a prolific writer about the preaching of his time, 
                    Andrews maintained that "'God . . . should be worshipped with the best of everything . . . --best architecture, best painting, 
                    best music, best sculpture, best poetry, and best genius" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HOODVOCATIONPREACHER"><hi rend="italic">Vocation of the Preacher</hi></ref>, 209, revised and expanded 
                    from <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#NOIRLAMPSOFTHETEMPLE"><hi rend="italic">Lamps of the Temple</hi></ref> [1852], first published under the pseudonym, <persName corresp="EPHPSEUD">L&#x02BC;Agneau Noir</persName>).</p>
                <p>Andrews entered the Congregationalist <orgName corresp="#HOXTONACAD">Hoxton Academy</orgName> in 1808. Founded in 1778, Hoxton was at this time a growing and important academy, 
                    accommodating 30-40 students in residence (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GLENLAUNCHINGCLERICALCAREER">Glen, &#x201C;Launching a Clerical Career in Late Georgian England&#x201D;</ref>, 645). 
                    The principal, a Scottish divine, <persName corresp="#RSREV">Robert Simpson</persName> (1746-1817), did not have the reputation of a scholar, 
                    and candidates were chosen primarily for their "good natural abilities," zeal, and commitment to evangeical doctrine 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#NUTTALLTRAININGHOXTON">Nuttall, &#x201C;Training for Hoxton and Highbury&#x201D;</ref>, 477; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GLENLAUNCHINGCLERICALCAREER">Glen, &#x201C;Launching a Clerical Career in Late Georgian England&#x201D;</ref>,643-44). 
                    Nonetheless, by the time of Andrews's matriculation, the Academy was observing higher standards of learning, 
                    including securing scholarships to <orgName corresp="#GLASGOWUNIV">Glasgow University</orgName>. An 1810 syllabus shows that available studies included the following, 
                    as divided among three tutors: "Hebrew and biblical criticism, Jewish antiquities, 
                    evidences of divine revelation, systematic divinity, ecclesiastical history, and its connexion with profane [especially Roman] history; . . . 
                    English grammar, geography, Latin (including prose composition) and Greek; . . . pneumatology, logic, and belles lettres, 
                    with special regard to pulpit composition and elocution." Students who, like Andrews, proceeded to Glasgow University fell under 
                    the supervision of <persName corresp="#GEREV">Greville Ewing</persName> (1767-1841), a Congregational minister and a tutor at the Glasgow Theological Academy 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#THOMPSONHOXTON">Thompson, &#x201C;Hoxton [Independent] Academy (1791&#x2013;1826) and Highbury College (1826&#x2013;1850)&#x201D;</ref></p>
                <p>The Ruskins began hearing Andrews preach in the parish of Walworth, which was a village of lying only a few miles south of London Bridge. Like Camberwell, a little farther to the south 
                    where the Ruskins lived, Walworth was a rapidly growing suburb but still on the edge of the open country and woods around Norwood and Dulwich. 
                    The Andrewses' household resembled the Ruskins' with its growing collection of pictures on the walls, a substantial library on the shelves, and gardens outside, 
                    but it would have been a much busier and noisier place than Herne Hill, with over seventeen inhabitants by the beginning of 1831, including Andrews and his wife, 
                    <persName corresp="#EHSA">Elizabeth (nee Elizabeth Honor Symons)</persName>, who was learned and fond of music like her husband; twelve children 
                    (by June 1831, two would die in infancy); three servants; and a few penurious clergymen dependent on the Andrews's charity. 
                    In addition, a constant flow of visitors was drawn to the house 
                    by the family's sociability and parish responsibilities 
                    (<ref type="bibiography" target="bibliography.php#ANSTRUTHERCOVENTRYPATMORESANGEL"><hi rend="italic">Coventry Patmore's Angel</hi></ref>, 13, 19).</p>
                <p>Andrews officiated in his own chapel in Walworth, <placeName type="building" corresp="#BERESFORDSTREETCHAPEL">Beresford Street Chapel</placeName>, which adjoined his house. 
                    He was at first a candidate for <placeName type="building" corresp="#CAMDENCHAPEL">Camden Chapel</placeName> in Camberwell, 
                    where he stirred such excitement that the congregation demanded him for their pastor. Blocked by their trustees, 
                    some members of the congregation broke away and built the Walworth chapel for him, financed to some extent by Andrews's wealthy father-in-law 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#CLEALSTORYCONGREGATIONALISM">Cleal, <hi rend="italic">The Story of Congregationalism in Surrey</hi></ref>, 105; 
                    <ref type="bibiography" target="bibliography.php#ANSTRUTHERCOVENTRYPATMORESANGEL"><hi rend="italic">Coventry Patmore's Angel</hi></ref>, 13). 
                    Such generous arrangements were not unheard-of among the most popular preachers--especially those whose congregations included wealthy members--the 
                    largest of such complexes being <placeName type="building" corresp="#SURREYCHAPEL">Surrey Chapel</placeName>, built to accommodate audiences of 3,000 for the preaching 
                    of <persName corresp="#RHREV">Rowland Hill</persName> (1744-1833) in <placeName corresp="#BLACKFRIARS">Blackfriars</placeName>, London 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GLENLAUNCHINGCLERICALCAREER">Glen, &#x201C;Launching a Clerical Career in Late Georgian England&#x201D;</ref>, 649; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HILLDNB">Munden, &#x201C;Hill, Rowland (1744&#x2013;1833)&#x201D;</ref>). The crowds pressing to hear Andrews 
                    soon grew too large for the Beresford Street Chapel, and Andrews decided to finance an expansion with the aid of a new mortgage, which ultimately proved a ruinous 
                    encumberment (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#CLEALSTORYCONGREGATIONALISM">Cleal, <hi rend="italic">The Story of Congregationalism in Surrey</hi></ref>, 105). 
                    In his glory days, Andrews attracted crowds larger than could gain seating even in the expanded structure accommodating 1,600 seats 
                    <ref type="bibiography" target="bibliography.php#ANSTRUTHERCOVENTRYPATMORESANGEL"><hi rend="italic">Coventry Patmore's Angel</hi></ref>, 22-23).</p>
                <p>In Praeterita, Ruskin remembered the chapel as an example of "the Londonian chapel in its perfect type, definable as accurately as a Roman basilica,--an oblong, flat-ceiled barn, 
                    lighted by windows with semi-circular heads, brick-arched, filled by small-paned glass held by iron bars, like fine threaded halves of cobwebs; galleries propped 
                    on iron pipes, up both sides; pews, well shut in, each of them, by partitions of plain deal, and neatly brass-latched deal doors, filling the barn floor, 
                    all but its two lateral straw-matted passages; pulpit, sublimely isolated, central from sides and clear of altar rails at end; a stout, four-legged box 
                    of well-grained wainscot, high as the level of front galleries, and decorated with a cushion of crimson velvet, padded six inches thick, with gold tassels at the corners, 
                    which was a great resource to me when I was tired of the sermon, because I liked watching the rich colour of the folds and creases that came in it when the clergyman thumped it." 
                    Like his representation in the autobiography of the toyless austerity of his boyhood, Ruskin is exaggerating the description, here in order to make the point that his 
                    "well-formed habit [in youth] of narrowing myself to happiness within . . . four brick walls" supported his "acute perception and deep feeling of the beauty of architecture 
                    and scenery abroad" (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 35:132); and see 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HANSONPRAETERITAEVANGELICAL">Hanson, &#x201C;Ruskin&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> and Landscape in Evangelical Children&#x02BC;s Education&#x201D;</ref>, 45-52). 
                    While an 1824 <title type="artwork" corresp="#HASSELLBERESFORDCHAPEL">watercolor of the exterior of Beresford Chapel</title> by <persName corresp="#JHARTIST">John Hassell</persName> (1767-1825), 
                    and a comic sketch of the interior of that "dreary Bethal" by <persName corresp="#ECBJ">Edward Burne-Jones</persName>, suggest 
                    that Ruskin's prose picture captures accurately enough the "perfect type" of the late-Georgian meeting house, 
                    <persName corresp="#EPH">Hood</persName> remembered that the building's unusually rich adornments "gave you certainly no idea of the dissenting conventicle." 
                    There were "stained glass, and the <persName corresp="#AARON">Aaronic</persName> and <persName corresp="#MOSES">Mosaic</persName> figures, 
                    the <persName corresp="STJOHNTHEBAPTIST">Baptist</persName> and <persName corresp="#STPAUL">St. Paul</persName> in carving--the rich, loud organ, and the altar-piece"--the 
                    grander fittings doubtless features in the heavily mortgaged expansion, and "far beyond what was usual in Nonconformist buildings of that period" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BURNEJONESMEMORIALS">G. Burne&#x2010;Jones, <hi rend="italic">Memorials of Edward Burne&#x2010;Jones</hi></ref>, 1:41-42; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HOODVOCATIONPREACHER">Hood, <hi rend="italic">Vocation of the Preacher</hi></ref>, 209; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#CLEALSTORYCONGREGATIONALISM">Cleal, <hi rend="italic">The Story of Congregationalism in Surrey</hi></ref>, 105).</p>
                <p>The organ, which members of the Andrews family played, was a particularly vital resource for recitalists contributing musical culture in the locale. 
                    Andrews himself was proficient on several instruments, and his accomplishments extended to other arts, as well 
                    (<ref type="bibiography" target="bibliography.php#ANSTRUTHERCOVENTRYPATMORESANGEL"><hi rend="italic">Coventry Patmore's Angel</hi></ref>, 18). 
                    He had some success as a sacred dramatist, with titles including <title type="drama" corresp="#ANDREWSVINEYARDNABOTH"><hi rend="italic">The Vineyard of Naboth: A Dramatic Fragment</hi></title> 
                    ("translated from the original Hebrew"), which was printed in 1825. Another title, <title type="drama" corresp="#ANDREWSSAMPSON"><hi rend="italic">Sampson</hi></title>, 
                    <persName corresp="#EPH">Hood</persName> effuses, might have been penned by Coleridge 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HOODVOCATIONPREACHER"><hi rend="italic">Vocation of the Preacher</hi></ref>, 212, 231). 
                    Of Andrews's varied pursuits--many of which were self-financed, like his chapel--a crucial one for Ruskin was the role of editor. As proprietor and editor of the 
                    <title type="periodical" corresp="#SPIRITUALTIMES"><hi rend="italic">Spiritual Times</hi></title>, Andrews gained the distinction of serving as Ruskin's first editor and publisher, 
                    by printing versions of the youth's poem, <ref type="apparatus" target="on_skiddaw_and_derwentwater_apparatus.php">"On Skiddaw and Derwentwater"</ref> 
                    in August 1829 and February 1830. The magazine also published poetry by Andrews's own children.</p>
                <p>In preaching, the method recommended by Andrews's principal at Hoxton, Robert Simpson, was to commit written sermons to memory in order to enjoy more "liberty in the pulpit," 
                    and thereby cultivate the "new style" of sermonizing by evangelical Dissenters, which pursued passion and drama and at least the impression of extempore inspiration 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GLENLAUNCHINGCLERICALCAREER">Glen, &#x201C;Launching a Clerical Career in Late Georgian England&#x201D;</ref>, 648). 
                    This method seems to account for Hood's anecdotes about Andrews's "eccentricities," such as his pausing in the middle of a sermon, confessing that "'as I came up those 
                    pulpit stairs, I had all the parts of this sermon well written on my mind,'" but that now he could not remember the third head; and so he commanded the organist to "'strike up 
                    a symphony'" while the remainder came back to him. His "luxuriant fancy" seemed all the more glorious "because apparently so unpremeditated" 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HOODVOCATIONPREACHER"><hi rend="italic">Vocation of the Preacher</hi></ref>, 210-13). 
                    The earliest reference to Andrews's preaching in a Ruskin family letter--the &#x201C;best sermon from Dr. Andrews," Margaret declared, that she "ever heard him preach,&#x201D; 
                    which occurred on 15 May 1826--indicates that the elder Ruskins were by that time already dazzled (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL">Burd, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 146). 
                    John grew old enough to pay attention to the sermons in 1829, shortly before his tenth birthday: "I always liked him," he explained to a family friend, 
                    "but of late I began to attend to his sermons and write them in a book at home" (<ref type="witness" target="letter_to_mrs_monro_msii.xml">Letter to Mrs. Monro</ref>). 
                    These sermon abstracts, as well as venturing forth into the streets "in a hunt after Dr Andrews" to put himself in the way of the dashing preacher, 
                    are usually carried out in conspiracy with Ruskin's older cousin, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_mary_note.php">Mary Richardson (<date notBefore="1815" notAfter="1849">1815&#x2013;49</date>)</ref>
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL">Burd, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 173; and see 
                    <ref type="apparatus" target="msii_apparatus.php"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSII">MS II</title></ref>).</p>
                <p>Within four months of this infatuation, Ruskin entered "a most important aera of my life . . . the coming of [Dr. Andrews as his] . . . tutor for the first time" (a  
                    date three weeks prior to his writing this, Ruskin said, which would have been about 20 April 1829; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL">Burd, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 200). 
                    Andrews, who came to Herne Hill to give lessons on Mondays, Wednesdays, and Fridays (<ref type="witness" target="letter_to_mrs_monro_msii.xml">Letter to Mrs. Monro</ref>), 
                    was the first outsider to take over Ruskin's parents' role of teaching, causing Margaret to seek a retreat in the small Herne Hill household, 
                    but eventually she reconciled herself and even shared in John's Hebrew lessons 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL">Burd, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 208, 227, 229 n. 2). 
                    Judgments vary about the scope of Andrews's abilities as a linguist and classicist. Two late-century reports are at odds, one pronouncing him 
                    "one of the first Greek scholars of the day, . . . said to have derived an income of &#x00A3;1,000 a year from teaching the sons of nobility" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#CLEALSTORYCONGREGATIONALISM">Cleal, <hi rend="italic">The Story of Congregationalism in Surrey</hi></ref>, 105), and 
                    Ruskin's own account in Praeterita dismissing his command of "little more of Greek than the letters, and declensions of nouns," although "he wrote the letters prettily, 
                    and had an accurate and sensitive ear for rhythm" (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 35:74). 
                    Whatever his qualifications for meeting the boy's admittedly basic needs, Andrews's most persuasive talent in Ruskin's estimation was that he was fun: 
                    he &#x201C;makes me laugh almost but not quite to use one of his own expressions . . . he is so funny comparing <name type="fictional" corresp="#NEPTUNE">Neptune</name>s lifting up 
                    the wrecked ships of <name type="fictional" corresp="#AENEAS">eenaes</name> with his trident to my lifting up a potato with a fork or taking a piece of bread out of a bowl of milk with a spoon&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="witness" target="letter_to_mrs_monro_msii.php"><title type="letter" corresp="JRALMONRO1829">Letter to Mrs. Monro</title></ref>). He was also gentle and kind with children, servants, and pets: 
                    &#x201C;What a nice face he has," Ruskin decided; "I do think to use one of his own expressions he looks best when he frowns next when he laughs and next when he neither frowns nor laughs  Every thing he does is nice&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 200). When John and Mary first accosted him in his career 
                    through the lanes of Walworth, he was arrested by the curtsy of their servant, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="strachan_ann_note.php">Ann Strachan</ref>, 
                    and he ended the interview with a pat for their dog, <name type="animal" corresp="#GIPSEY">Gipsey</name>. When he preached on 
                    <title type="sermon" corresp="#ANDREWSDUMBCREATION">"The Religious and Moral Duty of Man in the Dumb Creation"</title>, Beresford Chapel was swamped by members of the 
                    <orgName corresp="#SPCA">Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals</orgName> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 203, 204 n. 1).</p>
                <p>In his innocence, Andrews was unprepared to cope with increasing family and financial troubles. Following her twelfth child, Elizabeth grew ill, 
                    and in March 1831 Andrews paid an unseemly morning visit to Margaret Ruskin, to unload "a long account of [his wife's] complaints in the hope, I am certain,
                    that I should say there was no chance of her living long," for despite such an "imprudent" confession to a parishioner whom he had known "so short a time," 
                    Andrews could not prevent himself from "enlarg[ing] much on the torment she had been to him for these last ten years," making him endure "caprice, jealousy, 
                    unreasonableness and violence" that "has marred his respectability and fortune and prevented his filling that place in society his talents entitle him to" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 242-43). Margaret's account incidentally suggests 
                    an intellectual and talented woman who earned censure for failing to observe the boundaries that Ruskin would later, define for "queens," 
                    whose education should be "nearly, in its course and material of study, the same as a boy's; but quite differently directed," in order to 
                    "sympathize in her husband's pleasures, and in those of his best friends." The trouble here was that the man's course of study was not obviously 
                    "foundational and progressive," and no one thought to ask whether the woman's might have been more so ("Of Queens' Gardens," Sesame and Lilies, in 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 18:128).</p>
                <p>Margaret, at least, pointed out that Edward Andrews owed his share of blame for his wife's condition, since "to any woman with so numerous a family [he must] have caused much serious and distressing apprehension," 
                    given his "flighty . . . habits and manner of conducting his secular affairs, though with the best and kindest intentions." Margaret perhaps referred to his extravagance 
                    in bearing children no less than in cultivating the arts, his lack of self-government leading to "unwise indulgence of every caprice" in his wife, 
                    and causing "impatience and irritability as almost amounts to insanity" (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 243). 
                    After Elizabeth's death in 1831, the family fortunes declined, and the mortgage was called in on Andrews chapel. He continued to tutor Ruskin, apparently to everyone's satisfaction, 
                    until 1833 or 1834, when the youth's preparation for university was taken over by the <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="dale_thomas_note.php"></ref>Reverend Thomas Dale (1797-1870) 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 200 n. 4, 257, 262, 273, 275, and see 366).</p>
                <p>Andrews died in 1841, leaving his family destitute, and forcing the two eldest sons to emigrate in search of better fortune in Australia, while the rest of the family 
                    gathered for protection around their eldest sister, Eliza, who had married well 
                    (<ref type="bibiography" target="bibliography.php#ANSTRUTHERCOVENTRYPATMORESANGEL"><hi rend="italic">Coventry Patmore's Angel</hi></ref>, 22-23). 
                    A half century later, Eliza, now well known as a lawyer and social reformer, would open her memories to 
                    W. Robertson Nicoll, enabling him to track down Ruskin's first publication, <ref type="apparatus" target="on_skiddaw_and_derwentwater_apparatus.php">"On Skiddaw and Derwentwater"</ref>, 
                    in her father's magazine, the Spiritual Times.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>