<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <fileDesc xml:id="chamouni_prose_le">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;Chamouni&#x201d; [essay]</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1903)</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#">E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#KBV">Kyle B. Volkmann</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#SEP">Steven E. Petite</persName>
                    <resp>contributing review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2018-01-06">January 6, 2018</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <filiation><ref type="apparatus" target="apparatuses/account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_apparatus.php#account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_le">Back to apparatus</ref></filiation>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Works of John Ruskin</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">Library<hi rend="superscript"></hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1903">1903</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">380-82</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="witness" subtype="essay">
                <p>And this is our last excursion on <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Swiss</placeName> ground, thought I, scanning<lb/>
                    the provoking clouds that ever rolled massively among the regions of<lb/>
                    eternal snow, though far above the blue mountains that encircle their<lb/>
                    mighty monarch.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="chamouni_glosses_contextual.php#MCLIFFYDIADEMGLOSS"/> I have always a sort of kindred feeling for these<lb/>
                    beautiful blue hills; they ever look half <placeName corresp="#ENGLAND">English</placeName>, and I love them for it.<lb/>
                    They may not be so wonderful, so majestic, so mighty, or so beautiful, but<lb/><pb/>
                    they are more like home, sweet home, and it is pleasant, very pleasant, to<lb/>
                    meet a friend in a foreign land. We are going to <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">c&#x02BC;est vrai</hi>,<lb/>
                    but it seems exceeding strange. Before we left home, I had read of<lb/>
                    <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, heard of <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, and seen some few drawings of <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>,<lb/>
                    but never so much as dreamed of going to <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, it seemed so un&#x2010;<lb/>
                    come&#x2010;at&#x2010;able; and for the <geogName corresp="#MONTBLANC">Mont Blanc</geogName>, it seemed in another world, in fairy&#x2010;<lb/>
                    land, and of course had a magic halo thrown round it, an &#x00E6;therialness<lb/>
                    that can never be joined with reality. That halo comes again on looking<lb/>
                    back. And this is our last excursion on <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Swiss</placeName> ground, thought I, the<lb/>
                    last, and the wildest, and the sweetest, because&#x2014;because, perhaps it is<lb/>
                    the last. The day was exceedingly favourable for the scenery of the<lb/>
                    lower mountains, not for the <geogName corresp="#ALPS">Alps</geogName>; they were reserved for other times.<lb/>
                    The noon verged gradually from burning sunshine<ref type="gloss_textual" target="chamouni_prose_glosses_textual.php#SHINESHINEGLOSS"/> to thick thundery<lb/>
                    clouds, that rolled rapidly over the murky heaven as we entered a solitary<lb/>
                    mountain recess, a cliffy defile, leading from the valley of <placeName corresp="#MAGLAND">Maglan</placeName> to that<lb/>
                    of <placeName corresp="#SALLANCHES">Salenches</placeName>.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="chamouni_glosses_contextual.php#MAGLANTOSALLANCHESGLOSS"/> Down they burst with a fierce rattling turmoil and headlong<lb/>
                    flash, flash, flashing, and the bridleless clouds careered along the crags at<lb/>
                    such a wild rate that their own speed broke them into scattered confusion,<lb/>
                    that the blue sky shone calmly through their openings, and the labouring<lb/>
                    sun struggled strangely&#x2014;now gleaming waterily on the red&#x2010;ribbed skeleton<lb/>
                    crags, now mingling with the quiver of the lightning, now again plunged<lb/>
                    into the swift rack of the thunder&#x2010;clouds that seemed sweeping round the<lb/>
                    mountain summits like lashed ocean waves round a labouring vessel. The<lb/>
                    <geogName corresp="#ARVE">Arve</geogName> swelled on the instant, and his turbid waves tore madly down, trees,<lb/>
                    stones, rocks, all tost along the channel, by the arrowy force of that<lb/>
                    resistless river, ever mighty, but now fearful. As the sun verged towards<lb/>
                    the horizon, the clouds swept partially away; the hills, the cliffs, the<lb/>
                    mountains, the rocks, and the blue vaulted sky glowed with his last rays<lb/>
                    for a moment; he sunk and the night came, his darkness made yet more<lb/>
                    visible by the thunder gloom of the storm.</p>

                <p>&#x201C;Voil&#x00E0; les aiguilles,&#x201D; quoth our char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc driver. If any person in<lb/>
                    the whole world is totally insensible to pain, knocks, aches, and bruises, it<lb/>
                    must be a <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Swiss</placeName> char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc driver. The <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Swiss</placeName> char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc is a vehicle<lb/>
                    expressly built for the purpose of passing over those roads, which no<lb/>
                    other species of conveyance can pass over twelve yards of without immediate<lb/>
                    demolition. It is a sort of large side&#x2010;saddle, capable of containing, if<lb/>
                    well packed, three pauvres miserables, with a back and roof to it, and a<lb/>
                    board to put the feet on, with a leather to keep you in, all which are of<lb/>
                    a most ancient and venerable description; this is fixed totally without<lb/>
                    springs or anything of the kind, as far as I could see, upon four wheels,<lb/>
                    et voil&#x00E0; un char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc. With this kind of vehicle, upon roads which<lb/>
                    always resemble and are often carried through the beds of tumbling<lb/>
                    mountain torrents, any one may easily imagine the sort of pleasurable<lb/>
                    penance to which he is subjected who submits to be driven from <placeName corresp="#SALLANCHES">Salenches</placeName><lb/>
                    up to <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName> in a char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc.</p>

                <p>&#x201C;Voil&#x00E0; les aiguilles,&#x201D; quoth our char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc driver.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="chamouni_glosses_contextual.php#VOILAGLOSS"/> How I started,<lb/>
                    I believe I was dreaming of home at the time; it is odd you always think<lb/><pb/>
                    it would be very pleasant to be where you are not; it can&#x02BC;t be helped, but<lb/>
                    it is very provoking, the charms of a place always increase in geometrical<lb/>
                    ratio as you get farther from it, and therefore &#x02BC;tis a rich pleasure to look<lb/>
                    back on anything, though it has a dash of regret. It is singular that<lb/>
                    almost all pleasure is past, or coming. Well, I looked up, and lo! seven<lb/>
                    thousand feet above me soared the needles of <geogName corresp="#MONTBLANC">Mont Blanc</geogName>, splintered and<lb/>
                    crashed and shivered, the marks of the tempest for three score centuries,<lb/>
                    yet they are here, shooting up red, bare, scarcely even lichened, entirely<lb/>
                    inaccessible, snowless, the very snow cannot cling to the down&#x2010;plunging<lb/>
                    sheerness of these terrific flanks that rise pre&#x2010;eminently dizzying and<lb/>
                    beetling above the sea of wreathed snow that rolled its long surging waves<lb/>
                    over the summits of the lower and less precipitous mountains. Then came<lb/>
                    the stretching gloominess of the pine forests, jagging darkly upon the<lb/>
                    ridge of every crag, strangely contrasted with the cold blueness of the<lb/>
                    peaky glaciers that filled the huge ravines between the hills, descending<lb/>
                    like the bursting billows of a chafed ocean tide from the desolate dominion<lb/>
                    of the snow, and curling forward till they lay on the green fields of<lb/>
                    <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, which stretched away, one unbroken line of luxuriance, till<lb/>
                    bounded by the lonely desertness of the <placeName corresp="#COLDEBALME">Col de Balme</placeName>.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="chamouni_glosses_contextual.php#COLDEBALMEGLOSS"/> There is not<lb/>
                    another scene like <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName> throughout all <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Switzerland</placeName>. In no other<lb/>
                    spot that I have seen is the rich luxuriance of the cultivated valley, the<lb/>
                    flashing splendour of the eternal snow, the impending magnificence of the<lb/>
                    bare, spiry crag, and the strange, cold rigidity of the surgy glaciers so<lb/>
                    dreadfully and beautifully combined, There is silence unbroken, no<lb/>
                    thunder of the avalanche comes crashing from the recesses of the hills,<lb/>
                    there is no voice from the chasmy glacier, no murmur from the thousand<lb/>
                    mountain streams, you are in solitude, a strange unearthly solitude, but<lb/>
                    you feel as if the air were full of spirits.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="chamouni_glosses_contextual.php#SPIRITSMONTBLANCGLOSS"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
