<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <fileDesc xml:id="cologne_prose_le">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;Cologne&#x201d; [essay]</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1903)</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#">E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#KBV">Kyle B. Volkmann</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#KBT">Katrina B. Thomas</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#SEP">Steven E. Petite</persName>
                    <resp>contributing review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <filiation><ref type="apparatus" target="apparatuses/account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_apparatus.php#account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_le"></ref></filiation>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>
                            <persName>E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Works of John Ruskin</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">Library Edition</biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1891">1903</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">351-53</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="witness" subtype="essay">
                <p>And this is the birthplace of <persName corresp="#PPR">Rubens</persName>!<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#RUBENSBIRTHPLACEGLOSS"/> Sink these French bad roads. 
                    <lb/>A long day&#x02BC;s journey over them under a burning sun, together with a 
                    <lb/>perambulation on a damp evening at <placeName corresp="#AIXLACHAPELLE">Aix&#x2010;la&#x2010;Chapelle</placeName> so knocked me up 
                    <lb/>that I was forced to diet and quiet it, and could not stir out<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#STIROUTGLOSS"/> to see 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#PPR">Rubens</persName>&#x02BC; last picture, the masterpiece of the master, the <title type="artwork" corresp="#RUBENSCRUCIFIXIONSTPETER">Crucifixion of 
                    <pb/>
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#STPETER">St. Peter</persName></title>, bequeathed by him at his death to his native city,<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#RUBENSSTPETERGLOSS"/> and, yet more, 
                    <lb/>his birth&#x2010;chamber.</p>
                <p>There is in many, in most, of the pictures of <persName corresp="#PPR">Rubens</persName>, and that even 
                    <lb/>in his most sacred subjects, magnificent as they are viewed as paintings 
                    <lb/>only, an unholiness, a cast of Bacchanalian revelry, to say the least, an 
                    <lb/>unpleasingness, that does him dishonour.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#DISHONOURGLOSS"/> But there are a few, a chosen few, 
                    <lb/>of his pictures which the master hath poured his whole soul into, and the 
                    <lb/>production of one of which were enough to repay a lifetime of labour with 
                    <lb/>immortality. There is a picture, I neither know where it is, nor what it 
                    <lb/>is, but there is a picture curtained up in one of the royal palaces of 
                    <lb/><placeName corresp="#FRANCE">France</placeName>, the <title type="artwork" corresp="#RUBENSSTAMBROSIUS"><persName corresp="#STAMBROSE">St. Ambrosius</persName></title>, I think, kneeling before a crucifix.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#STAMBROSIUSGLOSS"/> There is 
                    <lb/>one single ray of yellow light falling faintly upon the grey hairs and holy 
                    <lb/>features of the venerable saint, the rest is in obscurity; there is nothing more, 
                    <lb/>nothing to disturb either the eye or the mind, and you feel calmed and 
                    <lb/>subdued when you look upon that one solitary figure, as if in the presence 
                    <lb/>of a superior being. It is impossible to see that picture, the reality is 
                    <lb/>too striking, and a reality so hallowed and so beautiful, that when the 
                    <lb/>curtain is again drawn over the picture, you feel as if awaking from a 
                    <lb/>dream of heaven. It is by such pictures as this that <persName corresp="#PPR">Rubens</persName> has gained 
                    <lb/>his immortality; and it was, I believe, such a picture as this that I did not 
                    <lb/>see at <placeName corresp="#COLOGNE">Cologne</placeName>. Then the disappointment made me worse, and I could 
                    <lb/>not stir out to see the room in which he was born. But it don&#x02BC;t signify 
                    <lb/>talking. Reader, beware of the <placeName corresp="#RHEINBERGHOTEL">Grosser Rheinberg hotel</placeName> at <placeName corresp="#COLOGNE">Cologne</placeName>. Art 
                    <lb/>thou a poet, a painter, or a romancer? Imagine the <geogName corresp="#RHINE">Rhine</geogName>, the beautiful, 
                    <lb/>the mighty, the celebrated <geogName corresp="#RHINE">Rhine</geogName>, fouler than the <geogName corresp="#THAMES">Thames</geogName> at <placeName corresp="#LONDONBRDG">London
                    <lb/>Bridge</placeName>, compressed into almost as narrow a channel, washing dirty coal 
                    <lb/>wharfs on the one side; bogs, marshes, and coke manufactories on the 
                    <lb/>other, yellow with mud from beneath, black with tar and coal&#x2010;dust from 
                    <lb/>above, loaded with clumsy barges and dirty shipping; in short, a vile, sordid, 
                    <lb/>mercenary river, fit only for traffic, high Germans and low Dutchmen, 
                    <lb/>and you will have some idea of the <geogName corresp="#RHINE">Rhine</geogName>, as seen from the bedroom 
                    <lb/>windows of the Grosser Rheinberg.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#GROSSERRHEINBERGGLOSS"/> Oh, if thou wouldest see the Rhine as 
                    <lb/>it may be seen, as it ought to be seen, shut your eyes, sleep your time 
                    <lb/>away, do anything but look about you, till you get to <placeName corresp="#BONN">Bonn</placeName>, then walk<pb/>
                    <lb/>out upon the terrace which looks forth over the swell of the deep waters 
                    <lb/>to the dim outline of the <geogName corresp="#SIEBENGEBIRGE">seven mountains</geogName>,<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#SEVENMOUNTAINSGLOSS"/> and there gaze and dream and 
                    <lb/>meditate. Secondly, Art thou an epicure? Imagine mutton&#x2010;chops which 
                    <lb/>ought to have been tough, but which age had made tender, accompanied 
                    <lb/>by circular cakes of congealed fat, denominated gravy, together with a 
                    <lb/>kind of brown ashes, apparently moistened with whale oil (which, I think, 
                    <lb/>they called fried potatoes), as an addition to your feast, and you have an 
                    <lb/>idea of a dinner of the Grosser Rheinberg. I have omitted one thing, 
                    <lb/>however, which was really capital&#x2014;the vinegar. They called it Hock wine, 
                    <lb/>certainly, but that don&#x02BC;t signify; you must not be led astray by names in 
                    <lb/>this part of the world. However, good vinegar would not make up for 
                    <lb/>the want, or worse than want, of everything else; and although the waiters 
                    <lb/>made a point of not appearing until the bell had been rung seven times, 
                    <lb/>we at last made them understand that we neither liked their mode of 
                    <lb/>waiting, nor the contents of their larder, and so, according to their 
                    <lb/>deserts, deserted them.</p>
                <p>The <placeName corresp="#STPETERCATHEDRAL">cathedral</placeName> is the richest in fretwork and carving, in the delicate 
                    <lb/>finish of every shaft, and buttress, and pinnacle, that I saw on the journey, 
                    <lb/>except <placeName corresp="#MILAN">Milan</placeName>. They showed us, in a little Gothic chapel, three skulls, 
                    <lb/>which they told us were those of the Magi. They were set in framework 
                    <lb/>of gold, and covered with jewels, but the pomp became not the dry 
                    <lb/>bones. The soul&#x2010;less eye and fleshless cheek looked not the less horrible 
                    <lb/>though a diamond beamed through the one and a bar of gold bound the 
                    <lb/>other.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#MAGIGLOSS"/> Returned home, and the next morning departed from <placeName corresp="#COLOGNE">Cologne</placeName> 
                    <lb/>with regret, to trace the mighty <geogName corresp="RHINE">Rhine</geogName> to his source among the <geogName corresp="#RHAETIANALPS">Rhetian
                    <lb/>Alps</geogName>.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="cologne_glosses_contextual.php#RHAETIANALPSGLOSS"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>