<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
       <fileDesc xml:id="monastery_msiii">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201C;The Monastery&#x201D;</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from a Transcription of the MS Fair Copy</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                    <!--Example entries have been provided for MS I from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <country type="nation">United States of America</country>
                        <region type="state">Connecticut</region>
                        <settlement type="city">New Haven</settlement>
                        <institution>Yale University</institution>
                        <repository>Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</repository>
                        <collection>MS Vault Ruskin</collection>
                        <msName>MS III</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <locus facs="1229189.jpg image.jpg">pp. ##-##</locus>
                            <note>For a discussion of foliation, see <ref type="apparatus" target="tite_of_apparatus.php#MAJORMS">"Title of Work": Manuscripts</ref>.</note>
                            <filiation><!--Entry needed here.--></filiation>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <!--If additional entries are made below, the hands count must be increased.-->
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote corresp="#HANDJR1826-27" scribe="JR">
                                <p>John Ruskin's early boyhood hand, circa <date when="1829">1829</date>,
                                    examples of which can be found in MS III, pages <locus from="##" to="##">##-##</locus>.</p>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <pb facs="1229189"/>
            <div type="witness" subtype="poem" met="-+|-+|-+|-+" rhyme="aa">
            
            <head type="title"><handShift new="#HANDJR1829" script="print" medium="ink"/>THE MONASTERY</head>
            <head type="chapter">BOOK FIRST</head>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aa">
                    

<l><hi rend="italic">WHITE</hi> lady white lady sing on in the glen,
    of glendarg<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="monastery_glosses_contextual.php#GLENDEARGGLOSS"/> but do not do ill to men,
many a haunt and many a nook,
many a thought and many a look,
<pb/>
has been reported of that place,
of the people of thy race.<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="monastery_glosses_contextual.php#WHITELADYWHITELADYGLOSS"/>
there was a river called the tweed,
where the sheep and cattle fed:
there was a drawbridge over the stream,
to let over travelling men,
that came down the narrow glen.
at the bridge there was a warder.
he lived in a lonly tower,
to let down the drawbridge when:
there came over travelling men,
but from them he exacted pay,
before he let them on their way.
one day a monk was going by,
to go home to his monastery:
the monk was forced to go to a ford,
he was not quite so rich as a lord,
he would not give the warder pay,
the warder told him to go that way.
when he came to the side of the stream,
where his mule was to go in,
<pb facs="1229190"/>
he saw a figure in great grief:
the monk resolved to give her relief,
she seemed as if to pass the water,
was her wish the cruel warder[:]
perhaps deprived her of her way,
but what it was she did not say.
she jumped upon his mule behind,
swifter even than the wind:
the mule did kick and plunge and leaped,
the monk did sit upon the beast and whipped:
at length she plunged into the river,
leaping oer a bunch of heather[:]
the ford was deep the current bore,
the mule along the winding shore.
the maiden then began to chaunt,
the stories of her avenel haunt:
which frightened still the monk much more,
as they swam along the winding shore.
they came at length to a water fall deep,
deeper een than a salmons leap,
the mule attempted on to go,
the abbot now was in great woe,
upon a black volume his hand he laid[:]
because he was much much afraid:
the maiden pitched him from the saddle,
out as well as he could to waddle:
and when he set his foot on land,
he sunk upon the yellow sand.
when the abbot did arise,
to behold the earth and skies,
home wards he did bend his way[:]
on a bed his head to lay.
but the monks around him crowd,
to hear his story told aloud,
and the first words he uttered then[:]
were the maidens song when in the glen.
the abbot did start when he heard the song,
and he said to his brother how long how long,
wilt thou keep up that spirits song
at length the monk did go his way,
to bed and glad he was to lay,
his head upon his pillow then,
we must return to the haunted glen.
the abbot when he first arose
which was when first the good cock crows,
he called good father eustace to:
his chamber and thus spoke to him lo.
our brother is no less than haunted,
with a spirit which to him chaunted:
some words which now we must not name,
lest open wide mouthed tattling fame:
should spread these curious news abroad,
and for the people pave the road,
to superstitions house to go:
and plunge them in a sea of woe.
now brother eustace go to the glen,
oer river bog or ford or fen,
and if a spirit shall arise[:]
and stand before your wondering eyes:
bring home the curious tale to me,
and i’ll believe what you do see.
the monk obeyed and off he rode,
before again the good cock crowed,
and rode on speedily through the glen,
oer river bog or ford or fen.
BOOK SECOND2
UP the glen a little way,
where a pretty meadow lay,
there was a tower upon the hill:
close beside the pretty rill.
at the battle of pinkie where,
the scotch fled like the frig{h}tened hare:
the owner of this tower expired,
rushed on his fate by anger fired:
the grey goose shaft did pierce him through,
to the rejoicing of the foe.
far from this tow’r there was a barons seat,
and woods and landscapes at its feet:
and the name of this baron was great avenel,
for the good of his country in battle he fell:
and his widow was left to provide for her child,
and beautiful was she and still more mild.
and farther on there was some land,
alotted to a farmers hand:
and the farmers name that did live there,
was martin and though they had but poor fare:
they were happy and good tibb tacket his consort,
would do every thing for her husbands comfort.
and the widow of avenel the baron did go,
away to this farmers for fear of the foe.
but shortly she staid there for soon came a band,
of english barbarians that plunder the land:
and they robbed the poor farmer of cow and of sheep,
and hardly would leave him poor shagram to keep.
now must we leave poor martin there,
while we relate the towers fare.
a band of english soldiers marched,
close by the tower and as they passed[:]
good dame glendinning her sons led,
out from the gate and thus she said.
no means of fighting have I on this land,
and I am at the mercy of your hand.
the serjeant of the troop replied,
though I have means of fighting on my side:
I scorn with women now to strive,
go to your tower again and live.
yet dame I own I envy you,
that little rogue with eyes so blue.
and will you come with me my lad,
the serjeant of the troop he said.
no said the blue eyed edward no,
because you are to us a foe:
not only that but then you are,
a heretic and fond of war.
why god a mercy old stawarth did say,
I see that alone I must go my way.
but stay thou black eyed come with me,
and many a fine sight thou shalt see.
no cried the furious halbert no,
because thou art to us a foe:
and when Im older thou shalt see,
the effects of my fathers sword on thee.
why again god a mercy old stawarth did say,
I see that alone I must go my way:
but stay heres a token that if some men,
come riding down this narrow glen:
they may know that you are under my,
protection then I say goodbye.
so saying from his bonnet he,
took a red cross and said dost see[:]
this token, here thou blackeyed boy,
take it and may it give thee joy:
give me thy bonnet off thy head,
the commander of the troop he said.
halbert was silent and would not stir,
more than the lofty towering fir:
command it to stir from the place where it stands,
and it will not without the help of hands:
but yet its green branches do wave in the wind,
and even so was proud halberts mind:
but from his head the mother snatched,
his cap at which young halbert catched:
but missed his aim the mother then,
gave it to the serjeant when:
he stuck the cross into the band
and put it in young halberts hand
no sooner had he done so but
young halbert with a furious look
took the cross and threw it in
the very pretty murmuring stream
young edward was instantly in the water
and brought it out safe to its rightful owner
why how now said the serjeant with some surprise
whats the reason of this my good blue eyes
that young rogue there throws it into the stream
and when he’s done so you leap in
and fetch it out and I demand
why you did throw it off the land
st georges cross and why did you
st Georges cross so soon pursue
because st george said halbert is
a southern saint, and the cross thats his
I will not wear in my bonnet or hat
why now said old stawarth I think that that
is a very good reason and why did you
st Georges cross so soon pursue
because the cross is the sign of our lord
and not only that but his blessed word
well good bye said old stawarth but theres the cross
if you lose it twill be a very great loss
so saying he rode down the glen
oer river bog or ford or fen1
END OF BOOK SECOND
HERN HILL
DULWICH

BOOK THIRD
I MUST return to martin now
whom I left standing in the bow
window of his cottage sweet
well to this tower they sped their feet
and martin and tibb tack did go
away to this tower for fear of the foe
and the widow of avenel with them did go
but between the tower and them
on the way to glendarg glen
there was a bog and oer this part
where even the lightfooted hart
go could not for his feet in clay
sunk as he sped him on his way
not only martin had to pass
but een good shagram with the lass
named mary avenel and when
they had come nearer to the glen
it was so bad that there they stuck3
for stir they could not een a foot
so martin took his task as guide
and all the women did in him confide
martin then did look about
to see where he could spy an out
let. then selecting the safest way
he to shagram began to say
come on good horse and let us see
whether thou wilt obey thy master me
come on but shagram would not go
though mute he very well said no
for shagram snorted laid his paws4
As if he encountered a great bears jaws
And would not go, Een tak your ain
Way said the shepherd I would fain
Get o’er to t’other side and be
Safe on our way so let us see
What you can do for us and when
We are safe at glendarg glen
Safe in stable you shall stand
With plenty hay and fodder at your hand
Just at this moment mary saw
Just as good shagram raised his paw
A beauteous lady far away
And seeing her she thus did say
I see a lady just up there
And I must say exceeding fair
Where where cried the whole of the family then
Why very near to glendarg glen
She signs to us to come yon gate
But it was great avenels fate
To have a spirit in their line
And so it was in this odd time
This tibb tacket thought it then
For twas near to glendarg glen
And her haunt was near this part
Where oft the very slender hart
Had drank at this place but was neer5
Frightened by her very fair
Form appearing like a fog
And this I suspect was that seen in the bog.
Shagram at his own free will
Did no longer stand stock still
But set off at [a or so]6 good rate
And then it was good shagrams fate
To take them safely through the bog
Indeed he did so though a fog
Oerspread the land. But worthy tis
Of remark that the little miss
Oft mentioned to the servants round
While they were still on boggy ground
The lady and her signals and
When they were off the boggy land
The servants changed expressive looks
With each other, for the nooks
Of fairies were supposed to be
Just in the glen and they thought they’d see
A fairy peeping out from moss
Or perhaps it might peep from a great morass
All halloween said tibby to
Martin. Woman you are too
Said martin or you would not dare
To speak of fairies ony mair.
When once more on firm ground they were
And had rid themselves of fear
Martin saw some landmarks high
Upon a hill against the sky
And taking them for his good guide
And ever keeping by their side
Very soon at the tower of glendarg they arrived
BOOK 4
ONE night when all the winds combined
To frighten een the strongest mind
And halloween it was and all
The fairies seemed and elves to call
In the loud wind that roared round
The tower with its awful sound
And when in gambols mongst the trees
The brownies used themselves to please
And when the kelpies liked to take
The careless traveller to the lake
And plunge him in and hear his cry
Ascending to the stormy sky
Well on this night of spirits power
Thats greatest at the midnight hour
Tibb and the rest sat round the fire
Unmindful of the tempest dire
While from the bible alice read
Stories of saints that long were dead
Martin hammered bored or sawed
The substance of the hardy board
Tibb watched the process of scalding the whey
While martin sawed or bored away
Dame elspeth pulling the thread sate
From her distaff near her mate
Mary of avenel halbert and all
Were allowed to run up and down the hall
There were some rooms adjacent to
The hall where sometimes they would go
I mean the children and at length
Into these rooms they all were sent
But from them openmouthed there came
To spread abroad the ghost like fame
The boys and they indeed did tell
That a man like he of the clinthill
Was in the spence. then Alice said
Where is my child and so she led
Halbert glendinning first to arm
With an old sword his open palm
And Edward seized the ladys book
And the ladys fear they all then took
And then unto the spence they went
When their alarm soon from them went
For no man armed there appeared
And what made you ye false misleard
Said good dame elspeth to her bairns
And what made you ye misleard loons
Come there yon gate into the hall
Roaring I am sure like a bull
And could ye find nae night for daffing
Save halloween when the leddy was reading
The elder boy bent eyes on ground
With the youngest tears their access found.7</l>

                    
                    
                </lg>
            </div>
        
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>