<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_glosses">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#GMS">Gabriella M. Smith</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE1GLOSS" resp="#DCH">It hangs down its head as if dazzled</note><!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#SOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->

                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE2GLOSS" resp="#DCH">Young January from being the first of the months</note><!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#ALSOSOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->

                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE3GLOSS" resp="#DCH">ken sight</note>
                
                <note xml:id="ROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Rose. Rosa, L .; Icos. Polyg. L.; and Rosacea, J. Rosier, Fr.;
                    Rosenstock , Ger.; and Rosajo, Ital.
                    1683. The rose is known by every body at first sight, and has been a favorite flower
                    from time immemorial among the civilized nations of Europe and Asia. The shrub
                    varies in size in different species , from one foot to six or eight, and the colors are red,
                    white, yellow, purple, black, striped; simple, or in almost numberless shades and mix-
                    tures; and single , semi-double, and double. It is cultivated in every garden, from that
                    of the most humble cottager upwards; some species as R. centifolia damascena, &#x0026;c. are
                    also cultivated by commercial gardeners on a large scale for distilling rose-water, and for
                    making attar, or essential oil of roses. Six pounds of rose leaves will impregnate by dis-
                    tillation a gallon of water strongly with their odour; but a hundred pounds afford
                    scarcely half an ounce of attar. The rose is also used in medicine.
                    Botanists are not agreed as to the number of original species of this genus, some
                    regard all the European species as originated from one source; others, and especially
                    the moderns, divide them into species, sub-species, and varieties. The most scientific
                    work which has appeared on the roses in England, is the "Rosarum Monographia"
                    of J. Lindley, 1819, in which above a hundred species or sub-species are described,
                    and some of them figured; and Miss Laurence has published ninety plates of "A
                    Collection of Roses from Nature," 1810. In France, Guillemeau has published "His-
                    toire Naturelle de la Rose," 1800; and P. J. Redouté and C. A. Thory are engaged in
                    a splendid work, in folio, entitled "Les Roses," containing plates of all the known species
                    and varieties of this flower. C. A. Thory has published a separate tract on their culture,
                    entitled "Prodrome de la Monographie du Genre Rosier, &#x0026;c." 1820; M. A. Pronville,
                    a "Nomenclature Raisonée," in 1818; and J. P. Vibert, Observations, &#x0026;c. in 1820.
                    A copious and intelligent account of the Scotch roses has been lately given by J. Sabine
                    (Hort. Trans. iv. 231.), and some hundreds of new varieties have flowered from seedling
                    plants, in the nursery of J. Lee, during the present year, and will be found in his cata-
                    logue for 1822.
                    Species and Varieties. The lists of the London and Paris nurserymen contain up-
                    wards of 350 names. The greater part of these have been raised from seed on the
                    continent, where it ripens better than in this country, within the last thirty years. A
                    number of varieties have also been raised in this country, especially of the R. spinosissima,
                    or Scotch rose, of which twenty-six sorts are enumerated by J. Sabine, as having been
                    raised within the last twenty years. New varieties are raised in France and Italy
                    annually; L. Villaresi , royal gardener at Monza has raised upwards of fifty varieties
                    of Rosa indica; not one of which have, as far as we know, reached this country. Some
                    of them are quite black, others shaped like a ranunculus, and many of them highly
                    odoriferous.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, 1015-1016)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="LILYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Lily.--Lilium, L.; Hexan. Monog. L .; and Liliæ, J. Lis, Fr.;
                    Lilie, Ger.; and Giglio, Ital.
                    1635. Of this genus there are sixteen species introduced in Britain, and the whole of
                    them may be reckoned very choice flowers. We shall notice particularly, only those
                    species, of which numerous varieties have been produced. These are:
                    The White Lily, L. Candidum  (Bot. Mag. 278.), has a large scaly bulb, a
                    leafy stem, from three to four feet in height, terminating in large pure white
                    flowers on peduncles. It is a native of the Levant , and was in most gar-
                    dens in Gerarde’s time. Of this species, there are above eight varieties.
                    The Orange Lily, L. bulbiferum (Bot. May.[sic] 36), has a scaly bulb, a leafy
                    stem, two feet and a half high, terminating in orange-colored flowers.
                    Sometimes the stem produces small green bulbs in the axillae of the leaves. Of this species, there are eight or ten varieties and sub-varieties. 
                    The Martagon or Turk's Cap, L. Martagon, (Bot. Mag. 893.), has a large 
                    scaly bulb, a stalk furnished with narrow leaves, near three feet high, and
                    terminating peduncles of fine carmine flowers in July. Of this species there
                    are half a dozen varieties, besides the scarlet martagon (L. Chalcedonicum),
                    of which there are also different sorts. 
                    Besides the above species and their varieties, there are the L. Canadense,
                    superbum, or Turk's cap; the Pomponium, and Tigrinum, or Tiger Lily; all
                    equally meriting cultivation as select flowers.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, 959)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="DAHLIAGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Dahlia.--Dahlia superflua and D. frustranea, H. K. (Cav. Ic. i.
                    t. 80. and 266.); Polyg. Super. L.; and Corymbiferæ, J.
                    1640. The roots are tuberous and fasciculated; the stems rise from five to eight feet,
                    covered with large compound leaves, resembling those of the common dwarf elder, and 
                    with side branches bearing numerous flowers of a great variety of colors, which appear
                    in August, and continue till destroyed by frost. The plant grows wild in Mexico, in
                    sandy meadows, and was sent to Madrid in 1789, and thence to England in the same 
                    year; but the plants being lost, seeds were reintroduced by Lady Holland in 1804, and
                    from these and some plants imported from France during the peace of 1814, the present 
                    extensive stock of dahlias has originated. Till this last period they were much more 
                    cultivated in France and Germany than in England, and more especially by the Count 
                    Lebeur, at Paris, and M. Otto, at Berlin. At present the dahlia is the most fashion-
                    able flower in this country, and the extent of its culture in some of the nurseries, espe-
                    cially that of J. Lee, is truly astonishing. Nor is this to be wondered at, as Sabine
                    observes, for, independently of the great beauty and diversity of the flowers, they are in
                    perfection at a season when, till they came into notice, our gardens had but little orna-
                    ment. The roots are edible, but not agreeable.
                    Varieties. The leading varieties of the fertile-rayed species D. superflua, are,
                    the purple, rose, pale, white, sulphur, yellow, tawny, copper, brick red,
                    dark-red, pomegranate colored , dark purple, very dark, and lilac flowered 
                    single, semi-double, and double, with innumerable sub-varieties.
                    Of the barren.rayed species, D. frustranea, there are the scarlet, bright-scarlet,
                    orange, saffron, and yellow flowered, single, semi-double, and double, with
                    several sub-varieties, though this spe-cies has not sported nearly so much as the other.
                    At the Hammersmith nursery, above 200 sorts may be procured.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, 962)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PRIMROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">1643. The Primrose, P. vulgaris, L. (Eng. Bot. 4.); Primavere, Fr.; Shaftlose Primule, Ger.;
                    and Primavera, Ital. (fig. 450), has a perennial root, appearing as if bit off at the end,
                    with a singular smell like that of the anise. It is a native of most parts of Europe, in woods,
                    coppices, and sheltered lanes, particularly in a clayey soil. The flowers of the wild plant are
                    almost always of a brimstone color, but some-times of a purple hue; they appear in March and April.
                    Varieties. The double varieties produced by culture are in most esteem, of which there are:
                    The stemless white. Crimson. Hose-in-hose. Purple. Lilac. Scotch. White. Yellow. Brimstone.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, 975)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HYACINTHGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Hyacinth.--Hyacinthus Orientalis, L. (Bot. Mag. 93.); Hex. Monog. L.;
                    and Asphodeleæ, B. P.; Jacinte, Fr.; Hyacinthe, Ger.; and Giacinto, Ital. (fig. 433.)
                    1627. The bulb of this plant is tunicated, the leaves broad and green, from the centre of which
                    arises a scape, with a spike of flowers, pointing in all directions, and by which it
                    is known, at first sight , from Hyacinthus nonscriptus, L.; (Scilla nonscripta, W.) in
                    which the scape is drooping, and the flowers all turned to one side. It is a native of
                    the Levant, and abundant about Aleppo and Bagdat, where it flowers in February;
                    here it flowers in March and April. It was cultivated by Gerarde in 1596; but had,
                    doubtless, long before been improved by the Dutch, who have added greatly to the
                    strength and beauty of the plant, and produced almost innumerable varieties.
                    Varieties. Gerarde mentions the single and double blue, the purple, and the white.
                    Parkinson, in 1629, enumerates eight sorts. Miller says, the Haerlem gardeners dis-
                    tinguish near 2000 sorts, and generally publish catalogues of them from year to year.
                    At present, the taste for this flower being considerably abated, the Dutch and English
                    catalogues contain only a few hundred sorts. Mason's Catalogue for 1820, contains
                    three hundred sorts with names. These names are quite arbitrary, being given by the
                    grower after himself or some public character; and therefore they are here omitted.
                    They are arranged as double-blues, whites, reds, and yellows, and single sorts of the
                    same colors; the blues and reds are the most numerous; the yellow, those of which there is least variety .
                    Only single hyacinths were, at first, cultivated; but about the beginning of the last
                    century, attention was paid to double-flowers by Peter Voerhelm, whose first double-
                    flower was named Mary, and is now lost; but his third flower, the King of Great Britain,
                    which is now looked upon as the oldest double-hyacinth, was greatly preferred to all the
                    flowers known, and the price of it was then above 1000 florins or 100l. sterling. Up
                    to the middle of last century, the greatest attention was paid at Haerlem to raising new
                    sorts of double-flowers; and as much as 200l. has been known to be given for a root;
                    but since that period, the taste for this and other bulbous flowers has considerably de-
                    clined, and at present there are few sorts for which more than 10l. are asked,
                    the general price being from one to ten shillings a bulb for the varied sorts, and what
                    are called the common mixtures, are sold at from 2l. to 3l. a hundred. A variety de-
                    generates, under bad treatment, in two or three years; but in Holland some have been preserved nearly a century.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, 940-941)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="CROCUSGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Crocus.--Crocus, L .; Trian. Monog. L .; and Iridea, B. P. Safran, Fr.; Safran, Ger.; and Zaffarano, Ital.
                    1631. The bulb is round, solid and compressed with a netted skin, from the centre of 
                    which arise four or five grass-like leaves, and one or two flowers. Out of the centre of the
                    tube of the flower arises a slender style, crowned by a broad flat stigma of a gold color.
                    After the flower is past, the germ, which hitherto was seated on the bulb at the base of
                    the tube, pushes out of the ground, and ripens its seeds; a singular economy in nature,
                    and which occurs only in the colchicum, and a few other plants.
                    All the known species of this genus may be considered as florists' flowers. Many
                    botanists, indeed, consider that there is only two species, the C. vernus, or spring-blowing
                    crocus; and the C. sativus, the saffron, or autumn crocus.
                    From the Crocus vernus, (Bag. Bot. 343 and our fig. 440.) they consider that 
                    the C. versicalor (fig. 441.), the C. biflorus (fig. 442. a) the C. susiana (b) the
                    C. sulphureus (c), and the C. mæsianus (d and e), with their numerous sub-
                    varieties, have been produced by cul-ture or locality.
                    From the Crocus sativus, or saffron crocus (Eng. Bot. 343. and our fig. 443. a),
                    they think it likely that the C. serotinus (fig. 443. b), and the C. nudiflorus (fig. 443. e),
                    have been also originated by cultivation or accident.
                    It is sufficient for our purpose to observe, that all the sorts have been time out of 
                    mind, and still are, great ornaments to the garden; the spring sorts coming into flower
                    in February and March, and the autumn sorts in September and October.
                    The color of the spring crocus in its wild state in Switzerland, is white with a pur-
                    ple base; it is considered as naturalized in England, but when found wild, is almost 
                    always of a yellow color. The autumn crocus, or saffron, is also found wild in some
                    places, and considered as naturalized; but it appears to be an African plant, and intro-
                    duced originally in Edward the Third's time, which its Arabic name, sahafaran, seems
                    to justify. Its colour is generally purple or blue, as is that of most of the autumn va-
                    rieties in cultivation at present.
                    Varieties. None of these are double. Of the spring crocus, Parkinson has enume-
                    rated twenty-seven varieties; the fundamental colours of which are blue, purple, yellow,
                    and white. Miller recites twelve as leading sorts. Mason's catalogue for 1820 men-
                    tions “twenty named sorts,” besides the light, dark, and striped purple, cloth of gold;
                    the Scotch crocus beautifully striped, the white, the large and small yellow, and several
                    striped sorts. The Dutch are continually producing new varieties, as are some florists
                    in this country, of which Haworth (Hort. Trans. i. 122.) may be cited as an instance.
                    Of the autumn crocus, Parkinson has enumerated four; and Ray, six varieties. Mil-
                    ler has only four: the sweet-smelling, of a deep blue; the mountain, of a paler blue;
                    the many-flowering, bluish; and the small flowering. Most of these varieties are now lost.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, 954-955)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="JONQUILGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Narcissus.--Narcissus, L.; Hex. Monog. L.; and Amaryllidea, B. P. Narcisse, Fr. and Ger.; and Narcisso, Ital.
                    1632. The bulb is pear-shaped and tunicated, the leaves succulent and linear, and
                    the flower-stems, which are from six to eighteen inches in height, bear either solitary or
                    fasciculated flowers; the color of the flower is either white or yellow, and generally
                    highly odoriferous. Most of the species are natives of the south of Europe, but one,
                    the N. Pseudo-Narcissus, is a native of England, and common in woods in clayey soils.
                    They come into flower in February, March, and April.
                    Species and Varieties. The popular division of this genus is into daffodils, white narcissi, jonquils, and polyanthus narcissi.
                    The Daffodils are, N. pseudo Narcissus (Eng. Bot. 17.), of which the varieties
                    are the common double, the double with white petals and a yellow cup;
                    the single with yellow petals and a golden cup; three or four concentric cups; Tradescant's daffodil and above
                    a dozen other nameless varieties; the peerless, or two-flowered daffodil, N. bifloras, (Eng. Bot. 276),
                    and a variety N. b. a. tenuior with one flower only on the scape; the two-colored daffodil, N. bicolor, (Bot. Mag. 1187.),
                    a native of Spain, and a variety of the great yellow Spanish, the largest flower of the genus;
                    the least daffodil N. minor, (Bot. Mag. 6.); the rush-leaved, N. triandrus, (Bot. Mag. 48.),
                    and some other species and varieties. 
                    The White Narcissi are the poets' narcissus, N. poeticus: the early-flowered,
                    N. p. a. angustifolius; and the late-flowered N. p. majalis; the musk narcissus,
                    N. moschatus, (Eng. Bot. 1300.); the eastern narcissus, N. orientalis, (Bot. Mag. 948.),
                    and the yellowish and large-flowered varieties; the hoop-pet-ticoat narcissus, N. bulbocodium, (Bot. Mag. 88.);
                    and the paper narcissus, N. papyraceus, with other varieties.
                    The Jonquils are, the common, N. jonquilla, (Bot. Mag. 15.), so named from
                    its rush or jonc-like leaves; the double-flowered jonquil; the sweet-scented jonquil, N. odorus, (Bot. Mag. 934.),
                    the great jonquil, N. calathinus, (Bot. Mag. 78.), and some minor varieties. 
                    The Polyanthus Narcissi are the com-mon N. tazzetta, (Bot. Mag. 925.);
                    the sulphur-colored, single and double; the white and yellow, single and double;
                    and above a hundred other sorts, with arbitrary names given by the Dutch, 
                    who have highly improved this division of the genus. Some of these sorts are considered species by botanists.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, 956)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="CROWNIMPERIALGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Fritillary.--Fritillaria, L.; Heran. Monog. L.; and Liliæ, J. (fig. 446.)
                    1634. Of this genus there are three species which are considered as florists' flowers;
                    of these species there are numerous varieties.
                    The Crown Imperial, F. Imperialis (Bot. Mag. 194.) La Couronne Imperiale, Fr.;
                    Kaiserkrone, Ger.; and La Corona Imperial, Ita. (fig. 446. a), has a scaly bulb,
                    from which arise strong stems, from two to four feet in height, furnished with
                    numerous broad shining green leaves, and crowned with a whirl of showy pendulous
                    flowers, yellow, red, or striped in various ways, which appear in March and April.
                    It is one of the earliest ornaments of the flower garden, producing a fine 
                    appearance in the middle of large borders , at a season when such flowers are most
                    wanted. The “singular nectary,” Professor Martyn observes, “cannot but engage 
                    the attention of the curious observer; it is a white glandular cavity, at the base
                    of each petal, and has a drop of limpid nectarious juice standing in it, when the
                    flower is in vigour. Another of the wonders of nature may be observed in the
                    peduncles which bend down while the plant is in flower, but become upright as the
                    seed ripens.” There are above a dozen varieties in cultivation, distinguished by
                    the different shades of yellow, white, and red in the flower, and by being striped double or semi-double.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, 958)</note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>