<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_glosses">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#GMS">Gabriella M. Smith</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE1GLOSS" resp="#DCH">It hangs down its head as if dazzled</note><!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#SOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->

                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE2GLOSS" resp="#DCH">Young January from being the first of the months</note><!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#ALSOSOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->

                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE3GLOSS" resp="#DCH">ken sight</note>
                
                <note xml:id="ROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Rose</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Rosa</hi>, L .; <hi rend="italic">Icos. Polyg.</hi> L.; and <hi rend="italic">Rosacea</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Rosier</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Rosenstock</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Rosajo</hi>, Ital.
                    1683. The rose is known by every body at first sight, and has been a favorite flower
                    from time immemorial among the civilized nations of Europe and Asia. The shrub
                    varies in size in different species , from one foot to six or eight, and the colors are red,
                    white, yellow, purple, black, striped; simple, or in almost numberless shades and mix-
                    tures; and single , semi-double, and double. It is cultivated in every garden, from that
                    of the most humble cottager upwards; some species as <hi rend="italic">R. centifolia damascena</hi>, &#x0026;c. are
                    also cultivated by commercial gardeners on a large scale for distilling rose-water, and for
                    making <hi rend="italic">attar</hi>, or essential oil of roses. Six pounds of rose leaves will impregnate by dis-
                    tillation a gallon of water strongly with their odour; but a hundred pounds afford
                    scarcely half an ounce of <hi rend="italic">attar</hi>. The rose is also used in medicine.
                    Botanists are not agreed as to the number of original species of this genus, some
                    regard all the European species as originated from one source; others, and especially
                    the moderns, divide them into species, sub-species, and varieties. The most scientific
                    work which has appeared on the roses in England, is the "<hi rend="italic">Rosarum Monographia</hi>"
                    of J. Lindley, 1819, in which above a hundred species or sub-species are described,
                    and some of them figured; and Miss Laurence has published ninety plates of "A
                    Collection of Roses from Nature," 1810. In France, Guillemeau has published "<hi rend="italic">His-
                    toire Naturelle de la Rose</hi>," 1800; and P. J. Redouté and C. A. Thory are engaged in
                    a splendid work, in folio, entitled "<hi rend="italic">Les Roses</hi>," containing plates of all the known species
                    and varieties of this flower. C. A. Thory has published a separate tract on their culture,
                    entitled "<hi rend="italic">Prodrome de la Monographie du Genre Rosier, &#x0026;c.</hi>" 1820; M. A. Pronville,
                    a "<hi rend="italic">Nomenclature Raisonée</hi>," in 1818; and J. P. Vibert, <hi rend="italic">Observations, &#x0026;c.</hi> in 1820.
                    A copious and intelligent account of the Scotch roses has been lately given by J. Sabine
                    (<hi rend="italic">Hort. Trans</hi>. iv. 231.), and some hundreds of new varieties have flowered from seedling
                    plants, in the nursery of J. Lee, during the present year, and will be found in his cata-
                    logue for 1822.
                    <hi rend="italic">Species and Varieties</hi>. The lists of the London and Paris nurserymen contain up-
                    wards of 350 names. The greater part of these have been raised from seed on the
                    continent, where it ripens better than in this country, within the last thirty years. A
                    number of varieties have also been raised in this country, especially of the <hi rend="italic">R. spinosissima</hi>,
                    or Scotch rose, of which twenty-six sorts are enumerated by J. Sabine, as having been
                    raised within the last twenty years. New varieties are raised in France and Italy
                    annually; L. Villaresi , royal gardener at Monza has raised upwards of fifty varieties
                    of <hi rend="italic">Rosa indica</hi>; not one of which have, as far as we know, reached this country. Some
                    of them are quite black, others shaped like a ranunculus, and many of them highly
                    odoriferous.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 1015-1016)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="LILYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Lily</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Lilium</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Hexan. Monog</hi>. L .; and <hi rend="italic">Liliæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Lis</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Lilie</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Giglio</hi>, Ital.
                    1635. Of this genus there are sixteen species introduced in Britain, and the whole of
                    them may be reckoned very choice flowers. We shall notice particularly, only those
                    species, of which numerous varieties have been produced. These are:
                    The <hi rend="italic">White Lily, L. Candidum</hi>  (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag.</hi> 278.), has a large scaly bulb, a
                    leafy stem, from three to four feet in height, terminating in large pure white
                    flowers on peduncles. It is a native of the Levant , and was in most gar-
                    dens in Gerarde’s time. Of this species, there are above eight varieties.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Orange Lily, L. bulbiferum</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bot. May</hi>.[sic] 36), has a scaly bulb, a leafy
                    stem, two feet and a half high, terminating in orange-colored flowers.
                    Sometimes the stem produces small green bulbs in the axillae of the leaves. Of this species, there are eight or ten varieties and sub-varieties. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">Martagon</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Turk's Cap, L. Martagon</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 893.), has a large 
                    scaly bulb, a stalk furnished with narrow leaves, near three feet high, and
                    terminating peduncles of fine carmine flowers in July. Of this species there
                    are half a dozen varieties, besides the scarlet martagon (<hi rend="italic">L. Chalcedonicum</hi>),
                    of which there are also different sorts. 
                    Besides the above species and their varieties, there are the <hi rend="italic">L. Canadense</hi>,
                    <hi rend="italic">superbum</hi>, or Turk's cap; the <hi rend="italic">Pomponium</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Tigrinum</hi>, or Tiger Lily; all
                    equally meriting cultivation as select flowers.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 959)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="DAHLIAGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Dahlia</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Dahlia superflua</hi> and <hi rend="italic">D. frustranea</hi>, H. K. (<hi rend="italic">Cav. Ic</hi>. i.
                    t. 80. and 266.); <hi rend="italic">Polyg. Super</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Corymbiferæ</hi>, J.
                    1640. The roots are tuberous and fasciculated; the stems rise from five to eight feet,
                    covered with large compound leaves, resembling those of the common dwarf elder, and 
                    with side branches bearing numerous flowers of a great variety of colors, which appear
                    in August, and continue till destroyed by frost. The plant grows wild in Mexico, in
                    sandy meadows, and was sent to Madrid in 1789, and thence to England in the same 
                    year; but the plants being lost, seeds were reintroduced by Lady Holland in 1804, and
                    from these and some plants imported from France during the peace of 1814, the present 
                    extensive stock of dahlias has originated. Till this last period they were much more 
                    cultivated in France and Germany than in England, and more especially by the Count 
                    Lebeur, at Paris, and M. Otto, at Berlin. At present the dahlia is the most fashion-
                    able flower in this country, and the extent of its culture in some of the nurseries, espe-
                    cially that of J. Lee, is truly astonishing. Nor is this to be wondered at, as Sabine
                    observes, for, independently of the great beauty and diversity of the flowers, they are in
                    perfection at a season when, till they came into notice, our gardens had but little orna-
                    ment. The roots are edible, but not agreeable.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. The leading varieties of the fertile-rayed species <hi rend="italic">D. superflua</hi>, are,
                    the purple, rose, pale, white, sulphur, yellow, tawny, copper, brick red,
                    dark-red, pomegranate colored , dark purple, very dark, and lilac flowered 
                    single, semi-double, and double, with innumerable sub-varieties.
                    Of the barren.rayed species, <hi rend="italic">D. frustranea</hi>, there are the scarlet, bright-scarlet,
                    orange, saffron, and yellow flowered, single, semi-double, and double, with
                    several sub-varieties, though this species has not sported nearly so much as the other.
                    At the Hammersmith nursery, above 200 sorts may be procured.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 962)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PRIMROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Primrose, P. vulgaris</hi>, L. (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 4.); <hi rend="italic">Primavere</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Shaftlose Primule</hi>, Ger.;
                    and <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi>, Ital. (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 450), has a perennial root, appearing as if bit off at the end,
                    with a singular smell like that of the anise. It is a native of most parts of Europe, in woods,
                    coppices, and sheltered lanes, particularly in a clayey soil. The flowers of the wild plant are
                    almost always of a brimstone color, but some-times of a purple hue; they appear in March and April.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. The double varieties produced by culture are in most esteem, of which there are:
                    The stemless white. Crimson. Hose-in-hose. Purple. Lilac. Scotch. White. Yellow. Brimstone.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 975)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HYACINTHGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Hyacinth</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus Orientalis</hi>, L. (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 93.); <hi rend="italic">Hex. Monog</hi>. L.;
                    and <hi rend="italic">Asphodeleæ</hi>, B. P.; <hi rend="italic">Jacinte</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthe</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Giacinto</hi>, Ital. (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 433.)
                    1627. The bulb of this plant is tunicated, the leaves broad and green, from the centre of which
                    arises a scape, with a spike of flowers, pointing in all directions, and by which it
                    is known, at first sight , from <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus nonscriptus</hi>, L.; (<hi rend="italic">Scilla nonscripta</hi>, W.) in
                    which the scape is drooping, and the flowers all turned to one side. It is a native of
                    the Levant, and abundant about Aleppo and Bagdat, where it flowers in February;
                    here it flowers in March and April. It was cultivated by Gerarde in 1596; but had,
                    doubtless, long before been improved by the Dutch, who have added greatly to the
                    strength and beauty of the plant, and produced almost innumerable varieties.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. Gerarde mentions the single and double blue, the purple, and the white.
                    Parkinson, in 1629, enumerates eight sorts. Miller says, the Haerlem gardeners dis-
                    tinguish near 2000 sorts, and generally publish catalogues of them from year to year.
                    At present, the taste for this flower being considerably abated, the Dutch and English
                    catalogues contain only a few hundred sorts. Mason's Catalogue for 1820, contains
                    three hundred sorts with names. These names are quite arbitrary, being given by the
                    grower after himself or some public character; and therefore they are here omitted.
                    They are arranged as double-blues, whites, reds, and yellows, and single sorts of the
                    same colors; the blues and reds are the most numerous; the yellow, those of which there is least variety .
                    Only single hyacinths were, at first, cultivated; but about the beginning of the last
                    century, attention was paid to double-flowers by Peter Voerhelm, whose first double-
                    flower was named <hi rend="italic">Mary</hi>, and is now lost; but his third flower, <hi rend="italic">the King of Great Britain</hi>,
                    which is now looked upon as the oldest double-hyacinth, was greatly preferred to all the
                    flowers known, and the price of it was then above 1000 florins or 100<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. sterling. Up
                    to the middle of last century, the greatest attention was paid at Haerlem to raising new
                    sorts of double-flowers; and as much as 200<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. has been known to be given for a root;
                    but since that period, the taste for this and other bulbous flowers has considerably de-
                    clined, and at present there are few sorts for which more than 10<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. are asked,
                    the general price being from one to ten shillings a bulb for the varied sorts, and what
                    are called the common mixtures, are sold at from 2<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. to 3<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. a hundred. A variety de-
                    generates, under bad treatment, in two or three years; but in Holland some have been preserved nearly a century.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 940-941)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="CROCUSGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Crocus</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Crocus</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Trian. Monog</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Irideæ</hi>, B. P. <hi rend="italic">Safran</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Safran</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Zaffarano</hi>, Ital.
                    1631. The bulb is round, solid and compressed with a netted skin, from the centre of 
                    which arise four or five grass-like leaves, and one or two flowers. Out of the centre of the
                    tube of the flower arises a slender style, crowned by a broad flat stigma of a gold color.
                    After the flower is past, the germ, which hitherto was seated on the bulb at the base of
                    the tube, pushes out of the ground, and ripens its seeds; a singular economy in nature,
                    and which occurs only in the colchicum, and a few other plants.
                    All the known species of this genus may be considered as florists' flowers. Many
                    botanists, indeed, consider that there is only two species, the <hi rend="italic">C. vernus</hi>, or spring-blowing
                    crocus; and the <hi rend="italic">C. sativus</hi>, the saffron, or autumn crocus.
                    From the <hi rend="italic">Crocus vernus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 343 and our <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 440.) they consider that 
                    the <hi rend="italic">C. versicalor</hi> (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 441.), the <hi rend="italic">C. biflorus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 442. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">C. susiana</hi> (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the
                    <hi rend="italic">C. sulphureus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>), and the <hi rend="italic">C. mæsianus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">d</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e</hi>), with their numerous sub-
                    varieties, have been produced by cul-ture or locality.
                    From the <hi rend="italic">Crocus sativus</hi>, or saffron crocus (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 343. and our <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 443. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>),
                    they think it likely that the <hi rend="italic">C. serotinus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 443. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>), and the <hi rend="italic">C. nudiflorus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 443. <hi rend="italic">e</hi>),
                    have been also originated by cultivation or accident.
                    It is sufficient for our purpose to observe, that all the sorts have been time out of 
                    mind, and still are, great ornaments to the garden; the spring sorts coming into flower
                    in February and March, and the autumn sorts in September and October.
                    The color of the spring crocus in its wild state in Switzerland, is white with a pur-
                    ple base; it is considered as naturalized in England, but when found wild, is almost 
                    always of a yellow color. The autumn crocus, or saffron, is also found wild in some
                    places, and considered as naturalized; but it appears to be an African plant, and intro-
                    duced originally in Edward the Third's time, which its Arabic name, <hi rend="italic">sahafaran</hi>, seems
                    to justify. Its colour is generally purple or blue, as is that of most of the autumn va-
                    rieties in cultivation at present.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. None of these are double. Of the spring crocus, Parkinson has enume-
                    rated twenty-seven varieties; the fundamental colours of which are blue, purple, yellow,
                    and white. Miller recites twelve as leading sorts. Mason's catalogue for 1820 men-
                    tions “twenty named sorts,” besides the light, dark, and striped purple, cloth of gold;
                    the Scotch crocus beautifully striped, the white, the large and small yellow, and several
                    striped sorts. The Dutch are continually producing new varieties, as are some florists
                    in this country, of which Haworth (<hi rend="italic">Hort</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Trans</hi>. i. 122.) may be cited as an instance.
                    Of the autumn crocus, Parkinson has enumerated four; and Ray, six varieties. Mil-
                    ler has only four: the sweet-smelling, of a deep blue; the mountain, of a paler blue;
                    the many-flowering, bluish; and the small flowering. Most of these varieties are now lost.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 954-955)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="NARCISSUSFLOWERGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Narcissus</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Narcissus</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Hex. Monog</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Amaryllideæ</hi>, B. P. <hi rend="italic">Narcisse</hi>, Fr. and Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Narcisso</hi>, Ital.
                    1632. The bulb is pear-shaped and tunicated, the leaves succulent and linear, and
                    the flower-stems, which are from six to eighteen inches in height, bear either solitary or
                    fasciculated flowers; the color of the flower is either white or yellow, and generally
                    highly odoriferous. Most of the species are natives of the south of Europe, but one,
                    the <hi rend="italic">N. Pseudo-Narcissus</hi>, is a native of England, and common in woods in clayey soils.
                    They come into flower in February, March, and April.
                    <hi rend="italic">Species and Varieties</hi>. The popular division of this genus is into daffodils, white narcissi, jonquils, and polyanthus narcissi.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Daffodils</hi> are, <hi rend="italic">N. pseudo Narcissus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 17.), of which the varieties
                    are the common double, the double with white petals and a yellow cup;
                    the single with yellow petals and a golden cup; three or four concentric cups; Tradescant's daffodil and above
                    a dozen other nameless varieties; the peerless, or two-flowered daffodil, <hi rend="italic">N. bifloras</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 276),
                    and a variety <hi rend="italic">N. b. a. tenuior</hi> with one flower only on the scape; the two-colored daffodil, <hi rend="italic">N. bicolor</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 1187.),
                    a native of Spain, and a variety of the great yellow Spanish, the largest flower of the genus;
                    the least daffodil <hi rend="italic">N. minor</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 6.); the rush-leaved, <hi rend="italic">N. triandrus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 48.),
                    and some other species and varieties. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">White Narcissi</hi> are the poets' narcissus, <hi rend="italic">N. poeticus</hi>: the early-flowered,
                    <hi rend="italic">N. p. a. angustifolius</hi>; and the late-flowered <hi rend="italic">N. p. majalis</hi>; the musk narcissus,
                    <hi rend="italic">N. moschatus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 1300.); the eastern narcissus, <hi rend="italic">N. orientalis</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 948.),
                    and the yellowish and large-flowered varieties; the hoop-petticoat narcissus, <hi rend="italic">N. bulbocodium</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 88.);
                    and the paper narcissus, <hi rend="italic">N. papyraceus</hi>, with other varieties.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Jonquils</hi> are, the common, <hi rend="italic">N. jonquilla</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 15.), so named from
                    its rush or jonc-like leaves; the double-flowered jonquil; the sweet-scented jonquil, <hi rend="italic">N. odorus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 934.),
                    the great jonquil, <hi rend="italic">N. calathinus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 78.), and some minor varieties. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">Polyanthus Narcissi</hi> are the common <hi rend="italic">N. tazzetta</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 925.);
                    the sulphur-colored, single and double; the white and yellow, single and double;
                    and above a hundred other sorts, with arbitrary names given by the Dutch, 
                    who have highly improved this division of the genus. Some of these sorts are considered species by botanists.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 956)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="CROWNIMPERIALGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Fritillary</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Fritillaria</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Heran. Monog</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Liliæ</hi>, J. (fig. 446.)
                    1634. Of this genus there are three species which are considered as florists' flowers;
                    of these species there are numerous varieties.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Crown Imperial</hi>, <hi rend="italic">F. Imperialis</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 194.) <hi rend="italic">La Couronne Imperiale</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Kaiserkrone</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">La Corona Imperial</hi>, Ita. (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 446. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>), has a scaly bulb,
                    from which arise strong stems, from two to four feet in height, furnished with
                    numerous broad shining green leaves, and crowned with a whirl of showy pendulous
                    flowers, yellow, red, or striped in various ways, which appear in March and April.
                    It is one of the earliest ornaments of the flower garden, producing a fine 
                    appearance in the middle of large borders , at a season when such flowers are most
                    wanted. The “singular nectary,” Professor Martyn observes, “cannot but engage 
                    the attention of the curious observer; it is a white glandular cavity, at the base
                    of each petal, and has a drop of limpid nectarious juice standing in it, when the
                    flower is in vigour. Another of the wonders of nature may be observed in the
                    peduncles which bend down while the plant is in flower, but become upright as the
                    seed ripens.” There are above a dozen varieties in cultivation, distinguished by
                    the different shades of yellow, white, and red in the flower, and by being striped double or semi-double.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 958)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="FLAG-IRISGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Iris</hi>–-<hi rend="italic">Iris</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Trian. Monog</hi>. L. and <hi rend="italic">Irideæ</hi>, B. P. <hi rend="italic">L’Iris</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Schwertlilie</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Iride</hi>, Ital. (<hi rend="italic">Figs</hi>. 444. <hi rend="italic">and</hi> 445.)
                    1633. There are several species of this genus, which are considered florists' flowers.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Persian Iris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. Persica</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>., and our <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 444. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>), a very low bulbous-
                    rooted plant, with delicate blue and violet-colored flowers, greatly esteemed
                    for their beauty and sweet smell, which is so powerful that one plant 
                    will scent a whole room. It is a native of Persia, and was cultivated by Parkinson
                    in 1629. The bulbs are generally imported from Holland, and blown in 
                    water-glasses, or pots of sand with very little earth intermixed, in February and March.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Snake's-head Iris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. tuberosa</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 551. and <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 444. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>), has long 
                    narrow four-cornered leaves, and a dark purple flower, which appears in April.
                    It is a native of the Levant, and was cultivated in 1597. The tubers are generally imported from Holland. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">Chalcedonian Iris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. susiana</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 91, and <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 444. <hi rend="italic">c</hi>), has finely
                    striated leaves, a scape a span high, and the largest and most magnificent 
                    corolla of all the species. Its petals are of a delicate texture, almost as
                    broad as a hand, purple or black striped with white. It flowers in the 
                    beginning of June; is a native of the Levant, and was cultivated by Gerarde in 1596.
                    The <hi rend="italic">bulbous-rooted</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Spanish Iris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. xiphium</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 686, and <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 445. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>),
                    has channelled leaves, convoluted during their whole length, and awl-shaped
                    at the tip; the flowers of the wild plant are blue, with emarginate
                    petals, and appear in June; but cultivation has produced a great number
                    of varieties with yellow, white, violet, and variegated flowers. It is a native
                    of the south of Europe, and was cultivated by Gerarde in 1596. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">Great bulbous-rooted Iris</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">English Iris</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Dutch</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. xiphioides</hi> 
                    (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 687, and <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 56. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>), is much larger than the other in all its parts,
                    the flower-stalk is near twice the height, and the flowers are more than
                    double the size. It is equally prolific in varieties as <hi rend="italic">Ixiphium</hi>, of which 
                    it is by some botanists considered only a variety. The tubers of both sorts are annually imported from Holland.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 957)
                
                Iris.
                Nat. Order: -Irideæ.
                Gen: Char: - Corolla superior, 6-parted, 3 segments large &#x0026;
                reflected. Stigmas 3, like petals, covering the stamens.
                This handsome genus of tuberous-rooted plants is
                one of those whose sword-shaped leaves are placed with
                one edge towards the stem. In most of the species the
                tuberous root is a continuation of the stem, but in
                some the fibres swell into true tubers of an oblong form.
                The seed-vepel<!--not sure what this word is supposed to be--> is composed of 3 valves<!--not sure what this word is supposed to be-->; forming as
                    many cells, each containing two rows of round seeds.
                    These plants mostly prefer a watery situation, but will
                    grow well in a common garden. The roots of some species
                    are highly medicinal; others are used as a perfume 
                    under the name of Orrice-root.
                (Sir James Edward Smith, English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. [...] The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 10, 1832, p. 27)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="GERANIUMGLOSS" resp="#CGP"><hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>, L. <hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Erodium</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Pelargonium</hi>,
                    of modern authors. <hi rend="italic">Monadelphia</hi>, L.; and <hi rend="italic">Geraniæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Geranier</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Geranio</hi>, Ital.
                    1711. This beautiful tribe comprehends numerous species and varieties of herbaceous
                    suffruticose and shrubby plants, generally of a somewhat succulent nature
                    throughout. They are almost all natives of the Cape of Good Hope, and with the
                    exception of three or four species, have been introduced, or originated here from
                    seed during the present and latter end of the last century. They are chiefly admired
                    for their flowers, which they produce in abundance from May to September,
                    generally in corymbs from the axillæ of the leaves of every shade of red, scarlet,
                    and purple, mixed with white and yellow. The plants are casily cultivated, and
                    by proper pruning, with the aid of gentle forcing in winter, many of the species, as the
                    <hi rend="italic">P. zonale, cuculatum, cordatum, &#x0026;c.</hi> may be kept in flower all the year. The best
                    collection of this family is in the nursery of Messrs. Colville, under the care of
                    R. Sweet, whose “<hi rend="italic">Geraniæ</hi>,” now publishing, is the most elegant and complete work of its kind.
                    <hi rend="italic">Species and Varieties</hi>. Many species and sub-species have been received from the
                    Cape; but the greater number of the admired sorts have been raised in this country
                    from seed; some of these have received systematic appellations, but the greater number
                    have been named by those who raised them after themselves, or their friends, in the
                    manner of florists' flowers.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 1032)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PEONYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Pæony</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Pæonia</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Polyan. Dig</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Ranunculaceæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Pivoine</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Päonie</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Peonia</hi>, Ital.
                    1639. Most of the species of this plant introduced in this country may be considered
                    as select flowers; but that which has been longest cultivated is the <hi rend="italic">P. officinalis</hi>
                    (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 1784.) The roots are composed of roundish tubers, the stalks of the leaves rise
                    between two and three feet high, and terminate in large red or purple flowers, which
                    appear in May. The leaves are composed of many unequal lobes, variously cut into
                    many segments. It is a native of Switzerland, Dauphine, and other parts of Europe,
                    and also of China and Japan; and was cultivated here in 1562. The roots were formerly
                    much used in medicine.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. Originally the common pæony was said to be of two sorts, male and
                    female, the flowers of the former being smaller and lighter colored than those of the
                    latter. These distinctions, which had no sexual allusion in this case, the pæony being
                    hermaphrodite, are now laid aside, and the varieties of <hi rend="italic">P. officinalis</hi> have been reduced
                    by J. Sabine (<hi rend="italic">Hort. Trans</hi>. ii. 273.) to the following:
                    The <hi rend="italic">double red</hi>, the most common, and formerly highly prized; being, when
                    introduced at Antwerp, near 250 years ago, sold for twelve crowns. 
                    The double flesh-colored. The double white. The double fringed. The double white Chinese.
                    The double sweet-scented Chinese. (<hi rend="italic">Hort. Trans</hi>. vol. ii. pl. 18) Whitley’s double white Chinese.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 962)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="OAKGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Oak is the Quercus, L., Monæc. Polyand. L., and Amentaceæ, J. Chêne, Fr.;
                    Eich, Ger.; and Querec, Ital. The following species and varieties are planted for their timber.
                    The Common Oak, Q. robur, (Eng. Bot. 1845.) a native of Britain. It grows to
                    the height of fifty or sixty feet when in a heavy loam; flowers in April, and ripens its
                    acorns in October and November.
                    The most valuable variety of the common oak is said (Caled. Hort. Mem. iii. 376.)
                    to be the pedunculata (Eng. Bot. 1342.), or the stalk fruited; by some considered a
                    distinct species. It is distinguished from Q. robur by the marked circumstance of the
                    acorns being placed on long fruit-stalks, whilst those of the robur are nearly sessile.
                    Besides, the superior utility and hardiness of the timber, the pedunculated oak is, in
                    fact, the most magnificent of the two British sorts. Miller says, this variety of the
                    Q. robur, (and which he calls the fæmina,) is more rare than the sessile-fruited; but
                    Professor Martyn says, this is not the case, and that the pedunculated is equally
                    general as the other. It is observed by Du Hamel, that oaks in forests being propagated
                    from the acorn, there are so many varieties that it is difficult to find two resembling
                    each other in every respect. Professor Martyn observes, that the figures in 
                    ancient authors have the fruit uniformly on foot-stalks, which shows that that variety
                    had been most common: and Ray considers it as the common oak of England. Du Roi
                    affirms, that the timber of the sessile-fruited is reddish, and brittle, whilst that
                    of the stalk-fruited is whitish and hard. From these, and various accounts, as well as our
                    own observation, we consider ourselves justified in recommending to nurserymen and
                    others, who gather acorns for seeds, to take effectual precautions that only the stalked sort be gathered.
                    1912. The Turkey Oak, Q. cerris, (Du Roi, 2 t. 5. f. 1.) a native of the south of
                    Europe, introduced in 1735. This species is distinguished by oblong, pointed, and
                    frequently lyrate leaves, jagged, and a little hoary on the under side. The acorns are
                    small, and have rough, prickly cups. The tree grows from forty to sixty feet high.
                    There are several varieties, but the best is that called the Devonshire or Luccombe,
                    from the name of the person who raised it from seeds, saved from a tree of the
                    Turkey-oak grown in Devonshire.
                    There are about forty species of exotic oaks introduced in this country, which may
                    be considered as timber trees, and are such in effect, in their native countries. Of
                    these, the greater part are natives of America; and it has been recommended,
                    (Caled. Mem. iii. 378.) to cultivate the Q. tinctoria or Quercitron on account of its
                    bark, which affords a valuable yellow die[sic. All these species, however, are either too
                    tender, or too scarce, or too dwarfish, and slow-growing, to warrant us in considering any
                    other than the common and Luccombe oaks, as fit for the purposes of profitable planting.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 1139-1140)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HAWTHORNGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Hawthorn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mespilus oxyacantha</hi>, E. B. (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>.); <hi rend="italic">Icosan. Di.-
                    Pentag</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Rosaceæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Aubépine</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Hagedorn</hi>, Ger.; <hi rend="italic">Branco spino</hi>, Ital.
                    It is a native shrub, of great importance as a hedge plant, and is also frequently
                    introduced into narrow plantations as an undergrowth. It will not grow, however,
                    under the drip of trees, and therefore, in a profitable point of view, is only to be
                    considered as affording the impermiable, close, and durable, and easily raised fences,
                    called quickset hedges. The timber of such plants as grow singly, and attain a tolerable
                    size, is valued by the millwright and turner, and the roots by the cabinet-maker. It
                    is often spoiled, Sang observes, through inattention after cutting; if it be allowed to
                    lie in entire logs or trunks, it soon heats, and becomes quite brittle and worthless; it
                    therefore ought to be instantly cut up into planks, and laid to dry. The haws and
                    foliage afford excellent food for deer.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 1145)
                
                MESPILUS Oxyacantha.
                <hi rend="italic">Common Hawthorn, Whitethorn, or May</hi>.
                
                    <hi rend="italic">ICOSANDRIA Pentagynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. in 5 segments. <hi rend="italic">Petals</hi> 5. <hi rend="italic">Drupa</hi>
                    inferior. <hi rend="italic">Nuts</hi> 2 to 5, with two kernels each. 
                SPEC. CHAR. Thorny. Leaves obtuse, deeply three-
                cleft, serrated, smooth. Styles one or two. 
                SYN. Mespilus Oxyacantha. <hi rend="italic">Sm. Fl. Brit</hi>. 529.
                    <hi rend="italic">Hull. ed</hi>. 2. 145[.] <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 190. 
                M. apii folio sylvestris spinosa, sive Oxyacantha.
                    <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 453.
                    Cratægus Oxyacantha. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 683. <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 214.
                    <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 459. <hi rend="italic">Fl. Dan. t</hi>. 634.
                    C. monogyna. <hi rend="italic">Jacq. Austr. t</hi>. 292. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 156. <hi rend="italic">Abbot</hi>. 108.
                
                THIS beautiful and useful shrub, whose abundance and luxuriance
                with us may well counterbalance the myrtle of more genial
                climates, forms the natural thickets of most parts of England.
                It adorns our parks, and makes our best fences. Its ruby-
                tipped buds are the first sign of vegetation in spring; its
                sweet blossoms the decoration and the pledge of approaching
                summer; its fruit the chief wild treasure of autumn. The hard
                and tough wood is useful for many different purposes, but of
                slow growth, and generally of no great size. The branches bear
                clipping to any extent, and the whole bush, if cut nearly to the
                ground, is speedily restored.
                
                The branches are furnished with rigid spines. The leaves are
                alternate, stalked, deciduous, of a dark shining green, smooth, in
                three or five deep serrated segments. Stipulas lunate, varying much
                in size. Flowers corymbose, terminal, with smooth stalks. Calyx
                reflexed. Petals concave, usually white; of a beautiful red on a
                strong or deep soil. Anthers pink, changing to black. Styles one
                or two in different flowers of the same bunch. Fruit red, rarely
                yellow, mealy, insipid, with one or two hard nuts. Sometimes
                there are three styles and as many nuts.—The leaves vary in
                shape, but we have in vain laboured to ascertain two species
                of Hawthorn in Britain; nor do the <hi rend="italic">Oxyacantha</hi> and <hi rend="italic">monogyna</hi>
                of Jacquin appear to us permanently distinct.
                (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 35, 1813, p. 2504)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="YEWGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Yew</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Taxus baccato</hi>, L. (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 746.); <hi rend="italic">Polyg. Monæc</hi>. L.; and
                    <hi rend="italic">Coniferæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">If</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Eihenbaum</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Tasso</hi>, Ital. It is a low, bush-like,
                    dark, evergreen tree, of great longevity, slow in growth, and affording a hard, white
                    valuable timber. It flowers in April and May, and its berries are ripe in November.
                    It is found in a wild state in bleak situations, and on a variety of soils, dry and
                    moist. It is very common in ancient church-yards, in many of which it has attained a
                    great size and age. Evelyn, and after him, Professor Martyn, have referred to a great
                    number of examples of notable trees of this species.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 1145)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="GENTIANGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">umbelliferous</hi> (umbel-bearing) plants, which compose nearly the
                    whole of the second order of the class Pentándria, have, with
                    few exceptions, <hi rend="italic">pinnate</hi> leaves, more or less compound.
                    The British Flora possesses only eight genera in this order,
                    that are not included in the natural family called Umbelliferæ
                    or Umbellátæ. Of this number are the beet (<hi rend="italic">B</hi>èta), of which
                    the root is eaten in salads (it contains a great quantity of sugar,
                    which may be extracted and manufactured for use); the glass-
                    wort (Salsòla), used in the manufacture of glass; the elm (<hi rend="italic">U</hi>'l-
                    mus); and the gentian (Genti<hi rend="italic">ána</hi>), a genus remarkable for the
                    brilliant blue colour of its flowers, and the bitterness of its
                    roots. “As bitter as gentian,” is a common phrase. The
                    root of a species of gentian growing on the Alps, and other
                    mountains on the Continent (<hi rend="italic">G</hi>. lùtea), is the bitter chiefly
                    used in medicine.
                    (Edward Charlesworth, The Magazine of Natural History, vol.2, 1829, p.156)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="COLUMBINEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">AQUILEGIA. <hi rend="italic">Columbine</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Nat. Order</hi>. RANUNCULACEÆ.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> 5-leaved, petaloid, deciduous. <hi rend="italic">Petals</hi> 5,
                    gaping above, elongated downwards into a hollow, horn-shaped
                    spur, projecting between the leaves of the calyx. Follicles 5.
                    Ornamental herbs with purple, blue, or white flowers, divided
                    leaves, and fibrous perennial roots. The genus which is small,
                    containing about 15 known species, is confined to the north
                    temperate zone. The plants are less acrid than the rest of
                    their order, and the common Columbine has been employed
                    medicinally as an astringent, but instances are on record
                    of its proving fatal in overdoses.
                    AQUILEGIA VULGARIS. <hi rend="italic">Common Columbine</hi>. TAB. 770. 
                    Spur of the petals incurved. Follicles hairy. Stem leafy, many-flowered,
                    smooth. Leaves glabrous. Styles as long as the stamens. 
                    Aquilegia vulgaris, E. B. 297. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> III. 33. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 13. <hi rend="italic">Hooker ed</hi>. 2. 261. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 3. 264.
                    Found wild in woods, thickets and pastures in many parts of England
                    and Wales, though probably in its origin a wanderer from the garden.
                    Leaves mostly radical, on long petioles, twice ternate, obtusely
                    lobed; more or less glaucous as well as the stem, which rises
                    a foot or 18 inches high, bearing a few sessile leaves, and several
                    drooping, purple, rarely rose-coloured or white, flowers. The inner
                    series of stamens is often abortive, in which case the filaments are
                    sometimes united, forming a plaited membrane around the germens,
                    as shown in our figures. Flowers in June.
                    (Sir James Edward Smith, English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. [...] The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 1, 1832, p. 13)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="POPPYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">PAPAVER. <hi rend="italic">Poppy</hi>. 
                    Nat. Order. PAPAVERACEÆ. 
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> inferior, 2-leaved, deciduous. <hi rend="italic">Petals</hi> 4.
                    <hi rend="italic">Stigma</hi> radiated, sessile on the top of the ovarium. <hi rend="italic">Capsule</hi> 1-celled.
                    <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> numerous, on parietal receptacles projecting
                    towards the centre of the cavity, and escaping by pores
                    beneath the projecting rim of the stigma.
                    Herbs with wing-cleft, alternate leaves, and solitary inflorescence.
                    The flowers, on long peduncles deflexed before expansion,
                    are of various shades of red, or purple, yellow, and white,
                    but never blue. All of the species are narcotic, and
                    secrete a white milk-like juice in which that property resides:
                    in its inspissated form this is the Opium of commerce. Europe
                    and the central parts of Asia seem to be the chief stations of the genus.
                    (Sir James Edward Smith, English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. [...] The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 1, 1832, p. 48)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="SNOWDROPGLOSS" resp="#CGP">GALANTHUS nivalis. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Snowdrop</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">HEXANDRIA Monogynia</hi>. 
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Corolla</hi> of six petals, three of which are
                    smaller than the rest, and emarginated. <hi rend="italic">Stigma</hi> simple.
                    SPEC. CHAR. …
                    SYN. Galanthus nivalis. Linn. Sp. Pl. 413. Huds. Fl. An. 140. With. Bot. Arr. 340.
                    
                    ON the authority of Mr. Hudson and Dr. Stokes, the Snowdrop
                    is now admitted into the list of British plants, although
                    not described as such by Ray. Whether originally a native or
                    not, it is now found in a wild state in many different situations,
                    such as orchards, grassy meadows, groves, and thickets. Dr. Stokes,
                    whose accuracy and extensive information none who
                    peruses the Botanical Arrangement of British Plants can doubt, is
                    particularly exact in asserting that he has gathered it remote
                    from all traces of buildings or gardens.
                    No plant is more generally cultivated, or more cordially welcomed
                    as the herald of approaching spring. It frequently
                    pierces through the unmelted snow, which it rivals in whiteness,
                    and remains uninjured by a season, during whose inclemency
                    most vegetable productions lie dormant. Who can
                    read the following charming lines on the Snowdrop, by
                    Mrs. Barbauld, without admiration?
                    
                    “As nature's breath, by some transforming pow'r,
                    “Had chang'd an icicle into a flow'r.--
                    “Its name and hue the scentless plant retains,
                    “And winter lingers in its icy veins.”
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 5, 1796, p. 19)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="VIOLETGLOSS" resp="#CGP">Viola. Violet.
                    Nat. Order. Violaceæ. 
                    Gen: Char:-<hi rend="underline">Calyx</hi> of 3 leaves, each extended at
                    the base. <hi rend="underline">Petals</hi> 5-unequal, the lowermost spurred
                    behind. <hi rend="underline">Anthers</hi> slightly cohering. Capsule superior,
                    of 1 cell, with 3 valves.
                    A genus of small herbaceous plants
                    generally admired &#x0026; well-known by the names
                    Violet, Heartsease, &#x0026; Pansey. The [sic] all have alternate
                    leaves with stipules at their bases &#x0026; fibrous
                    either annual or perennial roots. They may be
                    divided into two sections by their stipules, in some being membranous, in others leafy.
                [...]
                The Violet, so justly esteemed for its delightful fragrance, is, like
                many other desirable plants, frequently found wild. In England it
                is abundant, not uncommonly varying to white, but it is rare in Scotland.
                A double variety obtained by florists has a richer scent. The
                long prostrate scions seldom produce flowers until the second year,
                when flowers with petals are raised upon upright stalks in March and
                April, but are of short duration; they are followed by a long succession
                without petals upon stalks which bend to the ground, and there
                ripen their seeds. This is the case with several other species. At
                the same time the leaves greatly enlarge. A syrup made from the
                petals is a gentle laxative and, while it retains its colour, a delicate
                test for free acids and alkalies. The Sorbet of the Turks is also said
                to be prepared from them with sugar.
                (Sir James Edward Smith, English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. [...] The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 2, 1835, p. 58-59)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HEARTSEASEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">VIOLA TRICOLOR. <hi rend="italic">Pansy Violet</hi>. Tab. 333. 
                    Stems angular, diffuse. Leaves deeply crenate, oblong. Stipules
                    leaf-like, pinnatifid, the central lobe toothed. Petals longer than
                    the calyx. Germen oval. Root annual. 
                    Viola tricolor, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 1287. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 305. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 36. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 107. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2. 119.
                    The Wild Pansy or, in familiar language, Heart's-ease, the origin
                    of all our annual garden varieties, is very common in corn-fields, and
                    flowers from May to September.
                    (Sir James Edward Smith, English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. [...] The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 2, 1835, p. 60)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="GREEKVALERIANGLOSS" resp="#CGP">POLEMONIUM cæruleum. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Jacob's Ladder</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. in five segments. <hi rend="italic">Stamina</hi> standing
                    on five valves which close the tube. <hi rend="italic">Stigma</hi>
                    three-cleft. <hi rend="italic">Capsule</hi> three-celled, superior.
                    SPEC. CHAR. Leaves pinnated. Flowers erect. Calyx
                    longer than the tube of the corolla.
                    SYN. Polemonium cæruleum. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 230.
                    <hi rend="italic">Huds. Fl. An</hi>. 89. <hi rend="italic">With. Bot. Arr</hi>. 215.
                    P. vulgare cæruleum. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 288.
                    
                    THIS, although very common in gardens, is one of the
                    plants most rarely found wild in this country. Botanists of the
                    last century gathered it in the romantic and mountainous country
                    about Malham Cove, in the north of Yorkshire, where it still
                    grows, as well as in some parts of Derbyshire (<hi rend="italic">Withering)</hi>. 
                    
                    A variety with white flowers is very common, sometimes
                    even from the same root as the blue ones (<hi rend="italic">Linnæus</hi>); the faint
                    purplish blue seen in the flowers of this plant, being that which
                    of all colours is most apt to vary to white.
                    
                    Its items rise to the height of eighteen or twenty inches,
                    seldom more. The root is fibrous and perennial.
                    
                    This plant is absurdly enough reckoned among the Valerians
                    by the old authors, with which it has not the least affinity
                    either in appearance, botanical characters, sensible qualities, or
                    medical virtues.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 1, 1790, p. 14)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HONEYSUCKLEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">LONICERA. <hi rend="italic">Honeysuckle</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Nat. Order</hi>. CAPRIFOLIÆ.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Corolla</hi> of 1 petal, irregular. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> superior,
                    of 5 teeth, small. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi> of 1 or more cells. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> many.
                    Slender shrubs, with opposite leaves and branches; the
                    stems in some species twining up other shrubs and trees. The
                    fruit is not eatable.
                    
                    LONICERA CAPRIFOLIUM. <hi rend="italic">Pale Perfoliate Honeysuckle</hi>. TAB. 324.
                    Flowers ringent, whorled, terminal. Leaves deciduous, the upper
                    ones confluent and perfoliate.
                    Lonicera Caprifolium, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 799. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 325. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 103. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2. 116.
                    Caprifolium perfoliatum, <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 131.
                    This rare British plant may have been overlooked as one of the
                    many varieties of the Common Honeysuckle. The fragrant flowers
                    are in perfection through May or June. It is very commonly cultivated.
                    
                    LONICERA PERICLYMENUM. <hi rend="italic">Common Honeysuckle</hi>. TAB. 325. 
                    Flowers ringent, in terminal imbricated heads. Leaves deciduous, all separate. 
                    Lonicera Periclymenum, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 800. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 326. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 103. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2.116.
                    Caprifolium Periclymenum, <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 131. (Woodbine.)
                    An universal favourite which decorates our hedges abundantly, and
                    perfumes the air delightfully in an evening after rain. The stem
                    climbs by twisting to a considerable height upon trees and bushes.
                    There occurs in gardens a variety with sinuated and generally variegated
                    leaves, called the Oak-leaved, besides several varieties differing
                    in the colour of the flower and smoothness of the leaves. They all
                    flower most plentifully in June and July.
                    
                    LONICERA XYLOSTEUM. <hi rend="italic">Upright Honeysuckle</hi>. TAB. 326. 
                    Flower-stalks 2-flowered. Berries distinct. Leaves entire, downy.
                    Lonicera Xylosteum, E. B. 916. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 326. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 132. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 103. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2. 117.
                    Probably this has escaped from gardens; only two places are named
                    where it has been found wild, viz. under the Roman Wall near Shewing-
                    Sheels in Northumberland, and in a coppice, called the Hachetts,
                    to the east of Houghton Bridge, 4 miles from Arundel. The stem is
                    upright, bushy, very much branched. The
                    scentle[s]s flowers, which appear in June,
                    are by no means showy; it is however, a
                    favorite shrub in gardens. The berries
                    are of a bright scarlet, &#x0026; contain 6 or more seeds each.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 5, 1835, p. 56-57)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="IVYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">HEDERA Helix. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Common Ivy</hi>.
                   
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>. 
                   GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. of 5 teeth. <hi rend="italic">Petals</hi> 5, broadest at the
                    base. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi> encompassed with the calyx, containing 5 <hi rend="italic">seeds</hi>.
                    SPEC. CHAR. Leaves some ovate, some lobed.
                    SYN. Hedera Helix. Linn. Sp. Pl. 292. Sm. Fl. Brit. 267. Huds. 100. 
                    With. 267. Hull. 54. Relh. 97. Sibth. 85. Abbot. 53. Curt. Lond. fasc. 1. t. 16. 
                    H. communis major et minor. Raii Syn. 459.
                    
                    EVERY one is acquainted with the Ivy, so common and so
                    picturesque upon old walls, and the trunks of aged trees, whose
                    heads it frequently overtops, finally overwhelming its supporters
                    altogether. Nor does it less commonly creep on the ground
                    in dark woods, forming an evergreen carpet. It is the latest
                    of all our flowering plants, blossoming in October and November,
                    and ripening its berries in the spring.
                    
                    The stem and branches are long and flexible, a little compressed,
                    creeping, and closely attached to the tree or wall,
                    which supports them, by innumerable short fibres, which,
                    however, do not afford them any nourishment; for every
                    day's experience shows that Ivy is easily killed by cutting the
                    stem above the root. The upper branches spread in every direction,
                    and are round and smooth. The leaves are ever-green,
                    of a dark hue, beautifully veined with white, and
                    somewhat shining: the lowermost five-lobed, the uppermost
                    ovate; all entire and supported by footstalks. Flowers numerous,
                    in umbels, several of which together form a corymbus.
                    Stalks slightly clothed with starry down. Germen urn-shaped,
                    encompassed by the 5 teeth of the calyx. Petals
                    green, reflexed. Stamina erect. Style very short, with a
                    simple stigma. Berry globular, black, mealy within.
                    
                    The whole plant partakes of a peculiar aromatic flavour.
                    From the old stems, when bruised, a very fragrant resin
                    exudes. Mr. Curtis recommends this plant to be trained into
                    a head as a standard ever-green ; he also mentions that sheep
                    are very fond of the leaves.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 18, 1804, p. 1267)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="GUELDERROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">VIBURNUM Opulus. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Common Guelder-rose, or Water Elder</hi>.
                   
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Trigynia</hi>. 
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. superior, of five leaves. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. in five
                    segments. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi> with one seed. 
                    SPEC. CHAR. Leaves lobed; their foot-stalks set with glands. 
                    SYN. Viburnum Opulus. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 384. <hi rend="italic">Huds. Fl. An</hi>. 130.
                    <hi rend="italic">With. Bot. Arr</hi>. 318. <hi rend="italic">Relh. Cant</hi>. 127. <hi rend="italic">Sibth. Ox</hi>. 104.
                    Opulus. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 460.
                   
                   THIS shrub is common in woods and hedges in watery
                    places, flowering early in June; the bright-red berries ripen
                    about September, and towards the middle of October the leaves
                    assume a beautiful pink-colour, affording another instance, in
                    addition to that of the Cornel (see tab. 249), of a genus,
                    mostly American, the leaves of which turn red in autumn. In
                    gardens the Guelder-rose, bearing round bunches of abortive
                    flowers only, is very common, elegantly grouping with the
                    Lilac and Laburnum in the early part of summer.
                    It is a small bushy tree, smooth in all its parts. Leaves
                    with three great, unequally serrated, lobes; their foot-stalks
                    bearing several cup-like glands towards the top, and a pair or
                    two of erect linear appendages, scarcely to be called stipulæ,
                    near the base . Cymes of many white flowers; the perfect
                    ones small, resembling elder; abortive ones in the margin,
                    each consisting merely of a large irregular flat petal, without
                    organs of fructification. Stigmas nearly sessile, close together.
                    Berries drooping, very succulent. Seed flat, heart-shaped.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 5, 1796, p. 332)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="COMFREYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">SYMPHYTUM officinale. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Common Comfrey</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. Limb of the <hi rend="italic">corolla</hi> tubular, swelling;
                    its orifice closed with awl-shaped rays. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. in 5
                    deep segments. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> 4, naked.
                    SPEC. CHAR. Leaves ovato-lanceolate, decurrent. 
                    SYN. Symphytum officinale. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 195. <hi rend="italic">Sm. Fl. Brit</hi>. 218.
                    <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 81. <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 230. <hi rend="italic">Hull</hi>. 47. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 78. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 70. <hi rend="italic">Abbot</hi>. 42.
                    <hi rend="italic">Curt. Lond. fasc</hi>. 4. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 18. <hi rend="italic">Woodv. Suppl. t</hi>. 215.
                    S. magnum. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 230.
                    
                    A FREQUENT native of watery places, banks of rivers,
                    and about ditches, flowering from the end of May to September.
                    
                    Root perennial, fleshy, externally black. Stem two or three
                    feet high, upright, leafy, winged, branched at the top, clothed
                    with short bristly hairs that point rather downward. Leaves
                    decurrent, ovato-lanceolate, waved, pointed, veiny, rough;
                    the radical ones on footstalks, and broader than the rest.
                    Clusters of flowers in pairs on a common stalk, with an odd
                    flower between them, recurved, dense, hairy. Corolla yellowish-
                    white, sometimes purple, the rays downy at each edge.
                    
                    Dr. Sibthorp has made a new species of the red or
                    purple-flowered variety, distinguishing it by a shorter and
                    spreading calyx, a mark which we and several of our friends
                    have in vain tried to discover.
                    
                    The Comfrey root abounds in a pure tasteless mucilage, like
                    that of the Marsh-mallow; and being (as Dr. Woodville observes)
                    more easily obtained, it ought not to be omitted in lists
                    of medicinal plants. Such medicines are useful in irritations
                    of the throat, intestines, and above all the bladder.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 12, 1801, p. 817)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PERIWINKLEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">VINCA major.
                    <hi rend="italic">Greater Periwinkle</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Corolla</hi> twisted, salver-shaped. <hi rend="italic">Pouches</hi> 2,
                    erect. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> without beard or wing.
                    SPEC. CHAR. Stems erect. Leaves ovate, finely fringed. Flowers on stalks.
                    SYN. Vinca major. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 304. <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 91.
                    <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 269. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 89. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 79. <hi rend="italic">Curt. Lond. fasc</hi>. 4. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 19.
                    Clematis daphnoides major. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 268.
                    
                    IN hedges and groves not very unfrequent in a truly wild
                    state; though it is so generally cultivated in every ornamented
                    shrubbery, and grows so readily, that we cannot always
                    depend upon its being really of native growth. It
                    flowers in May, and is one of the greatest ornaments of that favourite season.
                    
                    The roots are perennial, creeping; the stems also, which
                    are roundish and leafy, some of them trail and throw out
                    roots, others grow erect and bear flowers, but even these
                    afterwards take root from near their extremities. Leaves
                    opposite, on footstalks, ovate, entire, finely fringed at their
                    edges with short rigid hairs, otherwise smooth and shining.
                    Flowers solitary, axillary, alternate, on stalks about half the
                    length of the leaves. Calyx in five awl-shaped fringed
                    segments, as long as the tube of the flower. Corolla of a
                    fine purplish blue, salver-shaped, twisted (as in all this natural
                    order of <hi rend="italic">Contortæ</hi>); its tube inflated, and five-sided in
                    the upper part. Stamina inserted about its middle, bowed,
                    ciliated and compressed. Antheræ hooded. Germen double,
                    with 2 glands at its base. Style simple. Stigma shaped
                    like a pulley, orange-coloured, its top five-lobed and downy.
                    The fruit, which Mr. Curtis has not even mentioned, and
                    which few botanists have seen, is produced every year in
                    Mr. Kett's grounds at Seething, Norfolk, and consists of
                    two awl-shaped, smooth, shining pouches, or folliculi, each
                    containing one or two oblong seeds, with a groove down
                    their upper side. These seeds are roughish, but naked,
                    or destitute of beard, down, or wing.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 8, 1799, p. 514)
                
                
                VINCA minor. 
                <hi rend="italic">Lesser Periwinkle</hi>.
                
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. twisted, salver-shaped. <hi rend="italic">Pouches</hi> 2,
                    erect. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> without beard or wing. 
                SPEC. CHAR. Stems procumbent. Leaves elliptic-
                lanceolate, smooth at the edge. Flowers on 
                stalks. Calyx-teeth lanceolate. 
                SYN. Vinca minor. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 304. <hi rend="italic">Sm. Fl. Brit</hi>. 270.
                    <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 91. <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 268. <hi rend="italic">Hull</hi>. 51. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 89. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 79.
                    <hi rend="italic">Abbot</hi>. 53. <hi rend="italic">Curt. Lond. fasc</hi>. 3. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 16.
                    V. pervinca minor. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 268.
                
                WE have never seen the Lesser Periwinkle (far rarer than
                the Greater, <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 514) more truly wild than about Honingham
                church, 6 miles west of Norwich. Our specimen was gathered
                near Rippon, Yorkshire, by the Rev. Mr. Dalton, and sent by
                Mr. W. Brunton, being in the opinion of those gentlemen perfectly
                wild there. It is very generally cultivated in shady places under
                trees, its evergreen leaves and early flowers conducing greatly
                to the ornament of such places. The wild plant blossoms earlier
                than <hi rend="italic">V. major</hi>; and the garden varieties, one of which is double
                and reddish, and another white with variegated leaves, are
                found in bloom even in March or April.
                
                The root is perennial and creeping. Whole plant smooth
                and shining. Stems round, slender, leafy; erect when in
                flower, afterwards prostrate, elongated, taking root at their
                joints. Leaves opposite, on short stalks, lanceolate inclining
                to elliptic, entire , of a full shining green, destitute of the
                fringed edge observable in <hi rend="italic">V. major</hi>. The flowers are also
                smaller than in that species, of a rather darker blue, with a
                much shorter, smooth, and less tapering calyx. The fruit of
                this species we have never seen.
                (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 13, 1801, p. 917)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="LILYOFTHEVALLEYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">CONVALLARIA majalis. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Lily of the Valley</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">HEXANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. in 6 segments. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. none. <hi rend="italic">Style</hi>
                    longer than the stamina. <hi rend="italic">Stigma</hi> 3-sided. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi>
                    superior, 3-celled, spotted before it is ripe. 
                    SPEC. CHAR. Stalk naked, semicylindrical. Flowers
                    spiked, drooping, on partial stalks.
                    SYN. Convallaria majalis. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 451. <hi rend="italic">Sm. Fl. Brit</hi>. 370.
                    <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 146. <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 341. <hi rend="italic">Hull</hi>. 72. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 138. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 111.
                    <hi rend="italic">Abbot</hi>. 76. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">Curt. Lond. fasc</hi>. 5. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 24. 
                    Lilium convallium. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 264.
                    
                    THIS elegant and delightfully fragrant plant, so generally
                    cultivated in flower-gardens, is sometimes to be met with in
                    shady mountainous spots, or on heathy ground, in several
                    parts of England, as about Hampstead and Highgate, and in a
                    holly wood between Norwich and Thorpe, where it is truly
                    wild. Our specimens were obligingly communicated by S. 
                    Hailstone and W. Hurstler, esqrs. from rocky woods at Hebden
                    bridge near Halifax.
                    
                    Roots perennial, matted and creeping. Leaves two, radical, on
                    long stalks, upright, elliptical, ribbed, entire; the stalks
                    invested with seales, from among which also arises the solitary
                    naked flower-stalk, shorter than the leaves, flat on one side,
                    round on the other, bearing a simple spike of drooping, white, 
                    bell-shaped, very odoriferous flowers, each on its own curved 
                    round little stalk, having a lanceolate bractea where it springs
                    from the principal one. Stamina awl-shaped, short. Style club-
                    shaped, triangular upwards. Berry globular, scarlet when ripe.
                    
                    The spots of the unripe fruit make a principal but unsatisfactory
                    part of the generic character of <hi rend="italic">Convallaria</hi> in Linnæus. The 
                    undivided stigma chiefly distinguishes it from <hi rend="italic">Asparagus</hi>.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 15, 1802, p. 1035)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="LAURELGLOSS" resp="#CGP">DAPHNE. <hi rend="italic">Mezereon and Spurge-Laurel</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Nat. Order</hi>. THYMELEÆ. 
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> inferior, 4-cleft, petaloid. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi> 1-seeded.
                    Shrubs, with entire leaves, and white, yellow, or reddish
                    flowers, which are often highly fragrant. They are chiefly
                    natives of the Eastern hemisphere. Every part of them is
                    highly acrid, especially the bark, which is remarkable for its
                    toughness, and the curious interlacing of its silky fibres.
                    
                    DAPHNE MEZEREUM. <hi rend="italic">Common Mezereon</hi>. TAB. 564. 
                    Flowers sessile upon the branches, about 3 together. Leaves lanceolate, deciduous. 
                    Daphne Mezereum, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 1381. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> II. 228. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 209.
                    <hi rend="italic">Hooker ed</hi>. 2. 180. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 3. 184.
                    This beautiful shrub, so common in our gardens and plantations,
                    is occasionally found wild in the woods in several parts of England,
                    possibly from its berries being dropped by birds which feed on them
                    with avidity. Its fragrant rose-coloured flowers appear in March,
                    generally previous to the expansion of the leaves; in cultivation they
                    sometimes vary to white. The Mezereon has a place in our authorized
                    Materia Medica, the bark being administered in decoction in cases of
                    nervous debility of the throat or stomach. The berries are of a bright
                    scarlet, contrasting finely with the light green of the leaves, but the
                    birds seldom allow them to remain long after they become ripe.
                    
                    DAPHNE LAUREOLA. <hi rend="italic">Spurge-Laurel</hi>. Tab. 565. 
                    Racemes axillary, about 5-flowered, drooping. Leaves lanceolate, smooth; evergreen. 
                    Daphne Laureola, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 119. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> II. 228. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 209. <hi rend="italic">Hooker ed</hi>. 2. 180. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 3. 184.
                    A shrub 2 or 3 feet high, but little branched, and bearing leaves
                    only towards the extremities. Common in woods and thickets in a
                    stiff clayey soil throughout England. The yellowish green flowers
                    expand in March. The berries are black; they are eaten by birds,
                    but said to be poisonous to all other warm-blooded animals. The
                    bark of the root is an acrid cathartic, and said to be an efficacious
                    remedy in worm cases, but is highly dangerous except in minute doses.
                    (Sir James Edward Smith, English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. [...] The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 8, 1839, p. 90)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PINEGLOSS" resp="#CGP"><hi rend="italic">Resinous or Coniferous Trees</hi>.
                    These are comprised in three genera belonging to the natural order of <hi rend="italic">Conifereæ</hi>,
                    J.; viz. <hi rend="italic">Pinus</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Cupressus, Monœc. Monad</hi>. L., and <hi rend="italic">Juniperus, Diœc. Monad</hi>., L.
                    The trees, which are valuable as timber, are comprehended under the genus <hi rend="italic">Pinus</hi>,
                    which comprises the three subdivisions of pines, larches, and firs. The first is
                    distinguished by fasciculated leaves in different sheaths, but proceeding from the
                    same sheathing base; the second by fasciculated leaves from solitary sheaths; and
                    the third by solitary leaves. The branches of the whole genus are frondose or spreading,
                    and caduceous: those of the pine-tribe spread the least; those of the larch tribe rather
                    droop; and those of the firs are thin and much spread, and are peculiarly frondlike.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 1134)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="POPLARGLOSS" resp="#CGP">1940. The Poplar is the Poplus, W. Diœc. Dodec. L.; and Amentaceæ, J. Peuplier, Fr;
                    Poppelbaum, Ger.; and Poppio, Ital. There are several species which may be reckoned timber trees.
                    
                    The Abele Tree, P. Alba, (Eng. Bot. 1618.) (fig. 518, a.) The variety called the hoary poplar
                    is distinguished from the common wild abele by its larger three, four, or five lobed leaves,
                    dark above and downy under, and by the young shoots having a purple bark covered with white
                    down. It is a rapid growing tree, speedily attaining great bulk of timber, a height of 60
                    or 70 feet, and great extent of branches. P. vistulensis seems a variety of this tree; and
                    on the banks of the Vistula, particularly at Villeneuve, near Warsaw, grows to upwards
                    of 100 feet high, with a clean trunk and ample head.
                    
                    1941. The Common Black Poplar, P. nigra, (Eng. Bot. 1910. fig. 518, b.) is a native tree, of
                    lofty growth, distinguished by its light-green leaves, and lightly notched on the edges, and
                    ash-colored bark. It is, by some, considered a mere variety of the alba, and for the purposes
                    of profit may be so considered.
                    
                    1942. The Trembling Poplar, P. tremula, (fig. 518, c.) and the Common Poplar, P.
                    canescens (d), are hardy natives; but being of less rapid growth than the species
                    mentioned, are little cultivated as timber trees. The common poplar in the northern
                    counties may be frequently seen in a pollard state in hedges, where it furnishes lop
                    for fuel, and sometimes for handles to hay-rakes, &#x0026;c.
                    
                    1943. The Lombardy Poplar, P. dilatata, grows to a lofty tree, occupies little space, and
                    is not very injurious by its shade. It will not thrive, however, in exposed situations,
                    or in very indifferent soils. Some of the largest trees of this species are at Blenheim.
                    Sang and Nicol say it seldom thrives in Scotland.
                    
                    1944. The Black Italian Poplar, (dilatatata, var.) of the northern nurseries, so strongly
                    recommended by Pontey, is thus described by him, by comparison with the Lombardy poplar.
                    “The leaves of both are very much alike in color, shape, and turn, the only difference
                    being in the latter producing them somewhat larger than the former, though not near so
                    large as the other poplars, whose leaves are of similar shape. The branches of the
                    latter grow much less erect, and, likewise, much thinner upon the stem. The only other
                    distinction necessary is the bark, which, on a stem or branch of from two to four or
                    five years’ growth, is always found smoother, and of a much darker color than any of
                    the poplars that are at all like it in other respects.”
                    
                    He says it was first sent to Scotland from America, and disseminated by Dicksons
                    and Co. of Hassendean-burn. Sang says, “many have ventured to assert, that it is
                    merely a play on the vanity of possessing new sorts, and that it is not really
                    distinct from those formerly cultivated.” Pontey says, he measured, in December,
                    1813, “a tree growing in the garden of Richard Atkinson, of Huddersfield, which
                    has been planted twenty-five years, being then about six feet high; the height is
                    now about sixty feet, and contains forty-six feet of good timber. It grows on the
                    side of a garden where the soil is light, and about a foot deep, upon a very coarse
                    gravel, having been formerly a water-course.”
                    
                    We could never find any poplar in general cultivation, or wild, in Italy, but the
                    Lombardy and alba, and occasionally in elevated moist places in the Alps and
                    Appenines, the tremula.
                    
                    1945. The Black Athenian, P. græca; Black American or Birch-leaved, P. betulifolia;
                    the Canadian, P. monilifera; and Carolina Poplars, P. angulata; are all rapid growing
                    lofty trees, which, in favorable soils and sheltered situations, speedily produce great
                    bulk of head and timber; but the hoary and the black Italian appear the best for the
                    general purposes of the profitable planter. They are all short-lived trees; flower in
                    March and April, and ripen their seeds from a fortnight to a month afterwards.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 1146-1147)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="SNOWBERRYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Snowberry</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Gaultheria serpyllifolia</hi>, Ps.; <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium hispidulum</hi>, L.;
                    and <hi rend="italic">Chiogenes of Salisbury</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Mich. Am</hi>. i. t. 23.); <hi rend="italic">Decan. Monog</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Ericeæ</hi>, J.
                    “At Shaw-hill, near Halifax, it produced fruit abundantly, planted under a north
                    stone wall, shaded behind by high trees, in a border of sandy peat; and it succeeded
                    pretty well in nearly a similar situation at Chapel Allerton, during the eighteen years
                    of my residence at that place, often ripening its berries; but they being little esteemed,
                    I only preserved a patch of it as a rare plant. The flavor of the fruit, however, is
                    exceedingly agreeable to some persons, being strongly perfumed, like <hi rend="italic">eau de noyau</hi>, or
                    bitter almonds, and mixed with a pleasant acid. I now regret that I never tried the berries
                    baked with sugar in a tart: if gathered before they are too soft, they may, no doubt, be
                    preserved in bottles, like cranberries, and possibly prove a valuable addition to our winter-
                    fruits of that sort.” <hi rend="italic">Salisbury in Hort. Trans</hi>. vol. ii.
                    (John C. Loudon, An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, 1822, p. 839-840)
                
                SYMPHORIA RACEMOSA. SNOW-BERRY.
                <hi rend="italic">Class and Order</hi>.
                PENTANDRIA MONOGYNIA.
                
                <hi rend="italic">Generic Character</hi>.
                <hi rend=":italic">Germen</hi> 4-loculare: loculis 2, polyspermis, sterilibus; 2 monospermis,
                    fertilibus. <hi rend=":italic">Bacca</hi> coronata. <hi rend=":italic">Cor</hi>. tubulosa, brevis, 5-fida, subæqualis.
                    <hi rend=":italic">Cal</hi>. 5-dentatus. BROWN. <hi rend=":italic">Loniceræ sp</hi>. LIN.
                
                <hi rend="italic">Specific Character and Synonyms</hi>.
                    SYMPHORIA <hi rend=":italic">racemosa</hi>; racemo interrupto subterminali, corolla intus barbata.
                    SYMPHORIA <hi rend=":italic">racemosa</hi>; racemo terminali, corolla intus barbata.
                    <hi rend=":italic">Persoon Syn</hi>. 1. <hi rend=":italic">p</hi>. 214. <hi rend=":italic">Michaux Flor. Bor. Amer</hi>. 1. <hi rend=":italic">p</hi>. 107.
                    <hi rend=":italic">Pursh Fl. Amer-sept</hi>. 1. <hi rend=":italic">p</hi>. 162. 
                    SYMPHORIA racemosa. <hi rend=":italic">Lodd. Cab</hi>. 230. <hi rend=":italic">Nuttall Gen. Pl. Amer</hi>. 1. <hi rend=":italic">p</hi>. 139.
                
                CAPRIFOLIUM, PERICLYMENUM, CHAMÆCERASUS, XYLOSTEON
                and DIERVILLA of TOURNEFORT, as well as SYMPHORICARPOS
                of DILLENIUS were united by LINNÆUS into one genus,
                under the name of LONICERA. Later botanists, however,
                seem generally to concur in restoring the three last
                to the rank of distinct genera.
                
                Our present plant belongs to DILLENIUS's genus Symphoricarpos,
                changed by PERSOON to SYMPHORIA; a genus established from
                SYMPHORIA <hi rend=":italic">conglomerata</hi>, the LONICERA <hi rend=":italic">Symphoricarpos</hi> of LINNÆUS.
                
                SYMPHORIA <hi rend=":italic">racemosa</hi> was first mentioned by MICHAUX,
                and a figure of it has been lately published by Messrs.
                LODDIGES and SONS in their Botanical Cabinet, where it
                is stated, that they first received it in the spring of
                1818, from Mr. ROBERT CARR.
                
                DESCR. A low bushy shrub; bark of the branches brightish
                brown. <hi rend=":italic">Leaves</hi> opposite, round-ovate with a mucro, mostly
                quite entire, but on the lower part of the shrub sometimes
                irregularly notched, smooth, glaucous. <hi rend=":italic">Flowers</hi> grow on the
                slender, terminal branches in pairs, at first distant, but
                toward the extremities crowded together, supported on very
                short pedicles; sometimes the branch becomes leafy beyond
                the flowers. <hi rend=":italic">Calyx</hi> superior 5-toothed, as it often, if not
                    generally, is in S. <hi rend=":italic">conglomerata</hi>, though described to be
                    4-toothed. <hi rend=":italic">Corolla</hi> rose-coloured, campanulate; <hi rend=":italic">limb</hi> 5-cleft,
                    obtuse: faux filled with hairs, below which the <hi rend=":italic">tube</hi> abounds
                    with honey. <hi rend=":italic">Stamens</hi> 5, inserted at the upper part of the
                tube, shorter than the corolla with the laciniæ of which they
                alternate. <hi rend=":italic">Germen</hi> ovate, with two or three small bractes
                applied close to its base. Mr. BROWN has observed that it is
                four-celled, 2 of the cells bearing each several ovula, but
                which are always abortive; the other two have each a single
                seed, which alone come to maturity. An analogous
                circumstance takes place, he observes, also in the fruit of
                LINNÆA, and of ABELIA, two nearly related genera belonging to
                the same family, the <hi rend=":italic">caprifoliaceæ</hi>; in both which the germen
                is 3-celled, two of the cells having several imperfect ovula,
                and the other a single ovulum, which alone comes to maturity.*
                
                The mature berry of SYMPHORIA <hi rend=":italic">racemosa</hi> appears to be
                only 2-celled, the expansion of the fertile cells
                obliterating the others. Each cell contains a kidney-
                shaped seed, much smaller than the cavity containing it.
                
                Native of Upper Canada, and the banks of the Missouri.
                Flowers in July, August and September, succeeded by
                large snow-white berries, which hang till the approach
                of winter[.] It is perfectly hardy. Communicated in July
                last by Messrs. WHITLEY, BRAME and MILNE, of the Fulham Nursery.
                
                *Vide characters and descriptions of three new species of plants, found in China, by Clarke Abel, Esq . by ROBERT BROWN, F. R. S.
                (John Sims, Curtis's botanical magazine, or, Flower-garden displayed: in which the most ornamental foreign plants, cultivated in the open ground, the green-house, and the stove, are accurately represented in their natural colours, v.48, 1821, p.2211)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="WALLFLOWERGLOSS" resp="#CGP">CHEIRANTHUS fruticulosus. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Wild Wall-flower</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">TETRADYNAMIA Siliquosa</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Germen</hi> with a glandular tooth on each
                    side. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> closed; 2 of its leaves gibbous at the
                    base. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> flat.
                    SPEC. CHAR. Leaves lanceolate, acute, hoary beneath.
                    Pubescence all simple and close-pressed. Stem
                    somewhat shrubby. Branches angular. 
                    SYN. Cheiranthus fruticulosus. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Mant</hi>. 94. <hi rend="italic">Sm.
                        Fl. Brit</hi>. 709. <hi rend="italic">Galp</hi>. 56. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 260. 
                    C. Cheiri. <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 287. <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 586. <hi rend="italic">Hull</hi>. 146.
                    <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 202. <hi rend="italic">Abbot</hi>. 144.
                    Leucojum luteum, vulgò Cheiri, flore simplici. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 291.
                    
                    ABUNDANT on the old ruined walls of cities, castles and
                    monasteries throughout Britain, where its bright golden flowers
                    are very ornamental and fragrant in April and May.
                    
                    The roots and stems are perennial and somewhat woody;
                    the branches copious, tufted, erect, leafy, angular, a little
                    hoary, each terminating in a corymbose simple cluster of
                    flowers. Leaves crowded, stalked, lanceolate, acute, for the
                    most part entire except some of the lowermost, all green except
                    a slight hoariness, chiefly beneath, caused by numerous, close-
                    pressed, simple hairs. Calyx often purplish or brown. Petals of
                    an uniform yellow, not stained with brown as in <hi rend="italic">C. Cheiri</hi>,
                    neither do they, as in that, hang loosely flaccid, but are
                    rather, as the late Mr. Crowe observed, rigid and slightly
                    recurved. Pods erect, nearly cylindrical, hoary, destitute of a
                    pair of small wings near the top noticed by Mr. J. D. Sowerby
                    in <hi rend="italic">C. Cheiri</hi>, which, if constant, greatly strengthen the
                    specific difference.
                    
                    It may be proper to mention that <hi rend="italic">C. fruticulosus</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Linn.
                        Sp. Pl. ed</hi>. 1. is <hi rend="italic">C. tristis</hi> of the 2d edition, very different
                    from the above.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. To which will be added, occasional remarks. By James Sowerby, vol. 27, 1808, p. 1934)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="LAURUSTINUSGLOSS" resp="#CGP">VIBURNUM TINUS. COMMON LAURUSTINUS.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Class and Order</hi>.
                    PENTANDRIA TRIGYNIA.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Generic Character</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> 5-partitus, superus. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. 5-fida. <hi rend="italic">Bacca</hi> 1-sperma.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Specific Character and Synonyms</hi>.
                    VIBURNUM <hi rend="italic">Tinus</hi> foliis integerrimis ovatis: ramificationibus
                    venarum subtus villoso-glandulosis. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Syst.
                    Vegetab. p</hi>. 294.
                    LAURUS sylvestris, corni fæminæ foliis subhirsutis. <hi rend="italic">Baub.
                    Pin</hi>. 461.
                    The wild Bay-tree. <hi rend="italic">Park. Parad. P</hi>. 400.
                    
                    We scarely recollect a plant whose blossoms are so hardy
                    as those of the Laurustinus, they brave the inclemency of our
                    winters, and are not destroyed but in very severe seasons.
                    
                    The beauties of this most charming shrub can be enjoyed
                    by those only who cultivate it at some little distance from
                    town, the smoke of London being highly detrimental to its growth.
                    
                    It is a native of Portugal, Spain, and Italy.
                    
                    Botanists enumerate many varieties of the Laurustinus, and,
                    so confiderably do some of these differ, that MILLER has been
                    induced to make two species of them, which he diftinguishes
                    by the names of <hi rend="italic">Viburnum Tinus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">V. lucidum</hi>; the last of
                    these is the most ornamental, and at the same time the most
                    tender; there are some other trifling varieties, besides those,
                    with variegated leaves, or the gold and silver striped.
                    
                    It is only in very favourable situations that these shrubs
                    ripen their seeds in England, hence they are most commonly
                    propagated by layers, which readily strike root: MILLER
                    says, that the plants raised from feeds are hardier than
                    those produced from layers.
                    
                    It thrives best in sheltered situations and a dry soil.
                    (William Curtis, The botanical magazine, or, Flower-garden displayed: in which the most ornamental foreign plants, cultivated in the open ground, the green-house, and the stove, are accurately represented in their natural colours, v.2, 1794, p.38)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="YELLOWALYSSUMGLOSS" resp="#CGP">ALYSSUM SAXATILE. YELLOW ALYSSUM.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Class and Order</hi>. 
                    TETRADYNAMIA SILICULOSA.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Generic Character</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Filamenta</hi> quædam introrsum denticulo notata. <hi rend="italic">Silicula</hi> emarginata.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Specific Character and Synonyms</hi>.
                    ALYSSUM <hi rend="italic">saxatile</hi> caulibus frutescentibus paniculatis, foliis
                    lanceolatis mollissimis repandis. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Syst. Veg.
                        ed</hi>. 14. <hi rend="italic">Murr. p</hi>. 590. <hi rend="italic">Ait. Hort. Kew. p</hi>. 381. 
                    ALYSSUM Creticum Saxatile, foliis undulatis incanis. <hi rend="italic">Tourn.
                    cor</hi>. 15.
                    THLASPI luteum leucoji folio. <hi rend="italic">Bocc. mus</hi>. 79. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 93.
                    
                    As this plant has very generally obtained in gardens and
                    nurseries the name of yellow Alyssum, we have retained it;
                    for though it is not the only one of the genus which produces
                    yellow flowers, it may still be called yellow by way of eminence,
                    such is the extreme brilliancy and profusion of its blossoms.
                    
                    It is a native of Crete, and was first cultivated in this
                    country by Mr. MILLER, in 1731*, at Chelsea garden.
                    
                    It begins to flower about the latter end of April, and continues
                    to blossom through great part of May; and it is not uncommon for
                    it to flower again in autumn.
                    
                    If it has a pure air and a dry situation, it will grow in almost 
                    any soil.
                    
                    The usual mode of propagating it is by slips, or cuttings. 
                    
                    As it is a small, shewy, hardy plant, and not disposed to
                    over-run others, it is very suitable to embellish rock-work.
                    
                    *<hi rend="italic">Ait. Hort. Kew</hi>.
                    (William Curtis, The botanical magazine, or, Flower-garden displayed: in which the most ornamental foreign plants, cultivated in the open ground, the green-house, and the stove, are accurately represented in their natural colours, v.5, 1792, p.159)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="SWEETWILLIAMGLOSS" resp="#CGP">DIANTHUS BARBATUS. BEARDED PINK or SWEET WILLIAM.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Class and Order</hi>.
                    DECANDRIA DIGYNIA.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Generic Character</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. cylindricus 1-phyllus: basi squamis 4. <hi rend="italic">Petala</hi> 5 unguiculata.
                    <hi rend="italic">Capsula</hi> cylindrica, 1-locularis.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Specific Character and Synonyms</hi>.
                    DIANTHUS <hi rend="italic">barbatus</hi> floribus aggregatis fasciculatis: squamis
                    calycinis ovato-subulatis tubum æquantibus, foliis lanceolatis.
                    <hi rend="italic">Linn. Syst. Vegetab. ed</hi>. 14. <hi rend="italic">Murr. p</hi>. 17. <hi rend="italic">Ait. Kew. v</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">p</hi>. 88. 
                    CARYOPHYLLUS hortensis barbatus latifolius. <hi rend="italic">Bauh. Pin</hi>. 208.
                    ARMERIUS latifolius simplex. Single Sweete Williams.
                    <hi rend="italic">Park. Parad. p</hi>. 321.
                    
                    LINNÆUS, in his <hi rend="italic">Spec. Pl</hi>. appears not to have known of
                    what country the Sweet William was a native, and even in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Hortus Kewensis</hi>, this circumstance is left undecided; yet
                    DODONÆUS, in his <hi rend="italic">Pemptades</hi>*, mentions its being found wild
                    in Germany, and PROF. HOFFMAN confirms this in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Germanys Flora</hi>+.
                    
                    At the time DODONÆUS wrote (1552) this plant was cultivated
                    in the Netherlands, from whence it was probably introduced
                    to this country, where it certainly is one of the oldest
                    inhabitants of our gardens.
                    
                    *In petrosis collibus et asperis, fabulosis apricisque locis, apud Germanos
                    nascitur. <hi rend="italic">Pempt. p</hi>. 177.
                    +Sponte in sylvaticis, montosis (Carn. Siles. Tubing) Germanys Fl. 1791. P. 147.
                    
                    Beautiful as are the numerous varieties of this species of
                    Dianthus, Florists have not deemed it worthy of that peculiar
                    attention which they have bestowed on its more favoured
                    relatives the Pink and Carnation, and hence it probably has
                    not arrived at that degree of improvement of which it is
                    capable; our figure is intended to represent one of the most
                    esteemed of its kind, viz. the <hi rend="italic">Painted Lady</hi> variety, which
                    has a deep rich purple eye, surrounded with a pure white,
                    having the edge of the petals slightly indented; but our
                    colours fall far short of the beauties of the original.
                    
                    Besides single flowers producing an infinite variety of
                    colours, there are several double varieties of the Sweet
                    William, some of which are observed to have more scent
                    than others.
                    
                    To possess these plants in perfection, we must renew them
                    yearly; for though the root be perennial, it is apt to decay,
                    especially if the foil in which it grows be either very moist, or
                    very dry; or if the air be not pure, the single sorts must be
                    raised from seeds , which should be saved from the choicest
                    flowers; the double sorts may be increased by cuttings,
                    pipings, or layers, in the same manner, and at the same time
                    as Pinks and Carnations; the feed should be sown early in
                    April, the feedlings transplanted into a bed in June, taking
                    advantage of a wet day and placed about six inches asunder
                    each way; in September they will be fit to transplant into the
                    flower border, where they will blossom the ensuing summer,
                    during the months of June and July, and ripen their seed in August.
                    (William Curtis, The botanical magazine, or, Flower-garden displayed: in which the most ornamental foreign plants, cultivated in the open ground, the green-house, and the stove, are accurately represented in their natural colours, v.6, 1793, p.207-208)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="TRUMPETFLOWERGLOSS" resp="#CGP">BIGNONIA CAPREOLATA. FOUR-LEAVED TRUMPET-FLOWER.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Class and Order</hi>.
                    DIDYNAMIA ANGIOSPERMIA.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Generic Character</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. 5-fidus, cyathiformis. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. fauce campanulata, 5-fida,
                    subtus ventricosa. <hi rend="italic">Siliqua</hi> 2-locularis. <hi rend="italic">Sem</hi>. membranaceoalata.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Specific Character and Synonyms</hi>. 
                    BIGNONIA <hi rend="italic">capreolata</hi>; foliis conjugatis cirrhosis: foliolis
                    cordato-lanceolatis, foliis imis simplicibus. <hi rend="italic">Hort.
                        Cliff</hi>. 317. <hi rend="italic">Sp. Pl</hi>. 870. <hi rend="italic">Willd</hi>. 3. 297. <hi rend="italic">Reich</hi>.
                    3. 157. <hi rend="italic">Hort. Kew</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">p</hi>. 347. 
                    BIGNONIA <hi rend="italic">capreolata</hi>; petiolis brevibus, cirrhosis, bifoliatis:
                    foliolis glabris, oblongo-ovalibus, basi subcordatis:
                    pedunculis axillaribus aggregatis; capsula lineari
                    plana. <hi rend="italic">Michaux Flor. Am. Bor</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">p</hi>. 25. <hi rend="italic">Mart. Mill. Dict.
                        n</hi>. 8. <hi rend="italic">quoad characterem et synonyma sed n</hi>. 9. <hi rend="italic">quoad descriptionem</hi>. 
                    BIGNONIA americana capreolis donata, siliqua breviore.
                    <hi rend="italic">Tourn. Inst</hi>. 164. <hi rend="italic">Breyn. Icon</hi>. 33. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 25. <hi rend="italic">Duham.
                        Arb</hi>. 1. <hi rend="italic">p</hi>. 104. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 40. <hi rend="italic">Catesb. Car</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 82. 
                    CLEMATIS americana siliquosa tetraphyllos. <hi rend="italic">Dod. Mem</hi>. 71.
                    <hi rend="italic">Rob. Icon</hi>. 108. <hi rend="italic">Bocc. Sicc</hi>. 31. <hi rend="italic">Raii Hist</hi>. 1329. 
                    PSEUDO-APOCYNUM americanum capreolatum. <hi rend="italic">Moris. Hist</hi>. 3. <hi rend="italic">p</hi>. 612.
                    
                    WILLDENOW enumerates fifty-four species of Bignonia,
                    and several others are contained in the Flora Peruviana, some
                    of these grow into large and lofty trees, but this, with many
                    more, is a climber; it seems however better adapted to raise
                    itself among the branches of underwood than to ascend the
                    trunks of lofty trees, for it does not put forth at its joints roots
                    capable of insinuating themselves into the bark, as BIGNONIA
                    <hi rend="italic">radicans</hi> does, but supports itself by its footstalks and tendrils,
                    which clasp round whatever plant or twig may happen to be near.
                    The flowers are produced on the axils of the petiole,
                    either singly or several together, but always on separate peduncles.
                    
                    In Miller's dictionary, by some accidental change of the
                    figure, the description of BIGNONIA <hi rend="italic">pubescens</hi> is applied to
                    this species, and Professor MARTYN, without observing the
                    blunder, has attached his additions intended for <hi rend="italic">capreolata</hi> to
                    the same article; by which means this plant is stated to come
                    from Campeachy, and to require the treatment of the bark
                    stove; whereas it is a native of North-America, from Virginia
                    to Florida, and hardy enough to bear our milder winters in
                    the open air. Flowers in June.
                    
                    Is propagated in the same manner and requires the like
                    treatment as BIGNONIA <hi rend="italic">radicans</hi>, No. 485; but, being tenderer,
                    a little more care to protect it from severe frost is necessary, or
                    it may be more safely considered as a hardy green-house shrub.
                    
                    Our drawing was taken several years ago at the Physic-Garden, at Chelsea.
                    (John Sims, Curtis's botanical magazine, or, Flower-garden displayed: in which the most ornamental foreign plants, cultivated in the open ground, the green-house, and the stove, are accurately represented in their natural colours, v.22, 1805, p.864)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="YUCCAFILAMENTOSAGLOSS" resp="#CGP">YUCCA FILAMENTOSA. THREADY ADAM'S NEEDLE.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Class and Order</hi>.
                    HEXANDRIA MONOGYNIA.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Generic Character</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. hexapetalo-partita, campanulata. <hi rend="italic">Stam</hi>. filamentis superne
                    crassioribus; antheris minimis. <hi rend="italic">Stigm</hi>. 3, sessilia. <hi rend="italic">Caps</hi>.
                    (<hi rend="italic">Bacca</hi> carnosa <hi rend="italic">Gærtn</hi>.) obtuse trigona. <hi rend="italic">Sem</hi>. plana.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Specific Character and Synonyms</hi>. 
                    YUCCA <hi rend="italic">filamentosa (acaulis)</hi> foliis oblongo-lanceolatis, marginibus
                    distanter filiferis; stigmatibus recurvato-patentibus. <hi rend="italic">G</hi>. 
                    YUCCA <hi rend="italic">filamentosa</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Syst. Vegetab. Murr</hi>. 337. <hi rend="italic">Mill. Dict</hi>. 4.
                    <hi rend="italic">Gron. Virg</hi>. 152; 58. <hi rend="italic">Trew Ehret. t</hi>. 37. <hi rend="italic">Hort. Kew</hi>. 1. 465.
                    <hi rend="italic">Willd. Sp. Pl</hi>. 2. 184. <hi rend="italic">Michaux Flor. Bor-Amer</hi>. 1. 196. 
                    YUCCA foliis filamentosis. <hi rend="italic">Moris. Hist</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">p</hi>. 419. 
                    YUCCA virginiana foliis per marginem apprime filatis.
                    <hi rend="italic">Pluk. Alm</hi>. 396.
                    
                    According to Michaux a native of the western parts of
                    Carolina and Virginia, growing on wilds near the sea-shore,
                    with a stem rising sometimes to the height of five feet.
                    An old inhabitant of our gardens, having been cultivated
                    in them as far back as 1675. Hardy. Very ornamental;
                    flowers about September or October. Is not uncommon in
                    our Nurseries; propagated by suckers. <hi rend="italic">G</hi>.
                    (John Sims, Curtis's botanical magazine, or, Flower-garden displayed: in which the most ornamental foreign plants, cultivated in the open ground, the green-house, and the stove, are accurately represented in their natural colours, v.23, 1806, p.900)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="FOXGLOVEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">DIGITÁLIS (so named from the resemblance of the
                    flower to the finger of a glove, <hi rend="italic">digitale</hi>, or from the adjective
                    <hi rend="italic">digitális</hi>, of or belonging to a finger. Parkinson says, some
                    thinking Foxglove to be a foolish name, do call them finger
                    flowers, because they are like unto the fingers of a glove, the
                    ends cut off.) Fuschs. hist. p. 892. Tourn. inst. p. 165. t. 73.
                    Lin. gen. no. 758. Schreb. gen. no. 1017. Juss. gen. p. 120.
                    ed. Usteri. p. 135. Gærtn. fruct. 1. p. 247. t. 53. Lindl.
                    dig. mon.--Campánula, Trag. kreut. 2. cap. p. 125.--Vírga
                    règia Cæsalp. pl. 348.--Gesnéria spec. Lin. hort. cliff. p. 318.
                    
                    LIN. SYST. <hi rend="italic">Didynàmia, Angiospérmia</hi>. Calyx unequal. Corolla
                    tubular at the base, funnel-shaped: limb obliquely 4-lobed:
                    upper segment much shorter than the lower one or lip, and is,
                    as well as it imbricate in æstivation. The rudiment of the fifth;
                    stamen hardly conspicuous. Stigma simple, or bilamellate.
                    Capsule ovate, acuminated.--Herbs with alternate leaves, and
                    terminal racemes of secund, bracteate, drooping flowers.
                    
                    § 1. <hi rend="italic">Corolla oblong-ventricose; upper segment transverse. 
                    Stamens shorter than the tube.</hi>
                    
                    1 D. PURPÚREA (Fuschs. hist. 892. t. 893. Lin. spec. 866.)
                    leaves oblong, rugose, crenated; calycine segments ovate-oblong;
                    segments of corolla transverse, acute; peduncles straight,
                    about equal in length to the calyxes. [symbol]. H. Native of Europe,
                    as of Denmark, Germany, Switzerland; Britain, in sandy gravelly
                    soils near London; it grows plentifully about Charlton wood,
                    Norwood, &#x0026;c. Gærtn. fruct. 1. p. 247. t. 53. Curt. fl.
                    lond. fasc. 1. t. 48. Woodv. med. bot. 71. t. 24. Oed. fl. dan.
                    t. 74. Hoffm. et Link, fl. port. p. 222. Lindl. dig. t. 2.
                    Stev. et Church, med. bot. 1. t. 18.--Blackw. t. 16.--Riv. mon.
                    t. 104.--Lob. icon. 1. p. 572. f. 1, 2—Mor. hist. sect. 5. t. 8.
                    f. 1. Plant pubescent. Corollas large, purple, marked inside
                    with dark purple spots, which are edged with white. The
                    colour, however, varies from dark purple to cream-colour and white.
                    (George Don, A general system of gardening and botany. Founded upon Miller's Gardener's dictionary, and arranged according to the natural system, vol. 4, 1838, p. 504)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="INDIANPINKGLOSS" resp="#CGP">S. MARYLÁNDICA (Lin. syst. 197. mant. 2. p. 330.)
                    herbaceous; stems simple, tetragonal, scabrous: leaves opposite,
                    sessile, oval-lanceolate, glabrous; spikes solitary; corolla
                    funnel-shaped; stamens inclosed; coccæ glabrous.? [symbol]. H.
                    Native of Virginia, Maryland, Carolina, Georgia, &#x0026;c. on the
                    edges of woods, in rich moist soil; and on the banks of the
                    Arkansas, in the forests near the first cliffs. Michx. fl. bor.
                    amer. 1. p. 148. Pursh, 1. p. 139. Curt. bot. mag. t. 80.
                    Lodd. bot. cab. 930. Stev. et Church. med. bot. 1. t. 7.
                    Plench, t. 89. Heyne, term. bot. t. 44. f. 5. Garden and Hope,
                    act. edinb. 3. 1771. p. 145-153. t. 1. Lonicéra Marylándica,
                    Lin. spec. 2. p. 249. Catesb. car. 2. t. 78. Corollas scarlet
                    outside and yellow inside. Calycine segments subulate. The
                    roots are sold under the name of <hi rend="italic">worm-grass</hi> or <hi rend="italic">pink-root</hi>, or
                    <hi rend="italic">Indian pink</hi> in the shops. This is a mucilaginous plant, with a
                    mild and not disagreeable taste. The infusion and decoction
                    of the root and leaves afford a flocculent precipitate with
                    alcohol. The plant was first used by the Cherokee Indians as an
                    anthelmintic. Drs. Lining, Garden, and Chalmers first introduced
                    it to notice; and their subsequent experience tended to confirm
                    its utility. The root possesses the greatest activity, and is
                    given in doses of from 10 grains, two or three times a day.
                    If it proves purgative it is said to be most effective; and
                    should it not, it must be combined with cathartics, which prevent
                    the narcotic symptoms, such as stupor, head-ache, dilated pupil,
                    flushings of the face, stiffness of the eyelids, that so frequently
                    follow its administration. It is said to be most useful in lumbrica;
                    and it is to its narcotic principle that Dr. Good attributes its
                    vermifuge powers, which it possesses in common with <hi rend="italic">Spigélia
                    anthélmia</hi>. Notwithstanding all that has been said in its favour,
                    its real anthelmintic properties are somewhat equivocal. The
                    plant is called <hi rend="italic">Unsteetla</hi> by the Cherokee Indians.
                    (George Don, A general system of gardening and botany. Founded upon Miller's Gardener's dictionary, and arranged according to the natural system, vol. 4, 1838, p. 171)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PROVENCEROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The common Provence Rose is well known in
                    the English gardens, and is one of the most beautiful
                    sorts yet known. The flowers are sometimes very
                    large, and the petals closely folded over each other,
                    like Cabbages, whence this variety is called the 
                    Cabbage Rose. The flowers of the Provence Roe have
                    the most fragrant odour of all the sorts.
                    
                    [The great double Damask Province or Holland
                    Rose, hath his bark, says Parkinson, of a reddish or
                    brown colour. The leaves are likewise more reddish
                    than in others, and somewhat larger. It usually groweth
                    very like the Damask Rose, and much to the same
                    height. The flowers are of the same deep blush colour,
                    or rather somewhat deeper, but much thicker, broader,
                    and more double by three parts almost, the outer
                    leaves turning back, when the flower hath stood long
                    blown, the middle part itself being folded hard with
                    small leaves. The scent cometh nearest unto the
                    Damask Rose, but yet is short of it by much.
                    
                    β. The stem and branches of the Red Provence Rose
                    are not so great as those of the other, but
                    greener, the bark being not so red. The flowers are
                    not so large, thick and double, but of a little deeper
                    damask or blush colour, turning to red, but not coming
                    near the full colour of the best red Rose: nor is the
                    scent so sweet as that of the damask Provence, but
                    coming near that of the ordinary red Rose. This is
                    not so plentiful in bearing as the Damask Provence*.]
                    
                    γ. The stalks of the Blush Provence Rose rise from
                    three to four feet high, and are unarmed: the leaves
                    are hairy on their under side: the peduncles have
                    some small spines: the segments of the calyx are semi-
                    pinnate: the corolla has five or six rows of petals,
                    which are large, and spread open; they are of a pale
                    blush colour, and have a musky scent.
                    
                    [δ. The White Provence Rose differs only in the
                    colour of the flowers.
                    
                    [...]
                    
                    *Smith
                    (Philip Miller, The Gardener’s and Botanist’s Dictionary; Containing the Best and Newest Methods of Cultivating and Improving the Kitchen, Fruit, and Flower Garden, and Nursery [...], vol.2, pt.2, 1807</note>
                
                <note xml:id="BLUEBELLGLOSS" resp="#CGP">Whether Ruskin is referring to the English bluebell or the Scotish bluebell (harebell) is unclear.
                    
                    The common English BLUEBELL is one of the most spectacular
                    botanical sights of the British Isles. Thousands carpet the woods in
                    April and May, and they are common sight from Kent and Sussex
                    in the southeast to the western Highlands of Scotland and the west
                    coast of Ireland. The nodding flowers produce a blue haze which
                    intensifies as it approaches eye level. BLUEBELLS are found on most
                    types of soil, from acid or limy clay to sand or chalk, in woods in
                    the south and centre of the country, but commonly in the open
                    along the western coasts, where summer cover may be provided by
                    BRACKEN.
                    Linnaeus (1753) described the BLUEBELL as <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus non-scriptus</hi>,
                    distinguishing it from the classical HYACINTH, whose petals were said
                    to be marked with letters. <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus</hi>, in Greek, ‘Υάκινθος a youth
                    from Laconia, the area around Sparta, was loved by Apollo, who
                    killed him with a careless throw of a discus; some say that the discus
                    was blown off course by Zephyr, out of jealousy. The name was
                    transferred to a flower, said to have sprung up from his blood, on
                    which were written the letters Al, or AIAI, a cry of woe Liddel &#x0026;
                    Scott, 1888). One of the most likely flowers to qualify for this is
                    the wild <hi rend="italic">Gladiolus</hi> whose lower three perianth segments have clear
                    markings (Stearn, 1993). The colour described for ‘Υάκινθος was
                    almost black, deep purple or crimson, and was used by Homer to
                    describe dark hair. In spite of this, by the 17th century, the name
                    <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus</hi> had become attached to the scented <hi rend="italic">H. orientalis</hi> L. as
                    well as to the BLUEBELL, which was called <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus anglicus, e.g.</hi> by
                    Besler in <hi rend="italic">Hortus Eystettensis</hi> (1613).
                    BLUEBELLS have also been placed in the genera <hi rend="italic">Scilla</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Endymion</hi>,
                    <hi rend="italic">Agraphis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthoides</hi>, the last three specially coined for <hi rend="italic">H. non-
                        scripta</hi> and its relatives. <hi rend="italic">Scilla</hi> was widely used in the 19th century,
                    particularly by Philip Miller in the <hi rend="italic">Gardener's Dictionary</hi>, and by the
                    influential Bentham and Hooker's <hi rend="italic">British Flora</hi> (1886) and again in
                    the recent <hi rend="italic">Flora Helvetica</hi> (Lauber &#x0026; Wagner, 1996); cultivated
                    bluebells are still sold (even in the Kew shop!) under the name <hi rend="italic">Scilla
                        campanulata</hi> Aiton. With <hi rend="italic">Endymion</hi>, in 1827, Dumortier continued
                    the classical theme, Endymion being a beautiful youth who was
                    loved by Diana, and with <hi rend="italic">Agraphis</hi>, in 1829, Link continued the <hi rend="italic">non-
                    scripta</hi> idea. Unfortunately Medicus had already published the
                    name <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthoides</hi> in 1791 and as this has priority, it is now
                    generally used.
                    Morphologically <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthoides</hi> differs from <hi rend="italic">Scilla</hi> in having paired,
                    not solitary, bracts and bulbs in which the scales are very thick at
                    the base, forming a tube and renewed each year. In <hi rend="italic">Scilla</hi> the bulb
                    structure is varied, but most species have several thin scales which
                    last several years (see Appendix).
                    <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthoides</hi> contains five species, of which three, <hi rend="italic">H. non-scripta</hi>,
                    <hi rend="italic">H. hispanica</hi> (Miller) Rothm. and <hi rend="italic">H. italica</hi> (L.) Rothm. are found in
                    most floras. In <hi rend="italic">H. italica</hi>, which is found in the Basses Alpes and the
                    Alpes Maritimes, the leaves are narrow and the flowers starry with
                    segments only 5-7 mm long. In southwest Portugal there occurs a
                    variety of <hi rend="italic">H. italica</hi>, sometimes considered a distinct species, <hi rend="italic">H. vicentina</hi>
                    (Hoffmans. &#x0026; Link) Rothm., which is smaller, with fewer flowers;
                    these two species are closest to <hi rend="italic">Scilla</hi>. Another species, <hi rend="italic">H. reverchonii</hi>
                    (Degen &#x0026; Hervier) F. Speta, from the Sierra de Cazorla in Spain, is
                    also close to <hi rend="italic">H. italica</hi> but has long leaves almost equalling the
                    scape, and a lax raceme, the flowers with erect, deep blue perianth
                    segments (Heywood, 1980). Brian Mathew (pers. comm.), from his
                    experience of growing both species, considers this to be distinct.
                    <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthoides hispanica</hi> is found in Spain, Portugal and North
                    Africa, and has open bell-shaped flowers, in which the segments do
                    not curl back; the flowers also hang down all round the stem, not
                    all to one side as do those of common BLUEBELLS. All six stamens are
                    nearly equal, with blue anthers, whereas in <hi rend="italic">H. non-scripta</hi> three of
                    the stamens are longer and the anthers are white. In the wild <hi rend="italic">H.
                    hispanica</hi> is a delicate plant, found in limestone pavements and open
                    woods, very different from the robust cultivated plants often called
                    SPANISH BLUEBELLS. These cultivated bluebells are robust and fertile,
                    and are probably of hybrid origin (Mathew pers. comm.). In gardens and 
                    woods adjacent to gardens, they hybridise with
                    wild <hi rend="italic">H. non-scripta</hi>, and these complex hybrids have been called
                    <hi rend="italic">H.</hi> × <hi rend="italic">massartiana</hi> Geerinck (1996), which just has priority (Leslie
                    pers. comm.) over <hi rend="italic">H.</hi> × <hi rend="italic">variabilis</hi> P.D. Sell (1996). There has been
                    some concern that the hybrids may invade the gene pool of
                    the native BLUEBELL; in many places they are aggressive weeds,
                    increasing both by division of the bulbs and by seed. 
                    The differences between <hi rend="italic">H. non-scripta</hi>, <hi rend="italic">H. hispanica</hi> and their
                    hybrids were studied by Baker (1872) and Turrill (1952), as reported
                    and extended more recently by Bond (1976). Bond compared the
                    length of the perianth segment and the extent of attachment of the
                    filament in various samples, including both wild and cultivated
                    <hi rend="italic">H. hispanica</hi>. He summarised his conclusions as follows:
                    <hi rend="italic">H. non-scripta</hi>: filaments distinctly unequal, the inner barely 3/4
                    the outer; the outer inserted just above the middle of the perianth,
                    adnate to it for more than 3/4 of their length.
                    <hi rend="italic">H. hispanica</hi>: filaments subequal, the inner at least 4/5 the outer,
                    the outer inserted below the middle of the perianth, adnate to it for
                    less than 3/4 of their length. His diagrams bear out the supposition
                    that most of the SPANISH BLUEBELLS in cultivation are hybrids.
                    <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthoides non-scripta</hi> is native only in western continental
                    Europe, particularly along the Atlantic from Belgium, Holland and
                    western France to Spain and Portugal. It does not extend much
                    west of Paris, or into eastern Spain. Where it is native it can be
                    invasive and is easily raised from seed, providing that the soil is
                    slightly acid and free from drying out completely in summer. The
                    finest bluebell woods are usually on sandy clays such as greensand,
                    on sandy loam over chalk or on boulder clay. Regular coppicing
                    keeps the populations healthy, as there is a slow decline in
                    flowering as shade increases. Because the bulbs have no tunics,
                    they are less tolerant of summer heat and drought than most
                    species of <hi rend="italic">Scilla</hi> from further east. The tubular hanging flowers are
                    sweetly scented, and generally pollinated by long-tongued bumble
                    bees and hover-flies (Proctor &#x0026; Yeo, 1973). The flowers are self-
                    fertile, but seed set is higher when the flowers are outcrossed
                    (Wilson, 1959). An experiment carried out at Kew found careful
                    picking of the flowers to be harmless, but trampling of the leaves
                    soon weakened the plants (Peace &#x0026; Gilmour, 1949).
                    CULTIVATION. BLUEBELLS are easily grown in moist leafy soil in
                    partial shade. The bulbs are best planted between the end of the
                    flowering season and the beginning of autumnal root growth, that
                    is in July and August. In woodland gardens even wild BLUEBELLS
                    may become weeds, seeding themselves freely, the young bulbs
                    pulling themselves downwards as they become older and therefore
                    difficult to eradicate. New populations may be established from
                    fresh seed broadcast in suitable locations, the first flowers
                    appearing in 4 or 5 years. There are two interesting ethical
                    questions surrounding BLUEBELL cultivation. On the one hand
                    cultivated BLUEBELLS, <hi rend="italic">H.</hi> × <hi rend="italic">massartiana</hi>, should be planted only
                    where they are unable to pollute native stocks, while at the same
                    time it is considered wrong to plant bulbs of <hi rend="italic">H. non-scripta</hi> which
                    have been dug from the wild, however common they may be.
                    Some bulb companies sell wild BLUEBELLS grown from seed, and
                    these would seem preferable for use in gardens which are near wild
                    populations; they also have the scent and elegance of habit absent
                    from the cultivated stocks.
                    <hi rend="bold">Hyacinthoides non-scripta</hi> (L.) Chouard ex Rothm., Feddes Repert. 53:
                    14 (1944).
                    <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus non-scriptus</hi> L., Sp. PI. 316(1753).
                    <hi rend="italic">Scilla non-scripta</hi> (L.) Hoffms. &#x0026; Link in Ges. Naturf. Fr. Neue Schrifr.4: 19
                    (1803).
                    <hi rend="italic">Endymion non-scriptus</hi> (L.) Garcke, Fl. Deutschl. ed. 1: 322 (1895).
                    DESCRIPTION. <hi rend="italic">Bulbous perennial</hi>, bulbs without tunics, ovoid, 1-2 cm
                    diameter, of 2-4 concentric scales, fused and thickened in the lower half
                    to form a solid tube. <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi> 4-6, basal, linear, glabrous, 20-45 cm long,
                    0.7-1.5 cm wide. <hi rend="italic">Scape</hi> terete, solid, 15-50 cm tall; inflorescence a lax spike-
                    like, one-sided raceme, nodding at the tip at flowering. <hi rend="italic">Floral bracts</hi> paired,
                    linear-lanccolate, bluish, <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 5 mm long, the lower usually exceeding the
                    pedicels, the upper shorter. <hi rend="italic">Pedicels</hi> curved downwards, <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 5 mm long at
                    anthesis, becoming erect and up to 3 cm long in fruit. Flowers 4-16, bluish,
                    rarely white; perianth segments 6, linear, forming a tube, recurved at the tips
                    1.3-2 cm long, <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 4 mm wide. <hi rend="italic">Stamens</hi> of 2 lengths; filaments flattened,
                    bluish, attached at base of and adnate to the perianth segments: the 3 outer
                    adnate for more than 3/4 of their length, reaching the mouth of the tube, the
                    3 inner shorter, adnate only at the base, the anther opposite the stigma;
                    anthers creamy-white, dorsifixed, versatile. <hi rend="italic">Ovary</hi> superior, green, 3-locular.
                    <hi rend="italic">Style</hi> 1, 4-5 mm; stigma capitate. <hi rend="italic">Fruit</hi> an ovoid or broadly obcordate, 3-
                    lobed capsule <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1.5 cm long; seeds shining black.
                    DISTRIBUTION. Western Europe, from Scotland and Belgium, south to
                    Spain and Portugal.
                    HABITAT. In deciduous woods, meadows or beneath <hi rend="italic">Pteridium aquilinum</hi> on
                    moorland.
                    FLOWERING TIME. Spring and early summer (April-June in Britain);
                    fruiting mid to late summer.
                    (Martyn Rix. “481. HYACINTHOIDES NON-SCRIPTA: Hyacinthaceae.” Curtis’s Botanical Magazine, vol. 21, no. 1, 2004, p. 20–23.)
                    
                    Harebell, Bluebell (esp. Scotland), Bellflower. Campanulaceae.
                    <hi rend="italic">Campanula rotundifolia</hi> L. is a slender, rhizomatous perennial
                    herb with a creeping, slender, elongated and much branched
                    rootstock which produces adventitious buds. A white tap root
                    is also occasionally present. All plant parts exude latex when
                    broken. Stems slender and wiry, shortly creeping, then ascending
                    to 15–60 cm, though prostrate, erect and lax forms also
                    occur. Stems glabrous to sparsely pubescent, but all British
                    plants are at least somewhat pilose, with short stiff white hairs
                    which are most obvious on the lower part of the stem.
                    
                    Basal and cauline leaves differ in morphology. Basal leaves
                    cordate and reniform, sometimes crenate, <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1 cm wide (total
                    area 1–10 cm2<!--how to tag exponent?-->) with long slender petioles. Sessile linear leaves
                    on ground-hugging creeping stems. Cauline leaves on flowering
                    stems, progressively narrower and more distant and stalkless
                    upwards towards the flowers, spathulate to lanceolate,
                    variable in number. Secondary veins slightly raised on leaf
                    adaxial surfaces, leafmargins with hydathodes.
                    
                    Inflorescence paniculate or racemose, with 1 – many flowers,
                    very slender pedicels, sometimes stout. Corolla bell-shaped
                    (varying from campanulate with a hemispherical base and
                    ovary to conical with a conical ovary) with five lobes, rarely
                    four, six or seven, 12–30(35) mm long, erect in bud, nodding
                    when open. Usually blue, but varying in colour from white
                    (rarely) through all shades of pale blue to deep blue and, in
                    non-British material, violet blue, sometimes weathering to pale
                    pink. Stamens 5, anthers cream, with cream to deep mauve
                    pollen; style 1, stigmas 3. Flower size and number is sometimes
                    used as a taxonomic character in the subsection Heterophylla
                    and as a guide to polyploid level in <hi rend="italic">C. rotundifolia</hi> s.s. and
                    <hi rend="italic">C. gieseckiana</hi>. However, although there may be differences,
                    flower size and number vary enormously with environmental
                    conditions.
                    
                    [...]
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi> L. is the largest genus of the Campanulaceae.
                    The British Isles are comparatively poor in <hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi> species,
                    with 17 species recorded (Stace 2010), compared with 144 in
                    Europe (Tutin <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1976) and about 85 species in Croatia, the
                    circum-Adriatic and west Balkan regions (Kovačić 2004).
                    Within the Britain Isles, <hi rend="italic">C. rotundifolia</hi> is readily distinguished
                    by its morphology from other native <hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi> species. The
                    classification of <hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi> taxa is the subject of ongoing
                    debate, and is largely unresolved (e.g. Eddie <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2003;
                    Shulkina, Gaskin &#x0026; Eddie 2003; Kovačić 2004; Roquet <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>
                    2008). Within this genus, the taxonomy and delimitation of
                    <hi rend="italic">C. rotundifolia</hi> is also difficult as it is an extremely variable
                    species, forming a complex polyploid series. Indeed, Hultén
                    (1971) described this as ‘An extremely complicated complex,
                    where different authors rarely arrive at the same conclusions
                    …’.Many variants have been described as distinct species and
                    there is a considerable number of subspecies.Much of the variation
                    is continuous and the taxonomic issues are not settled
                    (e.g. Kovanda 1970, 1977; Tutin <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1976; Kovačić &#x0026; Nikolic
                    2006). In addition to the recent distinction of two subspecies
                    in the British Isles already mentioned, particular difficulties
                    arise in distinguishing <hi rend="italic">C. rotundifolia</hi> from the very similar
                    <hi rend="italic">C. gieseckiana</hi> (Greenland, Iceland,N.Norway), <hi rend="italic">C. intercedens</hi>
                    Witas. (N. America), <hi rend="italic">C. latisepala</hi> Hultén (W. N. America)
                    and, perhaps especially, the contiguous <hi rend="italic">C. langsdorffiana</hi>
                    Fisch. (Siberia). In Europe, as infraspecific taxa, Flora Europaea
                    lists montane subsp. <hi rend="italic">polymorpha</hi> (Witasek) Tacik, subsp.
                    <hi rend="italic">sudetica</hi> (Hruby) Soó and var. <hi rend="italic">alpicola</hi> Hayek, which are tetraploid,
                    as is the morphologically similar <hi rend="italic">C. groenlandica</hi> Berlin.
                    However, in North America, Shetler’s (1982) survey of the
                    Nearctic harebells concluded that they all belonged to one species,
                    <hi rend="italic">C. rotundifolia</hi> L. The extent of confusion is exemplified by
                    a study of floralmorphometrics by Kovačić &#x0026; Nikolic (2006) of
                    western Balkan lineages of endemic <hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi> L. which concluded
                    that ‘the heterophyllous taxa cannot be successfully separated
                    only on the basis of their floral variables, while they are
                    often so polymorphous and variable that they cannot be recognised
                    even on the basis of entire plant morphology.’
                    
                    The current taxonomic difficulties are clearly associated
                    with evolutionary processes and further work is needed to gain
                    a fuller understanding of the taxonomic divisions indicated
                    above. In this work, we rely on the original naming by authors
                    of their species, and on their determinations of the ploidy of
                    their material. Within the British Isles, the cytotype of studied
                    material is rarely defined, but if the location of the experimental
                    study is known, it may often be deduced.
                    <hi rend="italic">Campanula rotundifolia</hi> is found in a range of acidic to calcareous
                    grasslands, heathlands, mires and dunes, as well as on
                    maritime cliffs and in woodland. It is widespread and locally
                    common but there is some evidence for recent decline in abundance
                    and range.
                    
                    [...]
                    
                    Within the British Isles, the first published record is Gerarde’s
                    (1597) well illustrated account of <hi rend="italic">Campanula rotundifolia</hi>,
                    which is described as growing ‘wilde in most places of
                    England, especially upon barren sandie heathes, and such
                    like grounds’.
                    
                    Fossil <hi rend="italic">C. rotundifolia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi>-type seed and pollen
                    occur in the palynological record, though they are never abundant.
                    Fossil <hi rend="italic">C. rotundifolia</hi> seed has been found in deposits
                    dated to <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 29 000–33 500 BP in Sourlie, western Scotland (Bos
                    <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2004), 37 400 years BP in Leicestershire (Bell <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1972)
                    and 42 000 BP in Worcestershire (Coope <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1961).
                    Although not identifiable to species, <hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi>-type pollen
                    occurs in post glacial deposits (Late Devensian) in Britain, primarily
                    in association with species-rich grassland communities.
                    For instance, in Scotland, pollen has been found in samples
                    dated to 11 115 years BP from the Abernethy Forest, Inverness-
                    shire (Birks &#x0026; Mathewes 1978), from 11 355 and before
                    10 200 BP from Fife (Whittington, Edwards &#x0026; Caseldine
                    1991; Whittington, Edwards &#x0026; Hall 2001). Ince (1983)
                    recorded <hi rend="italic">C. rotundifolia</hi> in cores collected in North Wales
                    (Llyn Llydaw and Cwm Cywion), dated to about 10 000 BP
                    andWhittington, Edwards &#x0026; Hall (2001) report a single grain
                    of <hi rend="italic">Campanula</hi>-type pollen from the Isle of Lewis in strata
                    between 9250 and 10 250 BP.
                    (C.J. Stevens, J. Wilson, and H.A. McCallister, "Biological Flora of the British Isles: Campanula rotundifolia." Journal of Ecology, vol. 100, 2012, p. 821-839)
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>