<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_glosses">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#GMS">Gabriella M. Smith</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE1GLOSS" resp="#DCH">It hangs down its head as if dazzled</note><!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#SOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->

                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE2GLOSS" resp="#DCH">Young January from being the first of the months</note><!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#ALSOSOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->

                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE3GLOSS" resp="#DCH">ken sight</note>
                
                <note xml:id="ROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Rose. Rosa, L .; Icos. Polyg. L.; and Rosacea, J. Rosier, Fr.;
                    Rosenstock , Ger.; and Rosajo, Ital.
                    1683. The rose is known by every body at first sight, and has been a favorite flower
                    from time immemorial among the civilized nations of Europe and Asia. The shrub
                    varies in size in different species , from one foot to six or eight, and the colors are red,
                    white, yellow, purple, black, striped; simple, or in almost numberless shades and mix-
                    tures; and single , semi-double, and double. It is cultivated in every garden, from that
                    of the most humble cottager upwards; some species as R. centifolia damascena, &#x0026;c. are
                    also cultivated by commercial gardeners on a large scale for distilling rose-water, and for making attar, or essential oil of roses. Six pounds of rose leaves will impregnate by dis-tillation a gallon of water strongly with their odour; but a hundred pounds afford scarcely half an ounce of attar. The rose is also used in medicine.
                    Botanists are not agreed as to the number of original species of this genus , some regard all the European species as originated from one source; others, and especially the moderns, divide them into species, sub-species, and varieties. The most scientific work which has appeared on the roses in England, is the "Rosarum Monographia" of J. Lindley, 1819, in which above a hundred species or sub-species are described, and some of them figured; and Miss Laurence has published ninety plates of "A Collection of Roses from Nature," 1810. In France, Guillemeau has published "His-toire Naturelle de la Rose," 1800; and P. J. Redouté and C. A. Thory are engaged in a splendid work, in folio, entitled "Les Roses," containing plates of all the known species and varieties of this flower. C. A. Thory has published a separate tract on their culture, entitled "Prodrome de la Monographie du Genre Rosier, &c." 1820; M. A. Pronville, a "Nomenclature Raisonée," in 1818; and J. P. Vibert, Observations, &c. in 1820. A copious and intelligent account of the Scotch roses has been lately given by J. Sabine (Hort. Trans. iv. 231.), and some hundreds of new varieties have flowered from seedling plants, in the nursery of J. Lee, during the present year, and will be found in his cata-logue for 1822.
                    Species and Varieties. The lists of the London and Paris nurserymen contain up-wards of 350 names. The greater part of these have been raised from seed on the continent, where it ripens better than in this country, within the last thirty years. A number of varieties have also been raised in this country, especially of the R. spinosissima, or Scotch rose, of which twenty-six sorts are enumerated by J. Sabine, as having been raised within the last twenty years. New varieties are raised in France and Italy annually; L. Villaresi , royal gardener at Monza has raised upwards of fifty varieties of Rosa indica; not one of which have, as far as we know, reached this country. Some of them are quite black, others shaped like a ranunculus, and many of them highly odoriferous.</note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>