<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_glosses">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#GMS">Gabriella M. Smith</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE1GLOSS" resp="#DCH">It hangs down its head as if dazzled</note><!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#SOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->

                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE2GLOSS" resp="#DCH">Young January from being the first of the months</note><!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#ALSOSOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->

                <note xml:id="RUSKINSNOTE3GLOSS" resp="#DCH">ken sight</note>
                
                <note xml:id="ROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Rose</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Rosa</hi>, L .; <hi rend="italic">Icos. Polyg.</hi> L.; and <hi rend="italic">Rosacea</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Rosier</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Rosenstock</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Rosajo</hi>, Ital.
                    1683. The rose is known by every body at first sight, and has been a favorite flower
                    from time immemorial among the civilized nations of Europe and Asia. The shrub
                    varies in size in different species , from one foot to six or eight, and the colors are red,
                    white, yellow, purple, black, striped; simple, or in almost numberless shades and mix-
                    tures; and single , semi-double, and double. It is cultivated in every garden, from that
                    of the most humble cottager upwards; some species as <hi rend="italic">R. centifolia damascena</hi>, &#x0026;c. are
                    also cultivated by commercial gardeners on a large scale for distilling rose-water, and for
                    making <hi rend="italic">attar</hi>, or essential oil of roses. Six pounds of rose leaves will impregnate by dis-
                    tillation a gallon of water strongly with their odour; but a hundred pounds afford
                    scarcely half an ounce of <hi rend="italic">attar</hi>. The rose is also used in medicine.
                    Botanists are not agreed as to the number of original species of this genus, some
                    regard all the European species as originated from one source; others, and especially
                    the moderns, divide them into species, sub-species, and varieties. The most scientific
                    work which has appeared on the roses in England, is the "<hi rend="italic">Rosarum Monographia</hi>"
                    of J. Lindley, 1819, in which above a hundred species or sub-species are described,
                    and some of them figured; and Miss Laurence has published ninety plates of "A
                    Collection of Roses from Nature," 1810. In France, Guillemeau has published "<hi rend="italic">His-
                    toire Naturelle de la Rose</hi>," 1800; and P. J. Redouté and C. A. Thory are engaged in
                    a splendid work, in folio, entitled "<hi rend="italic">Les Roses</hi>," containing plates of all the known species
                    and varieties of this flower. C. A. Thory has published a separate tract on their culture,
                    entitled "<hi rend="italic">Prodrome de la Monographie du Genre Rosier, &#x0026;c.</hi>" 1820; M. A. Pronville,
                    a "<hi rend="italic">Nomenclature Raisonée</hi>," in 1818; and J. P. Vibert, <hi rend="italic">Observations, &#x0026;c.</hi> in 1820.
                    A copious and intelligent account of the Scotch roses has been lately given by J. Sabine
                    (<hi rend="italic">Hort. Trans</hi>. iv. 231.), and some hundreds of new varieties have flowered from seedling
                    plants, in the nursery of J. Lee, during the present year, and will be found in his cata-
                    logue for 1822.
                    <hi rend="italic">Species and Varieties</hi>. The lists of the London and Paris nurserymen contain up-
                    wards of 350 names. The greater part of these have been raised from seed on the
                    continent, where it ripens better than in this country, within the last thirty years. A
                    number of varieties have also been raised in this country, especially of the <hi rend="italic">R. spinosissima</hi>,
                    or Scotch rose, of which twenty-six sorts are enumerated by J. Sabine, as having been
                    raised within the last twenty years. New varieties are raised in France and Italy
                    annually; L. Villaresi , royal gardener at Monza has raised upwards of fifty varieties
                    of <hi rend="italic">Rosa indica</hi>; not one of which have, as far as we know, reached this country. Some
                    of them are quite black, others shaped like a ranunculus, and many of them highly
                    odoriferous.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 1015-1016)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="LILYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Lily</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Lilium</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Hexan. Monog</hi>. L .; and <hi rend="italic">Liliæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Lis</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Lilie</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Giglio</hi>, Ital.
                    1635. Of this genus there are sixteen species introduced in Britain, and the whole of
                    them may be reckoned very choice flowers. We shall notice particularly, only those
                    species, of which numerous varieties have been produced. These are:
                    The <hi rend="italic">White Lily, L. Candidum</hi>  (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag.</hi> 278.), has a large scaly bulb, a
                    leafy stem, from three to four feet in height, terminating in large pure white
                    flowers on peduncles. It is a native of the Levant , and was in most gar-
                    dens in Gerarde’s time. Of this species, there are above eight varieties.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Orange Lily, L. bulbiferum</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bot. May</hi>.[sic] 36), has a scaly bulb, a leafy
                    stem, two feet and a half high, terminating in orange-colored flowers.
                    Sometimes the stem produces small green bulbs in the axillae of the leaves. Of this species, there are eight or ten varieties and sub-varieties. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">Martagon</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Turk's Cap, L. Martagon</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 893.), has a large 
                    scaly bulb, a stalk furnished with narrow leaves, near three feet high, and
                    terminating peduncles of fine carmine flowers in July. Of this species there
                    are half a dozen varieties, besides the scarlet martagon (<hi rend="italic">L. Chalcedonicum</hi>),
                    of which there are also different sorts. 
                    Besides the above species and their varieties, there are the <hi rend="italic">L. Canadense</hi>,
                    <hi rend="italic">superbum</hi>, or Turk's cap; the <hi rend="italic">Pomponium</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Tigrinum</hi>, or Tiger Lily; all
                    equally meriting cultivation as select flowers.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 959)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="DAHLIAGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Dahlia</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Dahlia superflua</hi> and <hi rend="italic">D. frustranea</hi>, H. K. (<hi rend="italic">Cav. Ic</hi>. i.
                    t. 80. and 266.); <hi rend="italic">Polyg. Super</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Corymbiferæ</hi>, J.
                    1640. The roots are tuberous and fasciculated; the stems rise from five to eight feet,
                    covered with large compound leaves, resembling those of the common dwarf elder, and 
                    with side branches bearing numerous flowers of a great variety of colors, which appear
                    in August, and continue till destroyed by frost. The plant grows wild in Mexico, in
                    sandy meadows, and was sent to Madrid in 1789, and thence to England in the same 
                    year; but the plants being lost, seeds were reintroduced by Lady Holland in 1804, and
                    from these and some plants imported from France during the peace of 1814, the present 
                    extensive stock of dahlias has originated. Till this last period they were much more 
                    cultivated in France and Germany than in England, and more especially by the Count 
                    Lebeur, at Paris, and M. Otto, at Berlin. At present the dahlia is the most fashion-
                    able flower in this country, and the extent of its culture in some of the nurseries, espe-
                    cially that of J. Lee, is truly astonishing. Nor is this to be wondered at, as Sabine
                    observes, for, independently of the great beauty and diversity of the flowers, they are in
                    perfection at a season when, till they came into notice, our gardens had but little orna-
                    ment. The roots are edible, but not agreeable.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. The leading varieties of the fertile-rayed species <hi rend="italic">D. superflua</hi>, are,
                    the purple, rose, pale, white, sulphur, yellow, tawny, copper, brick red,
                    dark-red, pomegranate colored , dark purple, very dark, and lilac flowered 
                    single, semi-double, and double, with innumerable sub-varieties.
                    Of the barren.rayed species, <hi rend="italic">D. frustranea</hi>, there are the scarlet, bright-scarlet,
                    orange, saffron, and yellow flowered, single, semi-double, and double, with
                    several sub-varieties, though this species has not sported nearly so much as the other.
                    At the Hammersmith nursery, above 200 sorts may be procured.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 962)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PRIMROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Primrose, P. vulgaris</hi>, L. (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 4.); <hi rend="italic">Primavere</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Shaftlose Primule</hi>, Ger.;
                    and <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi>, Ital. (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 450), has a perennial root, appearing as if bit off at the end,
                    with a singular smell like that of the anise. It is a native of most parts of Europe, in woods,
                    coppices, and sheltered lanes, particularly in a clayey soil. The flowers of the wild plant are
                    almost always of a brimstone color, but some-times of a purple hue; they appear in March and April.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. The double varieties produced by culture are in most esteem, of which there are:
                    The stemless white. Crimson. Hose-in-hose. Purple. Lilac. Scotch. White. Yellow. Brimstone.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 975)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HYACINTHGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Hyacinth</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus Orientalis</hi>, L. (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 93.); <hi rend="italic">Hex. Monog</hi>. L.;
                    and <hi rend="italic">Asphodeleæ</hi>, B. P.; <hi rend="italic">Jacinte</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthe</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Giacinto</hi>, Ital. (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 433.)
                    1627. The bulb of this plant is tunicated, the leaves broad and green, from the centre of which
                    arises a scape, with a spike of flowers, pointing in all directions, and by which it
                    is known, at first sight , from <hi rend="italic">Hyacinthus nonscriptus</hi>, L.; (<hi rend="italic">Scilla nonscripta</hi>, W.) in
                    which the scape is drooping, and the flowers all turned to one side. It is a native of
                    the Levant, and abundant about Aleppo and Bagdat, where it flowers in February;
                    here it flowers in March and April. It was cultivated by Gerarde in 1596; but had,
                    doubtless, long before been improved by the Dutch, who have added greatly to the
                    strength and beauty of the plant, and produced almost innumerable varieties.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. Gerarde mentions the single and double blue, the purple, and the white.
                    Parkinson, in 1629, enumerates eight sorts. Miller says, the Haerlem gardeners dis-
                    tinguish near 2000 sorts, and generally publish catalogues of them from year to year.
                    At present, the taste for this flower being considerably abated, the Dutch and English
                    catalogues contain only a few hundred sorts. Mason's Catalogue for 1820, contains
                    three hundred sorts with names. These names are quite arbitrary, being given by the
                    grower after himself or some public character; and therefore they are here omitted.
                    They are arranged as double-blues, whites, reds, and yellows, and single sorts of the
                    same colors; the blues and reds are the most numerous; the yellow, those of which there is least variety .
                    Only single hyacinths were, at first, cultivated; but about the beginning of the last
                    century, attention was paid to double-flowers by Peter Voerhelm, whose first double-
                    flower was named <hi rend="italic">Mary</hi>, and is now lost; but his third flower, <hi rend="italic">the King of Great Britain</hi>,
                    which is now looked upon as the oldest double-hyacinth, was greatly preferred to all the
                    flowers known, and the price of it was then above 1000 florins or 100<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. sterling. Up
                    to the middle of last century, the greatest attention was paid at Haerlem to raising new
                    sorts of double-flowers; and as much as 200<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. has been known to be given for a root;
                    but since that period, the taste for this and other bulbous flowers has considerably de-
                    clined, and at present there are few sorts for which more than 10<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. are asked,
                    the general price being from one to ten shillings a bulb for the varied sorts, and what
                    are called the common mixtures, are sold at from 2<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. to 3<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. a hundred. A variety de-
                    generates, under bad treatment, in two or three years; but in Holland some have been preserved nearly a century.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 940-941)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="CROCUSGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Crocus</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Crocus</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Trian. Monog</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Iridea</hi>, B. P. <hi rend="italic">Safran</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Safran</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Zaffarano</hi>, Ital.
                    1631. The bulb is round, solid and compressed with a netted skin, from the centre of 
                    which arise four or five grass-like leaves, and one or two flowers. Out of the centre of the
                    tube of the flower arises a slender style, crowned by a broad flat stigma of a gold color.
                    After the flower is past, the germ, which hitherto was seated on the bulb at the base of
                    the tube, pushes out of the ground, and ripens its seeds; a singular economy in nature,
                    and which occurs only in the colchicum, and a few other plants.
                    All the known species of this genus may be considered as florists' flowers. Many
                    botanists, indeed, consider that there is only two species, the <hi rend="italic">C. vernus</hi>, or spring-blowing
                    crocus; and the <hi rend="italic">C. sativus</hi>, the saffron, or autumn crocus.
                    From the <hi rend="italic">Crocus vernus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 343 and our <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 440.) they consider that 
                    the <hi rend="italic">C. versicalor</hi> (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 441.), the <hi rend="italic">C. biflorus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 442. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">C. susiana</hi> (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the
                    <hi rend="italic">C. sulphureus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>), and the <hi rend="italic">C. mæsianus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">d</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e</hi>), with their numerous sub-
                    varieties, have been produced by cul-ture or locality.
                    From the <hi rend="italic">Crocus sativus</hi>, or saffron crocus (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 343. and our <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 443. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>),
                    they think it likely that the <hi rend="italic">C. serotinus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 443. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>), and the <hi rend="italic">C. nudiflorus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 443. <hi rend="italic">e</hi>),
                    have been also originated by cultivation or accident.
                    It is sufficient for our purpose to observe, that all the sorts have been time out of 
                    mind, and still are, great ornaments to the garden; the spring sorts coming into flower
                    in February and March, and the autumn sorts in September and October.
                    The color of the spring crocus in its wild state in Switzerland, is white with a pur-
                    ple base; it is considered as naturalized in England, but when found wild, is almost 
                    always of a yellow color. The autumn crocus, or saffron, is also found wild in some
                    places, and considered as naturalized; but it appears to be an African plant, and intro-
                    duced originally in Edward the Third's time, which its Arabic name, <hi rend="italic">sahafaran</hi>, seems
                    to justify. Its colour is generally purple or blue, as is that of most of the autumn va-
                    rieties in cultivation at present.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. None of these are double. Of the spring crocus, Parkinson has enume-
                    rated twenty-seven varieties; the fundamental colours of which are blue, purple, yellow,
                    and white. Miller recites twelve as leading sorts. Mason's catalogue for 1820 men-
                    tions “twenty named sorts,” besides the light, dark, and striped purple, cloth of gold;
                    the Scotch crocus beautifully striped, the white, the large and small yellow, and several
                    striped sorts. The Dutch are continually producing new varieties, as are some florists
                    in this country, of which Haworth (<hi rend="italic">Hort</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Trans</hi>. i. 122.) may be cited as an instance.
                    Of the autumn crocus, Parkinson has enumerated four; and Ray, six varieties. Mil-
                    ler has only four: the sweet-smelling, of a deep blue; the mountain, of a paler blue;
                    the many-flowering, bluish; and the small flowering. Most of these varieties are now lost.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 954-955)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="NARCISSUSFLOWERGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Narcissus</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Narcissus</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Hex. Monog</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Amaryllidea</hi>, B. P. <hi rend="italic">Narcisse</hi>, Fr. and Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Narcisso</hi>, Ital.
                    1632. The bulb is pear-shaped and tunicated, the leaves succulent and linear, and
                    the flower-stems, which are from six to eighteen inches in height, bear either solitary or
                    fasciculated flowers; the color of the flower is either white or yellow, and generally
                    highly odoriferous. Most of the species are natives of the south of Europe, but one,
                    the <hi rend="italic">N. Pseudo-Narcissus</hi>, is a native of England, and common in woods in clayey soils.
                    They come into flower in February, March, and April.
                    <hi rend="italic">Species and Varieties</hi>. The popular division of this genus is into daffodils, white narcissi, jonquils, and polyanthus narcissi.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Daffodils</hi> are, <hi rend="italic">N. pseudo Narcissus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 17.), of which the varieties
                    are the common double, the double with white petals and a yellow cup;
                    the single with yellow petals and a golden cup; three or four concentric cups; Tradescant's daffodil and above
                    a dozen other nameless varieties; the peerless, or two-flowered daffodil, <hi rend="italic">N. bifloras</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 276),
                    and a variety <hi rend="italic">N. b. a. tenuior</hi> with one flower only on the scape; the two-colored daffodil, <hi rend="italic">N. bicolor</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 1187.),
                    a native of Spain, and a variety of the great yellow Spanish, the largest flower of the genus;
                    the least daffodil <hi rend="italic">N. minor</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 6.); the rush-leaved, <hi rend="italic">N. triandrus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 48.),
                    and some other species and varieties. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">White Narcissi</hi> are the poets' narcissus, <hi rend="italic">N. poeticus</hi>: the early-flowered,
                    <hi rend="italic">N. p. a. angustifolius</hi>; and the late-flowered <hi rend="italic">N. p. majalis</hi>; the musk narcissus,
                    <hi rend="italic">N. moschatus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 1300.); the eastern narcissus, <hi rend="italic">N. orientalis</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 948.),
                    and the yellowish and large-flowered varieties; the hoop-petticoat narcissus, <hi rend="italic">N. bulbocodium</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 88.);
                    and the paper narcissus, <hi rend="italic">N. papyraceus</hi>, with other varieties.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Jonquils</hi> are, the common, <hi rend="italic">N. jonquilla</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 15.), so named from
                    its rush or jonc-like leaves; the double-flowered jonquil; the sweet-scented jonquil, <hi rend="italic">N. odorus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 934.),
                    the great jonquil, <hi rend="italic">N. calathinus</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 78.), and some minor varieties. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">Polyanthus Narcissi</hi> are the common <hi rend="italic">N. tazzetta</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 925.);
                    the sulphur-colored, single and double; the white and yellow, single and double;
                    and above a hundred other sorts, with arbitrary names given by the Dutch, 
                    who have highly improved this division of the genus. Some of these sorts are considered species by botanists.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 956)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="CROWNIMPERIALGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Fritillary</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Fritillaria</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Heran. Monog</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Liliæ</hi>, J. (fig. 446.)
                    1634. Of this genus there are three species which are considered as florists' flowers;
                    of these species there are numerous varieties.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Crown Imperial</hi>, <hi rend="italic">F. Imperialis</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 194.) <hi rend="italic">La Couronne Imperiale</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Kaiserkrone</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">La Corona Imperial</hi>, Ita. (<hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 446. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>), has a scaly bulb,
                    from which arise strong stems, from two to four feet in height, furnished with
                    numerous broad shining green leaves, and crowned with a whirl of showy pendulous
                    flowers, yellow, red, or striped in various ways, which appear in March and April.
                    It is one of the earliest ornaments of the flower garden, producing a fine 
                    appearance in the middle of large borders , at a season when such flowers are most
                    wanted. The “singular nectary,” Professor Martyn observes, “cannot but engage 
                    the attention of the curious observer; it is a white glandular cavity, at the base
                    of each petal, and has a drop of limpid nectarious juice standing in it, when the
                    flower is in vigour. Another of the wonders of nature may be observed in the
                    peduncles which bend down while the plant is in flower, but become upright as the
                    seed ripens.” There are above a dozen varieties in cultivation, distinguished by
                    the different shades of yellow, white, and red in the flower, and by being striped double or semi-double.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 958)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="FLAG-IRISGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Iris</hi>–-<hi rend="italic">Iris</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Trian. Monog</hi>. L. and <hi rend="italic">Irideæ</hi>, B. P. <hi rend="italic">L’Iris</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Schwertlilie</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Iride</hi>, Ital. (<hi rend="italic">Figs</hi>. 444. <hi rend="italic">and</hi> 445.)
                    1633. There are several species of this genus, which are considered florists' flowers.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Persian Iris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. Persica</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>., and our <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 444. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>), a very low bulbous-
                    rooted plant, with delicate blue and violet-colored flowers, greatly esteemed
                    for their beauty and sweet smell, which is so powerful that one plant 
                    will scent a whole room. It is a native of Persia, and was cultivated by Parkinson
                    in 1629. The bulbs are generally imported from Holland, and blown in 
                    water-glasses, or pots of sand with very little earth intermixed, in February and March.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Snake's-head Iris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. tuberosa</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 551. and <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 444. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>), has long 
                    narrow four-cornered leaves, and a dark purple flower, which appears in April.
                    It is a native of the Levant, and was cultivated in 1597. The tubers are generally imported from Holland. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">Chalcedonian Iris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. susiana</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 91, and <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 444. <hi rend="italic">c</hi>), has finely
                    striated leaves, a scape a span high, and the largest and most magnificent 
                    corolla of all the species. Its petals are of a delicate texture, almost as
                    broad as a hand, purple or black striped with white. It flowers in the 
                    beginning of June; is a native of the Levant, and was cultivated by Gerarde in 1596.
                    The <hi rend="italic">bulbous-rooted</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Spanish Iris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. xiphium</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 686, and <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 445. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>),
                    has channelled leaves, convoluted during their whole length, and awl-shaped
                    at the tip; the flowers of the wild plant are blue, with emarginate
                    petals, and appear in June; but cultivation has produced a great number
                    of varieties with yellow, white, violet, and variegated flowers. It is a native
                    of the south of Europe, and was cultivated by Gerarde in 1596. 
                    The <hi rend="italic">Great bulbous-rooted Iris</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">English Iris</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Dutch</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. xiphioides</hi> 
                    (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 687, and <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 56. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>), is much larger than the other in all its parts,
                    the flower-stalk is near twice the height, and the flowers are more than
                    double the size. It is equally prolific in varieties as <hi rend="italic">Ixiphium</hi>, of which 
                    it is by some botanists considered only a variety. The tubers of both sorts are annually imported from Holland.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 957)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="GERANIUMGLOSS" resp="#CGP"><hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>, L. <hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Erodium</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Pelargonium</hi>,
                    of modern authors. <hi rend="italic">Monadelphia</hi>, L.; and <hi rend="italic">Geraniæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Geranier</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Geranium</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Geranio</hi>, Ital.
                    1711. This beautiful tribe comprehends numerous species and varieties of herbaceous
                    suffruticose and shrubby plants, generally of a somewhat succulent nature
                    throughout. They are almost all natives of the Cape of Good Hope, and with the
                    exception of three or four species, have been introduced, or originated here from
                    seed during the present and latter end of the last century. They are chiefly admired
                    for their flowers, which they produce in abundance from May to September,
                    generally in corymbs from the axillæ of the leaves of every shade of red, scarlet,
                    and purple, mixed with white and yellow. The plants are casily cultivated, and
                    by proper pruning, with the aid of gentle forcing in winter, many of the species, as the
                    <hi rend="italic">P. zonale, cuculatum, cordatum, &#x0026;c.</hi> may be kept in flower all the year. The best
                    collection of this family is in the nursery of Messrs. Colville, under the care of
                    R. Sweet, whose “<hi rend="italic">Geraniæ</hi>,” now publishing, is the most elegant and complete work of its kind.
                    <hi rend="italic">Species and Varieties</hi>. Many species and sub-species have been received from the
                    Cape; but the greater number of the admired sorts have been raised in this country
                    from seed; some of these have received systematic appellations, but the greater number
                    have been named by those who raised them after themselves, or their friends, in the
                    manner of florists' flowers.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 1032)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PEONYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Pæony</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Pæonia</hi>, L.; <hi rend="italic">Polyan. Dig</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Ranunculaceæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Pivoine</hi>, Fr.;
                    <hi rend="italic">Päonie</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Peonia</hi>, Ital.
                    1639. Most of the species of this plant introduced in this country may be considered
                    as select flowers; but that which has been longest cultivated is the <hi rend="italic">P. officinalis</hi>
                    (<hi rend="italic">Bot. Mag</hi>. 1784.) The roots are composed of roundish tubers, the stalks of the leaves rise
                    between two and three feet high, and terminate in large red or purple flowers, which
                    appear in May. The leaves are composed of many unequal lobes, variously cut into
                    many segments. It is a native of Switzerland, Dauphine, and other parts of Europe,
                    and also of China and Japan; and was cultivated here in 1562. The roots were formerly
                    much used in medicine.
                    <hi rend="italic">Varieties</hi>. Originally the common pæony was said to be of two sorts, male and
                    female, the flowers of the former being smaller and lighter colored than those of the
                    latter. These distinctions, which had no sexual allusion in this case, the pæony being
                    hermaphrodite, are now laid aside, and the varieties of <hi rend="italic">P. officinalis</hi> have been reduced
                    by J. Sabine (<hi rend="italic">Hort. Trans</hi>. ii. 273.) to the following:
                    The <hi rend="italic">double red</hi>, the most common, and formerly highly prized; being, when
                    introduced at Antwerp, near 250 years ago, sold for twelve crowns. 
                    The double flesh-colored. The double white. The double fringed. The double white Chinese.
                    The double sweet-scented Chinese. (<hi rend="italic">Hort. Trans</hi>. vol. ii. pl. 18) Whitley’s double white Chinese.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 962)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="OAKGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The Oak is the Quercus, L., Monæc. Polyand. L., and Amentaceæ, J. Chêne, Fr.;
                    Eich, Ger.; and Querec, Ital. The following species and varieties are planted for their timber.
                    The Common Oak, Q. robur, (Eng. Bot. 1845.) a native of Britain. It grows to
                    the height of fifty or sixty feet when in a heavy loam; flowers in April, and ripens its
                    acorns in October and November.
                    The most valuable variety of the common oak is said (Caled. Hort. Mem. iii. 376.)
                    to be the pedunculata (Eng. Bot. 1342.), or the stalk fruited; by some considered a
                    distinct species. It is distinguished from Q. robur by the marked circumstance of the
                    acorns being placed on long fruit-stalks, whilst those of the robur are nearly sessile.
                    Besides, the superior utility and hardiness of the timber, the pedunculated oak is, in
                    fact, the most magnificent of the two British sorts. Miller says, this variety of the
                    Q. robur, (and which he calls the fæmina,) is more rare than the sessile-fruited; but
                    Professor Martyn says, this is not the case, and that the pedunculated is equally
                    general as the other. It is observed by Du Hamel, that oaks in forests being propagated
                    from the acorn, there are so many varieties that it is difficult to find two resembling
                    each other in every respect. Professor Martyn observes, that the figures in 
                    ancient authors have the fruit uniformly on foot-stalks, which shows that that variety
                    had been most common: and Ray considers it as the common oak of England. Du Roi
                    affirms, that the timber of the sessile-fruited is reddish, and brittle, whilst that
                    of the stalk-fruited is whitish and hard. From these, and various accounts, as well as our
                    own observation, we consider ourselves justified in recommending to nurserymen and
                    others, who gather acorns for seeds, to take effectual precautions that only the stalked sort be gathered.
                    1912. The Turkey Oak, Q. cerris, (Du Roi, 2 t. 5. f. 1.) a native of the south of
                    Europe, introduced in 1735. This species is distinguished by oblong, pointed, and
                    frequently lyrate leaves, jagged, and a little hoary on the under side. The acorns are
                    small, and have rough, prickly cups. The tree grows from forty to sixty feet high.
                    There are several varieties, but the best is that called the Devonshire or Luccombe,
                    from the name of the person who raised it from seeds, saved from a tree of the
                    Turkey-oak grown in Devonshire.
                    There are about forty species of exotic oaks introduced in this country, which may
                    be considered as timber trees, and are such in effect, in their native countries. Of
                    these, the greater part are natives of America; and it has been recommended,
                    (Caled. Mem. iii. 378.) to cultivate the Q. tinctoria or Quercitron on account of its
                    bark, which affords a valuable yellow die[sic. All these species, however, are either too
                    tender, or too scarce, or too dwarfish, and slow-growing, to warrant us in considering any
                    other than the common and Luccombe oaks, as fit for the purposes of profitable planting.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 1139-1140)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HAWTHORNGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Hawthorn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mespilus oxyacantha</hi>, E. B. (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>.); <hi rend="italic">Icosan. Di.-
                    Pentag</hi>. L.; and <hi rend="italic">Rosaceæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">Aubepine</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Hagedorn</hi>, Ger.; <hi rend="italic">Branco spino</hi>, Ital.
                    It is a native shrub, of great importance as a hedge plant, and is also frequently
                    introduced into narrow plantations as an undergrowth. It will not grow, however,
                    under the drip of trees, and therefore, in a profitable point of view, is only to be
                    considered as affording the impermiable, close, and durable, and easily raised fences,
                    called quickset hedges. The timber of such plants as grow singly, and attain a tolerable
                    size, is valued by the millwright and turner, and the roots by the cabinet-maker. It
                    is often spoiled, Sang observes, through inattention after cutting; if it be allowed to
                    lie in entire logs or trunks, it soon heats, and becomes quite brittle and worthless; it
                    therefore ought to be instantly cut up into planks, and laid to dry. The haws and
                    foliage afford excellent food for deer.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 1145)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="YEWGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">Yew</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Taxus baccato</hi>, L. (<hi rend="italic">Eng. Bot</hi>. 746.); <hi rend="italic">Polyg. Monæc</hi>. L.; and
                    <hi rend="italic">Coniferæ</hi>, J. <hi rend="italic">If</hi>, Fr.; <hi rend="italic">Eihenbaum</hi>, Ger.; and <hi rend="italic">Tasso</hi>, Ital. It is a low, bush-like,
                    dark, evergreen tree, of great longevity, slow in growth, and affording a hard, white
                    valuable timber. It flowers in April and May, and its berries are ripe in November.
                    It is found in a wild state in bleak situations, and on a variety of soils, dry and
                    moist. It is very common in ancient church-yards, in many of which it has attained a
                    great size and age. Evelyn, and after him, Professor Martyn, have referred to a great
                    number of examples of notable trees of this species.
                    (An encyclopædia of gardening: comprising the theory and practice of horticulture, floriculture, arboriculture and landscape-gardening including all the latest improvements, John C. Loudon, p. 1145)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="GENTIANGLOSS" resp="#CGP">The <hi rend="italic">umbelliferous</hi> (umbel-bearing) plants, which compose nearly the
                    whole of the second order of the class Pentándria, have, with
                    few exceptions, <hi rend="italic">pinnate</hi> leaves, more or less compound.
                    The British Flora possesses only eight genera in this order,
                    that are not included in the natural family called Umbelliferæ
                    or Umbellátæ. Of this number are the beet (<hi rend="italic">B</hi>èta), of which
                    the root is eaten in salads (it contains a great quantity of sugar,
                    which may be extracted and manufactured for use); the glass-
                    wort (Salsòla), used in the manufacture of glass; the elm (<hi rend="italic">U</hi>'l-
                    mus); and the gentian (Genti<hi rend="italic">ána</hi>), a genus remarkable for the
                    brilliant blue colour of its flowers, and the bitterness of its
                    roots. “As bitter as gentian,” is a common phrase. The
                    root of a species of gentian growing on the Alps, and other
                    mountains on the Continent (<hi rend="italic">G</hi>. lùtea), is the bitter chiefly
                    used in medicine.
                    (The Magazine of Natural History, vol.2, 1829, p.156)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="COLUMBINEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">AQUILEGIA. <hi rend="italic">Columbine</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Nat. Order</hi>. RANUNCULACEÆ.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> 5-leaved, petaloid, deciduous. <hi rend="italic">Petals</hi> 5,
                    gaping above, elongated downwards into a hollow, horn-shaped
                    spur, projecting between the leaves of the calyx. Follicles 5.
                    Ornamental herbs with purple, blue, or white flowers, divided
                    leaves, and fibrous perennial roots. The genus which is small,
                    containing about 15 known species, is confined to the north
                    temperate zone. The plants are less acrid than the rest of
                    their order, and the common Columbine has been employed
                    medicinally as an astringent, but instances are on record
                    of its proving fatal in overdoses.
                    AQUILEGIA VULGARIS. <hi rend="italic">Common Columbine</hi>. TAB. 770. 
                    Spur of the petals incurved. Follicles hairy. Stem leafy, many-flowered,
                    smooth. Leaves glabrous. Styles as long as the stamens. 
                    Aquilegia vulgaris, E. B. 297. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> III. 33. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 13. <hi rend="italic">Hooker ed</hi>. 2. 261. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 3. 264.
                    Found wild in woods, thickets and pastures in many parts of England
                    and Wales, though probably in its origin a wanderer from the garden.
                    Leaves mostly radical, on long petioles, twice ternate, obtusely
                    lobed; more or less glaucous as well as the stem, which rises
                    a foot or 18 inches high, bearing a few sessile leaves, and several
                    drooping, purple, rarely rose-coloured or white, flowers. The inner
                    series of stamens is often abortive, in which case the filaments are
                    sometimes united, forming a plaited membrane around the germens,
                    as shown in our figures. Flowers in June.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. By Sir James Edward Smith... The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 1, 1832, p. 13)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="POPPYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">PAPAVER. <hi rend="italic">Poppy</hi>. 
                    Nat. Order. PAPAVERACEÆ. 
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> inferior, 2-leaved, deciduous. <hi rend="italic">Petals</hi> 4.
                    <hi rend="italic">Stigma</hi> radiated, sessile on the top of the ovarium. <hi rend="italic">Capsule</hi> 1-celled.
                    <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> numerous, on parietal receptacles projecting
                    towards the centre of the cavity, and escaping by pores
                    beneath the projecting rim of the stigma.
                    Herbs with wing-cleft, alternate leaves, and solitary inflorescence.
                    The flowers, on long peduncles deflexed before expansion,
                    are of various shades of red, or purple, yellow, and white,
                    but never blue. All of the species are narcotic, and
                    secrete a white milk-like juice in which that property resides:
                    in its inspissated form this is the Opium of commerce. Europe
                    and the central parts of Asia seem to be the chief stations of the genus.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. By Sir James Edward Smith... The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 1, 1832, p. 48)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="SNOWDROPGLOSS" resp="#CGP">GALANTHUS nivalis. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Snowdrop</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">HEXANDRIA Monogynia</hi>. 
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Corolla</hi> of six petals, three of which are
                    smaller than the rest, and emarginated. <hi rend="italic">Stigma</hi> simple.
                    SPEC. CHAR. …
                    SYN. Galanthus nivalis. Linn. Sp. Pl. 413. Huds. Fl. An. 140. With. Bot. Arr. 340.
                    
                    ON the authority of Mr. Hudson and Dr. Stokes, the Snowdrop
                    is now admitted into the list of British plants, although
                    not described as such by Ray. Whether originally a native or
                    not, it is now found in a wild state in many different situations,
                    such as orchards, grassy meadows, groves, and thickets. Dr. Stokes,
                    whose accuracy and extensive information none who
                    peruses the Botanical Arrangement of British Plants can doubt, is
                    particularly exact in asserting that he has gathered it remote
                    from all traces of buildings or gardens.
                    No plant is more generally cultivated, or more cordially welcomed
                    as the herald of approaching spring. It frequently
                    pierces through the unmelted snow, which it rivals in whiteness,
                    and remains uninjured by a season, during whose inclemency
                    most vegetable productions lie dormant. Who can
                    read the following charming lines on the Snowdrop, by
                    Mrs. Barbauld, without admiration?
                    
                    “As nature's breath, by some transforming pow'r,
                    “Had chang'd an icicle into a flow'r.--
                    “Its name and hue the scentless plant retains,
                    “And winter lingers in its icy veins.”
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth... The figures by James Sowerby, vol. 5, 1796, p. 19)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="VIOLETGLOSS" resp="#CGP">Viola. Violet.
                    Nat. Order. Violaceæ. 
                    Gen: Char:-<hi rend="underline">Calyx</hi> of 3 leaves, each extended at
                    the base. <hi rend="underline">Petals</hi> 5-unequal, the lowermost spurred
                    behind. <hi rend="underline">Anthers</hi> slightly cohering. Capsule superior,
                    of 1 cell, with 3 valves.
                    A genus of small herbaceous plants
                    generally admired &#x0026; well-known by the names
                    Violet, Heartsease, &#x0026; Pansey. The [sic] all have alternate
                    leaves with stipules at their bases &#x0026; fibrous
                    either annual or perennial roots. They may be
                    divided into two sections by their stipules, in some being membranous, in others leafy.
                [...]
                The Violet, so justly esteemed for its delightful fragrance, is, like
                many other desirable plants, frequently found wild. In England it
                is abundant, not uncommonly varying to white, but it is rare in Scotland.
                A double variety obtained by florists has a richer scent. The
                long prostrate scions seldom produce flowers until the second year,
                when flowers with petals are raised upon upright stalks in March and
                April, but are of short duration; they are followed by a long succession
                without petals upon stalks which bend to the ground, and there
                ripen their seeds. This is the case with several other species. At
                the same time the leaves greatly enlarge. A syrup made from the
                petals is a gentle laxative and, while it retains its colour, a delicate
                test for free acids and alkalies. The Sorbet of the Turks is also said
                to be prepared from them with sugar.
                (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. By Sir James Edward Smith... The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 2, 1835, p. 58-59)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HEARTSEASEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">VIOLA TRICOLOR. <hi rend="italic">Pansy Violet</hi>. Tab. 333. 
                    Stems angular, diffuse. Leaves deeply crenate, oblong. Stipules
                    leaf-like, pinnatifid, the central lobe toothed. Petals longer than
                    the calyx. Germen oval. Root annual. 
                    Viola tricolor, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 1287. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 305. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 36. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 107. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2. 119.
                    The Wild Pansy or, in familiar language, Heart's-ease, the origin
                    of all our annual garden varieties, is very common in corn-fields, and
                    flowers from May to September.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. By Sir James Edward Smith... The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 2, 1835, p. 60)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="GREEKVALERIANGLOSS" resp="#CGP">POLEMONIUM. <hi rend="italic">Jacob's Ladder</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Nat. Order</hi>. POLEMONIACEÆ. 
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Corolla</hi> deeply 5-cleft, closed below the throat
                    by the expanded, hairy bases of the filaments. <hi rend="italic">Stigma</hi>
                    3-cleft. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> 5-cleft. <hi rend="italic">Capsule</hi> superior, 3-celled, 3-valved. 
                    Perennial, sparingly branched, herbs, with alternate pinnate
                    leaves and terminal panicles of showy flowers. Pliny gives
                    the derivation of the name from πολεμος, <hi rend="italic">war</hi>, two kings having
                    engaged in a war about the discovery of it. These kings must
                    have been more jealous of botanical fame than even some of
                    our modern botanists, whose friendly alliances have been unhappily
                    destroyed by similar disputes. What plant was known
                    to Pliny by this name is now uncertain .
                    POLEMONIUM CŒRULEUM, <hi rend="italic">Blue Jacob's Ladder</hi>. TAB. 295. 
                    Leaves pinnated. Flowers erect. Calyx longer than the tube of the
                    corolla. Root fibrous. 
                    Polemonium cœruleum, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 14. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 286. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 168. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 96. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2. 111. Greek Valerian.)
                    This, although very common in gardens, is one of the plants most
                    rarely found wild in this country. It was found by botanists of the
                    17th century in the romantic and mountainous country about Malham
                    Cove in the North of Yorkshire, where it still grows. A variety
                    with white flowers, sometimes even from the same root as the blue
                    ones (<hi rend="italic">Linnæus</hi>): the faint purplish blue of the flowers being that
                    which of all colours is the most apt to vary to white. Its flowers
                    open in May and June. The herb has no sensible properties.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. By Sir James Edward Smith... The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 5, 1835, p. 43)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HONEYSUCKLEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">LONICERA. <hi rend="italic">Honeysuckle</hi>.
                    <hi rend="italic">Nat. Order</hi>. CAPRIFOLIÆ.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Corolla</hi> of 1 petal, irregular. <hi rend="italic">Calyx</hi> superior,
                    of 5 teeth, small. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi> of 1 or more cells. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> many.
                    Slender shrubs, with opposite leaves and branches; the
                    stems in some species twining up other shrubs and trees. The
                    fruit is not eatable.
                    
                    LONICERA CAPRIFOLIUM. <hi rend="italic">Pale Perfoliate Honeysuckle</hi>. TAB. 324.
                    Flowers ringent, whorled, terminal. Leaves deciduous, the upper
                    ones confluent and perfoliate.
                    Lonicera Caprifolium, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 799. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 325. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 103. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2. 116.
                    Caprifolium perfoliatum, <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 131.
                    This rare British plant may have been overlooked as one of the
                    many varieties of the Common Honeysuckle. The fragrant flowers
                    are in perfection through May or June. It is very commonly cultivated.
                    
                    LONICERA PERICLYMENUM. <hi rend="italic">Common Honeysuckle</hi>. TAB. 325. 
                    Flowers ringent, in terminal imbricated heads. Leaves deciduous, all separate. 
                    Lonicera Periclymenum, <hi rend="italic">E. B</hi>. 800. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 326. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 103. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2.116.
                    Caprifolium Periclymenum, <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 131. (Woodbine.)
                    An universal favourite which decorates our hedges abundantly, and
                    perfumes the air delightfully in an evening after rain. The stem
                    climbs by twisting to a considerable height upon trees and bushes.
                    There occurs in gardens a variety with sinuated and generally variegated
                    leaves, called the Oak-leaved, besides several varieties differing
                    in the colour of the flower and smoothness of the leaves. They all
                    flower most plentifully in June and July.
                    
                    LONICERA XYLOSTEUM. <hi rend="italic">Upright Honeysuckle</hi>. TAB. 326. 
                    Flower-stalks 2-flowered. Berries distinct. Leaves entire, downy.
                    Lonicera Xylosteum, E. B. 916. <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> I. 326. <hi rend="italic">Lindley</hi> 132. <hi rend="italic">Hooker</hi> 103. <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>. 2. 117.
                    Probably this has escaped from gardens; only two places are named
                    where it has been found wild, viz. under the Roman Wall near Shewing-
                    Sheels in Northumberland, and in a coppice, called the Hachetts,
                    to the east of Houghton Bridge, 4 miles from Arundel. The stem is
                    upright, bushy, very much branched. The
                    scentle[s]s flowers, which appear in June,
                    are by no means showy; it is however, a
                    favorite shrub in gardens. The berries
                    are of a bright scarlet, &#x0026; contain 6 or more seeds each.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth. By Sir James Edward Smith... The figures by James Sowerby, 2d ed., vol. 5, 1835, p. 56-57)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="IVYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">HEDERA Helix. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Common Ivy</hi>.
                   
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>. 
                   GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. of 5 teeth. <hi rend="italic">Petals</hi> 5, broadest at the
                    base. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi> encompassed with the calyx, containing 5 <hi rend="italic">seeds</hi>.
                    SPEC. CHAR. Leaves some ovate, some lobed.
                    SYN. Hedera Helix. Linn. Sp. Pl. 292. Sm. Fl. Brit. 267. Huds. 100. 
                    With. 267. Hull. 54. Relh. 97. Sibth. 85. Abbot. 53. Curt. Lond. fasc. 1. t. 16. 
                    H. communis major et minor. Raii Syn. 459.
                    
                    EVERY one is acquainted with the Ivy, so common and so
                    picturesque upon old walls, and the trunks of aged trees, whose
                    heads it frequently overtops, finally overwhelming its supporters
                    altogether. Nor does it less commonly creep on the ground
                    in dark woods, forming an evergreen carpet. It is the latest
                    of all our flowering plants, blossoming in October and November,
                    and ripening its berries in the spring.
                    
                    The stem and branches are long and flexible, a little compressed,
                    creeping, and closely attached to the tree or wall,
                    which supports them, by innumerable short fibres, which,
                    however, do not afford them any nourishment; for every
                    day's experience shows that Ivy is easily killed by cutting the
                    stem above the root. The upper branches spread in every direction,
                    and are round and smooth. The leaves are ever-green,
                    of a dark hue, beautifully veined with white, and
                    somewhat shining: the lowermost five-lobed, the uppermost
                    ovate; all entire and supported by footstalks. Flowers numerous,
                    in umbels, several of which together form a corymbus.
                    Stalks slightly clothed with starry down. Germen urn-shaped,
                    encompassed by the 5 teeth of the calyx. Petals
                    green, reflexed. Stamina erect. Style very short, with a
                    simple stigma. Berry globular, black, mealy within.
                    
                    The whole plant partakes of a peculiar aromatic flavour.
                    From the old stems, when bruised, a very fragrant resin
                    exudes. Mr. Curtis recommends this plant to be trained into
                    a head as a standard ever-green ; he also mentions that sheep
                    are very fond of the leaves.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth... The figures by James Sowerby, vol. 18, 1804, p. 1267)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="GUELDERROSEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">VIBURNUM Opulus. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Common Guelder-rose, or Water Elder</hi>.
                   
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Trigynia</hi>. 
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. superior, of five leaves. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. in five
                    segments. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi> with one seed. 
                    SPEC. CHAR. Leaves lobed; their foot-stalks set with glands. 
                    SYN. Viburnum Opulus. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 384. <hi rend="italic">Huds. Fl. An</hi>. 130.
                    <hi rend="italic">With. Bot. Arr</hi>. 318. <hi rend="italic">Relh. Cant</hi>. 127. <hi rend="italic">Sibth. Ox</hi>. 104.
                    Opulus. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 460.
                   
                   THIS shrub is common in woods and hedges in watery
                    places, flowering early in June; the bright-red berries ripen
                    about September, and towards the middle of October the leaves
                    assume a beautiful pink-colour, affording another instance, in
                    addition to that of the Cornel (see tab. 249), of a genus,
                    mostly American, the leaves of which turn red in autumn. In
                    gardens the Guelder-rose, bearing round bunches of abortive
                    flowers only, is very common, elegantly grouping with the
                    Lilac and Laburnum in the early part of summer.
                    It is a small bushy tree, smooth in all its parts. Leaves
                    with three great, unequally serrated, lobes; their foot-stalks
                    bearing several cup-like glands towards the top, and a pair or
                    two of erect linear appendages, scarcely to be called stipulæ,
                    near the base . Cymes of many white flowers; the perfect
                    ones small, resembling elder; abortive ones in the margin,
                    each consisting merely of a large irregular flat petal, without
                    organs of fructification. Stigmas nearly sessile, close together.
                    Berries drooping, very succulent. Seed flat, heart-shaped.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth... The figures by James Sowerby, vol. 5, 1796, p. 332)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="COMFREYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">SYMPHYTUM officinale. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Common Comfrey</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. Limb of the <hi rend="italic">corolla</hi> tubular, swelling;
                    its orifice closed with awl-shaped rays. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. in 5
                    deep segments. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> 4, naked.
                    SPEC. CHAR. Leaves ovato-lanceolate, decurrent. 
                    SYN. Symphytum officinale. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 195. <hi rend="italic">Sm. Fl. Brit</hi>. 218.
                    <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 81. <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 230. <hi rend="italic">Hull</hi>. 47. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 78. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 70. <hi rend="italic">Abbot</hi>. 42.
                    <hi rend="italic">Curt. Lond. fasc</hi>. 4. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 18. <hi rend="italic">Woodv. Suppl. t</hi>. 215.
                    S. magnum. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 230.
                    
                    A FREQUENT native of watery places, banks of rivers,
                    and about ditches, flowering from the end of May to September.
                    
                    Root perennial, fleshy, externally black. Stem two or three
                    feet high, upright, leafy, winged, branched at the top, clothed
                    with short bristly hairs that point rather downward. Leaves
                    decurrent, ovato-lanceolate, waved, pointed, veiny, rough;
                    the radical ones on footstalks, and broader than the rest.
                    Clusters of flowers in pairs on a common stalk, with an odd
                    flower between them, recurved, dense, hairy. Corolla yellowish-
                    white, sometimes purple, the rays downy at each edge.
                    
                    Dr. Sibthorp has made a new species of the red or
                    purple-flowered variety, distinguishing it by a shorter and
                    spreading calyx, a mark which we and several of our friends
                    have in vain tried to discover.
                    
                    The Comfrey root abounds in a pure tasteless mucilage, like
                    that of the Marsh-mallow; and being (as Dr. Woodville observes)
                    more easily obtained, it ought not to be omitted in lists
                    of medicinal plants. Such medicines are useful in irritations
                    of the throat, intestines, and above all the bladder.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth... The figures by James Sowerby, vol. 12, 1801, p. 817)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="PERIWINKLEGLOSS" resp="#CGP">VINCA major.
                    <hi rend="italic">Greater Periwinkle</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Corolla</hi> twisted, salver-shaped. <hi rend="italic">Pouches</hi> 2,
                    erect. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> without beard or wing.
                    SPEC. CHAR. Stems erect. Leaves ovate, finely fringed. Flowers on stalks.
                    SYN. Vinca major. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 304. <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 91.
                    <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 269. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 89. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 79. <hi rend="italic">Curt. Lond. fasc</hi>. 4. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 19.
                    Clematis daphnoides major. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 268.
                    
                    IN hedges and groves not very unfrequent in a truly wild
                    state; though it is so generally cultivated in every ornamented
                    shrubbery, and grows so readily, that we cannot always
                    depend upon its being really of native growth. It
                    flowers in May, and is one of the greatest ornaments of that favourite season.
                    
                    The roots are perennial, creeping; the stems also, which
                    are roundish and leafy, some of them trail and throw out
                    roots, others grow erect and bear flowers, but even these
                    afterwards take root from near their extremities. Leaves
                    opposite, on footstalks, ovate, entire, finely fringed at their
                    edges with short rigid hairs, otherwise smooth and shining.
                    Flowers solitary, axillary, alternate, on stalks about half the
                    length of the leaves. Calyx in five awl-shaped fringed
                    segments, as long as the tube of the flower. Corolla of a
                    fine purplish blue, salver-shaped, twisted (as in all this natural
                    order of <hi rend="italic">Contortæ</hi>); its tube inflated, and five-sided in
                    the upper part. Stamina inserted about its middle, bowed,
                    ciliated and compressed. Antheræ hooded. Germen double,
                    with 2 glands at its base. Style simple. Stigma shaped
                    like a pulley, orange-coloured, its top five-lobed and downy.
                    The fruit, which Mr. Curtis has not even mentioned, and
                    which few botanists have seen, is produced every year in
                    Mr. Kett's grounds at Seething, Norfolk, and consists of
                    two awl-shaped, smooth, shining pouches, or folliculi, each
                    containing one or two oblong seeds, with a groove down
                    their upper side. These seeds are roughish, but naked,
                    or destitute of beard, down, or wing.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth... The figures by James Sowerby, vol. 8, 1799, p. 514)
                
                
                VINCA minor. 
                <hi rend="italic">Lesser Periwinkle</hi>.
                
                    <hi rend="italic">PENTANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. twisted, salver-shaped. <hi rend="italic">Pouches</hi> 2,
                    erect. <hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi> without beard or wing. 
                SPEC. CHAR. Stems procumbent. Leaves elliptic-
                lanceolate, smooth at the edge. Flowers on 
                stalks. Calyx-teeth lanceolate. 
                SYN. Vinca minor. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 304. <hi rend="italic">Sm. Fl. Brit</hi>. 270.
                    <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 91. <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 268. <hi rend="italic">Hull</hi>. 51. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 89. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 79.
                    <hi rend="italic">Abbot</hi>. 53. <hi rend="italic">Curt. Lond. fasc</hi>. 3. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 16.
                    V. pervinca minor. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 268.
                
                WE have never seen the Lesser Periwinkle (far rarer than
                the Greater, <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 514) more truly wild than about Honingham
                church, 6 miles west of Norwich. Our specimen was gathered
                near Rippon, Yorkshire, by the Rev. Mr. Dalton, and sent by
                Mr. W. Brunton, being in the opinion of those gentlemen perfectly
                wild there. It is very generally cultivated in shady places under
                trees, its evergreen leaves and early flowers conducing greatly
                to the ornament of such places. The wild plant blossoms earlier
                than <hi rend="italic">V. major</hi>; and the garden varieties, one of which is double
                and reddish, and another white with variegated leaves, are
                found in bloom even in March or April.
                
                The root is perennial and creeping. Whole plant smooth
                and shining. Stems round, slender, leafy; erect when in
                flower, afterwards prostrate, elongated, taking root at their
                joints. Leaves opposite, on short stalks, lanceolate inclining
                to elliptic, entire , of a full shining green, destitute of the
                fringed edge observable in <hi rend="italic">V. major</hi>. The flowers are also
                smaller than in that species, of a rather darker blue, with a
                much shorter, smooth, and less tapering calyx. The fruit of
                this species we have never seen.
                (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth... The figures by James Sowerby, vol. 13, 1801, p. 917)</note>
                
                <note xml:id="LILYOFTHEVALLEYGLOSS" resp="#CGP">CONVALLARIA majalis. 
                    <hi rend="italic">Lily of the Valley</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">HEXANDRIA Monogynia</hi>.
                    GEN. CHAR. <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. in 6 segments. <hi rend="italic">Cal</hi>. none. <hi rend="italic">Style</hi>
                    longer than the stamina. <hi rend="italic">Stigma</hi> 3-sided. <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi>
                    superior, 3-celled, spotted before it is ripe. 
                    SPEC. CHAR. Stalk naked, semicylindrical. Flowers
                    spiked, drooping, on partial stalks.
                    SYN. Convallaria majalis. <hi rend="italic">Linn. Sp. Pl</hi>. 451. <hi rend="italic">Sm. Fl. Brit</hi>. 370.
                    <hi rend="italic">Huds</hi>. 146. <hi rend="italic">With</hi>. 341. <hi rend="italic">Hull</hi>. 72. <hi rend="italic">Relh</hi>. 138. <hi rend="italic">Sibth</hi>. 111.
                    <hi rend="italic">Abbot</hi>. 76. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">Curt. Lond. fasc</hi>. 5. <hi rend="italic">t</hi>. 24. 
                    Lilium convallium. <hi rend="italic">Raii Syn</hi>. 264.
                    
                    THIS elegant and delightfully fragrant plant, so generally
                    cultivated in flower-gardens, is sometimes to be met with in
                    shady mountainous spots, or on heathy ground, in several
                    parts of England, as about Hampstead and Highgate, and in a
                    holly wood between Norwich and Thorpe, where it is truly
                    wild. Our specimens were obligingly communicated by S. 
                    Hailstone and W. Hurstler, esqrs. from rocky woods at Hebden
                    bridge near Halifax.
                    
                    Roots perennial, matted and creeping. Leaves two, radical, on
                    long stalks, upright, elliptical, ribbed, entire; the stalks
                    invested with seales, from among which also arises the solitary
                    naked flower-stalk, shorter than the leaves, flat on one side,
                    round on the other, bearing a simple spike of drooping, white, 
                    bell-shaped, very odoriferous flowers, each on its own curved 
                    round little stalk, having a lanceolate bractea where it springs
                    from the principal one. Stamina awl-shaped, short. Style club-
                    shaped, triangular upwards. Berry globular, scarlet when ripe.
                    
                    The spots of the unripe fruit make a principal but unsatisfactory
                    part of the generic character of <hi rend="italic">Convallaria</hi> in Linnæus. The 
                    undivided stigma chiefly distinguishes it from <hi rend="italic">Asparagus</hi>.
                    (English botany; or, coloured figures of British plants, with their essential characters, synonyms, and places of growth... The figures by James Sowerby, vol. 15, 1802, p. 1035)</note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>