<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <fileDesc xml:id="harry_and_lucy_vol1_glosses_contextual">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy . . . Vol I&#x201D;</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="MAMMASAIDLUCYGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#MAMMA">mamma</persName> said <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">papa</persName> has gone out to town&#x201d; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Lucy is speaking; i.e., &#x201C;&#x2018;Mamma&#x2019;, said Lucy, &#x2018;Papa has gone out to town&#x2019;&#x201D;. 
                    Note that Ruskin's first story begins with the father's absence. For the transportation that John James Ruskin probably used to commute to his business in London, 
                    see <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="camberwell_note.php#COMMUTER">Camberwell: London Commuter Transport</ref>.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="TOWNCITYDOCKSGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;to go to town and then into the city and then to the docks&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>For the business center of London that had come to be called "the City", 
                    where John James Ruskin's counting house was located, see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="london_city_note.php#BILLITERST">City of London: Billiter Street and the Premises of <orgName corresp="#RUSKINETAL">Ruskin, Telford, and Domecq</orgName></ref>. 
                    By going "to town" as opposed to "into the city", Mamma probably means crossing the Thames and entering the environs of London, 
                    and not merely walking down the hill from their home, Herne Hill, into the village of 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="camberwell_note.php"><placeName corresp="#CAMBERWELL">Camberwell</placeName></ref>. 
                    Later, in chapter 2, Harry's father takes him "into town" to view "the apparatus for making ice", definitely referring to London. For the docks, see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="london_city_note.php#DOCKS">City of London: The London Docks</ref>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="NUMBERGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;and how many in number . . . eleven&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In Edgeworth's Frank, everyday experiences are frequently exploited for 
                    arithmetical exercises, such as when Harry and Lucy count the strawberries they gather for dessert, and then learn 
                    the meaning of the suffixes <hi rend="italic">teen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ty</hi> (Maria Edgeworth, Frank, 1:117–20).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="DISCOURSEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;discourse&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>This 
                    comparatively sophisticated word choice, which Ruskin does not used idiomatically (i.e., he writes, to "get" the discourse "of silkworms"), 
                    occurs only twice in Edgeworth, Harry and Lucy Concluded; 
                    the word occurs more frequently in Barbauld, Evenings at Home.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="ANSWEREDHERFATHERGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<hi rend="doubleletter">Y</hi>es I will <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> answered her <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName>&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>The 
                    <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName> is speaking: i.e., &#x201C;&#x2018;Yes, I will, Lucy&#x2019;, answered her <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName>&#x201D;.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="LUCYSAIDHERLESSONGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> said her lesson very well 
                   and after that her <persName type="fictional" corresp="#MAMMA">mother</persName> said&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>This sentence, despite 
                    its closing with a quotation mark, is the first instance of third-person narration in Ruskin's 
                    "Harry and Lucy", which up until this point is composed entirely of dialogue. This brief tag of narration is answered by a second passage of third-person narration (likewise punctuated with a closing quotation mark), 
                    in which a narrator addresses the reader ("we shall . . . attend to"). The two passages of narration frame an exchange in the voices of the parents, 
                    who knowingly confide in one another about Lucy's maneuver: the "cause" that "made Lucy not come to say her lesson to me", Mamma implies, 
                    is that Lucy has extracted a promise from her father to hear her lesson, despite Papa's pressing lack of "time". 
                    With the father snared into the narrative, the speaker declares that "we shall have time to attend to harry", 
                    and the narrative shifts to his "story".</p>
                    
                    <p>In Maria Edgeworth's Frank: A Sequel to Frank in Early Lessons, 
                        rather than the child choosing the parental auditor and commanding the auditor's time, as Ruskin's Lucy does, 
                        Frank is ordered by his father to recite his Latin lesson when the father reserves the time to hear him. 
                        Edgeworth's father is impatient of time--"'I cannot stand here talking or listening to you, my dear, all day'”--and 
                        Frank is assured by a family friend, the ominously named Mr. Birch, that "'there are very few fathers who would shorten 
                        their morning's ride for the sake of hearing their son's Latin lesson'” (Edgeworth, Frank: A Sequel, 1:52, 78). 
                        When the time comes to recite his lesson, Frank is disgraced, because he has procrastinated, 
                        distracted by play outdoors and by the more entertaining reading that occupyies his sister, Mary. 
                        Amid these distractions, Frank has studied only fitfully, trying "the patience of a mother" who has more time to hear his imperfectly memorized lesson. 
                        When even his mother limits the number of recitals she will entertain, Frank turns to his compliant sister. 
                        Although untrained in Latin, Mary reads well enough to warn him to be more exact (1:58, 75).</p>
                    
                    <p>Unlike the successful manipulation of auditors by Ruskin's Lucy, which leaves her parents with no option but bemused compliance, 
                        Edgeworth's episode poses a test of Frank's resolve to memorize his lesson efficiently and on time, 
                        that he may "early learn habits of attention and application" (Edgeworth, Frank: A Sequel, 1:89). His failure likewise leads the adults to confer among themselves, 
                        but they solemnly discuss the book's thesis, set forth in the author's preface, that parents should instill habits of self-control in their sons before sending them to public school. 
                        Neglect of training self-command will leave boys exposed to schoolfellows' reckless challenges to prove their "manliness" in foolish and damaging ways. 
                        Proper manliness is not to be instilled by corporal punishment: Franks's response to his disgrace ultimately disproves Mr. Birch's contention 
                        that a boy can learn Latin only by schoolmasters "flogging" its rules into him. Recovering from his sobs, 
                        Frank retires to gain control over himself and his get his lesson by heart, 
                        and then "march[es] up" to Mr. Birch to say it perfectly (a scene echoed by Ruskin's Lucy, who "marched up" to her father 
                        to command his time, but without disgracing herself like Harry). Over the following weeks, Harry proves that he can be relied on, 
                        and his father rescinds his decision to send Harry to school earlier than originally planned (see 1:86-96).</p>
                    
                    <p>According to Edgeworth's Frank: A Sequel, the danger to a home-schooled boy is effeminacy, but the undermining of manliness 
                        is caused only in part by living too much at home "'with gentle girls and women'". The "fault of the present day", according to the book's preface, 
                        is the phenomenon of "anxious private education". Contemporary home education is burdened by 
                        "too much anxiety concerning details. Parents and private tutors are not only too eager to adopt every new receipt 
                        for teaching much in a short time, but are also too easily alarmed by every deficiency which they perceive in their pupils, 
                        and draw too readily evil auguries from every trifle. They are so anxious to make their pupils go on, and go right, 
                        and go straight, every instant, that they deprive them of the power of acting, thinking, feeling for themselves. 
                        Thus they turn them either into helpless puppets, who must cease to move, or fall when the guiding strings are no longer pulled; 
                        or, if they be not reduced to this automaton state, they become restive, wilful creatures, who, the instant they are at liberty, 
                        set off in a contrary direction to that in which they have been forced" (1:54, xvi-xvii).</p>
                    
                    <p>To reward Frank for disciplining himself in his lessons, his father allows him "what I know will be agreeable", teaching him to ride--and 
                        not "the old pony; or, as Frank would call it, the <hi rend="italic">tame</hi> pony", but a "spirited" horse. 
                        When his mother demurs, his father explains: "Boys, who have been carefully brought up at home, have often something effeminate or precise about them; 
                        perhaps they do not know how to leap, or to run, or to ride; for this they are laughed at by their school-fellows, and they often get into mischief, 
                        merely to show that they are manly" (1:97, 98, 100). The earliest reference in the family letters to Ruskin riding his Shetland pony, 
                        Shagram, is January 1829, about two years after composing his "Harry and Lucy . . . Vol I" 
                        (John to John James Ruskin, 19 January 1829 [Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 172]).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="ICEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName>s <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName> 
                    said he would take him into town to see the apparatus for making ice . . . he did not see that part of the apparatus which made the ice&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In Edgeworth's Harry and Lucy Concluded, 
                    the children's father promises that, "'when we go to London, I will show you Mr. Carey's apparatus for making ice'".  
                    Using a portable air pump, their father has been conducting an experiment to demonstrate "that sudden evaporation produces cold 
                    sufficient to freeze in a vacuum"; and Harry hopes to adapt this experiment to prove to Lucy that the air pump is not limited to scientific uses, 
                    but good also for practical applications, such as helping to make ice cream. That part of their experiment using cream and sweetmeat fails; 
                    and their father explains "that, for this purpose, much larger air pumps than they had ever seen would be necessary" 
                    (1:151, 145, 150).</p>
                    
                    <p>The phenomenon of falling temperature produced by evaporation had first been demonstrated in 1810 
                    by Sir John Leslie (1766-1832), using an air pump. An imputation of plagiarism concerning this experiment, among other accusations, 
                    led Leslie to take Blackwood's Magazine to court for libel in 1822 (Napier, Memoir of Sir John Leslie, 23-26). 
                    Mr. Carey and his apparatus are unidentified.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="BALLOONGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;their <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName> took a little balloon 
                    filled it with gunpowder and hung it up at a pole in the room. . . . I understand you perfectly said <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Unless he was drawing directly on an unidentified source, 
                    Ruskin appears to have devised his own fictional experiment based on Conversation XI, "Of Sound", 
                    in volume 4, "Of Pneumatics", in Scientific Dialogues by Jeremiah Joyce.</p>
                    
                    <p>In this conversation, the father conducts no experiment on the spot, but describes experiments by others 
                        along with hypothetical illustrations to his children, Charles and Emma, in order to explain phenomena of sound. 
                        To illustrate the speed of sound, which Ruskin's unlikely experiment is meant to demonstrate, 
                    the Father in Scientific Dialogues bids his listeners to imagine: "'You see in a dark night the flash of a gun, but, 
                    being at a considerable distance from it, you hear no report. If, however, you knew that the light was occasioned 
                    by the inflammation of gunpowder in a musket or pistol, you would conclude that it was attended with sound, 
                    though it was not sufficiently strong to reach the place where you are.'" Elaborating on the illustration Charles recalls: 
                    "'As we were walking last summer towards Hampstead, we saw a party of soldiers firing at a mark near Chalk Farm, 
                    and you desired Emma and me to take notice as we approached the spot, how much sooner the report was heard after we saw the flash, 
                    than it was when we first got into the fields'". His father affirms: "'My intention was, that you should know, 
                    from actual experiment, that sound is not conveyed instantaneously, but takes a certain time to travel over a given space'".</p>
                    
                    <p>In the contrast of near and far sounds of the exploding gunpowder--the closer noise being "so much that it was near 
                    deafing <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName> and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>", 
                    while the more distant "noise could not be heard" at all--Ruskin is conflating evidence of the speed of sound 
                    with an example in Joyce's dialogue intended to show that sound cannot travel in a vacuum: "'I remember'", says Charles, 
                    "'being once in a room at the distance of but a few paces from the Tower guns when they fired 
                    [i.e., in the Tower of London], and the noise was infiniteJy worse than any thunder that I ever heard'". 
                    His father explains, "'This was because you were near them: gunpowder, so tremendous as it is in air, 
                    when inflamed in a <hi rend="italic">vacuum</hi> makes no . . . sound'" 
                        (Joyce, Scientific Dialogues, 4:102, 103-4, 99).</p></note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>