<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <fileDesc xml:id="harry_and_lucy_vol2_glosses_contextual">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"&#x201C;Harry and Lucy . . . Vol 2&#x201D;"</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses" subtype="contextual">
                <note xml:id="STEAMBOATGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName> going across the sea in a steamboat&#x201d; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi> <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02019;s drawing of <persName corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName>&#x02019;s steamboat 
                    resembles the first steam-powered commercial packets, which were driven by paddlewheels on each side of the vessel,
                    but which also carried sails. The first such vessel to be successful was <name type="vessel" corresp="#THECOMET"> The Comet (1812)</name>, 
                    which initially operated on the <geogName corresp="#CLYDERIVER">Clyde River</geogName> in <placeName corresp="#SCOTLAND">Scotland</placeName>, ferrying between <placeName corresp="#GLASGOW">Glasgow</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#GREENOCK">Greenock</placeName>. 
                    <name corresp="#THECOMET">The Comet </name> then toured <placeName corresp="#SCOTLAND">Scotland</placeName> in order to stir interest in steam voyaging, and it ended up in 1816 operating on the <geogName corresp="#FIRTHOFFORTH">Firth of Forth</geogName>. 
                    Its single tall funnel was sturdy enough to double as a mast (Batchelor and Chant, Complete Encyclpedia of Steamships, 32-33). 
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> drawing does not show a sail attached to his steamboat&#x02019;s chimney, 
                    but his actual experience of steam travel on water&#x02014;and according to his autobiography, <name corresp="#PRAETERITA">Praeterita</name>, 
                    he sailed by steam with his parents as early as age three (see Tours of 1822-24)&#x02014;would not necessarily 
                    have been aboard the famous <name corresp="#THECOMET">Comet</name>, since by that time its success had inspired construction of dozens of steam passenger vessels by the 1820s.</p>
                    
                    <p>What <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> <persName corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> means by crossing the &#x0201C;sea&#x0201D; is unclear. The phrase &#x0201C;across the sea&#x0201D;, if it reflects actual experience at all, 
                        could refer to crossing the <geogName corresp="#BRISTOLCHANNEL">Bristol Channel</geogName>. Ruskin's drawing, "picture of the <geogName corresp="#BRISTOLCHANNEL">Bristol channel</geogName>", later in "<persName corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> and <persName corresp="#Lucy"></persName> . . . Vol 2" (p. 15), 
                        depicts two steamboats among other craft, one close to the viewer and the other in the distance. 
                        The nearer vessel is chugging into (or out of) the scene, its smokestack parallel with the frame of the picture, 
                        seeming to impinge on a world of sail represented by a ship with three masts in full sail, which is towing a smaller craft. 
                        The Ruskin family could have boarded a sidewheeler steam packet in the course of their Wye Tour of 1827, 
                        described in his second volume of <persName corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> and <persName corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>, or their aborted Tour of 1828, which was interrupted when they had reached <placeName corresp="#PLYMOUTH">Plymouth</placeName>. '
                        The first regular passenger service in this region was established between <placeName corresp="#CITYOFBATH">Bath </placeName>and <placeName corresp="#BRISTOL">Bristol</placeName> in 1813, 
                        and extended into the <geogName corresp="#BRISTOLCHANNEL">Bristol Channel</geogName> in 1822. By the end of the 1820s, several routes were established around the channel 
                        including a crossing from <placeName corresp="#BRISTOL">Bristol</placeName> to <placeName corresp="#CHEPSTOW">Chepstow</placeName> on the <geogName corresp="#WYERIVER">Wye River </geogName>(Farr, West Country Passenger Steamers, 2-3; 
                        Coombes, Passenger Steamers of the Bristol Channel, 7).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="NOONGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;The rest of the noon&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In the episode 
                    closing volume one of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> <persName corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> and <persName corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>, in which he combines an account of atmospheric electrical phenomena 
                    from <persName corresp="#JJ">Jeremiah Joyce's</persName> Scientific Dialogues with the <persName corresp="#WITCHOFTHEALPS">Witch of the Alps </persName>episode from Byron's Manfred, he does not ascribe a time of day to the events; 
                    however, since <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> begins that final chapter of volume one by placing <persName corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> on the beach in the morning, digging seashells, the subsequent events would logically last until noon. 
                    More compelling, however, is the time of day in Byron's <persName corresp="#WITCHOFTHEALPS">Witch of the Alps</persName> scene, 
                    which commences when "[i]t is not noon" and therefore "the Sunbow's rays still arch / The torrent with the many hues of heaven" 
                    (<hi rend="italic">Manfred</hi>, act 2, scene 2, in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BYRONWORKS"><persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#BYRONWORKS"><hi rend="italic">Complete Poetical Works</hi></title></ref>, 5:70 [act 2. scene 2]).</p></note>

                <note xml:id="ECHOGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;saw that it was an echo&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Echoes, 
                    are explained in the volume on Pneumatics in <persName corresp="#JJ">Jeremiah Joyce's</persName> <name corresp="#SCIENTIFICDIAG">Scientific Dialogues</name>. <persName corresp="#TUTORJJ">The Tutor </persName>explain the phenomenon of repeated echoes, 
                    which "happens where there are a number of walls, rocks, &#x0026;c., which reflect the sound from one to the other"
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES"><persName corresp="#JJ">Joyce</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#JOYCESCIENTIFICDIALOGUES"><hi rend="italic">Scientific Dialogues</hi></title></ref>, 4:126 [conversation 13]). 
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> conversation with <persName corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> does not incoporate this theory, unless one considers himself, "you", as one of the walls.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CARRIAGE" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;the carriage had got to the door and all getting in drove off&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>For 
                        the Ruskins' traveling <hi rend="italic">chaise</hi> or <hi rend="italic">chariot</hi>, see 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="travelling_carriages_note.php">The Ruskins' Traveling Carriages</ref>.</p></note>   
                
                <note xml:id="LANDSCAPES" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;sometimes landscapes sometimes none at all&#x201d; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>This is <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> first known surviving usage of the term <hi rend="italic">landscape</hi>, 
                    which he employs in the sense of the Picturesque--that is, forming a picture as opposed to "none at all", 
                    the land cohering (or not) according to expected norms of artful composition such as the rules of the Picturesque 
                    codified by William Gilpin (1724-1804).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="FRIEND" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;certain friend living near this place&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>The 
                        friend and place are unidentified.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="SALTHILL" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;salt hill&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In 
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> time, <placeName corresp="#SALTHILL">Salt Hill</placeName> was a village situated a mile west of Slough, within the old borders of Buckinghamshire. Known for its inns, 
                        the village was reached along the so-called <placename corresp="#GRW">Bath Road</placename> or <placeName corresp="#GRW">Great West Road</placeName> that led from <placeName corresp="#LONDON">London</placeName> to <placeName corresp="#BRISTOL">Bristol</placeName>. 
                        For the young traveller <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>, the place featured poetic and scientific associations. 
                        The vicinity offered views of <orgName corresp="#ETON">Eton</orgName> and <placeName corresp="#WINDSORCAS">Windsor Castle</placeName> to the south, which brought to mind <persName corresp="#TGRAY">Thomas Gray's (1716-71)</persName>
                        "Ode on a Distant Prospect of <orgName corresp="#ETON">Eton College</orgName>"; and a Norman church, <placeName corresp="#STLAURENCE">St. Laurence</placeName>&#x02019;s, in the village of <placeName corresp="#UPTON">Upton</placeName>, was claimed as the original 
                        of Gray's church tower and churchyard inspiring "Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard". 
                        Since <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> was studying astronomy at this time, he may also have remarked the house belonging to <persName corresp="#WHERSCHEL">Sir William Herschel (1738-1822)</persName>, 
                        "in the garden of which his great telescope was set up; here most of his discoveries were made, including that of the planet Uranus". 
                        At the time of an 1860 guidebook, "[t]he tube of the telescope alone remain[ed] on the spot"; at the time of the Ruskins' Tour of 1827, 
                        <persName corresp="#WHERSCHEL">Herschel</persName> had been dead for only five years and buried in <placeName corresp="#STLAURENCE">St. Laurence</placeName>&#x02019;s churchyard 
                        (Hare, Handbook for Travellers in Berks, Bucks, and Oxfordshire, 95).</p>
                    
                    <p>The name <placeName corresp="#SALTHILL">Salt Hill</placeName> also refers to a tumulus within the village, which was the site of a "singular custom celebrated at <orgName corresp="#ETON">Eton school</orgName>, every third year, 
                        on Whit Tuesday, under the name of the <hi rend="italic">Montem</hi>". As described in a guidebook of the 1820s, a "procession is made to a tumulus, 
                        near the <placeName corresp="#GRW">Bath road</placeName>, which has acquired the name of <placeName corresp="#SALTHILL">Salt-hill</placeName>, by which also the neighbouring inns have long been known. 
                        The chief object of this <hi rend="italic">ceremony</hi>, which has of late years been conducted with more decorum than formerly, 
                        is to collect money for <hi rend="italic">salt</hi>, as the phrase is, from all persons travelling on the road. 
                        The scholars who collect the money are called <hi rend="italic">salt-bearers</hi>, and are dressed in rich silk habits. 
                        'Tickets, inscribed with some motto, by way of password, are given to such persons as have already paid for <hi rend="italic">salt</hi>, 
                        as a security from any further demands. The procession has been frequently honoured with the presence of his Majesty and the royal family, 
                        whose liberal contributions, added to those of many of the nobility and others, who have been educated at <orgName corresp="#ETON">Eton</orgName>, 
                        and purposely attend the meeting, have so far augmented the collection, that it has been known to amount to more than 800&#x00A3;. 
                        The sum so collected is given to the senior-scholar, who is going off to <placeName corresp="#CAMBRIDGE">Cambridge</placeName>, for his support at the university" 
                        (Cooke, Topography of Great Britain, 148-49).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="OXFORDGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;after riding on for a very very very long time and changing horses often they reached <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">oxford</placeName>&#x201d; 
                            (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Since the Ruskins' route to <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName> lay through <placeName corresp="#SALTHILL">Salt Hill</placeName>, 
                        a possible route was turn north at Maidenhead, cross the <geogName corresp="#THAMES">Thames</geogName> at <placeName corresp="#GREATMARLOW">Great Marlow</placeName>, and follow the <placeName corresp="#TYBURNTURNPIKE">Tyburn Turnpike</placeName> road via <placeName corresp="#HIGHWYCOMBE">High Wycombe</placeName> to <placeName corresp="OXFORD">Oxford</placeName>, 
                        approaching the city from the east ("London to Bath" and "London to Gloucester", Mogg, Paterson's Roads, 97, 119). Alternatively, 
                        from <placeName corresp="#MAIDENHEAD">Maidenhead</placeName> they could have continued west to cross the river at <placeName corresp="#HENLEYNTHAMES">Henley on Thames</placeName> and then turn northwest via <placeName corresp="#WATLINGTON">Watlington</placeName>, 
                        approaching <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName> from the south ("London to Worcester through Henley and Oxford", Mogg, Peterson's Roads, 114). Either way, 
                        the traveling distance from <placeName corresp="#MAIDENHEAD">Maidenhead</placeName> to <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxfore</placeName> would have amounted to 30-32 miles.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="OXFORDVIEWGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;it was so very late when they arrived at <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">oxford</placeName> that they could not see any thing&#x201d; 
                            (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>If not too dark for the Ruskins to have viewed <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName> from their approach, 
                        the entrance from the east was described as follows in The Oxford Visitor (ca. 1821), 
                        an illustrated collection of "picturesque views" drawn, engraved, and probably written by
                        the father-and-son team of topographical artists, <persName corresp="#JSTORER">James Storer (1771-1853)</persName> and <persName corresp="#HSSTORER">Henry Sargant Storer (1796-1837)</persName>: 
                        &#x0201C;<placeName corresp="#MAGCOLBRIDGE">Magdalen College Bridge</placeName>, with the groves and towers of that College, together with the rich <placeName corresp="#BOTANICGARDENOX">Botanic Gardens</placeName>, 
                        are seen near the foreground--over and beyond which peer around the towers and spires of <placeName corresp="#ALLSAINTSCHURCHOXFORD">All Saints' </placeName>
                        and St. Mary's Churches, and those of Christ Church College to the left. 
                        On passing over the Bridge, and proceeding up High Street, the fronts of several colleges, churches, and private dwellings are gradually and successively unfolded to the sight. 
                        The street is broad and long,--it has a gentle bend, or curve, along its whole extent. 
                        At every step the passenger is struck with new objects and fine combinations; 
                        and what with the tower of Caerfax, &#x0026;c. completing the vista at the extremity of the above side-scenery, 
                        on both hands,--the whole 'forms a street-scene of unrivalled variety and beauty'". The entrance from the south, "though not so grand", 
                        led "from meadows, over three or four bridges", to Ruskin's future college--"the noble towers and turrets of Christ Church, with its stately avenue of elms"
                        (The Oxford Visitor, 2-3).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="HOTELGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;hotel&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>A 
                        decade later, the Ruskins referred to the <placeName corresp="#ANGELHOTEL">Angel Hotel</placeName>, 84 High Street, as their usual accommodations in <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName> 
                        (Margaret to John James Ruskin, 23 December 1836, in Burd, Ruskin Family Letters, 385, and see 424 n. 1). 
                        The Angel originated under that name in the early 1500s, and a portion of its frontage on the High Street survives today, 
                        as shown on the website, <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName> History: The High, along with an engraving of the hotel as the Ruskins would have viewed it in the 1820s. 
                        Until its trade declined with the advent of rail, the <placeName corresp="#ANGELHOTEL">Angel</placeName> was <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName>&#x02019;s principal coaching inn, 
                        with "coaches depart[ing] in all directions from 3 a.m. until midnight every day, including Sundays". 
                        It would not have been unusual, therefore, to arrive here "so very late", as Ruskin describes, if this was their inn. 
                        The Angel was also highly respectable, described in the 1830s as the "fashionable hotel" where even royalty sometimes lodged 
                        ("The Angel Inn &#x0026; Hotel (formerly at 79&#x2013;84)", in Jenkins, Oxford History).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="ARCHITECTUREGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;looked at their architecture&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>This 
                        is <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> first known surviving usage of the term <hi rend="italic">architecture</hi>, 
                        which he employs to describe something worth looking at on the outside of a building--"father and mother", 
                        at any rate, "thought very much of it"--when one cannot get inside a building.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="GLOSTERGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName> asked what the distance might be from <hi rend="italic"><placeName corresp="#GLOUCESTER">gloster</placeName></hi> 
                            which he was told they were going to next his <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName> told him that he did not know&#x201d; 
                            (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>According to the 1826 edition of Peterson's Roads, 
                        the distance from <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName> to <placeName corresp="#Gloucester">Gloucester</placeName> was reckoned at almost 50 miles 
                        (&#x0201C;London to Gloucester through Oxford, Cheltenham, and Monmouth&#x201D;, Mogg, Peterson's Roads, 119-20). 
                        If &#x201C;Papa&#x201D; could not tell &#x201C;Harry&#x201D; the distance, perhaps <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> was unable to consult a printed source, 
                        thus causing <persName corresp="#JJR">John</persName> to misspell the place name by parsing it phonetically.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CONVOLVOLUSGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;The white major convolvolus&#x201d; 
                            (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In his 
                        Encyclopaedia of Gardening (1st ed., 1822), <persName corresp="#JCL">J. C. Loudon</persName> lists convolvulus (slightly misspelled by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>) 
                        among <hi rend="italic">border flowers</hi>, which &#x201C;are hardy plants, with showy blossoms, of easy culture&#x201D;, 
                        used &#x201C;in floriculture . . . to decorate the flower-garden, shrubbery, and other spots or borders considered as ornamental&#x201D;. 
                        Convolvulus major is listed among annuals that grow "5 to 7 or 10 feet high"; most varieties bloom in June-July
                        (Loudon, Encyclopaedia of Gardening [4th ed., 1826],
                        866, 878-80 [pt. 3, bk. 2, chap. 8, sects. 6488, 6506-9]).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="BEANSPEASGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;the black and white broad beans the butterfly like pea&#x02bc;s&#x201d; 
                            (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In his 
                        Encyclopaedia of Agriculture (1st ed., 1825), <persName corresp="#JCL">J. C. Loudon</persName>identifies &#x201C;legumes cultivated in British farming&#x201D; 
                        as &#x201C;the pea, bean, tare, and vetch, to which might be added the lentil, kidneybean, and chick pea&#x201D;, with the pea 
                        regarded as &#x201C;the most esteemed legume in field cultivation both for its seed and haulm&#x201D;. He divides the varieties of pea 
                        into &#x201C;those grown for the ripened seed, and those grown for gathering in a green state. The culture of the latter is chieHy near large towns, 
                        and may be considered as in part belonging to gardening rather than agriculture&#x201D;. Varieties of beans are divided 
                        into &#x201C;the white or garden beans, and the grey or field beans&#x201D;. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> description <hi rend="italic">butterfly like</hi> 
                        refers presumably to the shape of the blossom (Loudon, Encyclopaedia of Agriculture [1826], 
                        765, 769, [pt. 3, bk. 6, chap. 3, sect. 1, 4737, 4739-40; sect. 2, 4766]).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="WATERFALLGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;on turning a corner such a beautiful waterfall presented itself to their view 
                            that they stood for above four minutes looking at it&#x201d; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>A 
                        waterfall on the route between <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#GLOUCESTER">Gloucester</placeName> has not been identified. If the sight had a basis in reality for,<persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>, 
                        perhaps he transposed the experience to this place in the narrative from another point in the journey. 
                        For example, in the 1826 edition of Paterson's Roads, the route &#x201C;<placeName corresp="#LONDON">London</placeName> to <placeName corresp="#GLOUCESTER">Gloucester</placeName>, through <placeName corresp="#OXFORD">Oxford</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#CHELTENHAM">Cheltenham</placeName>, and <placeName corresp="#MONMOUTH">Monmouth</placeName>&#x201D;, 
                        encourages a visit to Symonds Yate, where the view of a waterfall will &#x201C;amply compensate for the trouble and delay of exploring it&#x201D;, 
                        just as <persName corresp="JR">Ruskin</persName> comments on the time slipping past as the family gazes. Probably referring to <geogName corresp="#CLEDDONFALLS">Cleddon Falls</geogName>, the guidebook describes how the 
                        &#x201C;channel of the [Wye] river is intersected by one of the most sublime cascades imaginable&#x201D; where a  
                        &#x201C;chasm is situated between 2 lofty ranges of hills rising almost perpendicularly from the waters&#x201D;, 
                        over which &#x201C;the water rolls . . . with terrific sounds&#x201D; (Paterson's Roads, 121).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="PNEUMATICSGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;she asked <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName> why he did not go on with pneumatics&#x201d; 
                            (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>)&#x2014;</hi>As at the start of this volume, 
                        here <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> establishes continuity with volume 1 of &#x201C;<persName corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> and <persName corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>&#x201D; in which <persName corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> participates in experiments in pneaumatics, 
                        which <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> copied from the volume devoted to that subject in <persName corresp="#JJ">Jeremiah Joyces's</persName> <name corresp="#SCIENTIFICDIAG">Scientific Dialogues</name> (see, e.g., "Harry and Lucy . . . vol I", 
                        chaps. 2, 8, 9).</p></note>
                             
                        
                        
                
                
                        
                    
                
                
                <!--
                5Two framed plates follow this text on p. 8, one a diagram of the constellation Charles’s Wain, and the second a house labeled “harry and lucys friends house.”
                Harry might have learned to regard Charles’s Wain as “an introduction to astronomy” from Joyce, Dialogues, which takes up the constellations starting from the second conversation on astronomy, and which supplies a diagram of Charles’s Wain that might well have served as the source of Ruskin’s drawing—both Joyce’s diagram and Ruskin’s drawing including not only Charles’s Wain but also the pole star and Arcturus. Joyce’s Tutor uses Charles’s Wain to orient his boys to the north pole star and other stars in the night sky and on the celestial globe. He also points to the many names of this constellation as indicating the arbitrariness of the sky’s mapping from ancient times  (Conversation 23, “Of the Fixed Stars,” 1:121-25; and pl. v, fig. 1).
                6See “Harry and Lucy,” vol. 1 (no. 3), e.g., chaps. 2, 8, and 9.
                7The frontispiece of this volume of “Harry and Lucy” (see part 2, MS III, “Description”) shows “harry going across the sea in a steamboat,” a drawing of a sidewheeler under full steam at sea and crowded with people.
                8The missing e is clearly visible in light pencil, Ruskin having failed to trace the letter in ink. This, along with pencil text visible beneath the ink throughout this “Harry and Lucy,” tells us that, at this time, Ruskin’s use of the pen was limited to tracing (see no. 12).
                9At the bottom of the page, “picture of the Bristol channel,” in which a three-master pulls a smaller boat by a rope, a steamboat approaches from the edge of the frame, and distant vessels are visible on the horizon.
                10This very common experiment appears in an early chapter on hydrostatics in Joyce, Dialogues, Conversation 2, “Of the Weight and Pressure of Fluids” (2:21-22); however, Ruskin’s language very closely—too closely for coincidence—matches the opening of Conversation 19 on hydrostatics, “Of the Diver’s Bell.” A description of the machine is given with embellishments from Erasmus Darwin’s poem The Botanical Garden, e.g., to the effect that “Britannia [shall] rule the wealthy realms, / Which Ocean’s wide, insatiate wave o’erwhelms” (2:115-19).
                <note xml:id="GUMGLOSS" resp="#ZSS">a substance or deposit resembling a plant gum (as in sticky or adhesive quality)</note>The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#SOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.
                <note xml:id="GRAYGLOSS" resp="#ZSS">"The Curfew tolls the knell of parting day / . . . / And leaves the world to darkness and to me" (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GRAYPOEMS">Gray, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi></ref> 37 [lines 1, 4].</note>
                <note xml:id="ALSOSOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS" resp="#DCH">This is another gloss.</note>The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#ALSOSOMETHINGUNIQUEGLOSS"/>.-->
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>