<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="harry_and_lucy_vol1_glosses_textual">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy . . . Vol I&#x201D;</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="glosses" subtype="textual">
                <note xml:id="CHAPDIVISION" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Chapter divisions (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Chapter divisions are Ruskin's addition to his imitation 
                    of the physical and design features of Edgeworth's text, as are his "frontispiece" and "plates". In the first edition (1825) of Harry and Lucy Concluded, 
                    which Ruskin owned (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="boyhood_books_note.php">Physical Descriptions of Some Books Used by Ruskin in Youth</ref>), 
                    episodes are divided simply by a horizontal bar, and no pictures or diagrams embellish the text. Beginning in chapter III, 
                    Ruskin does adopt the typographical treatment used to highlight the start of section divisions in Edgeworth's text.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="JUSTIFICATION" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Justification mark (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>See <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php#JUSTIFICATION">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology: Element, Attribute, and Value Usage&#x2014;Justification, Runover, and Word Division</ref>. 
                    In the transcription, end-of-line horizontal marks that are not notated as justification marks are hyphens connecting syllables of words broken between lines, 
                    as will be evident where they occur. Occasionally, Ruskin drops word-break hyphens to the beginning of the line following the beginning of the word division. 
                    More often, he breaks words without using a hyphen at all.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CAPY" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<hi rend="doubleletter-fill">Y</hi>es&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Ruskin appears to have modeled his decorative capital <hi rend="italic">Y</hi> 
                    on the font of large capitals used on the title page of Maria Edgeworth, Harry and Lucy Concluded (1825). See the <hi rend="italic">Y</hi> in "<hi rend="caps">EARLY</hi>". 
                    See also <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="hand_note.php#RUSKINSHANDEARLYPRINTPENCIL">The Ruskin Family Handwriting: <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02bc;s Early Print Lettering in Pencil</ref>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="QUERYOREXCLAMATION" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Question mark or exclamation mark (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Throughout 
                    his dialogue, Ruskin writes an ambiguously shaped mark that might be taken for a question mark or an exclamation mark. 
                    We have interpreted the mark as one or the other, depending on context, but its meaning is unclear.</p></note>                    
                
                <note xml:id="THISPENCILS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;this pencils are lost&#x201D; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>In the continuation of this exchange on the next page, 
                    Ruskin corrected the pronoun <hi rend="italic">it</hi> to <hi rend="italic">they</hi> but neglected to correct the pointer <hi rend="italic">this</hi>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="PAUSEPERIOD" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Pause&#x2013;period (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>See <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php#COMMA">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology: Element, Attribute, and Value Usage&#x2014;Commas, Periods, and Other Punctuation</ref>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CAPB" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<hi rend="doubleletter-fill">B</hi>ut&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Ruskin now begins to 
                    decorate initial capitals other than <hi rend="italic">Y</hi>, as well.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="JUSTIFICATION2" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;I have been<g type="justification">&#x2013;</g>ou<g type="justification">-</g>t<g type="justification">-</g>&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>These 
                    two horizontal marks might be interpreted as two successive justification marks (an unprecedented use between two words, much less one between two letters within a word), 
                    or the longer mark might be interpreted as a dash and only the second as a justification mark 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php#JUSTIFICATION">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology: Element, Attribute, and Value Usage&#x2014;Justification, Runover, and Word Division</ref>). 
                    In Harry and Lucy Concluded, Edgeworth does use a dash to express a speaker's pause for emphasis.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="DASHENDQUOTE" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Ending quotation mark above horizontal line (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>This 
                    mark may be Ruskin's attempt to imitate Edgeworth's use of a dash <hi rend="italic">followed by</hi> a closing quotation mark, 
                    which is used in Harry and Lucy Concluded to represent a pause or speech broken off, although Ruskin's usage does not appear to conform with this meaning.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="DEAFING" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;deafing&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Probably a misspelling rather than a dialect usage 
                    for <hi rend="italic">deafening</hi>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="FIG2" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;2&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>The numeral probably signifies "plate 2", the first being the 
                    <title type="artwork" corresp="#JRFRONTISPIECEMSI">"frontispiece"</title>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="HEIGHT" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;heigh&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Ruskin ran out of space to write the closing <hi rend="italic">t</hi> of <hi rend="italic">height</hi>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="LETTERS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;s&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>The letter <hi rend="italic">s</hi> by itself at the start of the line 
                    apparently is meant to compensate for the squeezing of the closing <hi rend="italic">s</hi> of <hi rend="italic">bits</hi> at the end of the line above.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="EENGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;between&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Ruskin initially attempted to keep the letters <hi rend="italic">een</hi> inside the right-justified margin 
                    by reducing the size of the letters, but then apparently decided to sacrifice right-justification to clarity by overwriting the syllable with larger letters.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="TERMINALCOMMA" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Terminal comma (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>See <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php#COMMA">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology: Element, Attribute, and Value Usage&#x2014;Commas, Periods, and Other Punctuation</ref>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CAPSMALLCAPS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Decorative chapter openings (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>While the first edition (1825) of Edgeworth's 
                    Harry and Lucy Concluded contains no chapter divisions, sections are separated by a horizontal bar, and initial words are highlighted 
                    typographically with a capital and small capitals--a treatment that, beginning with this chapter, Ruskin imitates and further embellishes 
                    with his "double letter" style.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="LETTERL" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;l&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>This mark is possibly the letter <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, 
                    Ruskin having started to complete the word <hi rend="italic">merrilly</hi> on this line, but instead placed the suffix at the top of p. 26.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="COMMA" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Non-terminal comma (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>In "Harry and Lucy . . . Vol I", 
                    Ruskin has once previously used a carefully drawn comma as terminal punctuation. Here for the first time he uses a comma 
                    as nonterminal punctuation, and does so a second time in the line at the bottom of this page. 
                    More or less correct usage of commas--at least, in the middle of sentences, rather than at the end--remains rare 
                    in "Harry and Lucy . . . Vol I", next occurring on pp. 29, 33.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CARET" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Caret (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>For the first time, Ruskin uses a caret to signify 
                    where an insertion above the line belongs; however, he has drawn it upside down.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="MENDEDTEAR" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Caret (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>This leaf, pp. 36-37, 
                    has been torn out and reattached, using a gummed strip (see MS I:Description). 
                    Since the tear line fits the remaining stub, the leaf evidently was not moved here from elsewhere. 
                    Gummed strips can be found put to a similar use in W. G. Collingwood’s proof sheets for Poems (1891) (RF MS 70), 
                    so he may have been responsible for this crude but effective mending.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="PLATENUMBER" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Caret (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>In numbering this "plate" (as the drawings are named, starting with plate 3), 
                    Ruskin scored through "4" and replaced the number with "5". The number <hi rend="italic">4</hi> would have been correct 
                    in the current condition of MS I, with its missing leaf, pp. 30-31. Changed to <hi rend="italic">5</hi>, 
                    the plate numbering suggests that the missing leaf contained a plate, numbered plate 4. Taking speculation further afield, 
                    another possibility is opened up by Ruskin's having left p. 25 blank, the verso of the page containing plate 3. 
                    Did he mean to add a plate to this space, which would have been plate 4?</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CARETS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Caret (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>For a second time, Ruskin uses the caret symbol, 
                    again drawn upside down, and multiplied three in a row apparently in order to extend the width of the insertion, which is set above the line.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="JUSTIFICATIONCARET" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">Caret (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>The horizontal mark before the suffix <hi rend="italic">ly</hi> 
                    may be meant as a justification mark, but the function of the (upside-down) caret can only be guessed. Possibly, having stretched out the word 
                    <hi rend="italic">Presently</hi> using a justification mark to fill the line, Ruskin felt he needed to tie the suffix securely to the base word.</p></note>
                

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>