<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <fileDesc xml:id="harry_and_lucy_vol1_glosses_contextual">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy . . . Vol I&#x201D;</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="MAMMASAIDLUCYGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#MAMMA">mamma</persName> said <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">papa</persName> has gone out to town&#x201d; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Lucy is speaking; i.e., &#x201C;&#x2018;Mamma&#x2019;, said Lucy, &#x2018;Papa has gone out to town&#x2019;&#x201D;. 
                    Note that Ruskin's first story begins with the father's absence. For the transportation that John James Ruskin probably used to commute to his business in London, 
                    see <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="camberwell_note.php#COMMUTER">Camberwell: London Commuter Transport</ref>.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="TOWNCITYDOCKSGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;to go to town and then into the city and then to the docks&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>For the business center of London that had come to be called "the City", 
                    where John James Ruskin's counting house was located, see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="london_city_note.php#BILLITERST">City of London: Billiter Street and the Premises of <orgName corresp="#RUSKINETAL">Ruskin, Telford, and Domecq</orgName></ref>. 
                    By going "to town" as opposed to "into the city", Mamma probably means crossing the Thames and entering the environs of London, 
                    and not merely walking down the hill from their home, Herne Hill, into the village of 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="camberwell_note.php"><placeName corresp="#CAMBERWELL">Camberwell</placeName></ref>. 
                    Later, in chapter 2, Harry's father takes him "into town" to view "the apparatus for making ice", definitely referring to London. For the docks, see 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="london_city_note.php#DOCKS">City of London: The London Docks</ref>.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="MYDEARGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;my dear&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In 
                    Harry and Lucy Concluded and in Frank: A Sequel to Frank in Early Lessons, this term of endearment is used constantly 
                    by the siblings Harry and Lucy and the cousins Frank and Mary for one another, 
                    and by the parents for the children. In volume 1 of Ruskin's Harry and Lucy, 
                    the epithet occurs six times--five occurrences by Mamma and Papa 
                    for the children, which are clustered early in the dialogue, and only one occurrence by Harry for Lucy, 
                    falling later in the dialogue.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="NUMBERGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;and how many in number . . . eleven&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In Edgeworth's Frank, everyday experiences are frequently exploited for 
                    arithmetical exercises, such as when Harry and Lucy count the strawberries they gather for dessert, and then learn 
                    the meaning of the suffixes <hi rend="italic">teen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ty</hi> (Maria Edgeworth, Frank, 1:117–20).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="DISCOURSEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;discourse&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>This 
                    comparatively sophisticated word choice, which Ruskin does not used idiomatically (i.e., he writes, to "get" the discourse "of silkworms", perhaps omitting the word <hi rend="italic">to</hi> as in "get to the dscourse"), 
                    occurs only twice in Edgeworth, Harry and Lucy Concluded; 
                    the word occurs more frequently in Barbauld, Evenings at Home.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="SILKGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;your silkworms . . . How are they getting on . . . Yes said <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> so we will&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In Frank: A Sequel, Frank and Mary are surprised to learn from Lewis, 
                    the good-natured and intelligent son of the engineer, that the boys at Lewis's school raise silkworms. He describes how they feed the caterpillars 
                    with mulberry leaves and collect the silk from the cacoons: "'I have wound a great deal of it myself'", Lewis exclaims, 
                    and shows Frank and Mary the yellow silk wound on cards". Mary wishes she could raise silkworms too, but Lewis advises against it, 
                    since they emit a "disagreeable smell . . . and sometimes eat till they burst" 
                    (Edgeworth, Frank: A Sequel, 2:275-76). At Herne Hill, 
                    the Ruskins' back garden enclosed an old mulberry tree (Dearden, John Ruskin's Camberwell, 1).</p></note>                    
                
                <note xml:id="ANSWEREDHERFATHERGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<hi rend="doubleletter">Y</hi>es I will <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> answered her <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName>&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>The 
                    <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName> is speaking: i.e., &#x201C;&#x2018;Yes, I will, Lucy&#x2019;, answered her <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName>&#x201D;.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="LUCYSAIDHERLESSONGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> said her lesson very well 
                   and after that her <persName type="fictional" corresp="#MAMMA">mother</persName> said&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>This sentence, despite 
                    its closing with a quotation mark, is the first instance of third-person narration in Ruskin's 
                    "Harry and Lucy", which up until this point is composed entirely of dialogue. This brief tag of narration is answered by a second passage of third-person narration (likewise punctuated with a closing quotation mark), 
                    in which a narrator addresses the reader ("we shall . . . attend to"). The two passages of narration frame an exchange in the voices of the parents, 
                    who knowingly confide in one another about Lucy's maneuver: the "cause" that "made Lucy not come to say her lesson to me", Mamma implies, 
                    is that Lucy has extracted a promise from her father to hear her lesson, despite Papa's pressing lack of "time". 
                    With the father snared into the narrative, the speaker declares that "we shall have time to attend to harry", 
                    and the narrative shifts to his "story".</p>
                    
                    <p>In Maria Edgeworth's Frank: A Sequel to Frank in Early Lessons, 
                        rather than the child choosing the parental auditor and commanding the auditor's time, as Ruskin's Lucy does, 
                        Frank is ordered by his father to recite his Latin lesson when the father reserves the time to hear him. 
                        Edgeworth's father is impatient of time--"'I cannot stand here talking or listening to you, my dear, all day'”--and 
                        Frank is assured by a family friend, the ominously named Colonel Birch, that "'there are very few fathers who would shorten 
                        their morning's ride for the sake of hearing their son's Latin lesson'” (Edgeworth, Frank: A Sequel, 1:52, 78). 
                        When the time comes to recite his lesson, Frank is disgraced, because he has procrastinated, 
                        distracted by play outdoors and by the more entertaining reading that occupyies his sister, Mary. 
                        Amid these distractions, Frank has studied only fitfully, trying "the patience of a mother" who has more time to hear his imperfectly memorized lesson. 
                        When even his mother limits the number of recitals she will entertain, Frank turns to his compliant sister. 
                        Although untrained in Latin, Mary reads well enough to warn him to be more exact (1:58, 75).</p>
                    
                    <p>Unlike the successful manipulation of auditors by Ruskin's Lucy, which leaves her parents with no option but bemused compliance, 
                        Edgeworth's episode poses a test of Frank's resolve to memorize his lesson efficiently and on time, 
                        that he may "early learn habits of attention and application" (Edgeworth, Frank: A Sequel, 1:89). His failure likewise leads the adults to confer among themselves, 
                        but they solemnly discuss the book's thesis, set forth in the author's preface, that parents should instill habits of self-control in their sons before sending them to public school. 
                        Neglect of training self-command will leave boys exposed to schoolfellows' reckless challenges to prove their "manliness" in foolish and damaging ways. 
                        Proper manliness is not to be instilled by corporal punishment: Franks's response to his disgrace ultimately disproves Mr. Birch's contention 
                        that a boy can learn Latin only by schoolmasters "flogging" its rules into him. Recovering from his sobs, 
                        Frank retires to gain control over himself and his get his lesson by heart, 
                        and then "march[es] up" to Mr. Birch to say it perfectly (a scene echoed by Ruskin's Lucy, who "marched up" to her father 
                        to command his time, but without disgracing herself like Harry). Over the following weeks, Harry proves that he can be relied on, 
                        and his father rescinds his decision to send Harry to school earlier than originally planned (see 1:86-96).</p>
                    
                    <p>According to Edgeworth's Frank: A Sequel, the danger to a home-schooled boy is effeminacy, but the undermining of manliness 
                        is caused only in part by living too much at home "'with gentle girls and women'". The "fault of the present day", according to the book's preface, 
                        is the phenomenon of "anxious private education". Contemporary home education is burdened by 
                        "too much anxiety concerning details. Parents and private tutors are not only too eager to adopt every new receipt 
                        for teaching much in a short time, but are also too easily alarmed by every deficiency which they perceive in their pupils, 
                        and draw too readily evil auguries from every trifle. They are so anxious to make their pupils go on, and go right, 
                        and go straight, every instant, that they deprive them of the power of acting, thinking, feeling for themselves. 
                        Thus they turn them either into helpless puppets, who must cease to move, or fall when the guiding strings are no longer pulled; 
                        or, if they be not reduced to this automaton state, they become restive, wilful creatures, who, the instant they are at liberty, 
                        set off in a contrary direction to that in which they have been forced" (1:54, xvi-xvii).</p>
                    
                    <p>To reward Frank for disciplining himself in his lessons, his father allows him "what I know will be agreeable", teaching him to ride--and 
                        not "the old pony; or, as Frank would call it, the <hi rend="italic">tame</hi> pony", but a "spirited" horse. 
                        When his mother demurs, his father explains: "Boys, who have been carefully brought up at home, have often something effeminate or precise about them; 
                        perhaps they do not know how to leap, or to run, or to ride; for this they are laughed at by their school-fellows, and they often get into mischief, 
                        merely to show that they are manly" (1:97, 98, 100). The earliest reference in the family letters to Ruskin riding his Shetland pony, 
                        Shagram, is January 1829, about two years after composing his "Harry and Lucy . . . Vol I" 
                        (John to John James Ruskin, 19 January 1829 [Burd, ed., Ruskin Family Letters, 172]).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="ICEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName>s <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName> 
                    said he would take him into town to see the apparatus for making ice . . . he did not see that part of the apparatus which made the ice&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In Edgeworth's Harry and Lucy Concluded, 
                    the children's father promises that, "'when we go to London, I will show you Mr. Carey's apparatus for making ice'".  
                    Using a portable air pump, their father has been conducting an experiment to demonstrate "that sudden evaporation produces cold 
                    sufficient to freeze in a vacuum"; and Harry hopes to adapt this experiment to prove to Lucy that the air pump is not limited to scientific uses, 
                    but good also for practical applications, such as helping to make ice cream. That part of their experiment using cream and sweetmeat fails; 
                    and their father explains "that, for this purpose, much larger air pumps than they had ever seen would be necessary" 
                    (1:151, 145, 150).</p>
                    
                    <p>The phenomenon of falling temperature produced by evaporation had first been demonstrated in 1810 
                    by Sir John Leslie (1766-1832), using an air pump. An imputation of plagiarism concerning this experiment, among other accusations, 
                    led Leslie to take Blackwood's Magazine to court for libel in 1822 (Napier, Memoir of Sir John Leslie, 23-26). 
                    Mr. Carey and his apparatus are unidentified.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="BALLOONGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;their <persName type="fictional" corresp="#PAPA">father</persName> took a little balloon 
                    filled it with gunpowder and hung it up at a pole in the room. . . . I understand you perfectly said <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Unless he was drawing directly on an unidentified source, 
                    Ruskin appears to have devised his own fictional experiment based on Conversation XI, "Of Sound", 
                    in volume 4, "Of Pneumatics", in Scientific Dialogues by Jeremiah Joyce.</p>
                    
                    <p>In the conversation by Joyce, the father conducts no experiments of his own involving sound, but describes experiments by others 
                        and poses hypothetical illustrations--embellished with lines from Capell Lofft's Eudosia--in order to explain phenomena of sound to his children, Charles and Emma. 
                        Ruskin's invented experiment, in which gunpowder is exploded in balloons positioned at different heights, although improbable, 
                        does demonstrate the point of a scenario that Joyce's Father bids his young listeners to imagine: 
                        "'You see in a dark night the flash of a gun, but, 
                    being at a considerable distance from it, you hear no report. If, however, you knew that the light was occasioned 
                    by the inflammation of gunpowder in a musket or pistol, you would conclude that it was attended with sound, 
                    though it was not sufficiently strong to reach the place where you are.'" Charles shows that he gets the point 
                    by recalling an actual experience of the same kind: "'As we were walking last summer towards Hampstead, 
                    we saw a party of soldiers firing at a mark near Chalk Farm, 
                    and you desired Emma and me to take notice as we approached the spot, how much sooner the report was heard after we saw the flash, 
                    than it was when we first got into the fields'". His father ties together the past experience and the present conversation: 
                    "'My intention [at that time] was, that you should know, 
                    from actual experiment, that sound is not conveyed instantaneously, but takes a certain time to travel over a given space'" 
                    (Joyce, Scientific Dialogues, 4:102, 103-4; Chalk Farm, near Primrose Hill in Hampstead, was known as a remote place for dueling 
                    in the eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries [Wheatley, London Past and Present, 1:344-45]).</p>
                    
                    <p>In Ruskin's devising his own imaginary experiment to measure near and distant sounds of exploding gunpowder, 
                        his lexical choices--the closer noise being "so much that it was near deafing <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName> and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>", 
                    while the more distant "noise could not be heard" at all--suggest that he conflated two different sections of Joyce's dialogue. 
                    Ruskin's experiment encapsulates discussion of the speed of sound, but inaudible sounds in Joyce have more to do with showing that 
                    sound cannot travel in a vacuum: "'I remember'", says Charles, "'being once in a room at the distance of but a few paces from the Tower guns when they fired 
                    [i.e., artillery in the Tower of London], and the noise was infinitely worse than any thunder that I ever heard'". 
                    His father explains, "'This was because you were near them: gunpowder, so tremendous as it is in air, 
                    when inflamed in a <hi rend="italic">vacuum</hi> makes no . . . sound'" 
                        (Joyce, Scientific Dialogues, 4:99).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="PIPEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Now I will show you one other experiment. . . . This then proved that 
                    water is a good conductor&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In this second, 
                    and even more alarming procedure, Ruskin appears again to have devised an imaginary experiment to demonstrate a point 
                    about pneumatics that the Father in Joyce's Scientific Dialogues makes anecdotally: "'Experiments have been instituted 
                    to ascertain how much water, as a conductor of sound, was better than land; and a person was heard to read very distinctly 
                    at the distance of 140 feet on the Thames, and on land he could not be heard farther than 76 feet'" 
                    (Joyce, Scientific Dialogues, 4:103).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="DOCKGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName> . . . showed her a little canal he had made and a little boat 
                    with some blocks fastened together by wedges . . . <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> now recollected a promise <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName> 
                    had made her to show her how ships were floated into docks to be repaired&#x201D; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Ruskin draws this account of how ships are repaired in dry dock 
                    from an exchange between brother and sister in Edgeworth's Harry and Lucy Concluded. 
                    His summary of the procedure for lifting and supporting a ship's keel, besides being slightly inaccurate, 
                    is difficult to follow, because Ruskin omits Harry's contextualizing.</p>
                    
                    <p>Harry begins with more obvious and traditional means of raising a ship in dry dock: 
                    "'Some time ago, the day my father took me into the dock-yard, he showed me a ship lying in what is called a dock. 
                    The keel was to be repaired, and for this purpose it was necessary to raise up the ship, so that the workmen might get underneath. 
                    The question my father asked me was, 'how the vessel could be raised?' I was an hour puzzling about it, . . . 
                    but never [thought] of the easy way that was before my eyes--to let in the water from outside of the dock. The water,
                    you know, would gradually float the vessel, and raise it up to the proper height, where it could be propped up, and the water let out again next tide.'"</p>
                    
                    <p>Lucy inquires about a "different way of raising a ship" that she knows their father had described to Harry. 
                        Harry goes on: "'You must first of all know, that when a vessel is floated into a dock to be repaired, 
                        <hi rend="italic">she</hi> is allowed to settle down with her keel upon thick wooden blocks, along the middle of the dock: 
                        . . . formerly when she was to be raised up, for the people to get under the keel, two or three hundred <hi rend="italic">shores</hi>, 
                        or props of timber, were placed all under her bottom, nearly upright; wedges were then just pointed under the lower end of each of these shores, 
                        and all the workmen from every part of the dock-yard being summoned with their <hi rend="italic">mauls</hi>, or huge hammers, 
                        and stationed one or two to each shore, the wedges were all struck at the same instant by word of command. 
                        A few blows from all the mauls was sufficient just to raise the ship from off the blocks, which were then taken away, 
                        and the ship was left hanging in the air, supported by the shores'".</p>
                    
                    <p>The new way, which has replaced this time- and labor-intensive method, is what Ruskin summarizes: 
                        "'The blocks on which the keel is to lie are not solid lumps of wood; they are composed of three pieces, two of which are <hi rend="italic">wedges</hi>, 
                        and when these are knocked out, the centre piece of the block falls. The ship is floated into the dock as usual, 
                        and when the water subsides, the keel rests on the new-fashioned blocks: the forest of shores are then firmly placed 
                        under all parts of the ship's bottom, in the same way as I described to you before, but without any wedges [pointed beneath the shores]. 
                        Now, Lucy, comes the beautiful contrivance—-two or three men only are sufficient to do the rest: 
                        they give a few knocks on the sides of the wedges, of which the blocks are composed—-out they fly-—the blocks sink, 
                        and the ship hangs on the shores'".</p>
                    
                    <p>Lucy agrees that "'it is such a pretty contrivance, that 1 should like very much to see it done. 
                        Suppose you make an experiment with your little boat in our canal'" (Edgeworth, Harry and Lucy Concluded, 4:234-37). 
                        Edgeworth's Harry temporizes, but Ruskin carries on to invent just such a scene for his fictional siblings in their garden, 
                        where they examine Harry's workmanship in constructing blocks and shores to lift a boat in his little canal.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="SHORESGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;<hi rend="italic">shores</hi>&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Here, and in a previous occurrence on p. 17, 
                    Ruskin imitates the italic font used in Edgeworth's text to highlight this term.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="BENTCANEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Harry now took a cane . . . broke the window&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Ruskin 
                    may intend both Harry's cane experiment and its accidental outcome as proofs of the "attraction of cohesion", 
                    a principle illustrated in Conversations III and IV of volume 1, "Of Mechanics," of Joyce's Scientific Dialogues. 
                    Father explains: "That a piece of thin steel, or cane, recovers its usual form, after being bent, 
                    is owing to a certain power called <hi rend="italic">elasticity</hi>; which may, perhaps, arise from the particles of those bodies, 
                    though disturbed, not being drawn out of each other's attraction; therefore, as soon as the force upon them ceases to act, 
                    they restore themselves to their former position". However, "the reverse of the attraction of cohesion" or "repulsion" 
                    prevails "if a glass or any hard substance be broken", and "the parts cannot be made to cohere without first being moistened, 
                    because the repulsion is too great to admit of a reunion" (Joyce, Scientific Dialogues, 1:37, 36).</p></note>
                
                    <note xml:id="TELLMAMMAGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;But we will not let our spirits go by this let us run and tell mamma&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>It is unclear 
                    whether both of these sentence are spoken by <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName>. 
                    The first could be read as spoken by <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> as a continuation of her preceding reply, 
                    "No it is not". The second sentence must be spoken by Harry, however, since Lucy answers it by consenting to his urging to report the accident to their mother.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="WEHAVEBROKEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;We have broke the window&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Both 
                    <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName> 
                    appear to be speaking, as suggested by the pronoun <hi rend="italic">they</hi> in the preceding paragraph.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="REWARDGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;No not in reward for breaking the window . . . but in reward 
                    for coming and telling me of it . . . that is it my dears&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>Rewards for honesty are frequent 
                    in Edgeworth's Early Lessons series. Frank, like <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>’s <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName>, 
                    is given two balls in reward for telling the truth about breaking a window. One of the balls is soft for more prudent play 
                    near glass. Unlike <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>’s characters, however, Frank must also punish himself 
                    by throwing away the horse chestnut that had cracked the window (Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi>, 1:38&#x2013;40).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="MISSINGPAGEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Now <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">harry</persName> had a long 
                    while, been thinking&#x201d; (MS I)&#x2014;</hi>What <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> had been thinking is lost 
                    to us, torn away with a missing leaf containing pp. 30&#x2013;31 (see <ref type="apparatus" target="msi_apparatus.php#DESCRIPTION">MS I: Description</ref>). 
                    The missing leaf may have included a drawing, numbered as plate 4, since that number is skipped between 
                    extant plates 3 and 5. The latter, however, was renumnbered from 4 to 5, a fact that only obscures the mystery of what pp. 30-31 contained. 
                    As shown by the frequently erased and overwritten page numbers, Ruskin had difficulty numbering sequences consistently.</p>
                    
                    <p>In the next extant text, from the top of p. 32, <persName type="fictional" corresp="#HARRY">Harry</persName> is in the process 
                        of posing riddles to <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LUCY">Lucy</persName>. 
                        The missing page must have contained only the start of the first riddle, which Lucy solves on p. 32, 
                        since Lucy expresses surprise at Harry's posing only three riddles altogether--the second and third of which appear on pp. 32-33.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="HARRYSAIDGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;a little book is made of paste&#x201d; 
                    (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Harry, it seems, is speaking, 
                    as he has been putting all the riddles to Lucy. She, then, answers that "the side of a book is made of paste." 
                    They then speak alternately, ending with Harry saying, "So we will."</p></note>
                
                    
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>