<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_glosses">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-01-12">January 12, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="VESUVIUSGLOSS" resp="#DCH">Ruskin’s knowledge of Vesuvius has two likely origins, 
                    one being an 1830 annual entitled Friendship’s Offering, which includes a story about Vesuvius’s eruption and the devastation it caused nearby towns. 
                    The story, “Il Vesuviano,” opens with, “On one of the last evenings of a residence in Naples, I visited the grand Lion of the soil, Vesuvius” 
                    (Friendship's Offering for 1830 4). 
                    The story includes an illustration of Vesuvius, as it was erupting, by J.M.W. Turner. 
                    Towards the end of the story, the narrator details the eruption, which Ruskin likely drew inspiration from while constructing the poem. 
                    Ruskin’s poem also bears a strong resemblance to a poem by Rev. C. Strong entitled “Eruption of Vesuvius,” which was included in The Amulet, 1828, 
                    which references the volcano and which likely informed some of the details of Ruskin’s piece (The Amulet for 1828).</note>
                
                <note xml:id="POMPEIIGLOSS" resp="#DCH">Pompeii is referenced in Rev. C. Strong’s “Eruption of Vesuvius,” in The Amulet, 1828, 
                    which Ruskin plausibly would have read: “I never with such horror stood aghast / as when in lone Pompeii’s silent street / 
                    I felt thy mighty pulse, Vesuvius, beat” (Strong, lines 2-3). It also establishes Pompeii’s location in relation to Vesuvius. 
                    The syntax and rhythm of Ruskin’s poem also greatly mirrors Strong’s, with both poems outlining the devastation caused by Vesuvius. 
                    Ruskin’s poem distinguishes itself by having the narrative told from the perspective of Herculaneum, as opposed to Pompeii, 
                    which is where Strong tells his story from.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HERCULANEUMGLOSS" resp="#DCH">Ruskin likely would have read about Herculaneum in Maria Edgeworth’s The Parent’s Assistant: or, Stories for Children, 
                    in the story “The Little Merchant,” which includes a reference to Herculaneum, followed by a detailed accounting of it in the story’s footnotes. 
                    Edgeworth geared the footnote towards “young English readers who may not be acquainted with the ancient city of Herculaneum” (Edgeworth, Parent's Assistant, 203). 
                    The footnote reads like an educational chronology of how a volcanic eruption would play out: “flames and immense clouds of smoke issue from different openings…. 
                    A rumbling, and afterwards a roaring, noise is heard within, and prodigious quantities of stones and minerals burnt into masses are thrown out of the crater, 
                    sometimes to a great distance” (Edgeworth, Parent's Assistant, 203). This footnote would have been critical in Ruskin’s understanding of the mechanics of a volcano, 
                    something which would have been pretty foreign to a young English boy.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="HERCULANEUMHALLSGLOSS" resp="#DCH">In the footnotes of “The Little Merchant,” Edgeworth establishes the spatial location of Herculaneum in relation to Vesuvius; 
                    she calls Herculaneum a “large city”, which likely informed Ruskin’s description of the city’s “palaces” and “ancient halls”. 
                    She describes the city as being “situated at about four miles’ distance from the volcano,” and proceeds to describe the devastation it wrought: 
                    “overwhelmed by streams of lava which poured into [Herculaneum], filled up the streets, and quickly covered over the tops of the houses….” 
                    (Edgeworth, Parent's Assistant 203-4) Ruskin’s description of the lava’s “burning fold” enveloping Herculaneum appears to have been informed by this previous excerpt.</note> 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>