<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Compositional Methods in the Early Manuscripts</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-27">October 27, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">Compositional Methods in the Early Manuscripts</head>
                <p>W. G. Collingwood, the first editor to examine the early manuscripts systematically, concluded that Ruskin&#x02BC;s compositional abilities in youth 
                    were effortless, especially the boy's composition in verse: &#x201C;invention and versification . . . were
                    apparently spontaneous, and&#x2014;to judge from the comparatively small
                    amount of interlineation&#x2014;almost improvisational&#x201D; 
                    (<hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891], 1: 261; 
                    <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891], 1: 262). 
                    The facility of Ruskin's poetic composition was remarked likewise during his youth--for example, 
                    by his father, John James Ruskin, in an 1834 letter to <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="hogg_james_note.php">James Hogg (ca. 1770&#x2013;1835)</ref>, 
                    commenting on the rapidity and prolificacy of the verse writing. These qualities combined with lack of originality appear to have been viewed as characteristic 
                    of the precocious youthful writer. At the same time, no negative impression attached to what the Ruskins described as 
                    the <hi rend="italic">ease</hi> of John's writing: 
                    "I do not like to check or point out faults," Ruskin's mother, Margaret, wrote to her husband at an early stage of John's practice as a writer, 
                    "lest I might make that a labour which is at present done with perfect ease &#x0026; delight." 
                    She deferred to John's "talent of writing letters with astonishing ease" as a trait shared between father to son, 
                    with John inheriting the ability "of expressing all he wishes on paper with all his papas superiority" cementing the bonds of the family, 
                    and representing an openness among them. Margaret therefore "let Johns letters come just as he writes them," 
                    she told her husband, "that you may not be misled in your judgment as to his hopes and feelings" 
                    (letters of 14 February and 4 March 1829, 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFL"><hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 176, 185).
                </p>
                <p>There is no trace of subsequent revision on the author's part of any poems, except those which actually appeared in print during his youth." 
                    Poetic  . The extent of revision in fact varies among extant drafts of various works, 
                    and we can rarely determine with certainty whether an earliest available extant draft represents an initial state of composition--a 
                    state that may have reflected more complex decisions than the apparently spontaneous flow of text in extant drafts.Interlineation is not so uncommon
                    as Collingwood&#x02BC;s remarks suggests; and the editors of the Library
                    Edition, who were more interested than Collingwood in genetic text, took issue
                    with this generalization (Ruskin, Works, 2:529 n. 2). Collingwood does, however,
                    make an apt distinction between the extent of revision in differing works. For
                    most of Ruskin&#x02BC;s poems, he asserts, the surviving rough draft may
                    be &#x201C;difficult to read&#x201D;
                    and&#x2014;since &#x201C;a single poem was often composed in fragments,
                    at different times, interspersed between all sorts of other
                    writings&#x201D;&#x2014;appear &#x201C;chaotic&#x201D; at
                    first glance. Nonetheless, the confused appearance arises from
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s spontaneous method and not revision. &#x201C;There is
                    no trace of subsequent revision on the author&#x02BC;s part of any poems,
                    except those which actually appeared in print during his youth&#x201D;
                    (Poems [4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>, 1891], 1:261; Poems [8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>,
                    1891], 1:262). The caveat is important. While it
                    is certainly an exaggeration to deny categorically that Ruskin revised, except
                    when faced with publication, it is nonetheless a valuable observation that he
                    tended to revise extensively only when prodded to so by the prospect of seeing
                    his work in print. Most other works exhibit relatively minor (if sometimes
                    revealing) differences between draft and fair copy. What this may suggest is not
                    that Ruskin resisted changing ideas, but that, in his spontaneity, he preferred
                    to explore new ideas by writing new works.</p>
                <p>This hypothesis may explain a new procedure in the documentary witness of draft
                    and fair copy that emerges in 18??. In that year, Ruskin started keeping
                    notebooks for rough draft separately from notebooks for fair copy, MS VI and MS
                    VIII being the prime examples of rough&#x2010;draft notebooks. Their
                    purpose may have been less to alter given works than to spin out new ones, and
                    there is some indication that he wished to explore those ideas privately. It is
                    probably not a coincidence that the rough draft notebooks emerge when Ruskin was
                    entering adolescence.</p>
                <p>Prior to this time, Ruskin may have worked more or less directly in his Red Books
                    without significant prior drafting. Separate drafts may of course now be lost or
                    have existed only in temporary form, such as on an erasable slate, but E. T.
                    Cook and Alexander Wedderburn take too much for granted in asserting that, for
                    example, the poems forming the MS I Poetry Anthology &#x201C;were no doubt
                    fair&#x2010;copied into the book from rough, if contemporary,
                    drafts&#x201D; (Ruskin, Works, 2:529). Evidence suggests that MS I was
                    itself the place for both drafting and fair&#x2010;copying. Deletions and
                    insertions become prominent only at the points when Ruskin transcribed text
                    directly from a published source&#x2014;a phenomenon that would have
                    characterized copying from his own drafts, as well, had he done
                    so&#x2014;suggesting that, in the portions of text containing original
                    composition, invention flowed easily, whereas copying was for him a mechanical
                    business (see &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1: Composition and
                    Publication). Moreover, in the same Red Book, some places reveal erasure of a
                    text beneath the fair copy&#x2014;text that is probably a variant of the
                    fair copy&#x2014;suggesting that Ruskin drafted and fair&#x2010;copied
                    in the same document, perhaps without much change.</p>
                <p>By contrast, MS VI and MS VIII, while certainly providing Ruskin with a space in
                    which he could freely revise in the course of composition, are often less
                    remarkable for variants in works that he fair&#x2010;copied elsewhere than
                    for works that were expunged or removed altogether. MS VI is missing <!--Entry needed here.-->. ; and
                    MS VIII contains works that have been carefully inked out <!--Entry needed here.-->. Of course, we
                    have no way of knowing who expunged such works or tore out pages, or exactly
                    when and why the obfuscations occurred. But an overall pattern is noticeable of
                    composing, and sometimes disposing of new works, rather than heavily revising
                    existing ones.</p>
                <p>In keeping with this tendency, MS and MS VIII contain a great deal of fragmentary
                    verse, often of such similar character that it is difficult to decide whether
                    some fragments form segments of a single work&#x2014;divided by other,
                    intervening projects&#x2014;or represent projects in themselves. To some
                    degree, if one reads these notebooks as ongoing explorations of ideas and
                    emotions, the distinction is less interesting than their sequential unfolding;
                    and even at those points when Ruskin identifiably shifts between different
                    projects and genres, the segments can be as profitably examined in the emotional
                    and thematic context of the surrounding fragments as in the implied context of
                    the forming, unitary work.</p>
                <p>It is revealing that the Sermon Books, which Ruskin worked on at the same time
                    that MS VI and MS VIII <!--Correction needed here?-->, to some extent revert to his apparent earlier
                    practice in the Red Books of fair&#x2010;copying over top of draft <!--Entry needed here.-->.
                    </p>
                <p>Collingwood&#x02BC;s caveat that extensive revision does characterize poems
                    that &#x201C;actually appeared in print during [Ruskin&#x02BC;s]
                    youth&#x201D; applies even to his first published work, &#x201C;On
                    Skiddaw and Derwentwater,&#x201D; a birthday poem for his father that
                    Ruskin revised for publication in the Spiritual Times <!--Correction needed here?-->, a journal edited by his
                    tutor, Edward Andrews <!--Entry needed here.-->. (It may have been the experience of revising this
                    work for publication that prodded Ruskin into the practice of separating
                    notebooks for drafting and for fair&#x2010;copying.) MS II, in which Ruskin
                    both initially drafted and subsequently revised the poem, is a hybrid document,
                    entitled &#x201C;Works&#x201D; by Ruskin as if holding the same status
                    as the Red Books, but containing what appear meant as fair copies along with the
                    draft for &#x201C;On Skiddaw and Derwentwater.&#x201D; It is also the
                    first manuscript to present a version <!--Entry needed here.-->. [Discuss The Ship. </p>
                <p>Discuss the kinds of revision that do and do not appear. Like Praeterita in that
                    lexical choices and word order often close; unlike Praeterita in that order of
                    original composition usually maintained.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
