<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#KCM">Katie C. Moore</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department
                        of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc></fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="bibliographical">
                <head type="title">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <p>For a detailed description of the kinds of webpages contained in the archive and their organization and navigation, 
                        see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="plan_of_archive_note.php">Plan of the Archive</ref>. 
                        The present note discusses the more fundamental rationale and methodology for editing and encoding the manuscripts. 
                        Past editorial appproaches are reviewed in 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="history_of_bibliography_and_editing_note.php">History of the Bibliography and Editing of the Early Manuscripts</ref>.</p> 
                    <p>The present note is divided into the following sections:
                    <list><!-- add code for internal jumps to heads below -->
                        <item>The Editorial Design of the Archive</item>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <item>Defining <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Manuscripts</hi></item>
                                <item>teiCorpus Markup and the Tension between Corpora and Works</item>
                                <item>Expressing the Materiality of Manuscripts</item>
                                <item>Collection and Anthology</item>
                                <item>Apparatuses, Notes, and Annotation</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>The Documentary Editorial Orientation in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi></item>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <item>Transcription</item>
                                <item>The Private, Confidential, and Public in the Early Manuscripts</item>  
                            </list></item>
                        <item>The Scope of the <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> Archive</item>
                    </list></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Editorial Design of the Archive</head>
                    
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Defining <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Manuscripts</hi></head>
                        <p>The archive contains, at the most fundamental level, two sets of edited primary materials: 
                            <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Manuscripts</hi>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>A <hi rend="italic">work</hi> in this edition consists of a discrete text
                                by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> (e.g., a poem, an essay, a
                                sermon, a mathematical proof), including all available witnesses of that
                                text (each of these edited and annotated), and accompanied by the
                                work&#x02BC;s explanatory apparatus and available facsimiles.</item>
                            <item>A <hi rend="italic">manuscript</hi> is a physical document manifesting
                                <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s texts,
                                represented in the archive by its own explanatory apparatus in addition to
                                the <hi rend="italic">works</hi> that make up the manuscript.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>As translated into Web pages, these two sets of materials form a given work&#x02BC;s Work Pages,
                            and a given manuscript&#x02BC;s Manuscript Pages (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="plan_of_archive_note.php">Plan of the Archive</ref>). 
                            This organization arose from our determination editorially to strive for a double centeredness, reflecting 
                            a creative tension between <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> composition of a unitary work and a dynamic conception of the collection containing that work.
                        </p>
                        <p>Historically, a more static editorial approach to the early manuscripts was adopted by <persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood,</persName> the editor of Poems (1891),<!--2 notes--> and, 
                            following his suit, by  <persName corresp="#ETC">E. T. Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Alexander Wedderburn,</persName> the editors of the Library Edition,<!--3 notes-->. 
                            They divided the early writing by genre, poetry and prose, with  <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> taking the lead by dividing his task into the Poems (1891) and 
                            a complementary edition of prose, the latter never realized under his editorship. 
                            Accordingly, in fashioning the first descriptive bibliography of the early manuscripts, 
                            &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems,&#x201D; published as an appendix to the Poems (1891), 
                            <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> awkwardly set apart the verse manuscripts 
                            from the archive available to him, describing and chronologically ordering only those manuscripts (primarily the bound &#x201C;notebooks&#x201D;) containing poetry. 
                            The division is problematic even on terms of the &#x201C;Preliminary Note&#x201D; itself, 
                            which fails to explain the presence of prose genres contained within some of the manuscripts that it does describe, 
                            and which is altogether silent about manuscripts omitted from the list presumably because they contain solely prose.</p> 
                        <p>In the Library Edition, <persName corresp="#ETC">Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName> addressed the problems raised by this division only imperfectly. 
                            The first two volumes fulfill <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> vision by housing early prose and poetry, respectively, 
                            but the former was a rough and ready repackaging of existing <persName corresp="#GA">George Allen</persName> editions. They attempted no serious reexamination of the underlying approach; 
                            and in the second volume, &#x201C;Poems,&#x201D; the editors reprinted <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> &#x201C;Preliminary Note,&#x201D; 
                            expanding it with brief descriptions of some additional manuscripts, and with lists by title of the poems contained in the manuscripts, 
                            but without questioning the flawed logic of the division. Of the early manuscripts that they found written exclusively in prose, they bound some together with poems 
                            but omitted details about the prose pieces in their revision of the &#x201C;Preliminary Note,&#x201D;  while they relegated description of other such manuscripts to the &#x201D;Bibliography&#x201D; volume 
                            of the Library Edition, classifying these under &#x201C;Juvenilia&#x201D;&#x2014;as if the early poetry manuscripts were not juvenilia (see 
                            <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="history_of_bibliography_and_editing_note.php">History of the Bibliography and Editing of the Early Manuscripts</ref>).
                        </p><!-- DCH, intros to these volumes -->
                        <p><persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> decision to divide the editorial task by genre is nonetheless historically significant, 
                            since <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself in his late autobiographical writing encouraged readers to conceptualize his career as divided between an early misguided ambition for poetry 
                            and a discovery of true vocation in prose. By prose, according to the later autobiographical writing of <hi rend="italic">Fors Clavigera</hi> 
                            and <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> meant not the poetic prose of his youth, but the allegedly more analytical and plain prose 
                            by which he sought to position himself rhetorically. This account is faithfully reflected in fin de si&#x00E8;cle biographical and editorial projects, even 
                            at the cost of distorting facts, such as <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> insistence that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> started his writing life with scientific prose, 
                            despite the opposite picture revealed by <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> own careful chronological analysis of the manuscripts.</p>
                        <p>While the late&#x2010;century reception of the early manuscripts forms an important part of the discussion in the archive, 
                            ERM is organized editorially around a persistent phenomenon in the early writing that entails both the poetry and the prose manuscripts&#x2014;namely, 
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> urge to conceptualize his compositions 
                            in terms both of a unitary work and of some larger anthology or collection containing it. In the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Red Books</hi> of the <date notBefore="1800" notAfter="1820">1820s,</date></ref> 
                            Ruskin projected his prose compositions as &#x201C;volumes&#x201D; in an ongoing multi&#x2010;volume series, while he filled out each of these &#x201C;volumes&#x201D; with poems collected as small anthologies. 
                            In the &#x201C;Account of a Tour on the Continent of <date notBefore="1833" notAfter="1834">1833&#x2010;34,</date>&#x201D; he collaborated with his father on what appears designed initially as a travelogue in verse, 
                            but then <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> re&#x2010;conceived the project as a composite genre, an anthology&#x2010;like travelogue in verse, prose, and picture. 
                            At the same time, along with increasingly complex composite projects, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> observes 
                            generic boundaries in some poetic, scientific, and theological manuscripts of the mid&#x2010;1830s onward.
                        </p>
                        <p>As <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself testified, the tension between work and anthology was a creative one, his process of composition and invention 
                            depending on simultaneous attention and resistance to 
                            bounding and containing structures. . . . Inevitably, the archive&#x02BC;s organization 
                            into Works Pages and Manuscript Pages tends to dispel these tensions by the effort to achieve clarity at those levels. 
                            In an attempt to represent some of the dynamic tension between container and contained, however, 
                            we have adopted an approach to encoding that describes <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> nested structures at least within the confines of a single bound manuscript.</p>
                        </div>
                    
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">teiCorpus Markup and the Tension between Corpora and Works</head>
                        <p>To represent the competing integrity of the unitary work and of the anthology containing it, 
                            and even of anthologies containing anthologies, <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> uses the element &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009;<!-- these angle brackets taken from math signs; these should be replaced with &#x3008; and &#x3009; --> 
                            combined with standoff markup using XInclude. Since &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; can both contain and be contained by other &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; documents, 
                            as well as contain other TEI documents, the element is the most available means of representing the double centeredness of the archive.</p>
                        <p>Typically, the highest&#x2010;level entity described as a <hi rend="italic">corpus</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> 
                            is the bound <hi rend="italic">manuscript</hi>, which <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> likewise recognized as a basic unit of the archive, and which he numbered 
                            according to chronological sequence in his "Preliminary Note," using roman numerals 
                            (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="overview_of_mss_note.php">Overview of Manuscripts</ref>).<!-- cite also ms title note -->
                            Cook and Wedderburn annotated the &#x201C;Preliminary Note&#x201D; with lists of titles of works contained in each of these manuscripts, 
                            an expansion that supplies the sequence of works as they appear in a manuscript (although not necessarily their order of composition),
                            but that did fundamentally affect <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> editorial practice, which was present eclectic texts of single works, arranged chronologically. 
                            ERM likewise seeks to display and annotate single works (as documentary, not eclectic texts), but also to exhibit the context of <persName corresp="#WGC">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> strategies for inclusion 
                            in larger bounding structures such as anthologies, and anthologies within anthologies.</p>
                        <p>For example, in the originally blank, pre&#x2010;bound notebook that <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> named <ref type="apparatus" target="msi_apparatus.php">MS I</ref>, 
                            and that the <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> family knew as one of the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php">Red Books</ref>, 
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> used the inside front endboard to make a title page for a text, <ref type="apparatus" target="harry_and_lucy_vol1_apparatus.php">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1</ref>, 
                            which he possibly intended, at least initially, to be coextensive with the physical Red Book 
                            (see <ref type="apparatus" subtype="works" target="harry_and_lucy_vol1_apparatus.php#TITLE">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1: Title</ref>, and 
                            <ref type="apparatus" subtype="mss" target="msi_apparatus.php#TITLE">MS I: Title</ref>). Having completed this installment of the prose work&#x2014;a terminus 
                            that he declared by inscribing &#x201C;end of harry and Lucy&#x201D;&#x2014;<persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                            extended the contents of MS I with an anthology, <ref type="apparatus" target="msi_poetry_anthology_apparatus.php">&#x201C;Poetry&#x201D;</ref>. 
                            This, too, reached a terminus declared by a colophon:</p>
                            <ab type="colophon" rend="center">
                                The end<lb/>
                                <placeName corresp="#HERNE">hernhill</placeName><lb/>
                                <placeName corresp="#FOUNTAINST">fountain street</placeName><lb/> 
                                <del>end of the poems</del><lb/>
                                juvenile library <placeName corresp="#FOUNTAINST">fountain street</placeName><lb/>
                            </ab>                               
                        <p>The colophon reflects the play of closure by doubly declaring an &#x201C;end&#x201D;&#x2014;the second declaration, &#x201C;end of the poems,&#x201D; specifying 
                            the end of the anthology. This declaration is then erased (with a roughly scrawled strikethrough), 
                            apparently in order to mark the end of a larger entity. That larger entity may be understood as 
                            volume 1 of the prose work plus the poetry anthology, the latter appended to but distinct from that first prose &#x201C;volume&#x201D;; 
                            or the entity may <hi rend="italic">be</hi> volume 1, which comprises both the prose work and the poetry anthology. 
                            Compounding the possible tensions, we do not know who scored through &#x201C;end of the poems.&#x201D; If not <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself, 
                            one of his parents may have &#x201C;corrected&#x201D; the redundancy&#x2014;perhaps his mother, also added a kind of colophon of her own, 
                            which dated her son&#x02BC;s beginning and completion of the manuscript 
                            (<ref type="apparatus" subtype="gloss" target="mr_gloss_dating_msi_apparatus.php">Margaret Ruskin&#x02BC;s Gloss on the Dating of MS I</ref>). 
                            Whoever was responsible, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> violated both his mother&#x02BC;s gloss and his own colophon 
                            by adding a new work to the inside back endboard&#x2014;an emblem representing the &#x201C;heights of wisdom&#x201D; and &#x201C;depths of folly,&#x201D; which 
                            he dated a few months later. It was not the &#x201C;end&#x201D; of the Red Book, after all.</p>
                        <p>The &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; markup represents MS I as a corpus containing other corpora made up of nested unitary works (TEI documents). 
                            Thus, for MS I, the markup uses &#x3008;TEIcorpus&#x3009; elements to describe two containers&#x2014;the 
                            manuscript or Red Book as a whole, and the poetry anthology&#x2014;with &#x3008;xi: include&#x3009; pointing to standoff markup 
                            of &#x3008;TEI&#x3009;<!-- angles --> files containing the texts, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1, and the six poems in the anthology.</p>
                        
                        <p>&#x3008;teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"&#x3009;<lb/>
                            <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;teiHeader type="anthology"&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;fileDesc xml:id="msi_poetry_anthology"&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;titleStmt&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;title type="main"&#x3009;"Poetry"&#x3008;/title&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;title type="sub"&#x3009;Electronic Text Generated from a Transcription of the MS I Fair Copy&#x3008;/title&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;author&#x3009;<lb/>
                                            <space quantity="15" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;persName corresp="#JR"&#x3009;John Ruskin&#x3008;/persName&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/author&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>...<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/titleStmt&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;sourceDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;msDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                             <space quantity="15" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;msIdentifier&#x3009;<lb/>
                                                 <space quantity="18" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;country type="nation"&#x3009;United States of America&#x3008;/country&#x3009;<lb/>
                                                        <space quantity="21" unit="chars"/>...<lb/>
                                             <space quantity="15" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/msIdentifier&#x3009;<lb/>
                                             <space quantity="15" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;msContents&#x3009;<lb/>
                                                 <space quantity="18" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;msItem&#x3009;<lb/>
                                                        <space quantity="21" unit="chars"/>...<lb/>
                                                 <space quantity="18" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/msItem&#x3009;<lb/>
                                             <space quantity="15" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/msContents&#x3009;<lb/>
                                         <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/msDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                     <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/sourceDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                 <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/fileDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                             <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/teiHeader&#x3009;<lb/>
                        &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009;</p>
                        
                        <!-- schematization showing corpora of MS I, Harry and Lucy vol 1, poetry anthology, JR's colophon, emblem, but NOT MR's gloss and NOT titles of Harry and Lucy or poetry anthology -->
                        <p>Further, the standoff markup using &#x3008;xi: include&#x3009; accommodates the necessary complexity involved in representing the integrity 
                            of <hi rend="italic">works</hi> as well as <hi rend="italic">manuscripts</hi>. As explained in 
                            <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="plan_of_archive_note.php">Plan of the Archive</ref>, 
                            a <hi rend="italic">work</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> is repesented by Work Pages, 
                            which comprise an Appartus Page discussing the work and Text Pages showing edited transcriptions and facsimiles of the various witnesses of that work. 
                            A <hi rend="italic">manuscript</hi> is represented 
                            by an Apparatus Page, while its Text Pages are effectively the sum of the Text Pages for those witnesses contained within it, 
                            and of any Apparatus pages for corpora also contained within the manuscript&#x2014;such 
                            as the Apparatus for the poetry anthology inside MS I. The &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; element accommodates these various 
                            &#x3008;TEI&#x3009; document types in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">apparatus</hi>, 
                            <hi rend="italic">witness</hi>, <hi rend="italic">drawing</hi>, 
                            <hi rend="gloss">gloss</hi>, and so on&#x2014;that make up the archive. Thus, the markup for MS I with the &#x3008;xi: include&#x3009; standoff markup 
                            fully unfurled would look like this:</p>
                                
                        <p>&#x3008;teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;teiHeader type="anthology"&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;fileDesc xml:id="msi_poetry_anthology"&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;titleStmt&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;title type="main"&#x3009;"Poetry"&#x3008;/title&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;title type="sub"&#x3009;Electronic Text Generated from a Transcription of the MS I Fair Copy&#x3008;/title&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;author&#x3009;<lb/>
                                            <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;persName corresp="#JR"&#x3009;John Ruskin&#x3008;/persName&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/author&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;sourceDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;msDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                            <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;msIdentifier&#x3009;<lb/>
                                                <space quantity="15" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;country type="nation"&#x3009;United States of America&#x3008;/country&#x3009;<lb/>
                                                     <space quantity="18" unit="chars"/>...<lb/>
                                            <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/msIdentifier&#x3009;<lb/>
                                            <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;msContents&#x3009;<lb/>
                                                    <space quantity="15" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;msItem&#x3009;<lb/>
                                                     <space quantity="18" unit="chars"/>...<lb/>
                                                <space quantity="15" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/msItem&#x3009;<lb/>
                                            <space quantity="12" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/msContents&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/msDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/sourceDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/fileDesc&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/teiHeader&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;xi:include href="msi_poetry_anthology_title.xml"&#x3009;<!--John Ruskin's title for the anthology.--><lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;xi:fallback&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;ab&#x3009;WARNING: Could not include msi_poetry_anthology_title.xml.&#x3008;/ab&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/xi:fallback&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/xi:include&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;xi:include href="the_steam_engine_msi.xml"&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;xi:fallback&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;ab&#x3009;WARNING: Could not include the_steam_engine_msi.xml.&#x3008;/ab&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/xi:fallback&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/xi:include&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;xi:include href="on_scotland_msi.xml"&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;xi:fallback&#x3009;<lb/>
                                        <space quantity="9" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;ab&#x3009;WARNING: Could not include on_scotland_msi.xml.&#x3008;/ab&#x3009;<lb/>
                                    <space quantity="6" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/xi:fallback&#x3009;<lb/>
                                <space quantity="3" unit="chars"/>&#x3008;/xi:include&#x3009;<lb/>
                            &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009;</p>
                        
                        <!-- schematization showing at least one of the standoff markups opened up and showing apparatus, text files etc. -->
                        
                        
                        
                        <p>Expression of corpora allows for interpretation of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> intention as unfolding rather than teleological and fixed. Here and in other instances, 
                            he seems to have been intrigued by corpora as provisional. In MS III&#x2014;chronologically, the next Red Book he used after MS I&#x2014;he worked simultaneously 
                            on volume 2 of the prose work, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; which starts on the first page of the notebook, 
                            and on an anthology entitled &#x201C;poetry discriptive,&#x201D; which starts several leaves into the notebook. Thus, it appears that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> did not just imagine filling MS III 
                            by running up one text, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; against another group of texts, the anthology, 
                            but that he conceived the manuscript in terms of two corpora vying for the space between them. 
                            As it turned out, he left this volume of &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; incomplete (a fate common to many of his works), 
                            so that the remaining blank leaves between the stop of &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; and the start of the &#x201C;poetry discriptive&#x201D; anthology 
                            became available to enter two additional poetry anthologies and allow them to clash for space as well.</p>
                        <p>Other examples of provisional corpora include MS II, a handmade booklet that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> compiled around the same time as MS III, 
                            and that he inscribed with the title &#x201C;Works&#x201D; at the top of the first page, 
                            suggesting perhaps that now that all his writing&#x2014;MS I, MS II, and MS III, and perhaps unbound pieces too&#x2014;formed a single corpus, 
                            like <persName corresp="#WW">Wordsworth&#x02BC;s</persName> cathedral with its tripartite naves forming the great philosophical poem and with the single poems ranged round as antechapels. 
                            By <date when="1834">1834,</date> <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> ambitions rose to the &#x201C;Account of a Tour on the Continent,&#x201D; 
                            which he modeled on the composite, anthology&#x2010;like genre of the illustrated travelogue, such as <persName corresp="#SR">Samuel Rogers&#x02BC;s</persName> <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>, 
                            and consisting of poems, prose, and his hand&#x2010;drawn imitations engravings and lithographs.</p>
                       <p>An older way of representing such collections in TEI would be to enclose texts with the &#x3008;group&#x3009; element, 
                            an element that does validate a representation of groups within groups, such as a poetry anthology enclosed within a manuscript that is itself conceived as a group. 
                            But because this element can nest only within a &#x3008;TEI&#x3009; document, 
                            and unlike &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; cannot itself contain a &#x3008;TEI&#x3009; document, 
                            the &#x3008;group&#x3009; element is too inflexible to represent <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> double centeredness of work and manuscript and their dynamic, evolving relation. 
                            Conceivably, the entirety of <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> could be encoded as a single corpus, with each manuscript forming a group, 
                           but this expression would conceal <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> evolving intentionality as grandly and deceptively as <persName corresp="#WW">Wordsworth&#x02BC;s</persName> metaphor overwrote 
                            the provisional status of <hi rend="italic">The Recluse</hi>.
                       </p>
                        <p>The &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; markup also allows for potentially reordering corpora athwart manuscripts, such as the &#x201C;volumes&#x201D; making up the uncompleted &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; 
                            drawn from MS I, MS III, and MS IIIA, or the poems, prose, and drawings forming the uncompleted &#x201C;Account,&#x201D; 
                            drawn from fair copy of two versions, in MS IA and MS IX respectively, and from draft in MS VIII.
                            We could choose from the start to represent an eclectic text of &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; or of the &#x201C;Account,&#x201D; 
                            by nesting the texts of the parts inside a &#x3008;group&#x3009; element, but this structure would assume a fixed rather than unfolding intention, 
                            requiring subordination of the separate texts to a common frontmatter, but that frontmatter, even if only implicit, would be an editorial invention. 
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> &#x201C;volumes&#x201D; of &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; are related to one another only loosely, resembling less the volumes in <persName corresp="#ME">Maria Edgeworth&#x02BC;s</persName> <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy; or Early Lessons Concluded</hi>,<!-- check --> 
                            the book on which <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> modeled his title page, than the separate books in the series, each aimed at a successively older age group: 
                            <hi rend="italic">Early Lessons</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy; or Early Lessons Concluded</hi>.<!-- check --> 
                            Nonetheless, if one can argue for forming these volumes into a unified work, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; the &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; markup does not prevent such a move. 
                            Meanwhile, encoding each volume of &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; as a corpus within MS I, MS III, and MS IIIA also expresses those volumes&#x02BC; relation to those respective 
                            corpora&#x2014;a relation that is perhaps closer than that binding the volumes to one another.</p>
                        <p>Other texts potentially form groups in which the bonds between texts do appear stronger than their adherance to separate corpora in which they are found. The 
                            <ref type="apparatus" subtype="works" target="sermons_on_the_pentateuch_apparatus.php">Sermons on the Pentateuch</ref> exist in fair copy in five handsewn booklets, 
                            while their drafts (some revised and fair&#x2010;copied in the booklets, and some unique) are contained in various Red Books. Because <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> entered these drafts in unused spaces 
                            in Red Books that he had abandoned some time earlier as an integral corpus&#x2014;in some instances, the draft text of a sermon running reverso and upside down to the original contents 
                            of the Red Book&#x2014;these drafts probably should not be interpreted in terms of the dynamic competition for space that characterizes <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> composition of the corpora forming MS III. 
                            Again, &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; markup does not prevent reordering of the sermons&#x02BC; separate text documents into a whole, while also allowing the presence of the sermons&#x02BC; drafts 
                            to be expressed in their various manuscripts.
                        </p>
                        <p>In this markup, insertions by outside parties, such as glosses by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> parents are represented as &#x201C;works&#x201D; in themselves with TEI headers, 
                            when the glosses refer to the manuscript corpus as a whole. 
                            They are a file type named <hi rend="italic">gloss</hi>, with an ordered presence in the manuscript, but not a hierarchical dominance:</p>
                            <!-- Same schematization as preceding, but now showing (and highlighting) the gloss file. --> 
                        <p>By its placement in the midst of the poetry anthology, the gloss is ambiguous about what state the manuscript had achieved when <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> pronounced it &#x201C;finished.&#x201D; 
                            The gloss&#x02BC;s declaration of completion was trumped, at the very least, by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> addition of the emblem on the inside back endboard, 
                            if not also by the two poems physically situated beneath the gloss on the page. 
                            Alternatively, <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> may have timed her insertion of the gloss appropriately, if not positioned it so clearly, in response to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> signals of closure&#x2014;his 
                            colophon, and his final poem in the anthology, <ref type="apparatus" subtype="works" target="on_the_rainbow_apparatus.php">&#x201C;On the Rainbow&#x201D;</ref>, 
                            which may pose its emblem of the rainbow as mirroing a drawing of a rainbow in the &#x201C;frontispiece&#x201D;<!-- link this apparatus --> of MS I, 
                            and hence strengthening appearance of closure&#x2014;however provisional that closure turned out to be.
                        </p>
                        <p>An apparent limitation of this approach to markup is that we are sometimes driven to representing such components of a corpus as the title &#x201C;Poetry,&#x201D; 
                            the head for the MS I Poetry Anthology, as a separate TEI document, since &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; cannot accommodate such a textual element at a lesser level 
                            of granularity. But if it seems to stretch credulity to create a TEI document to witness a one&#x2010;word head, the solution is responsible to the provisional quality 
                            of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> title page for MS I, which may refer solely to the prose tale, but which may also refer to the prose tale plus the poetry anthology plus the emblem of 
                            the &#x201C;heights of wisdom&#x201D; and &#x201C;depths of folly.&#x201D; The &#x201C;Account&#x201D; lacks a main title in any of its manuscripts, even the fair copies, 
                            and the starting and ending point of its draft in MS VIII, amid drafts of unrelatied works, is ambiguous.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Expressing the Materiality of the Manuscripts</head>
                        <p>For <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin,</persName> was the physical Red Book containing MS I co&#x2010;terminous with &#x201C;volume 1&#x201D; of a compound text, 
                            consisting of a title page (oddly situated on the inside front endboard, a verso); the prose work, &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D;; 
                            the poetry anthology with its title and individual texts; the colophon; and the late&#x2010;added emblem? 
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> seems keenly conscious of the uses of materiality&#x2014;pre&#x2010;bound notebooks, ledgers, handsewn pamphlets, folded sheets&#x2014;to set boundaries for texts, 
                            which he could both push against and accept as a constraint. Another justification for reliance on &#x3008;teiCorpus&#x3009; to define a manuscript is that 
                            its physical description can be encoded within the header for the highest&#x2010;level teiCorpus element (as well as described discursively in the Apparatus Page) 
                            that circumscribes a given manuscript&#x2014;MS I, MS II, and so on&#x2014;with the implication that these physical elements apply 
                            significantly to the various text corpora contained therein. Because <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> often imitated the material condition of a published codex in his manuscripts&#x2014;lettering 
                            his fair copies in imitations of typographic elements such as title pages, colophons, pages with justified margins, and illustrating them with drawings that imitate 
                            the stippling of an engraving or the wash of a lithograph&#x2014;the binding of a manuscript may prove as significant to express as the hand in which it is copied.
                        </p>
                        <!-- Discussion of how categories of intention overlap that are kept separate in Tanselle&#x02BC;s rationale of copytext  -->
                    </div>
                        
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Collection and Anthology</head>   
                        <p>Corpora range in levels of cohesion from collection to anthology. . . .</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> thought of a class of manuscripts that the family called his 
                            <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php">Red Books</ref> as embodying collections that could be defined by beginnings and endings. 
                            &#x201C;I am trying to get that red book of mine which has the Monastery in it finished, by the time you come home. I am putting in the shipwreck altogether 
                            and the adventures of an ant &#x0026;c&#x201D; (letter from <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName> to <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin,</persName> 10 March 1829, RFL 192).<!-- ADD LINKS TO MS III, MONASTERY, SHIPWRECK, ADVENTURES --> 
                            What prompted these openings and closings in a given instance is a question of interpretation, but the boundaries often appear defined 
                            by the manufactured physical notebook.</p>
                        <!-- Is there a way to relate the notebook type to textual condition of anthology / collection or is the relation arbitrary? -->
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Apparatuses, Notes, and Annotation</head>   
                        <!-- Discuss organization of apparatuses, and distinguish between notes and annotation. Scope of description and annotation -->
                    </div>
                </div>
                        
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Documentary Editorial Orientation in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi></head>
                        <p>At the levels of both the <hi rend="italic">work</hi> and the <hi rend="manuscript">manuscript</hi>, the editorial orientation of <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> is documentary. 
                            This approach contrasts with <persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> in Poems (1891), which can be characterized as aesthetic in method, in the sense described by 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SCHOLARLYEDITING">Shillingsburg in <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age</hi></ref><!-- Bibl -->,  
                            although a more historical orientation developed when Cook and Wedderburn incorporated the Poems (1891) into the Library Edition. 
                            A documentary approach might seem to threaten the double centeredness sought in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> by favoring the work over the manuscript, 
                            since documentary editing tends to treat 
                            each witness of a text as monolithic&#x2014;annotated perhaps, but not amended 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#SCHOLARLYEDITING">Shillingsburg, <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi></ref>, 23), 
                            but in the design of the archive a documentary account of a given witness can be related either to the manuscript containing that witness or to the work&#x02BC;s 
                            subsequent publishing history, if any.
                        </p>
                        <p>Moreover, juvenilia as a field of study privileges a documentary rather than an eclectic methodology. 
                            The aim of documentary editing, as summarized by <persName corresp="#MJK">Mary&#x2010;Jo Kline,</persName> is to represent &#x201C;inscribed artifacts whose unique 
                            physical characteristics and original nature give them special evidentiary value&#x201D; (Guide to Documentary Editing, 2, and see 9). Writing in the mid&#x2010;1980s,
                            <persName corresp="#MJK">Kline</persName> could still generalize a contrast between this approach and literary editing. 
                            Increasingly, literary scholars have adopted a more sociological approach focuseed on study of the  artifact in its cultural moment, 
                            while historians have come to recognize that their allegedly purist documentary editing has always been more interventionist and &#x201C;literary&#x201D; 
                            than some wanted to claim, prompted apparently by the politics of academic discipline 
                            (see the introduction to the third edition of the Guide to Documentary Editing). The study of juvenilia foregrounds the merits that historians have traditionally claimed 
                            for diplomatic editing of manuscript documents while highlighting the difficulties of achieving the purity of a diplomatic method, on which some historians insisted 
                            while refusing to own up to ways in which they compromised that supposed purity.<!--Tanselle on historical editing-->
                        </p>
                    <p>Earlier editors of the <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> juvenilia apparently took for granted that readers would benefit by an almost opposite editorial orientation, the aesethetic. 
                        From <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> and <persName corresp="#WHH">W. H. Harrison,</persName> to <persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood,</persName> 
                        to <persName corresp="#ETC">E. T. Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Alexander Wedderburn,</persName> the early editors freely and without acknowledgment changed punctuation, invented titles, 
                            revised lines and reorganized strophes of poetry, and joined fragments that are unrelated in the manuscripts to 
                            form texts that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> never wrote 
                            (see History of the Bibliography and Editing of the Early Ruskin Manuscripts). These edited texts are encoded in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> 
                        as witnesses contributing to a sociological representation of a given work, as they embody a conception of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskins</persName> boyhood 
                        as formed by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and his circle in the <date notBefore="1880" notAfter="1899">1880s and 1890s.</date></p>
                    <p>In twentieth&#x2010;century editing of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin,</persName> the orientation swung to a documentary method, prompted in part by <persName corresp="#HGV">Helen Viljoen&#x02BC;s</persName> scorn for the methods 
                        of Cook and Wedderburn in the Library Edition. (She was less willing to point out similar faults in <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> editing, 
                            failing to situate either the Poems [1891] or the Library Edition in a context of the history of editing.) The results of this swing are reflected in 
                        <persName corresp="#VAB">Van Akin Burd&#x02BC;s</persName> 0000 edition of the <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> Family Letters, which influenced Victorian studies by his insistence on treating 
                            the entire family&#x02BC;s historical papers&#x2014;the <hi rend="italic">family</hi> letters&#x2014;as requisite to scholarship, 
                        and not just <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskins</persName> literary accomplishment. Before Burd [Viljoen and the Bowerswell Papers]<!-- DEVELOP and reference history of edting note--></p>
                        <!-- DISCUSS ALEXANDER  -->
                
                    
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Transcription</head>   
                        <!-- Discuss organization of apparatuses, and distinguish between notes and annotation. Scope of description and annotation -->
                        <p>Whereas Ruskin's first editors were determined to regularize Ruskin's punctuation, 
                            later editors and critics, such as Van Akin Burd, attempted faithfully to reproduce Ruskins punctuation, 
                            on the grounds that one could detect the pulse of thought in his hand. Similarly, for Emerson, 
                            the lack of punctuation in Ruskin's early writing provided a window to how he bound his phrases each to each 
                            and allowed their movement [to jam] back and forth in the mind (RGI 27).</p>
                        <p>These movements of mind, if indeed reflected in Ruskin's punctuation or lack of it, are preserved in the documentary transcripts and accompanying facsimiles. 
                            Nonetheless, Ruskin's punctuation must be coherently and consistently encoded, especially in its idiosyncracies. 
                            Fortunately, Ruskin's inventions and oddities prove sufficiently persistent and consistent, at least for a period in the evolution of his hand, 
                            that they can be represented in XML/TEI more meaningfully than as an accidental.</p>
                        <p>Some of these marks are more accurately understood in terms of Ruskin's reflection of the materiality of the published texts that he imitated 
                            than as an expression of thought according to a Romantic poetics. For example, in order to imitate printed prose that is justified on both left and right 
                            margins, yet without having to achieve that effect in a given line of text by adjusting space between words or between letters within a word, 
                            Ruskin invented a mark that simply fills any remaining space in a line to the margin. In his earliest prose text, 
                            <ref type="apparatus" target="harry_and_lucy_vol1_apparatus.php">&#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1</ref>, 
                            the mark has the appearance of a dash of varying lengths, but it would misrepresent the mark to encode it as a hyphen, en-dash, or em-dash according to appearance. 
                            Rather, we encode this consistently as a geije of @type purposed for justifying text:
                            &#x003C;g type&#x003D;&#x201C;justification&#x201D;&#x003E;-&#x003C;/g&#x003E;.
                            In the MS IX fair copy of <ref type="apparatus" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_apparatus.php">Account of a Tour on the Continent</ref>, 
                            the mark takes the form of a point combined with a dash:
                            &#x003C;g type&#x003D;&#x201C;justification&#x201D;&#x003E;.-&#x003C;/g&#x003E;.
                            We do not attempt to encode the varying length of this geije, as the length is apparent in the facsimile; 
                            and in any case, the mark's length is a function of its purpose of filling remaining space to the margin.
                        </p>
                        <p>In practice, the justification geije is typically followed by tags indicating a line break or a page break; 
                            and the line break is the @type for "runover"--that is, the prose text spills over to the next line: 
                            Harry determined<g type="justification">-</g><lb type="runover"/>
                            to go on with science and<lb type="runover"/>
                            There are instances, however, of Ruskin using the justification geije at the start of a line, rather than at the end. 
                            It seems in some texts that he did not like indentations for paragraphs; and if he did indent a paragraph, he filled in the space 
                            with his justification geije. Correspondingly, he used the justification geije to signal the end of a paragraph, so he could start the next paragraph 
                            flush left. Examples are found in <!-- Calais prose MS IX: how code a jump to this? -->
                        </p>
                        <p>In some cases, what looks like the justification geije, and may effectively function as such, serves primarily to indicate a word division. 
                            These instances are encoded as a hyphen followed by a line-break tag, as follows:
                            now I<lb type="runover"/>
                            will show you some experi&#x2010;<lb type="runover"/>
                            ments on sound.
                            It is possible that, at this early stage, Ruskin did not clearly distinguish a word-division hyphen from a justification geijeFor the same reason, I ignore dots and fancy flourishes used to fill out and justify lines with the margin (unless, as in some cases, a flourish indicates the end of a paragraph) and other marks that serve only decorative or doodling purposes (e.g., a prominent dot raised above the line in the middle of a sentence where one would expect to find no punctuation, or stray horizontal lines that seem have occupied the writer in moments of abstraction). Where Ruskin omitted ending punctuation, I follow suit and supply extra space, as does Burd in RFL. I do indent paragraphs, althoughwhether to give the appearance of a solid block of text, or merely to save paperRuskin often indents only slightly or inserts a narrow extra line space at the end of a paragraph and brings the next one flush.
                        </p>
                        <p>Rough drafts present the usual problems of transcription. Conjectural readings are represented in square brackets and with a query mark: for example, W[ho(?)]. 
                            When I cannot make out a word at all, I supply simply the query [(?)]. 
                            Words that Ruskin crossed out are enclosed in angle brackets: for example,. 
                            Double angle brackets indicate letters or words written over by other letters or words, 
                            although I have more often found it clearer to write out such explanations in the textual notes. 
                            I prefer to let stand, often without comment, Ruskins remarkably rare misspellings and grammatical errors, 
                            supplying [sic] only when the problem might appear to be my error. 
                            One error I do consistently and silently correct is Ruskins doubled letters arising from dividing a word between lines, 
                            and doubled words occurring before and after page breaks. 
                            Except where noted otherwise, I retain Ruskins capitalizations, ampersands, and spaces in words like to day, every day, and every one. 
                            Omitted letters usually are meant to serve poetic meter, both in rough and fair copy; 
                            however, when a missing letter is clearly an error, as in the prose works, I supply it in braces { }.
                            The prose works, such as Harry and Lucy and the sermons, present special problems in their accidental features, 
                            precisely because the fair copies are on such good behavior.</p>
                        <p>A frequent oddity, perhaps related to Ruskins later idiosyncracy that Burd terms his half-comma, 
                            are periods in the place of commas in the middle of sentences. 
                            Conversely, commas often stand for periods at the end of sentences. 
                            This reversal is not consistent but occurs regularly enough that the modern reader should be made aware of it without having to translate the punctuation. 
                            My compromise is to substitute the customary punctuation in square brackets, 
                            so that the reader will understand that [,] means Ruskin used a period and that [.] means he used a comma. 
                            I substitute [.] for an ending comma, however, only when that punctuation is followed by a capital at the beginning of the following sentence; 
                            if independent clauses are strung together and divided by commas with no capitalization, I leave the commas.</p>
                        <p>In years prior to using the period and comma reversal, Ruskin evidently has trouble writing commas on the baseline, 
                            and they float like apostrophes and quotation marks. These marks are regularly interpreted as commas.</p>
                        <p>In the earliest writing, Ruskin appears to have developed some  punctuation peculiar to himselfas obscure, 
                            in some instances, as his later mineralogical code symbols. In the first Harry and Lucy (no. 3), 
                            Ruskin ends sentences with a mark that might be a question mark or might be an exclamation point, 
                            and that seems to serve both of those functions. I have interpreted this mark similarly to my treatment of Ruskins comma and period reversal, 
                            using [?] for the mark when the sense calls for a question, and [!] for the mark in other cases.</p>
                        <p>As another system of his own in the earlier writing, especially in no. 3, Ruskin added closing quotation marks only to the ends of paragraphs, 
                            never paired with opening quotation marks. Not all the paragraphs with closing quotation marks are dialogue, 
                            and not all dialogue paragraphs have quotation marks. I suspect either that Ruskin misunderstood the symbol as indicating the end of a paragraph, 
                            or that he just liked the marks appearance. In either case, the mark would be best omitted altogether in transcription; 
                            however, I have retained it, since another reader might make better sense of it.</p>
                        <p>Still more bizarre is Ruskins doubled period, which he uses in the second Harry and Lucy (no. 20) and still more frequently in Eudosia (no. 27). 
                            The mark certainly does not indicate an emphatic stop; the opposite is more likely, a two-point ellipsis suggesting a slight pause, 
                            in the way a dash would normally be used. Ruskin may have needed to invent his own sign to function as a dash, 
                            since he used dashes and hyphens for another purpose, namely, to fill out and justify lines. 
                            In nos. 20 and 27, a bracketed dash [] is used in place of Ruskins double period (..).
                        </p>
                    </div>
                
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">The Private, Confidential, and Public in the Early Manuscripts</head>
                        <p>In <hi rend="italic">The Study of Modern Manuscripts</hi>, <persName corresp="#DHR">Donald Reiman</persName> recommends that editors &#x201C;use different procedures for analyzing and editing 
                            private and confidential manuscripts from those they employ in presenting public documents.&#x201D; <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman</persName> defines these three categories, 
                            not by the depth of intimacy between writer and reader, nor by the intricacy of artfulness in the writing, 
                            but by &#x201C;the nature and extent of the writer&#x02BC;s intended audience. 
                            A manuscript is <hi rend="italic">private</hi> if its author intended it to be read only by one person 
                            or a specific small group of people whose identity he knew in advance; 
                            <hi rend="italic">confidential</hi> if it was intended for a predefined but larger audience who may&#x2014;or may not&#x2014;be personally known to or interested in 
                            the author; and <hi rend="italic">public</hi> only if it was written to be published or circulated for perusal by a widespread, unspecified audience, 
                            including such abstractions as the nation, the reading public, and posterity&#x201D; 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REIMANMODERNMANUSCRIPTS">Reiman, <hi rend="italic">Study of Modern Manuscripts</hi></ref>, 43, 65).
                        </p>
                        <p>Which of these definitions applies to juvenilia and youthful writing, which often imitates public forms&#x2014;even to the extent of mimicking 
                            the appearance of published documents&#x2014;but which, in practical terms, cannot have been intended for an audience beyond the family circle? 
                            In considering an example of juvenilia, Jane Austen&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Volume the First</hi>, <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman</persName> proposes a special subcategory, 
                            &#x201C;<hi rend="italic">polished</hi> private and confidential manuscripts,&#x201D; and frames the question regarding the intention of such artifacts in terms of manuscript authority. 
                            <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">Nineteenth&#x2010;century</date> juvenilia is special case among manuscripts belonging to an &#x201C;age of printing&#x201D; when professional &#x201C;authors realized that their final manuscripts 
                            were way stations on the road to a perfected text, rather than the thing itself.&#x201D; For mature, professional writers in the industrial age of print, 
                            &#x201C;the manuscript no longer carried the same textual authority that it once had, 
                            even when it represented the author&#x02BC;s final involvement in such matters as the orthography and punctuation of most of the text.&#x201D; Authors in the age of print 
                            &#x201C;send their work to press . . . anticipating&#x2014;and in many cases hoping&#x2014;that changes in the text or its presentation will be introduced by the printers 
                            or the publishers.&#x201D; Not so manuscript &#x201C;poems or other compositions that were intended for the perusal of a few specific individuals&#x2014;in short, 
                            <hi rend="italic">private</hi> or <hi rend="italic">confidential</hi> documents&#x201D;&#x2014;that the author fair&#x2010;copied for limited distribution, but did not intend 
                            for publication. These kinds of artifacts, typical of nineteenth&#x2010;century juvenilia, 
                            bear authority comparable to that of scribal copies of pre&#x2010;modern manuscripts, which &#x201C;the writer never expected . . . to be superseded 
                            by a more authoritative printed text. Such a manuscript had to be more carefully prepared than a press copy, because it would neither be vetted by publisher&#x02BC;s 
                            readers and compositors nor corrected in proof&#x201D; 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REIMANMODERNMANUSCRIPTS">Reiman, <hi rend="italic">Study of Modern Manuscripts</hi></ref>, 92, 93, 94-95).
                        </p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman</persName> is referring to the authority of copytext; and he points to sensible measures for situating an artifact like 
                            <!-- DH, do I need to put Jane Austen in crib sheet?-->Austen&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Volume the First</hi> in the category of polished confidential or private manuscript: 
                            in this case, &#x201C;since some neighbors and acquaintances whom [Austen] disliked seem to have been targets of her satirical thrusts, 
                            the manuscript was clearly not intended to circulate beyond Jane Austen&#x02BC;s circle of like&#x2010;minded intimates, 
                            who alone could understand the point of these barbs and share the humor of them&#x201D; 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REIMANMODERNMANUSCRIPTS">Reiman, <hi rend="italic">Study of Modern Manuscripts</hi></ref>, 94). 
                            Similar evidence is available of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> carefully prepared fair&#x2010;copy manuscripts circulating among a close circle of admiring and sympathetic readers, 
                            such as the couple, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richard_gray_note.php">Richard</ref> and 
                            <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="mary_gray_note.php">Mary</ref> Gray, who were intimate friends of <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> and <persName corresp="#JJR">John James&#x02BC;s.</persName> 
                            &#x201C;I should like Mr. &#x0026; Mrs. Gray to see Johns letters,&#x201D; <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> wrote to her husband in <date notBefore="1831-03-01" notAfter="1831-03-31">March 1831,</date> 
                            suggesting that, when <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName>in his travels neared <placeName corresp="#GLASGOW">Glasgow,</placeName> 
                            where the Grays had recently relocated, he &#x201C;make up a small parcel and send also [the poems] the fairies&#x2014;the lines on Jessy these on Lord Nelson[.] 
                            I do not know exactly what you have but any you might wish to send I could let you have&#x2014;Weep for the Dead&#x2014;O to My Heart I should like them to see&#x201D; 
                            (RFL 232). For all of these poems, 
                            there survive fair copies in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> hand, and these were probably the manuscripts that <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> deemed presentable for perusal by initimate friends&#x2014;in 
                            <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman&#x02BC;s</persName> terms, the polished confidential manuscripts, bearing authority of copytext.
                        </p>
                        <p>What does this classification indicate for the &#x201C;different procedures&#x201D; that, according to <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman,</persName> should be observed in editing and analyzing private or confidential 
                            manuscripts as compared with public? First, the class of manuscripts that derive authority from both their polished presentation and their confidential status 
                            suggests that readers perceived authority in the material artifact itself, which bore direct witness to the authority of the writer&#x2014;or 
                            of something about the writer. &#x201C;I let Johns letters come just as he writes them,&#x201D; <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> explained to <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> when enclosing their son&#x02BC;s letters inside her own, 
                            &#x201C;that you may not be misled in your judgment as to his hopes and feelings&#x201D; 
                            (4 March 1829, in RFL 185). 
                            <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> assumes a Romantic idea about writing as an open window to the writer&#x02BC;s expression, which if copied in her own hand 
                            would not only lose authority, but even potentially mislead the reader. 
                            There do survive copies of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> works in his parents&#x02BC; hands, but these are far less common than <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> own fair copies; 
                            and it seems unlikely that what <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> wanted the Grays to "see"&#x2014;not just read&#x2014;would have been a fair copy in her own hand, 
                            which derived authority from her adult sophistication of punctuation, spelling, orthography, and the like. 
                            Rather, &#x201C;judgment as to [the child writer&#x02BC;s] hopes and feelings&#x201D; derived from an intimate experience and knowledge that were available 
                            only through the authoritative original artifact; and by virtue of the artifact&#x02BC;s materiality, 
                            this experience could be extended to a trusted confidential circle.
                        </p>
                        <p>Evidence suggests that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> shared this sense of an intended confidential audience that, to refine <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman&#x02BC;s</persName> defintion, 
                            was most likely "personally known to or interested in the author."  
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> understanding of these conditions is indicated by his inclusion of a letter to the Grays&#x02BC; relation, Mrs. Robert Monro, <!-- DH, do I need to put Mrs. Robert Monro in crib sheet?-->
                            as part of MS II, a manuscript that he entitled &#x201C;vol 1&#x201D; of his &#x201C;Works.&#x201D; 
                            By including the letter as part of the handsewn pamphlet, which otherwise contains poems, 
                            <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> appears implicitly to invite Mrs. Monro to form part his confidential audience beyond the immediate family circle. 
                            The designation &#x201C;Works,&#x201D; moreover, attests to the significance of this production, both as a physical thing, a &#x201C;volume,&#x201D; 
                            and as an abstract promise of more to come.
                        </p>
                        <p>It follows that, as an editorial procedure that <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman</persName> calls for establishing in keeping with a manuscript&#x02BC;s classification, 
                            an edition of <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth&#x2010;century</date> juvenilia should include manuscript images; diplomatic, and not eclectic or otherwise &#x201C;corrected&#x201D; transcriptions of texts; 
                            and a thorough physical description the manuscript. In <hi rend="italic">fin de siecle</hi> editions of the poems and early prose, 
                            interest in the physical manuscripts was attested by facsimiles of selected pages, 
                            although the basis of selection was rarely made evident, and the sparseness of the facsimiles was doubtless legislated by cost. 
                            (Like illustrations, manuscript facsimiles on heavier stock were bound only into the large&#x2010;paper, quarto collector&#x02BC;s edition of the 1891 Poems, 
                            and not the inexpensive octavo edition; the Library Edition was designed solely as a collector&#x02BC;s set, differing only in the luxury of bindings.) 
                            The editors also supplied descriptive bibliographies of the manuscripts, although limited in detail, and aimed primarily at dating their contents. 
                            At the same time, the editors intervened heavily in the texts, improving them according to what they presumably deemed a public standard.
                        </p>
                        <p>By this procedure, the earlier editors misled readers about the family context of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> writing, a context that <persName corresp="#VAB">Van Akin Burd</persName> . . . conbut also confused evidence of variations in that context. 
                            In <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman&#x02BC;s</persName> example of an editorial procedure inattentive to distinctions of private, confidential, and public status of manuscripts, 
                            <persName corresp="#PBS">Percy Bysshe Shelley&#x02BC;s</persName> poems were arranged &#x201C;primarily by chronology, rather than by the author&#x02BC;s intentions,&#x201D; 
                            resulting in indiscriminate mixing of &#x201C;highly polished completed poems 
                            (with a few fragments) that <persName corresp="#PBS">[P. B. Shelley]</persName> released for publication with false starts and rejected fragments,&#x201D; which &#x201C;Mary Shelley had so assiduously 
                            rescued from his draft notebooks,&#x201D; readers of these chronologically ordered editions inadvertently developed &#x201C;a less positive picture of <persName corresp="#PBS">Shelley&#x02BC;s</persName> intelligence&#x201D; 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REIMANMODERNMANUSCRIPTS">Reiman, <hi rend="italic">Study of Modern Manuscripts</hi></ref>, 43, 53-54). 
                            Fundamental as these distinctions between private, confidential, and public may be, however, juvenilia highlights ambiguities in an age of print rather than 
                            supplying a unique case of manuscript authority. As <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman</persName> realizes, professional authors&#x02BC; intentions about audiences can be ambivalent or ambiguous; 
                            and intentions, like the circumstances of reception, can change over time, even respecting the same document. 
                            In the case of juvenilia, these ambiguities can be as compounded as they are clarified by the apparently straightforwardly confidential status of a fair copy 
                            meant for circulation among intimate friends, since more than one cook is involved in making the stew.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, in an edition of juvenilia and youthful writing, the greater the distance that the editor interposes between text and artifact, 
                            the less authoritative the transcription, by standards of the child writer&#x02BC;s original circle. 
                        </p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> classes some poems as confidential based on genre: 
                            what she &#x201C;should like [the Grays] to see&#x201D; are especially elegies, whether eulogizing family members (<persName corresp="#JRP">Jessie Richardson</persName>) or national heroes (Horatio Nelson), 
                            along with poems about childhood fantasy (fairies). Did she rein in the circle of confidentiality around other kinds of poems, 
                            or did she simply regard <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> other productions as less worthy of regard? 
                            It was his parents, moreover, who decided the wider, if still select audience for the elegies 
                            along with whatever letters <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> singled out for the &#x201C;small parcel.&#x201C; 
                            Much or even most of the time, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> may equally have taken that potential audience for granted. 
                             But some of the time, 
                            he may have regarded his letters as more narrowly confidential or some writings even as private, 
                            whatever his parents may have assumed.Even on the level of a unique manuscript witness of a given juvenile text, however, 
                            authority can be complicated by tensions. As remarked above, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> intentions included an awareness of tensions 
                        between competing boundaries of work and of manuscript, tensions to which he responded creatively; 
                        and his authority over text and/or manuscript was potentially shared&#x2014;often willingly, sometimes submissively, and perhaps sometimes unwillingly&#x2014;with 
                        his parents and, at times, with his cousin, <persName corresp="#MBR">Mary Richardson.</persName> These complications do not scuttle the basic usefulness of <persName corresp="#DHR">Reiman&#x02BC;s</persName> categorizing of modern manuscripts 
                        by intended audience. Reiman
                        
                        </p>
                            <p>Circumstances could also tilt texts, and perhaps <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> polished confidential manuscripts, toward the public. 
                                In the letter recommending her son&#x02BC;s writings to the Grays, <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> reveals that <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> 
                            carried many of these documents with him on his travels. Why? Did he cherish John&#x02BC;s writings only privately, or could he be moved by fatherly pride 
                            to exhibit them to customers or fellow travelers? Hardly less speculative is the process by which some works, 
                            which had circulated in confidential manuscript, became publications by &#x201C;J. R.&#x201C; As argued in the apparatus for 
                            &#x201C;Account of a Tour on the Continent,&#x201D; the precocious fair copy of this ambitious work might have gained <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> entree 
                                to the man of taste, <persName corresp="#SR">Samuel Rogers,</persName> and his celebrated palace of art. 
                        </p>
                        
                    </div>
                </div>
                    
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Scope of <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi></head>
                    <p>For a descriptive survey of the manuscripts planned for inclusion in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>, 
                        see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="overview_of_mss_note.php">Overview of the Manuscripts</ref>.
                    </p>
                    <p>Chronologically, a starting point for the scope of <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> would appear easily determined by the earliest available manuscripts in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> hand. 
                        
                        However, the elusiveness of beginnings was proved by <persName corresp="#HGV">Helen Viljoen,</persName> whose interest in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> early writings drove her farther back to his "Scottish heritage" in order to understand <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> parents. 
                        The personalities and influence of <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> and of <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret Ruskin,</persName> <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen</persName> believed, were foundational to any understanding of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> as a writer 
                        (<!-- SUPPLY SCOTTISH HERITAGE CITATION; ADD NOTE FOR VILJOEN -->).
                        <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> is not primarily a biographical resource, but an archive supporting the study of childhood and youthful writing, a purpose 
                        that narrows the scope to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> own writing, and not his parents&#x02BC; and relatives&#x02BC;, except as others&#x02BC; writing occurs in the early manuscripts.
                        Still, if the study of childhood writing establishes a reasonable terminus a quo in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> own juvenilia, that aim opens up difficulties in determining a terminus ad quem for the archive.</p>
                    <p>The parameters proposed for many <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth&#x2010;century</date> authors&#x02BC; &#x201C;apprentice&#x201D; work point up the inadequate critical attention to juvenilia. 
                        As Juliet McMaster and Christine Alexander remark, 
                        in their contributions to a seminal collection on the <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth&#x2010;century</date> child writer, the peculiarly pejorative connotations of the term <hi rend="italic">juvenilia</hi> in literary criticism 
                        has caused, for example, the separation between the Bront&#x00EB; sisters&#x02BC; early writing (assumed to be inferior) and their novels (called "mature") to be regarded as a "problem" in a derogatory sense, 
                        with the <hi rend="italic">juvenile</hi> understood to persist as a kind of infection into the later work. On the same uncritical grounds, 
                        the term <hi rend="italic">juvenilia</hi> has been applied to the entirety of Branwell Bront&#x00EB;&#x02BC;s work, although he died at age 31 
                        (<!-- REFERENCE --> 3, 71-72). The term continues to be applied quizzically to writers in our own time: in the <date notBefore="1970" notAfter="1979">1970s,</date> the publisher of the novelist <persName corresp="#PKF">Penelope Fitzgerald</persName> struggled 
                        to situate her first novel, <hi rend="italic">The Golden Child</hi>, in the writer&#x02BC;s corpus, declaring the work to be &#x201C;the only piece of juvenilia I know of by a sixty&#x2010;one year old&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GORDONFITZGERALD">Gordon, "C&#x02BC;est qu&#x02BC; elle a v&#x00E9;cu"</ref>). Such pronouncements not only beg questions about the definition of 
                        <hi rend="italic">juvenilia</hi> but also suggest an indifference to authors&#x02BC; early writing as a critical focus.</p>
                    <p>Pejorative views of major authors&#x02BC; childhood writing have a deep history, not least among writers themselves, and much remains to be studied in order to examine these prejudices critically. 
                        In this archive, hostility to the study specifically of <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth&#x2010;century</date> writers is explored in attitudes surrounding 
                        (<ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.php">The Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>), 
                        a fin de si&#x00E8;cle practice that significantly influenced the bibliography and editing of the <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> juvenilia. 
                        Whereas many &#x201C;modern&#x201D; authors expressed embarrassment about their juvenilia&#x2014;and directed their anger at collectors who sought out early publications, and at the dealers, publishers, bibliographers, 
                        and editors who supported this collecting fashion&#x2014;<persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> willingly risked 
                        &#x201C;whatever charge of folly may come on me&#x201D; by printing his <date when="1828">1828</date> poem, <ref type="apparatus" subtype="work" target="glenfarg_apparatus.php">&#x201C;Glenfarg&#x201D;</ref>, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">The Queen of the Air</hi> (1869). The comment suggests that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin,</persName> 
                        at least in his later writing, was unusual in giving any serious attention at all to the critical status of juvenilia; 
                        and his justification&#x2014;that &#x201C;the weak little rhyme already&#x201D; demonstrated &#x201C;all that I ever could be, and all that I cannot be&#x201D;&#x2014;suggests he would have considered an attempt 
                        to define the dividing line between juvenilia and mature work to be futile 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKS">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 19:396).</p>
                    <p>The difficulty of defining a terminus ad quem for juvenilia also returns us to <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen&#x02BC;s</persName> enigma in establishing a starting point, 
                        in that the continuities of self that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> claimed between his early and later writing reopen the question of continuities between the self who writes and others who write in response. 
                        In his masterful edition, <hi rend="italic">The Ruskin Family Letters</hi>, <persName corresp="#VAB">Van Akin Burd</persName> included the full, available correspondence not only between <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and his parents 
                        but also between <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> and <persName corresp="#MR">Margaret</persName> and even between the latter and <hi rend="italic">their</hi> parents. 
                        <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd</persName> does not justify this inclusiveness directly, but allows the rationale to evolve implicitly from his critique of the biographical tradition, 
                        which had omitted reference to much of this correspondence. The critical issue, for <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd,</persName> was marked by <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen&#x02BC;s</persName> identification of two, seemingly conflicting principles, 
                        which she perceived as setting the scope for materials included in the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref>: namely, that &#x201C;nothing should be made public which might reflect adversely, 
                        from [the editors&#x02BC;] point of view, either upon <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> or upon any member of the family&#x201D;; 
                        and yet that &#x201C;all that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> said autobiographically, especially in <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>, about his life and that of his parents should be given unqualified editorial support&#x201D; 
                        (<!-- RFL xxviii, and see xvi-xxxvi; and see Viljoen Scottish 16-17?? -->). <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd</persName> shared <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen&#x02BC;s</persName> determination that the first principle should no longer interfere with the second, 
                        but he also hinted that his publication of the full scope of the family letters would likely force a reassessment of <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen&#x02BC;s</persName> rather strident views 
                        on the personalities of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> parents and their influence on their son. Particularly open to question on the evidence of the family letters was <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen&#x02BC;s</persName> view 
                        of <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> as a tyrant and narcissist (<!-- xxxvii-xliii RFL xxxv; Scottish, 143, 151?? check Dark Star-->). 
                        Another possibility offered by <hi rend="italic">The Ruskin Family Letters</hi>, which <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd</persName> did not touch on, but which the edition prompts, is evidence of collaboration 
                        between <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and his parents in the early manuscripts&#x2014;evidence
                        that <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen,</persName> given her assessments of the parents&#x02BC; personalities, was unlikely to detect, 
                        except in the form parental impositions on the genius of their son.<!-- cite my TEXT article here --> 
                        An inherently collaborative aspect of child writing as a family enterprise, so obvious in the case of the Bront&#x00EB; juvenilia, is another insufficiently explored critical question 
                        that problematizes the scope of an archive of juvenilia.</p>
                    <p>Thus, in establishing the scope as well as editorial methodology of a corpus of juvenilia, the aim should be to encourage new questions about a category of <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth&#x2010;century</date> writing that Alexander and McMaster call "almost a genre" 
                        (<!-- p 3 -->&#x2014;questions that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and other <date notBefore="1837-06-20" notAfter="1901-01-22">Victorian</date> writers recognized, if their responses were sometimes derisive, hostile, and dismissive. 
                        In ERM, the modifier <hi rend="italic">early</hi> is based on a precedent set by the Library Edition, not because the editors were particularly thoughtful in their choice&#x2014;"by &#x02BC;early&#x02BC; writings,&#x201C; 
                        they wrote, &#x201C;is meant such as were composed previously to the first volume of <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters</hi>," and they tended to use the term interchangeably with <hi rend="italic">juvenilia</hi> 
                        (<!-- 1:xxiii -->)&#x2014;but because the neutrality of the term offers the advantage of leaving questions open for investigation. In <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> early manuscripts, what is the relation 
                        between <hi rend="italic">childhood writing</hi> and <hi rend="italic">youthful writing</hi>? Between <hi rend="italic">amateur status</hi> and <hi rend="italic">professional writer</hi>? 
                        Between the personae of <hi rend="italic">J.R.</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Kata Phusin</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Graduate of Oxford</hi>? 
                        Between <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> personae and the publications that featured them, and between these publications and the family circle in which <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> initially tried out these personae? 
                        Many of the publications that featured <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> first publications placed him in dialogue&#x2014;with artists and other writers in the literary annuals, and 
                        with amateur scientists in the <hi rend="italic">Magazine of Natural History</hi>&#x2014;and these dialogues may have been reflected the society of the minor art and literary professionals that <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> 
                        hosted at the family dining table&#x2014;presumably in part for his son&#x02BC;s benefit. To support such explorations, ERM&#x02BC;s goal is to be as comprehensive as possible in scope and, as discussed below, 
                        flexible in editorial and encoding methodology.</p>
                    <p>At the same time, practical and reasonable limitations on the scope of the archive are set by the relation of the archive to other editions in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> studies. 
                        <persName corresp="#VAB">Van Akin Burd</persName> granted permission for <hi rend="italic">The Ruskin Family Letters</hi> to be incorporated into <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> so long as we maintained his edition&#x02BC;s exact integrity. 
                        Burd&#x02BC;s conditions effectively require a stand&#x2010;off, searchable electronic reproduction of his edition, a comparatively low priority since the edition remains so readily available in paper form. 
                        Moreover, thanks to the extraordinary quality of <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd&#x02BC;s</persName> editing, there is no call at present for new transcription of the letters. When transcribing the juvenilia at the Beinecke Library, 
                            David Hanson checked the accuracy of <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd&#x02BC;s</persName> transcriptions of the letters&#x2014;not exhaustively, but sufficiently 
                        to conclude that this labor would result in only minor disagreements over the text of the letters. Thus, the scoope of ERM is limited to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> early writings exclusive of the letters.</p>
                    <p>ERM does re&#x2010;edit the poems contained in <hi rend="italic">The Ruskin Family Letters</hi>, since <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd</persName> included only those poems whose fair copies could be considered epistolary presentations. 
                        For those works, <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd</persName> did not attempt thorough, systematic comparison or collation with drafts and other fair copies and published versions; and this thoroughness, 
                        including transcription and editing of epistolary versions, is the province of ERM. We have therefore captured images of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> letters to his parents at the Beinecke Library, 
                        as these are required to support the editing of the other juvenilia.</p>
                    <p>This division of labor with <hi rend="italic">The Ruskin Family Letters</hi> also justifies ERM in taking <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> &#x201C;own&#x201D; earliest writing in his hand as its starting point, 
                        without reaching earlier into family papers, except for purposes of annotating the edition. 
                        The endpoint of ERM reflects Burd&#x02BC;s choice to close <hi rend="italic">The Ruskin Family Letters</hi> in <date when="1843-06">June 1843,</date> when the first volume of <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters</hi> appeared. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters I</hi> was also selected by the Lancaster University Ruskin Programme as the most productive starting point for a digital reediting of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> major works.<!-- cite ed --> 
                        This date remains a justifiable target for ERM, not only because publication of <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters I</hi> represents a convenient and long&#x2010;standing fulcrum in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> scholarship, 
                        but also because the range of <date notBefore="1826" notAfter="1843">1826 to 1843</date> is sufficiently expansive for the reader to explore the definintion of <hi rend="italic">juvenilia</hi> and related questions. Nonetheless, since <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                        did not cease in <date when="1843">1843</date> writing poetry and publishing in the gift annuals, the investigation of his relation to this venue of publication requires extension of the scope 
                        in this one respect into the later 1840s. The manuscripts included are surveyed in <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="overview_of_mss_note.php">Overview of the Manuscripts</ref></p>
                    <p>Another superior published edition of an early <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> manuscript is A Tour to the Lakes in Cumberland, the account of the joint travel diary by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and his cousin, <persName corresp="#MBR">Mary Richardson,</persName> 
                        edited by <persName corresp="#JSD">James S. Dearden</persName> and <persName corresp="#VAB">Van Akin Burd.</persName> Again, as <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd</persName> and <persName corresp="#JSD">Dearden</persName> stipulate that any use of their editorial work is to be copied &#x201C;as it stands, introducing comments or variants as an addendum&#x201D; 
                        (Van Akin Burd to David C. Hanson, 14 August 2003; James S. Dearden to David C. Hanson, 3 September 2003), what would amount to a stand&#x2010;off, searchable reproduction of their widely available edition 
                        need not take high priority. However, inclusion of this manuscript in an electronic archive provides new benefits for investigating travel and collaborative writing in the Ruskin family, 
                        and therefore it is re&#x2010;edited on ERM&#x02BC;s terms, while pointing the reader to Burd&#x02BC;s and Dearden&#x02BC;s edition as an invaluable complement. Less valuable from a textual standpoint is 
                        <persName corresp="#JSD">James Dearden&#x02BC;s</persName> <date when="1969">1969</date> edition of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> <date when="1830">1830</date> Lake District tour poem, &#x201C;Iteriad.&#x201D; For copytext, <persName corresp="#JSD">Dearden</persName> relied on the transcript of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> fair copy 
                        that <persName corresp="#ETC">Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName> prepared for use in the Library Edition. While adequate for <persName corresp="#JSD">Dearden&#x02BC;s</persName> intended audience at the time, general readers interested in the history of tourism in the Lakes, 
                        <persName corresp="#ETC">Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn&#x02BC;s</persName> transcript has little scholarly interest owing to its errors, the editors&#x02BC; policy of freely repunctuating juvenilia, and their neglect of the poem&#x02BC;s draft. 
                        <persName corresp="#JSD">Dearden</persName> has given permission, however, to quote from his lively notes for the edition. Unpublished scholarly attention to the juvenilia, which is quoted and referenced in ERM, 
                        includes the unfinished biography of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> by <persName corresp="#HGV">Helen Viljoen,</persName> and her edition of the Sermons on the Pentateuch, now among the Viljoen Papers (see Spates, "Dark Star"; 
                        and <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd,</persName> "Ruskin&#x02BC;s Testament of His Boyhood Faith").</p>
                    <p>Earlier editions themselves form a portion of the edited materials in ERM. For most readers, the primary source for the early <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> remains the first two volumes of the Library Edition, 
                        edited by <persName corresp="#ETC">E. T. Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Alexander Wedderburn,</persName> which in turn incorporate the Poems (1891), edited by <persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood,</persName> and the editions of eqrly prose compiled by <persName corresp="#GA">George Allen</persName> in the <date notBefore="1890" notAfter="1899">1890s.</date> 
                        The editorial inadequacies of these editions are discussed in 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="history_of_bibliography_and_editing_note.php">History of the Bibliography and Editing of the Early Manuscripts</ref>, 
                        and below in The Documentary Editorial Orientation in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>. Rather than simply displacing these editions, however, ERM treats their orientation to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> texts as itself 
                        historically and biographically valuable, reflecting fin de si&#x00E8;cle attitudes (including <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> own) about juvenilia in general and <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> juvenilia and boyhood in particular. 
                        Transcripts of <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s,</persName> <persName corresp="#GA">Allen&#x02BC;s,</persName> and <persName corresp="#ETC">Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn&#x02BC;s</persName> edited texts are therefore included for collation and comparison with ERM&#x02BC;s transcripts of the manuscripts.
                    </p>
                    <p>Of course, the notes, bibliographies, and editorial apparatuses for these earlier editions contain much that is valuable&#x2014;indeed, in some respects foundational&#x2014;for editing the early manuscripts, 
                        and these resources are referenced throughout ERM. The archive also upholds <persName corresp="#VAB">Burd&#x02BC;s</persName> and <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen&#x02BC;s</persName> standards of rich annotation by quoting from family and related papers, 
                        as opportunity allows. <!-- link following to bibliography and bio notes -->
                        Unpublished <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> manuscripts that have been transcribed for this use include: <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> autobiographical reflections on his childhood and early writing, 
                        such as the manuscript of Praeterita; his correspondence with Sarah Corlass; and his correspondence with Susan Beever. Besides manuscript sources, 
                        rare printed sources include <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> childhood books, some of which contain drawings and marginalia, and copies of the gift annuals, magazines, and other venues for his early publications.</p>
                    <p>Unpublished manuscripts by members of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> circle, which have been collected to annotate the edition, include: 
                        <persName corresp="#MBR">Mary Richardson&#x02BC;s</persName> diary and sketchbook; <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> earlier diaries and some unpublished letters of later years regarding <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> poems; 
                        <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> and <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> correspondence with the editor, <persName corresp="#WHH">W. H. Harrison,</persName> concerning publication of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> poems in annuals throughout the <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1849">1830s and 1840s, </date>
                        and concerning the publication of Poems by J.R. in 1850; <persName corresp="#WHH">Harrison&#x02BC;s</persName> marked set of printer&#x02BC;s proofs for Poems by J.R.; 
                        <persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> marked set of printer&#x02BC;s proofs of Poems (1891); <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood&#x02BC;s</persName> annotated catalog for his 1900 exhibition of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> drawings and manuscripts; 
                        and <persName corresp="#GA">George Allen&#x02BC;s</persName> correspondence with <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin, Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> editors and executors, and Allens family. Later editors&#x02BC; papers include: 
                        <persName corresp="#ETC">Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn&#x02BC;s</persName> records of editing the Library Edition, such as their scrapbook of newspaper clippings of reviews and other notices, 
                        their annotations of Poems (1891), and bound volumes of transcripts; and the <persName corresp="#HGV">Viljoen</persName> Papers. Some materials that it is hoped can be sifted in the future include juvenilia by the 
                        children of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> first tutor, Edward Andrews; and the records of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> years as an Oxford undergraduate.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    
                
                   <!--      Cataloging the early drawings lies beyond the
                        financing of this edition as well as beyond the editors expertise; however, the
                        so-called first sketchbook (in fact, probably the first two sketchbooks) are
                        included and reproduced as one of the early manuscripts since it includes
                        significant passages of writing, and other important drawings will be discussed
                        throughout the edition in connection with the writings. Public domain images,
                        such as published engravings, are included where useful. The Beinecke Library of
                        Yale University cares for the largest collection: twelve holograph notebooks
                        plus bound letters and a box of loose sheets. All but one of the notebooks,
                        along with the loose items (some formerly bound), correspond to the designations
                        MSS I, IA, II, III, IV, V, VII, VIII, IX, X, and XI and Juvenilia ac in
                        Collingwoods bibliography. Discrepancies between the manuscripts and the
                        bibliography are owing partly to the editors errors and omissions but primarily
                        to damage sustained in a house fire of the manuscripts last private owner,
                        Charles Goodspeed of Boston, who donated them to Yale. The Beinecke owns in
                        addition to this gift a holograph fair copy of King of the Golden River, maps,
                        and some of Ruskins letters to his college friend Edward Clayton. Burd has
                        expertly edited the Beineckes MS XI, a bound volume of poems and letters to
                        Ruskins father, as part of Ruskin Family Letters. In working with these
                        manuscripts, I have encountered only occasional and minor questions about Burds
                        transcription and bibliographic description of the letters; and, therefore,
                        apart from re-editing the poems for the reasons already given, I see no
                        justification for including the texts of the letters or of the 1830 diary, which
                        has likewise been well edited by Burd and Dearden. Indeed, Burd has given
                        tentative blessing to the proposal of incorporating Ruskin Family Letters into
                        the new electronic edition as a way of extending the availability of these
                        important letters to scholars. The condition is reasonable since
                        no sufficient case has been made for substantive re-editing of the letters and
                        diary; however, the stipulation reduces the advantages of incorporating the
                        printed editions in ERM to rendering them electronically searchablethe
                        equivalent of transferring the Library Edition to CD-Rom, as was done a few
                        years ago by the Lancaster Ruskin Programme. That is no mean advantage, but an
                        insufficient one to justify the cost and labor of obtaining extensive
                        permissions (from the original manuscripts owners as well as from the editors)
                        and of keyboarding and proofing the edited texts exactly as they stand. Both
                        editions, although out of print, are widely available (which could not be said
                        for the Library Edition when it was transferred to CD); and they are furnished
                        with excellent indexes, which, along with their chronological organization, will
                        enable researchers to make convenient use of them in tandem with the electronic
                        edition. Some portions of Ruskins early letters, however, must be included in
                        the edition since he composed poems as a part of their fabric. Indeed, some
                        letters are poemsverse epistlesand Burd also included in his edition
                        fair-copied poems that were not meant to be posted but were presented by hand on
                        holidays and birthdays. Since these lettersapproximately 30 of the 270 letters
                        in the Family Lettersform an essential part of the textual history of the poems
                        they contain, portions at least of these texts must be included. In re-editing
                        these portions, should the new edition come to rely on Burds editing and notes
                        in Ruskin Family Letters to an extent beyond fair use, then we would of course
                        seek permission and pay appropriate fees. Otherwise, at this stage, we propose
                        only to quote from Family Letters and Tour in accordance with fair use, as would
                        any scholarly publication. Another important collection of early Ruskin to be
                        represented in the edition is the Morgans, which includes four of the five
                        so-called sermon books plus another possibly early sermon; an early sketchbook;
                        the larger portion of the 1830 diary (the basis of Tour); The Puppet Show (i.e.,
                        MS IB); draft for The Exile of St. Helena; fair-copy holographs of the Essay on
                        Literature and a portion of The Poetry of Architecture; and some scattered
                        sheets of drawings and notes. In addition, the Morgan houses the Bowerswell
                        Papers, related to the Ruskins earlier family history, and the Viljoen Papers.
                        Princeton University Library holds the rough-draft poetry notebook, MS VI;
                        geological studies; and the holograph fair copies of Essay on Painting and Music
                        and Chronicles of the St. Bernard. The Ruskin Library at Lancaster University
                        has an early commonplace book, another draft of Exile of St. Helena, and more
                        letters to Clayton. The richest collection of early work at the Ruskin Library
                        consists of drawings and diaries. See James S. Dearden, Ruskin, Bembridge, and
                        Brantwood: The Growth of the Whitehouse Collection (Staffordshire: Ryburn, for
                        Keele University Press, 1994). The diaries for 1835 and 183943 fall within the
                        scope of the new edition (none are extant for 183638), although members of the
                        Ruskin Programme and I need to discuss the advisability of leaving aside the
                        diaries to be reedited as a separate project. Smaller but important holdings
                        include the Huntington Librarys notebook of Euclidean exercises, the letters to
                        Edward Clayton and the religious essay that were published as Letters to a
                        College Friend (other Clayton letters at the Beinecke and the Ruskin Library
                        were omitted from that publication but will be included in the new edition), and
                        some scattered pieces probably dating from college years. The British Library
                        has maps drawn in childhood and a copy of Aristotle heavily annotated in
                        college. The Coniston Ruskin Museum completes missing parts of the Morgans
                        holdings with a fifth sermon book, a leaf of the 1830 diary, and sketch books
                        containing draft for The Poetry of Architecture. Finally, the Ruskin Library in
                        Tokyo has a manuscript of Exile of St. Helena plus scattered pieces of
                        juvenilia. In addition to this corpus, the following supporting materials will
                        be analyzed and amply quoted: </p>
                
                The editors can be charged with questionable
                    principles of selection, erroneous dating, inaccurate and outdated bibliographic
                    description, and unacknowledged meddling with the texts.The description of the major manuscripts has a long bibliographic
                    history in Ruskin scholarship, and because the manuscripts themselves are
                    inextricably tied to the meaning of the works they contain, organizationally the
                    archive turns also on their respresentation as ; and at the level of TEI
                    encoding, it is a given manuscript that sets the parameters of TEI Corpus file.
                    Descriptively, it would be equally legitimate to make each corpus coterminous
                    with a workbut not, we believe, equally powerful. Ruskin was as interested in
                    the material volumes and anthologies that he formed from witnesses of his
                    works, as he was engaged by the drafts and fair copies of given works that
                    extend athwart the manuscripts. 
                    
                    Approach in Ruskin studies.  Because juvenilia are not masterpieces, production of a
                    clear reading text in parrt because the possibilities opened by thehi
                    decentered interlinking of unlimited quantities of potentially interesting text
                    are so narcotic.  In contrast, two modern editionsVan Akin Burds Ruskin
                    Family Letters (1973) and Burds and J. S. Deardens edition of the 1830 diary,
                    A Tour to the Lakes (1990)achieve exemplary standards of accuracy and
                    annotation. . . . . Other modern
                    editions of the early writing do not rise to these standards. 
                    Finally, the Diaries (1956), edited by J. Evans and J. H. Whitehouse, makes
                    available the 1835 and 183943 diaries, but that edition is notorious among
                    Ruskin scholars for its inexplicable omissions, faulty transcriptions, and
                    inadequate annotations. Among critics and biographers who have drawn extensively
                    on the early writing, Helen Gill Viljoen stands out as the first to expose the
                    failings of the Library Edition generally and of its presentation of the
                    Ruskins family life in particular. She relied on her own study of the early
                    manuscripts as the basis for Viljoen, Ruskins Scottish Heritage, which she
                    published as a prelude to a substantially drafted, but incomplete and
                    unpublished, biography of Ruskin (see Spates, Dark Star). She also prepared an
                    edition of early religious writing, Sermons on the Pentateuch, likewise
                    unpublished (see Burd, Ruskins Testament). Viljoens notes and unpublished
                    scholarship (Viljoen Papers) are now housed in the Pierpont Morgan Library and
                    are cited and appreciatively discussed throughout ERM. The Viljoen Papers, as
                    forming an archive in itself for study of Ruskins early writing, however, is
                    not only an impractical resource for most scholarsobscurely organized, fragile,
                    as well as requiring travel to the Morgan Librarybut also unreliable since
                    Viljoens manuscript transcriptions are filled with errors, doubtless owing to
                    the haste and isolation with which she had to pursue her pioneering task. Among
                    other critics and biographers to make use of unpublished early manuscripts,
                    Emerson, Genesis of Invention (1993) cites poems and scientific notes to discuss
                    Ruskins creative development and compositional techniques; Hunt, Wider Sea
                    (1982) studies the early prose tales for clues about family life; Spear, Dreams
                    of an English Eden (1984) finds the origins of Ruskins social thought in early
                    poems and drawings; and Finley, Natures Covenant (1992) exploits the sermons
                    for evidence of Ruskins theological training. These scholars, however,
                    consulted unpublished manuscripts in a necessarily limited and partial way, if
                    an intelligently selective one, since the manuscripts are scattered among more
                    than half a dozen collections on three continents, and since there exists no
                    up-to-date, comprehensive, and accurate bibliography to describe the current
                    condition of those manuscripts. In ERM, these constraints are removed, not only
                    by contemporary editorial standards improving on century-old editions, but also
                    by hypertext presentation. The electronic archive accommodates the size and
                    breadth of the corpus while also interlinking the texts to highlight the complex
                    interplay of Ruskins texts and his overlapping poetic, artistic, scientific,
                    and religious interests. A hypertext edition lends itself, too, to representing
                    the changing constructions of Ruskins youth, from his self-conscious adoption
                    of the culturally coded role of the precocious child to the late-Victorian
                    portrayal of childhood, which Ruskin freighted with cultural meanings connected
                    with his critique of society, in the public letters Fors Clavigera (187184) and
                    the autobiography Praeterita (188589). These diffuse and difficult later works,
                    such as Fors, have taken center stage in Ruskin studies, as Tim Hiltons
                    two-volume biographyHilton, Early Years (1985), and Hilton, Later Years
                    (2000)has moved attention beyond fixation on the canonical texts of the middle
                    period. The late texts, however, hinge to a significant degree on Ruskins
                    reinterpretation of his childhood. That reinterpretation profoundly influenced
                    W. G. Collingwood, E. T. Cook, and Alexander Wedderburn, who produced their
                    editions of the early writing while living and working close to Ruskin in his
                    last home, Brantwood. Since those editions remain the primary available sources
                    for the early writing, scholars have had few resources to query the earlier
                    editors constructions of the childhood and youthful writing. Scope of the
                    Archive and Survey of Manuscripts  Research
                    completed.  I have transcribed (or, in the case of printed materials, obtained
                    photocopies of) all the materials listed above in Materials Contained in the
                    Edition, both the main corpus of manuscripts and the related materials, except
                    for the manuscripts in Tokyo and the 183942 diaries. I also stopped short of
                    completely transcribing the mineralogy notes at Princeton and the Beinecke,
                    unsure of whether long lists of minerals would be of any use; therefore, as
                    mentioned in Context and Work Plan, I place high priority on conferring about
                    these materials at Princeton with Francis OGorman, and I would use the strength
                    of an ATLAS grant to bid for travel support from Princeton University Library.
                    Otherwise, only a few minor tasks remain to complete the manuscript-collection
                    stage of the project: I have not closely examined Ruskins annotated Aristotle
                    at the British Library, and I will require Dinah Birchs assistance to do so. I
                    have not visited the Christ Church archiveif indeed anything is to be found
                    thereand I have not seen the two private collections pertaining to Ruskins
                    boyhood tutor, Edward Andrews. Beyond collecting materials, I have completed the
                    foundational work of a 140-page descriptive manuscript bibliography as well as a
                    lengthy account of provenance, and I have established a chronology of the
                    individual works. The critical apparatus includes the following: ABBREVIATIONS
                    OF COMMONLY CITED WORKS BIBLIOGRAHIC INTRODUCTION APPROACHES TO BIBLIOGRAPHY AND
                    EDITING OF THE EARLY MANUSCRIPTS THE DESIGN OF THIS EDITION The Scope of the
                    Edition The System of Title Citation The System of Date Citation Publication
                    Information Head Notes and Annotations for the Individual Entries The
                    Transcription of Texts HE DESIGN OF THE DESCRIPTIVE BIBLIOGRAPHY OF RUSKINS
                    EARLY MANUSCRIPT NOTEBOOKS The Roman Numeral Designation of the Major
                    Manuscripts The Provenance of the Major Manuscripts Sothebys 1930 Sothebys
                    1931 Viljoen SharP Huntington The next stage is to annotate and collate texts
                    and write accounts of sources and composition and publication history. I have
                    completed this work for the earliest pieces, those of 182631, and then more
                    sketchily for the remainder, through 1842. As I resume work on these materials,
                    I will develop points of entry into the edition for the audience beyond Ruskin
                    scholars. In consultation with Dinah Birch, Christine Alexander, Francis
                    OGorman, Keith Hanley, and Michael Wheeler, who have confirmed their
                    willingness to lend support to the project, I will devise broad topical essays
                    of interest to a broader audience. For example, general Romantic and Victorian
                    scholars (who, I hope, will access the site through the NINES cluster of
                    electronic projects) may wish to enter the edition via pages on forms of
                    education, following links to individual educational texts, while Ruskin
                    scholars will likely prefer to start with texts and navigate toward more general
                    materials. In either case, ERM will be unique in anchoring the general materials
                    on Romantic and Victorian childhood in specific texts and images, allowing the
                    child to speak for himself as far as possible. Methods.  As explained earlier,
                    understanding of the early work has until now been distorted by the earlier
                    editors darkly hinted criteria of selection: no fragments; no gore; nothing
                    disturbing. This edition will present the entire surviving corpuswith the
                    possible exception of the mineralogy notes, concerning which OGorman and I will
                    arrive at a rationale. Remarkably few pieces seem absolutely trivial. As
                    demonstrated by the wide use in Victorian scholarship of the early letters and
                    other published early works, the young Ruskin really could be that consistently
                    engaging and inventive. The corpus appears reasonably complete. Most works
                    mentioned in the family letters survive in some form; and Collingwoods
                    bibliography, as amended by Cook and Wedderburn, supplies a survey of the early
                    manuscripts kept at Brantwood at the turn of the century, most of which can
                    still be identified. I have never found evidence that the editors deliberately
                    destroyed any juvenilia, although Ruskins literary executors did burn some
                    documents that embarrassed them. A few pieces that the editors transcribed or
                    photographed can no longer be located, and comparison of their descriptive
                    bibliographies with the present state of the manuscripts presents some puzzles;
                    however, the only known deliberate destructionhalf of one notebook, whose
                    former contents are known from a surviving indexappears to have been
                    perpetrated by Ruskin himself in childhood. I have transcribed every manuscript
                    with scrupulous attention to detail. As a shortcut in the archives, I
                    occasionally marked up transcripts photocopied from the Viljoen Papers, but I
                    always checked these against the originals, as Viljoen was a rapid but
                    inaccurate copyist. Symbols are used where necessary to explain rather than
                    correct Ruskins punctuation. Burd detects a language in Ruskins punctuation,
                    in which even the varying lengths of dashes have significance. The lack of
                    punctuation can likewise be purposeful as well, as Emerson remarks. Oddities and
                    ambiguities, although explained as systematically as possible in the
                    transcriptions, should be resolved for the reader by reference to accompanying
                    images of the manuscripts. Lancasters edition of Modern Painters I (hereafter,
                    MPI) was conceived as a social edition in two senses: first, the edition was
                    constructed by a large team of researchers; second, rather than presenting the
                    reader with a single, eclectic reading text, the edition displays all the main
                    printed editions available over time to the Victorian public. In one window, the
                    reader can alternate between the manuscript and the 1843, 1846, 1851, 1878, and
                    1888 editions, as if the physical texts were open to the same passage. The
                    reader can turn the pages simultaneously since Garside innovated a way to mark
                    up images of the printed pages. This prioritizing of the visible, as it is
                    termed in the editions introduction, is a persuasive approach to the early
                    manuscripts as well since, throughout his life, Ruskin was concerned with the
                    physical presentation of his writing. He conveyed meaning visually, from his
                    childish imitation of typeface and plates in his earliest homemade books to
                    the elegant presentation of his poetry in literary annuals, accompanied by steel
                    engravings based on his own drawings; and his editors re-presented the
                    juvenilia as controlled, completed texts, corrected to make them appear more
                    finished. A difference from MPI, however, arises from a large proportion of
                    ERMs texts existing only in manuscript. Images of many of these manuscripts,
                    although essential for information, would be useless as a reading text,
                    especially in cases where only very rough draft survives. (Users of MPI, it
                    appears, shrink from reading the image of the manuscript and turn immediately to
                    the transcript.) In these cases, a machine-readable transcript must move to the
                    center of the users approach to the edition, if not to the physical center of
                    the screen, where the main window will consistently be reserved for images of
                    manuscripts and printed pages. As in MPI, the reader will always be able to
                    access a transcript of the manuscript in a pop-up window, alongside whatever
                    image has been called up in the main window. Another difference is that, whereas
                    in MPI the reader chooses from a consistent set of six imagesthe five main
                    editions and the manuscriptin ERM the reader will be presented with a variable
                    number of images, depending on the manuscript and publication history in
                    question, which differs for each text. (Ideally, whichever image of a given text
                    the reader calls up, annotations should be consistently accessible from the same
                    textual feature. In the present release of MPI, only the image of the 1846
                    edition carries the annotation links, compromising the sense of history since
                    readers tend to privilege that edition as a reading text. This result was
                    dictated neither by technology nor by editorial preferences but by ad hoc
                    decisions.) In design, the website will encase the edition in a shell providing
                    two main pathways, one leading directly to the edition proper, the other leading
                    into the edition by way of guided tours. The latter path, intended to make the
                    edition accessible to a broader range of researchers who are not committed
                    primarily to Ruskin studies, will offer the user a menu of topics: family and
                    childhood; education and literature; travel and history; fine arts and art
                    education; amateur science and collecting; and worship and theology. This menu
                    will lead the researcher to essays on the respective topics. The essays will
                    orient the user to relevant clusters of texts in the edition, by situating them
                    in scholarship pitched at the level of a general, interdisciplinary scholarly
                    audience (i.e., the kind of reader I keep in view for the journal I edit,
                    Nineteenth Century Studiesa reader who wishes to cross disciplines, and so must
                    have material outside his or her specialization made accessible, but who has the
                    scholarly sophistication to recognize whether the material forms an original
                    contribution to the ongoing conversation in the field in question). These guided
                    tours will render ERM, to borrow Woofs terms regarding the Lancaster edition,
                    more classical in approach than gothic and organic. The latter approach, in
                    which the annotations avoid hierarchical structures, is more Ruskinian. However,
                    since ERM consists of over 300 texts ranging across several fields of knowledge,
                    a truly Ruskinian designhowever interesting to specialistsmight thwart general
                    researchers. Once inside the edition, the general reader will be led by the
                    hypertext environment to explore how, for Ruskin, any given interest tended to
                    overlap with others. This approach, gothic nestled inside of classical,
                    approximates the experience of Ruskins childhood. His mother instructed him in
                    sharply differentiated fields of knowledgethe hours for Bible study being
                    strictly set apart from, and taking precedence over, time allowed for poetry and
                    drawingand Ruskin did obey these constraints. Nonetheless, he found ways to
                    overcome boundaries by forming unexpected links. This gothic aspect of the
                    edition will be supported by projected NINES tools allowing users to play
                    different interpretive games: Ivanhoe, for example, will allow users to adopt
                    multiple, differing interpretive roles and to observe the record of the
                    interactions, a game that would apply usefully to Ruskins composing his poems
                    in the context of his letters to his father and with his mother looking on;
                    Collex will allow users to collate and rearrange on-line archives, a capacity
                    that mimics Ruskins own proclivity for constantly rearranging and recombining
                    his collections. Participation in the University of Virginia workshop mentioned
                    in Context and Work Plan would enable me to integrate such tools. For the
                    edition properwhich researchers will be able to access directly from the outer
                    shell, if desiredtwo levels of navigation are required: one for specific texts;
                    a second for the manuscript notebooks containing the texts, the manuscript
                    bibliography, and other global-level apparatuses. At the global level,
                    individual titles will be indexed alphabetically and chronologically as well as
                    according to their place within the notebook containing them. At the level of
                    the individual text, as described earlier, readers will access images of the
                    manuscript and/or published forms of the workthe number of images varying
                    according to the history of the text in questionand consult a manuscript
                    transcript in a pop-up window. Each text will be annotated with a master note
                    summarizing the composition, publication, and source history. Other annotations
                    and images will include, as in MPI, a list of collations, explanatory notes
                    keyed to particular textual features, and additional images related to the text.
                    Following this prospectus, I supply excerpts from two sample edited texts. I
                    take the samples from two stages in Ruskins developmentfrom earliest
                    childhood, a portion of his Harry and Lucy books, which he modeled on Maria
                    Edgeworths tales of that title; and, from adolescence, a portion of his sermons
                    explicating texts from the Pentateuch as a means of explaining the major
                    doctrines of his familys moderately Calvinist evangelical faith. These samples
                    afford representative master notes on composition history and sources as well as
                    explanatory notes. Also supplied is a section of the manuscript bibliography
                    describing the notebook containing the Harry and Lucy sample. In this paper
                    sample, directions to the reader to see and see also, as well as numbered
                    references to the three hundred other texts, should be understood as being
                    replaced by active links in the electronic edition. Electronic editing at
                    Lancaster.  Electronic editing was included in the founding vision of the
                    Lancaster Ruskin Programme when the director, Michael Wheeler, consulting with
                    the Ruskin scholar and hypermedia expert George Landow, proposed Modern Painters
                    I as a logical starting point for re-editing Ruskins works. Supported by a
                    19972001 grant from the Leverhulme Trust, which monitored and approved
                    progress, Wheeler assembled and led a large editing team that comprehensively
                    represented the many research areas associated with Modern Painters, and he
                    appointed Lawrence Woof as a research fellow to help coordinate the editing. The
                    edition was launched in its first fully operational public version in July 2002
                    (www.lancs.ac.uk/ users/ruskin/empi/index.php). With its completion, electronic
                    editing in the Ruskin Programme is proceeding case by case, taking advantage of
                    the interests of individual scholars associated with the program. Since each
                    project is self-contained, ERM can follow its own schedule. Consultants. 
                    Senior consulting scholars would not be paid out of the ATLAS grant, and they
                    have agreed to advise the project without pay at all, so long as any travel and
                    serious investment of skill and time are appropriately remunerated. Strictly,
                    the project could go forward without them, especially with peer oversight being
                    provided by the NINES board, which includes the Ruskin scholar and hypertext
                    expert George Landow. Obviously, however, ERM will benefit by the participation
                    of the Ruskin scholarly community. As a journal editor, I believe in scholarship
                    as a communal activity, and I have experience in promoting exchangenever
                    ceasing to marvel at individuals generosity in supporting worthwhile projects.
                    n the strength of the ATLAS grant application, I will seek to supply various
                    kinds of remuneration for consultants through such sources as the travel grants
                    that I have mentioned from Princeton University Library and the Huntington
                    Library (applications due in December 2004 and January 2005) and small SLU
                    grants such as the Arts and Lectures series, which I could use to bring Garside
                    to SLU, and Faculty Development grants, which I could use to defray my own
                    travel. Such additional support will need to be pieced together as we go along,
                    but I am confident that the project is financially well within reach because it
                    is already so far advanced; the need, apart from what would be provided by
                    ATLAS, is not large in dollar terms and clearly justifiable to granting
                    agencies; and the smaller requests of a few thousand dollars at a time can be
                    spread over not only the ATLAS year of academic leave but also the year beyond.
                    The ATLAS grant would provide the most essential boost, by supporting
                    much-needed release from a heavy teaching load, as well as by financing the
                    large one-time expense of imaging fees. Here are brief biographies of the
                    contributing staff: This archive has evolved over below the clearly
                    distinguishable editorial titleedition is divided in two parts. Part 1 presents
                    a revised and comprehensive chronology of all known individual prose and poetry
                    piecespublished or unpublished, extant or lostcontained in the major early
                    manuscripts, preserved on stray sheets elsewhere, or known at least by title.
                    Next, the whereabouts and publication (if any) of each item is identified. Each
                    item is then followed by a note justifying its dating, and discussing its
                    sources and compositional historymore or less lengthily, depending on the
                    complexity of the work. Part 1 also selectively prints texts of works that are
                    either previously unpublished or published with such invasive emendations by
                    earlier editors as to justify a new text. Where silent editorial emendations in
                    existing printed texts are localized or minor, a textual note summarizing the
                    differences between the manuscript and printed text is deemed sufficient. Part 2
                    presents a revised and comprehensive descriptive bibliography. For each known
                    major manuscript of juvenilia, I supply its physical characteristics and
                    provenance, enumerate its contents, and attempt to reconstruct the order and
                    circumstances of its compositionthat is, the compositional history of the major
                    manuscript, as opposed to that of an individual title contained therein, which
                    is presented in part 1. Throughout this edition, MS followed by a roman numeral
                    refers to the manuscripts described in part 2; no. followed by an arabic numeral
                    refers to individual items in part 1. I do not attempt to list Ruskins
                    drawings, better left to the expertise of art historians. In part 2, I do
                    include, however, descriptions of Ruskins first two sketchbooks (MSS VIIIA,
                    VIIIB), dating from 183132, since the logic of the edition demands that they be
                    included in part 2 as major early manuscripts. Their inclusion is necessitated,
                    moreover, by the prose writings contained in one of them. In part 1, I also omit
                    the letters published in RFL, which the reader may easily compare against the
                    chronology. I do, on a few occasions in part 1 in connection with other items,
                    dispute Burds dating of a letter; and, in part 2, where MS XI is described,
                    which contains letters, I have been able to supply portions of some letters for
                    the first time, portions that were omitted from RFL. All the poems printed in
                    RFL, as a matter of course, will be found listed in the chronology, part 1. My
                    editorial principles governing the various segments of parts 1 and 2 are
                    explained in greater detail below. First, a broad survey of Ruskins early
                    writing will help to orient the reader. THE DESIGN OF PART 1, COMPLETE
                    CHRONOLOGY AND SELECTED TEXTS OF RUSKINS WRITINGS, 182638 Much can be learned
                    from the proper ordering of the notebooks contents, so long as one remains
                    aware that a given notebook may include several sequences from differing times
                    and that the overall, day-to-day sequence of Ruskins activities must be
                    reconstructed from his simultaneous use of several notebooks. For these reasons,
                    Cook and Wedderburn were wise to pair Collingwoods descriptive bibliography of
                    the major manuscripts with the Chronology of the individual poems that the
                    manuscripts contain. Accordingly, I have gratefully adopted their fundamental
                    design, by pairing a complete chronology of the individual items of juvenilia
                    (part 1) with a descriptive bibliography of the major manuscripts (part 2). I
                    have revised and expanded the chronology beyond a merely enumerative list of
                    poetry titles like Cook and Wedderburns, to comprise the nearly three hundred
                    items of poetry as well as prose through 1838, each item annotated by a
                    justification of its position in the sequence. The manuscript notebooks by
                    themselves give a perplexing impression of Ruskins activities, since he wrote
                    in a given notebook at many different times, spread in some cases over years,
                    and he worked with more than one notebook simultaneously. Ones head reels in
                    leafing through the manuscript notebooks, trying to discern a sequence in
                    Ruskins interests and developing literary activity. Notebooks starting with his
                    careful but childish pencil print lettering, used for his Harry and Lucy and
                    earliest poems of 182628, might also contain ink and pencil script used for
                    drafts of sermons and mineralogical articles of a considerably later time. A
                    range of one to eight years is possible for his use of any single notebook. Even
                    wider parameters characterize MSS IA, X, and XI, which are not notebooks already
                    bound when Ruskin first used them but collections of loose manuscripts compiled
                    and bound in later years by Alexander Wedderburn. What is more confusing, the
                    notebooks contents are not always sequential. Although Ruskin seems usually to
                    have placed his initial entry in a notebooks first pages, frequently even
                    providing a title page, he at various times copied groups of poems in the
                    middle, and returned years later and drafted new projects starting at the
                    opposite end from, and upside down to, the text at the beginning. The texts
                    coming from opposite ends often meet, and in some cases the new text extends
                    over top of the oldRuskin either erasing part of the old text to accommodate
                    the new, or running the new text into whatever marginal spaces were left over.
                    Other available gaps here and there were filled at almost any time. In another
                    procedure, causing a conundrum that Dearden successfully unraveled in the 1830
                    diary (TLC, 1014), Ruskin would leave gaps to fill in later, but, discovering
                    he had allowed insufficient space, he would fill the gap and continue the
                    inserted text elsewhere in the notebook. The task of ordering the notebooks
                    contents involves an exacting and elaborate game of cross-referencing. Each poem
                    or prose item takes its place on a conceptual grid, its position fixed by
                    vectors converging from various determinationsRuskins own dates when
                    available, the items placement in a notebook vis--vis other datable pieces,
                    references to it in datable family letters, and its source in books the family
                    is known to have bought or read at a certain time. With these items fixed, a
                    story gradually emerges of how and when an entire notebook was used, and this
                    story can in turn inform us both about individual items that cannot be dated by
                    any other method and about the simultaneous evolution of other notebooks.
                    Fortunately, substantial sections of some notebooks were composed more or less
                    sequentiallymost importantly, those like MSS II, VI, and VIII, in which Ruskin
                    entered rough drafts of his work and which therefore preserve a successive
                    record of his compositions. The sequences in the rough-draft notebooks also
                    became convoluted in certain places, howeverextremely so, in MS VIIIrequiring
                    meticulous interpretation provided in parts 1 and 2. In part 1, each entry
                    begins with an items title, followed by its most precise known date, its
                    manuscript source, publication history, and a note discussing the evidence for
                    dating, compositional history, and sources. Texts follow for those poems and
                    prose works I have chosen to publish. The Scope of the Chronology The chronology
                    begins with the earliest known compositionsthose of 1826, putting aside
                    possibly earlier drawings and signatures on the flyleaves of books, and
                    Ruskins first letter of 1823.#FN01# The chronology extends through 1838,
                    thereby encompassing all the individual items contained in the major
                    manuscripts. Items are grouped by year and, insofar as can be determined,
                    arranged chronologically within the year, according to the earliest known
                    datethat is, the date of an items draft, if known, rather than its fair copy
                    or publication. The choice of inclusive dates to frame the chronology, 182638,
                    has been governed by the contents of the major manuscript notebooks. It has
                    proved prudent to extend the chronology from the earliest known compositions
                    through the latest items contained in the major manuscripts, although by 1838
                    Ruskin had produced work certainly too mature to be regarded as juvenilia, such
                    as The Poetry of Architecture (no. 255). Since Ruskin returned to his early
                    notebooks long after their initial childhood use, appropriating available leaves
                    to draft such comparatively sophisticated pieces as Marcolini (no. 241) and
                    the Essay on the Relative Dignity of the Studies of Painting and Music . . .
                    (no. 270), the evidence for dating these later items needs to be in place in
                    part 1, in order to decode the manuscript notebooks comprehensively in part 2.
                    As it has turned out, some work by the emerging critic and prose writer, such as
                    the Essay on . . . Painting and Music and the Chronicles of St. Bernard (no.
                    216), is as problematic to date as work by the juvenile poet, although Cook and
                    Wedderburns (and the elder Ruskins) dates for this youthful criticism have
                    always been taken for granted. Some works are listed that have been lost
                    altogether, but whose titles and dates remain recoverable, especially from MS
                    VI. These deserve to be listed and annotated for what they can tell us about
                    Ruskins interests and compositional habits. THE DESIGN OF PART 2, DESCRIPTIVE
                    BIBLIOGRAPHY OF RUSKINS EARLY MANUSCRIPT NOTEBOOKS In part 2, each major
                    manuscript entry begins with its designation by roman numeral; its location
                    (when appropriate, using the abbreviations listed at the front of this book),
                    along with any specialized cataloging information; and its inclusive dates of
                    composition. These opening identifications are followed by three discursive
                    sections: (a) provenance; (b) physical description, and discusssion of any
                    special circumstances that affected the manuscripts composition or compilation;
                    and (c) contents, listed in their sequential order (not necessarily the same as
                    the contents compositional order, which is accounted for in part 1). #FN01#See,
                    e.g., the penciled drawings and signatures in Ruskins childhood copies of
                    Maria Edgeworths Frank and Aesops Fables (described in Viljoen, Sharp
                    Collection, 6, 7 [items 2, 5b]), and in a book Little Jack (listed in Adams
                    Collection, 317). Ruskins first letter, written by his mother from his
                    dictation on 15 March 1823 and signed by himself in very awkward capital
                    letters, is printed in Collingwood, Life, 1819?; Works 1:xxvi, n. 3; and RFL
                    12728. The autograph letter itself is reproduced in Dearden, The Ruskin
                    Galleries at Bembridge School, Isle of Wight, pl. III.</p>  -->
                
            </div>   
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
