<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Work</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="subtype">
                <head type="title">Provenance of the Early Manuscripts at Denmark Hill and Brantwood</head>
                <p>In the period extending from Ruskin's life at Denmark Hill, which is associated with his central canonical work, to his life at Brantwood, associated with his late work, 
                    the provenance of the early manuscripts is bound up with the increasingly fraught relation between the private and public in Ruskin's writing. 
                    His attention to the manuscripts, insofar as his actions can be documented, appears prompted by emotionally epochal events such as his mother's death, 
                    and his making peace with the memories both of his parents and of Rose La Touche through his autobiographical writing. 
                    When Ruskin was forced to abandon his public writing, leaving uncompleted his autobiography, <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>, 
                    ownership of many of the early manuscripts and responsibility for their preservation passed to others. As it turned out, the early manuscripts became positioned 
                    in the vanguard of a debate about how to represent Ruskin's work editorially and biographically, now that he had ceded control and was advancing toward death.</p>
                <p>Toward the end of Ruskin's years at Denmark Hill, in September 1870, he scrutinized and docketed some of the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php">Red Books</ref>. 
                    His reasons for sorting through these manuscripts at this time are undocumented, and his system for docketing them is obscure. 
                    Possibly, he was reviewing the early writing and drawings because he anticipated parting ways with the domicile of his parents.</p>
                <p>More than a year later, in December 1871, the death of the author's mother, Margaret Ruskin, represented a watershed for Ruskin, and the close of the Denmark Hill years. 
                    Ruskin had already purchased his first house entirely his own, Brantwood, in ??? 1871, 
                    and he took up residence in summer 1873, having removed from Denmark Hill in spring 1872. It was presumably these changes that prompted a gift of an early manuscript, "The Puppet Show" (MS IB), 
                    to his valet, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="crawley_f_note.php">Frederick Crawley</ref>.<!-- 
                        Why would Crawley want this? What about Charles Eliot Norton? When did he get Wales/Spring letter? --> 
                    In 1900, after Ruskin's death, this manuscript returned to Brantwood (see MS IB: Provenance).</p>
                <p>In ????, after Ruskin had moved to Brantwood, his cousin, Joan Severn, and her family came to live with him. The Severns continued living at Brantwood after Ruskin's death in 1900. Joan died in ????, 
                    and Arthur Severn died in . . . . From ???? to ????, the sole remaining resident was Violet Severn. . . .
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RUSKINLATERYEARS">Hilton, <hi rend="italic">John Ruskin: The Later Years</hi></ref>, 212, 223, 255 . . . .). The Severns' reign over the household
                    influenced the destiny of the early manuscripts, owing to a combination of nostalgia, acquisitiveness, and neglect.</p>
                <p>The earliest record I have found of the early manuscripts' preservation at Brantwood emerges a decade after Ruskin's taking up residence. 
                    In a diary entry dated "18 July [18]80 and afterwards," Ruskin notes: "Things done or Designed at Brantwood." These things accomplished included: 
                    "Drawer of Precious things examined, and all my Fathers and Mother’s things put with my childish books.&#x2014;upper shelf of Bible compartment of Bookcase. 
                    also Joanies important letters&#x2014;and any of pathetic interest respecting friends[.]  Several of Carlyle’s precious. Little Arthurs Poo" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFMS13">Ruskin, Diary, 1861&#x2013;63, 1870, [1880]</ref>, 13r).<note>One hopes that the "poo" of young Arthur Severn (age ??, at this time) 
                        refers to a spoon. The "things done" I have quoted comprise item 1.<hi rend="italic">a</hi> in a list. 
                        The remainder of that list, 1.<hi rend="italic">b</hi>&#x2013;<hi rend="italic">f</hi> through 
                        2.<hi rend="italic">a</hi>&#x2013;<hi rend="italic">d</hi> 
                    appears as follows:
                    <list>
                        <item>1. "Things done or Designed at Brantwood. . . ."</item>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. [As quoted, above.]</item>         
                        <item><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. "My mother’s watch&#x2013;with the snowdrop and moss gathered the winter before my illness, when I thought they had come by miracle"</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">c</hi>. "The letters of 22nd Feb. 1878"</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">d</hi>. "Rosie’s Sesame and Lilies"</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">e</hi>. "Thanks of University for gift of Turners."</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">f</hi>. "Mr Guyards souvenir du 9ne Aout"</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. "The middle shelf of Bible compartment now contains, behind."</item>
                        <item><list>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. "Philostratus"</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. "Sir Joshua Reynolds. 3 vols. fine. plates"</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">c</hi>. "Letters of my own. those from Harristown of great interest."</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">d</hi>. "my oldest sketchbooks and loose drawings."</item>
                        </list></item>
                    </list>
                    </note> 
                    It is possible that, by "childish books," Ruskin referred to printed books that he had read in boyhood, 
                    rather than his bound notebooks, such as the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php">Red Books</ref>, 
                    containing the juvenilia. He did relish and refer to the texts of favorite boyhood books, such as Maria Edgeworth's tales; he even arranged for reprinting (see . . . <!-- note on Wiggins -->). 
                    There appears less evidence that he took an interest in his boyhood <hi rend="italic">copies</hi> of these texts, however, than he did in the texts themselves, or in his own juvenilia. 
                    By comparison, he repeatedly and publicly paid attention to his own early manuscripts, and it seems entirely consistent that he would have reserved a special place for those manuscripts, 
                    sharing a shelf with memorabilia of his parents.</p>
                <p>Following this diary record of 1880, the next evidence of Ruskin consulting the early manuscripts while at Brantwood emerges almost exactly five years later, 
                    when he drew on <ref type="apparatus" subtype="mss" target="msi_apparatus.php">MS I</ref> 
                    in writing his autobiography, <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 35:???).
                    As I have argued elsewhere, Ruskin's use of the juvenilia in the compositional process prompted, on 15 July 1885, 
                    a breakthrough for the autobiography, one that probably appeared to him spiritual in nature&#x2014;literally spiritual, in that he believed that a spirit had sent him a sign 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#DARKWATERS">Hanson, "Dark Waters of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>"</ref>, ???).
                    (Ruskin had initially been prompted to open the Red Books in July 1885 probably in order to show them to 
                    a child visiting the house [see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#DARKWATERS">Hanson, "Dark Waters of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>"</ref>, ???].)
                    Occult associations with family effects was not unprecedented; in 1880, Ruskin's list of "things done" at Brantwood included such suggestions 
                    (see previous note)<!-- can one link back to an in-line note? -->.</p>
          <here></here>
                <p>The first glimpse of some <major manuscripts> being resurrected in order to compile the <Poems by J.R.> of 1850, at which time <John James Ruskin annotated> at least one major manuscript. Did jjr get mss. from anyone else? Did they get sent to Harrison?
                    Ruskin’s annotation of red books on 8 September 1870. He was in London, but did he look at them at Herne Hill or Denmark Hill. His interest at this time explained by renewed negotiations with Rose. Hewison (179) says he was seeking legal council to establish that he was unmarried. Diary for 8 September says..... Note that he was reading poems of 1848 on September 11: this would be because that was his marriage year. WHAT POEMS OF 1848? Don’t know of any.</p>
                    </p>
                <p>Thus, this key use of the juvenilia in the autobiography indicates that the Red Books remained stored at Brantwood, presumably along with the other juvenilia  
                    Ruskin went on in <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> to remark, more offhandedly, 
                    on his having made gifts of various early manuscripts and drawings. Of his so-called first sketchbook<!-- identify ms -->, he notes having already sent 
                    its drawings of Canterbury Cathedral to his friend Miss Gale of Canterbury<!-- identify -->; and 
                    he was packing off the remnants of the sketchbook to Fanny Talbot<!-- cite ms viiia provenance --> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 35:???).
                    These public announcements are curious, suggestive of Ruskin's habitual generosity and thoughtfulness in making appropriate gifts, 
                    but he also frames the presentation in terms of his own contempt for the juvenilia. As he says of MS IX, 
                    “I leave the unfinished folly in Joanie’s care, that none but friends may see it” 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 35:???).
                    The preservation of juvenilia by famous authors could suffer from the ambivalence that writers in their maturity felt about their early work. 
                    Ruskin, as Christine Alexander remarks, "writing his autobiography <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> at the end of his career, 
                    proudly includes information  about its beginnings" by reproducing a passage from MS I
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ALEXANDERDEFINING">Alexander, "Defining and Representing Literary Juvenilia"</ref>, 73);
                    at the same time, in these public bequests, he felt compelled, like other authors mentioned by Alexander, 
                    to toss away his early "follies." <here></here>
                    containing the 1833-34 tour poem, Account of a Tour on the Continent (Ruskin, Works, 35:81 [chapter 4, published September 1885, but composed ...?]).</p>
                <p>Presumably, Joan Severn had no reason to remove these gifts of early manuscript from Brantwood; nonetheless, her possession was made scrupulously clear by W. G. Collingwood 
                    in his descriptive bibliography for the <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891), 
                    the &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems.&#x201D; To prepare his edition, Collingwood needed access to all the early manuscripts at Brantwood, 
                    but he confirms that MS IX was in “the possession of Mrs. Arthur Severn,” and he also ascribes to her MS VII, which contains the fair copy of "Iteriad," and 
                    MS X, which originally included the diary of the 1830 Lakes tour and the poetic travelogue of the 1835 Continental tour (Poems [1891], 1:265, 266, 267). 
                    Thus, Ruskin appears to have given Joan Severn specifically the tour poems as a group.</p>
                <p>Possibly also at about this time, Ruskin presented Alexander Wedderburn with a collection of letters by Ruskin to his father. Such a collection was bound, 
                    at any rate, in 1889; and while this collection would continue to undergo rebinding and a complicated provenance 
                    (see MS XI: Provenance), the collection retains Wedderburn's documentation of the gift. According to an ink notation on the front endpaper of the last volume (vol. 6, which was originally vol. 7): 
                    "The letters in this volume were given by M<hi rend="super">r</hi> 
                    Ruskin to A. Wedderburn, &#x0026; arranged by him in this book, which was deposited at Brantwood, after M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Ruskin's death, 
                    by arrangement with M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Severn. / A. Wedderburn / Oct. 1900." 
                    The frustrating ambiguity of the referent for the pronoun <hi rend="italic">him</hi> leaves in doubt whether Wedderburn 
                    or Ruskin "arranged" the letters. If the parallel passive verb construction is meant to indicate Ruskin both "giving" and "arranging in this book," 
                    then the date of binding (1889) reveals Ruskin carefully preserving his letters to his father in the final year of his working life--a significant valedictory gesture.</p>
                <p>Wedderburn also owned "a large folio scrap-book, wherein Ruskin's father, up to the date of his death, had pasted every review of his son's books, or other references to them, 
                    which he could find" (Ruskin, Works, 38:xviii). The scrapbook would have complemented the letters to Ruskin's father, if presented at the same time. 
                    The scrapbook seems an appropriate gift to the editor of Ruskin's own clippings, as it were--that is, Ruskin's collected letters to newspapers that form The Arrows of the Chase. 
                    Perhaps this gift prompted that of the letters; it is not obvious, otherwise, why Ruskin would have presented the letters to Wedderburn.<!-- question of why AW a trustee --></p>
                <p>It was in this period--as Ruskin relinquished public writing, leaving the autobiography incomplete--that the provenance of the early manuscripts at Brantwood entered a new stage, 
                    in which scholarship and biography, trusteeship, publishing, and cataloguing and preservation of manuscripts overlap and interweave. This stage commenced with the editing of the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891) by W. G. Collingwood, a project that was transitional with respect to authority over the material remains and editorial representation of the Ruskin canon. 
                    On the one hand, Collingwood was carrying out Ruskin's intentions in treating the edition as an extension of Ruskin's autobiography; 
                    on the other hand, the editor achieved a scholarly distance made possible by Ruskin's having ceased to write his autobiography, which had entailed such an eccentric use of the early manuscripts 
                    (see Introductory Essay on Editing and Bibliography). Collingwood's scholarly objectivity is measured by his descriptive bibliography for the edition, 
                    the &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:261&#x2013;67; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:???). 
                    The &#x201C;Note&#x201D; was the first manuscript bibliography in Ruskin studies, taking its place in the growing bibliographical scholarship on Ruskin, 
                    which had already arisen as part of 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.php">The Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>.</p>
                <p>Since Collingwood started his &#x201C;Preliminary Note,&#x201D; as the title suggests, prior to the publication date of 1891, he described the manuscripts in their condition approximately 
                    at the point when Ruskin was using them in writing Praeterita and giving some of them away. As already remarked, the "Note" recognizes Joan Severn's ownership of the tour poem manuscripts, 
                    setting a terminus a quo for the "Note" of 1885, when Ruskin composed the chapter of Praeterita in which he declares his gift to her of MS IX.<!-- add note documenting composition date --> 
                    His description of MS XI as an "envelope containing collected loose papers, including poems" 
                    (<ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1891_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891), ????</ref>)
                    must predate the binding of all or some portion of that collection in Wedderburn's possession&#x2014;ownership 
                    that Collingwood does not mention, and binding that probably (but not certainly, 
                    owing to the loss of evidence by rebinding) took place in 1889, setting a terminus ad quem for the "Note."</p>
                <p>Another bibliographic activity set afoot in 1889 was the part publication of the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="bibliography_of_ruskin_wise_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Complete Bibliography of . . . Ruskin</hi> (1889&#x2013;93)</ref> by 
                    J. P. Smart and T. J. Wise, the bibliography in which Wise planted the falsified entries creating a spurious history for his forged pamphlets 
                    (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="forgery_and_piracy_note.php">Forgery and Piracy</ref>). 
                    Trusting to Wise and Smart's scholarly credentials, Collingwood admitted to relying on their bibliography, as attested by the concluding paragraph of the "Note" 
                    (a paragraph omitted from the revised "Note" in the Library Edition): "Full account of the published poems has been given by Mr. Thomas J. Wise in his 'Bibliography of the Writings, &#x0026;c., 
                    of John Ruskin,' part <hi rend="sc">I</hi>,  <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi>  1889 (printed for subscribers only); of which I have gladly availed myself" (Poems [1891], 1:268). 
                    Collingwood could not have known, of course, that Wise was exploiting the Poems (1891) to lend credence to his forgeries 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" subtype="bibliography.php#WISERUSKINI">Dearden, "Wise and Ruskin I"</ref>, 46).</p>
                <p>Wise apparently did not seek an audience with Ruskin at Brantwood before May 1893, after both Collingwood's edition and his own bibliography had been published, 
                    and after he had insinuated the spurious <hi rend="italic">Scythian Guest</hi> pamphlet into Collingwood's research for his biography of Ruskin 
                    (Collingwood to Wise, 13 September 1892, 23 May 1893, in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RUTGERSALS">Collingwood et al., ALS to Thomas J. Wise)</ref>. 
                    <here></here>By this time, Wise may have been on the prowl for manuscripts, since his series of "privately printed" Ruskin letters began at this time 
                    (Dearden, "Ruskin and Wise III," 318-39). One can well imagine Wise attempting a dodge at Brantwood like that of Clement Shorter, who, according to Partington, 
                    wheedled Thomas Hardy into allowing him to bind some of the writer's manuscripts and then kept one to defray his trouble; or the cheat that Wise perpetrated on Rev. F. A. Malleson 
                    by borrowing the clergyman's holograph correspondence with Ruskin (via Smart) and then publishing the letters "privately" without permission 
                    (Thomas J. Wise in the Original Cloth, 109, 114-15; Dearden, "Wise and Ruskin III," 325-28).</p>
                <p>To If  
                    Wise's earliest personal visit to Coniston appears to have occurred in 1893, two years following publication of Poems, and even then Collingwood strove to keep Wise at a distance from Brantwood 
                    (Dearden, "Wise and Ruskin I,"> 47); and a letter of 1892 from Collingwood to Smart shows the former positioning himself against outsiders as the authority in matters of authenticity and attribution 
                    (ironically), precisely because he had access to the manuscripts (and to Ruskin himself). Wise can therefore be discounted, I think, even as an agent for binding the manuscripts at Brantwood.</p>
                
                <p>The binding of MS XI perhaps initiated the set of blue morocco slipcases and bindings that characterized most of the manuscripts described in Collingwood's "Note" by the time they were sold at the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1930</ref>. 
                    Many of these casings show no evidence when they were made or by whom, but the few that are dated indicate a range of 1889 (MS XI) to 1902 (MS V, MS VII) for this activity.<note>The 
                        slipcases for MS V and MS VII were made in 1902, as indicated by their spines: for MS V, 
                        "RUSKIN &#x007C; MS. &#x007C; POEMS &#x007C; 1829–32 &#x007C; 1902"; and for MS VII, "RUSKIN &#x007C; MS. &#x007C; ITERIAD &#x007C; &#x0026;c &#x007C; 1902." The reason for this choice of material 
                            requires research. Perhaps blue morocco bore reference to the so-called "Ruskin calf"--that is, 
                            the "purple calf, with gilt edges, tooled after an ecclesiastical fashion," used for the 
                            <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="works_series_note.php">Works Series</ref> 
                            (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RUSKINBIBLIOGRAPHYWISE">Wise and Smart, <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of Ruskin</hi></ref>, 1:119).</note>
                    Thus, the preservation efforts for the early manuscripts roughly tracked the editorial projects at Brantwood&#x2014;Collingwood's, and Cook and Wedderburn's start on the Library Edition&#x2014;and 
                    this elegant treatment of the early manuscripts was in the vanguard of both editorial projects.</p>
                <p>The responsibility for this uniform treatment of the early manuscripts is not recorded. As suggested earlier, Wedderburn's remarks about the provenance of MS XI may point to Ruskin himself having a hand 
                    in the arrangement at least of the letters for binding. Ultimately, Joan Severn would have claimed ownership, if not responsibility for the uniform preservation of all the early manuscripts. 
                    As the Library Edition explains, "in the edition of 1891" some of the early manuscripts were "named as 'in the possession of Mrs. Arthur Severn,'" but "since Ruskin's death" 
                    this statement of ownership was to be extended to "them all" (Ruskin, Works, 2:532 n. 1). 
                    Practically, if not legally, however, the preservation and care of the early manuscripts at Brantwood was a joint effort.</p>
                <p>Collingwood exerted some influence, directly and indirectly, over the preservation of the manuscripts he described. In MS I, a gummed strip was used (unprofessionally) to mend a torn leaf; 
                    and similar strips, which resemble the perforated edge of a sheet of postage stamps,<note>Sheets of postage stamps were issued with perforations starting in the 1850s.</note> 
                    can be found put to a similar use in Collingwood’s proof sheets for Poems (1891) (RF MS 70). More importantly, it was Collingwood's scholarship that provided the basis for how the early manuscripts 
                    were grouped in the bindings and slipcases. One blue-morocco slipcase, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="harry_lucy_poems_c_note.php">HARRY &#x0026; LUCY &#x007C; POEMS &#x007C; &#x0026;c</ref>, 
                    was made for a group comprised of MS I, MS II, MS III, MS IIIA, and MS IV. The slipcase is unlikely to have been constructed 
                    prior to 1902, when the Library Edition pointed out, in its "revised and completed" version of Collingwood's "Note," 
                    the existence of <ref type="apparatus" subtype="mss" target="msiiia_apparatus.php">MS IIIA</ref>. While Collingwood omitted MS IIIA from his "Note," if he even knew of this manuscript, 
                    presumably because it contained no poetry, the encasing of this set of Red Books, I through IV, was based on the thread of "Harry and Lucy" and the early poems that he first identified. 
                    Similarly, the choice to make blue-morocco slipscases for, respectively, MS V, MS VII, MS VIII, MS IX, and MS XI, is traceable ultimately to Collingwood's "Note." 
                    Only two manuscripts described in Collingwood's "Note" failed to receive the blue-morocco treatment&#x2014;MS X, which was divided up, partly in service of contributions made to the Ruskin Museum in Coniston, 
                    which was Collingwood's and Joan Severn's project; and MS VI, the neglect of which is harder to explain, since its roan boards are no sturdier than those of some other early manuscripts 
                    (perhaps its ravaged condition, with pages missing, made it seem unworthy of a slipcase, while rebinding was impractical).</p>
                <p>If Collingwood founded the group identity of the early manuscripts, others sustained and slightly extended this identity. The few manuscripts besides MS IIIA that were encased in blue morocco but that had 
                    <hi rend="italic">not</hi> been included in Collingwood's "Note" are exceptions that prove the rule of this identity. Three Red Books housed in the slipcase, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="juvenilia_note.php">Juvenilia</ref>--namely, <ref type="apparatus" subtype="mss" target="msja_apparatus.php">MS Juvenilia A</ref>, 
                    <ref type="apparatus" subtype="mss" target="msjb_apparatus.php">MS Juvenilia B</ref>, and <ref type="apparatus" subtype="mss" target="msjc_apparatus.php">MS Juvenilia C</ref>--formed 
                    an outlier because, like MS IIIA, they contained no poetry, but they also made no contribution to the "Harry and Lucy" series. 
                    The other manuscript to be handed down in blue morocco, a fair copy of <hi rend="italic">The King of the Golden River</hi>, probably was regarded as occupying a class by itself. 
                    Composed almost too late to qualify as juvenilia, yet in its subject matter seeming a culmination of Ruskin's early works, this manuscript was so treasured that, three decades later, 
                    it commanded one of the highest prices given for 
                    <hi rend="italic">any</hi> single manuscript in the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1930</ref>.</p> 
                <p>Early manuscripts that did not received the blue-morocco treatment were bound in the more workmanlike 
                    red buckram that characterizes all of Cook and Wedderburn's preservation efforts connected with editing the Library Edition&#x2014;from the bindings of their own transcripts 
                    (the volumes of typescript and handwritten transcriptions that formed the basis of the editing), to the many Ruskin manuscripts that still lay in the Brantwood study when they started work. 
                    Again, in this process, the early manuscripts were in the vanguard, the use of red buckram occurring as early as 1902 for MS X, which Collingwood described in his "Note" as merely a "cover," 
                    but which Cook and Wedderburn described in the revised "Note" for the Library Edition as "bound up in a volume." Likewise, MS IA, which the revised "Note" listed as an addition to Collingwood's bibliography, 
                    was a "thin folio, bound in red cloth"; and the early prose works, "Essay on the Relative Dignity of the Studies of Painting and Music" 
                    and "Chronicles of St. Bernard" had been bound together in red buckram by the time they were described in volume 1 (1902) of the Library Edition 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 2: 534, 530, 1: 266, 504; 
                    see <ref type="essay" target="editing_essay.php">Introductory Essay on Editing and Bibliography</ref> for the Library Edition's revision of Collingwood's "Note"). 
                    Thus, in 1902, the use of red buckram overlapped with the use of blue morocco, the latter being abandoned for care of the early manuscripts--and indeed for all other manuscripts bound in course of editing 
                    the Library Edition--perhaps because the trustees only now recognized the huge scope of the material remains to be preserved. The perceived difference in the treatments remained apparent decades later, 
                    however, when the blue morocco group was catalogued together in the first Sotheby's sale, the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1930</ref>, 
                    while the red buckram group of early manuscripts had to await the second sale, the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1931</ref>.</p>
                <here></here>
                <p>Sales authorized and unauthorized, were made to collectors and their agents who were already interested in Ruskin, but important questions arise regarding who among them were interested 
                    in the early Ruskin and why. No one was a collector exclusively of the early manuscripts, although some collectors such as Goodspeed and Sharp clearly thought of developing a significant portion 
                    of their collections around the earlier work. Even before Ruskin's death, the market for his early work had been stirred by collectors' interest in his early publications 
                    (but not in his manuscripts, which did not become legitimately available until later). This market interest in Ruskin's early and--by the later decades of the century--rare publications was, 
                    like the value of early rarities by other important Victorian writers, partly stimulated by the activities of forgers, especially the actions and publications of T. J. Wise.</p>
                
                
                
                 
                
                
                
                
                
                <p>In 1901, immediately following Ruskin's death, Joan Severn and W. G. Collingwood (jointly?) deposited a few of the early manuscripts in the Coniston village museum. 
                    One can perhaps think of this gift as enshrining the linear descent of possession within the family (now broadened to embrace the extended "family" members of the village, such as Susie Beever). 
                    Does this make sense?</p>
                <p>Another factor in instigating preservation may have been the bibliographic and collectors' interest in Ruskin outside the Brantwood circle, 
                    which developed prior to Ruskin's death. This kind of influence would have been indirect, since the collector's market traded only in published Ruskin. 
                    Manuscripts rarely within Brantwood and beyond, is very speculative, but it can be helpful merely to frame the questions accurately. no sales til Joan died? Puppet Show kept off market? 
                    Wedderburn in sole control (38: xxvi) and greatest collector (38:xviii) Following the period of preserving manuscripts in connection with editing the Library Edition 
                    and founding the Ruskin Museum in Coniston, some early manuscripts took a more shadowy, unauthorized course to their present locations, both before and after the Sotheby’s and Brantwood estate sales. 
                    Unauthorized sales can usually be traced, through documentation or presumptively, to Wilks.... Discussed in connection with collectors. 
                    Dearden says Haddon Adams “began laying the foundations of his collection during a visit to Coniston in June, 1928” (Dearden, “Haddon C. Adams Bequest”) Why Americans? 
                    The American interest in Ruskin doubtless formed part of the more general surge of American collecting, particularly by those interested in English literature 
                    (see Carter, Taste and Technique in Book-Collecting 34–36) See “My First Editor”: little shelf, p. 96</p>
                <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                        <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                        <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Body paragraph.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>