<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="annuals_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Annuals and Other Illustrated Books</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#KBV">Kyle B. Volkmann</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#KBT">Katrina B. Thomas</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="bibliographical">
                <head type="title">Annuals and Other Illustrated Books</head>
                <p>Annuals were anthologies of verse, short fiction, and pictures&#x2014;the latter typically reproduced by engraving&#x2014;which were intended to serve as gifts and tokens of friendship. 
                    Combining literary and pictorial interest, the annuals were essentially ekphrastic collections, 
                    in that they tended to privilege pictures, and situated writing in relation to a picture in some fashion. 
                    Often, writers were hired to write to an engraving, rather than the artist illustrating existing tales or verse, 
                    just as <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> composed his poem, <ref type="apparatus" target="saltzburg_apparatus.php">&#x201C;<title type="poem" corresp="#SALTZBURG">Saltzburg</title>&#x201D;</ref> in response to an engraved view of the city. 
                    As a form of gift publication, the annuals were published toward the end of a given year, 
                    typically in November in time for the holiday season of Christmas and New Year&#x02BC;s; hence, their titles named the year following that of their actual publication. 
                    For example, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> first appearance in an annual was in the volume entitled 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; and Winter&#x02BC;s Wreath: A Christmas and New Year&#x02BC;s Present for MDCCCXXXV</hi></ref>, 
                    which went to press as early as <date when="1834-08">August 1834</date>, to be available for purchase before <date when="1834-12">December</date> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#VIGNEPRINGLE">Vigne, <hi rend="italic">Thomas Pringle</hi></ref>, 244). 
                    The annuals first emerged in the <date notBefore="1820" notAfter="1829">1820s</date>, quickly becoming a distinctive feature of early Victorian print culture, 
                    and they were widely popular with the middle and upper classes by the time <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> began publishing in them in the <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date>.
                </p>
                <div type="section" xml:id="HISTORY">
                    <head type="section">History and Development</head>
                    <p>The first British annual was <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title>, published by the firm of <orgName corresp="#ACKERMANN">Ackermann</orgName> in <date when="1822">1822</date>, for the holiday season of <date notBefore="1822-11" notAfter="1823-02">1822&#x2013;23</date>. 
                        <persName corresp="#RAP">Rudolf Ackermann</persName> (<date notBefore="1764" notAfter="1834">1764&#x2013;1834</date>) as a publisher&#x2014;putting aside his many other interests and entrepreneurial successes&#x2014;was known primarily for his high quality, extravagant topographical books, 
                        usually illustrated by brightly hand&#x2010;colored aquatints. For the <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title>, <persName corresp="#RAP">Ackermann</persName> hit upon a successful blend 
                        of polite and sentimental verse, tales, and engraved illustration aimed at middle&#x2010; and upper&#x2010;class consumers, especially women, 
                        who already formed the primary audience for the <orgName corresp="#ACKERMANN">Ackermann</orgName> firm&#x02BC;s in&#x2010;house magazine, 
                        the <title type="periodical" corresp="#REPOSITORYOFARTS" rend="italic">Repository of Arts</title> (<date when="1809">1809</date>&#x2013;<date when="1828">28</date>). 
                        The magazine&#x02BC;s editor, <persName corresp="#FS">Frederic Shoberl</persName> (<date notBefore="1775" notAfter="1853">1775&#x2013;1853</date>), did double duty as the editor of the <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FORDACKERMANN">Ford, <hi rend="italic">Ackermann</hi></ref>, 70, 64&#x2013;65, 80&#x2013;83).
                    </p>
                    <p>According to <persName corresp="#AR">Anne Renier</persName>, <persName corresp="#RAP">Ackermann</persName> based his creation on a combination of two models, the German <hi rend="italic">Taschenbuch</hi>, and the British &#x201C;pocket book.&#x201D; 
                        The former kind of publication offered the literary contents and illustration for which the British annuals became known, 
                        whereas the latter kind were familiar to British consumers as supplying tables of useful information along with blank or illustrated pages for the owner&#x02BC;s memoranda 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RENIERFRIENDSHIPSOFFERING">Renier, <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref>, 5&#x2013;6). 
                        To this ancestry of the annual, <persName corresp="#KDH">Katherine Harris</persName> adds the printed traditions of the emblem book and the almanac, 
                        as well as the homemade fashions of the lady&#x02BC;s album and the scrapbook, which were compiled by hand for personal collecting, 
                        although the cover and blank pages may have been manufactured 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HARRISBORROWING">Harris, <title type="essay" corresp="#HARRISBORROWING">&#x201C;Borrowing, Altering, and Perfecting the Literary Annual Form&#x201D;</title></ref>).
                        (Some confusion of terms arises from the similarity between the German <hi rend="italic">Taschenbuch</hi> 
                        and the English <hi rend="italic">pocket book</hi>, both terms referring to the publications&#x02BC; portable size, 
                        but the German form was literary, whereas the English <date notBefore="1701" notAfter="1800">eighteenth&#x2010;century</date> pocket book was akin to the almanac and diary.)
                    </p>
                    <p><date notBefore="1701" notAfter="1800">Eighteenth&#x2010;century</date> pocket books resembled almanacs by including reference information, especially tables of facts that were deemed appropriate 
                        for fashionable readers, such as lists of the members of the British royalty, the crowned heads of Europe, and names of other dignitaries. 
                        This convention appealed to <persName corresp="#RAP">Ackermann</persName>, since he marketed his books and art supplies primarily to leisured and wealthy clientele, 
                        and accordingly the first <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title> included a &#x201C;General Summary of Houses, Families, and Persons in <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">Great Britain</placeName>, in <date when="1821">1821</date>,&#x201D; along with tables of other demographic 
                        information about <placeName corresp="#ENGLAND">England</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#WALES">Wales</placeName>, and <placeName corresp="#SCOTLAND">Scotland</placeName>. 
                        This first British annual also reflected the original use of the pocket book as an engagement calendar,   
                        presenting a series of emblematic treatments of the twelve months, reproduced from copper engravings 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JUNGSTOTHARD">Jung, <title type="essay" corresp="#JUNGSTOTHARD">&#x201C;Print Culture, Marketing, and Thomas Stothard&#x02BC;s Illustrations for <hi rend="italic">The Royal Engagement Pocket Atlas</hi>, 1779&#x2013;1826&#x201D;</title></ref>, 31; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HUNNISETTSTEELENGRAVED">Hunnisett, <title type="essay" corresp="#HUNNISETTSTEELENGRAVED"><hi rend="italic">Steel&#x2010;Engraved Book Illustration in England</hi></title></ref>, 139; 
                        and see the facsimiles of <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title> available in 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HARRISFORGETMENOT">Harris, ed., <hi rend="italic">&#x201C;Forget Me Not&#x201D; Archive</hi></ref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>After the first <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title>, the <orgName corresp="#ACKERMANN">Ackermann</orgName> firm dropped the almanac features; and according to <persName corresp="#KDH">Katherine Harris</persName>, by <date when="1825">1825</date> 
                        all annuals had abandoned presentation of fashionably useful information in favor of strictly literary and pictorial contents 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HARRISBORROWING">Harris, &#x201C;Borrowing, Altering, and Perfecting the Literary Annual Form&#x201D;</ref>, 7).
                        Nonetheless, the annuals reflected lasting legacies of the pocket book, characteristics that point to the original uses of the earlier ephemeral print items. 
                        One legacy was the publication schedule of pocket books, which were released on the market in the autumn for purchase as Christmas and New Year&#x02BC;s presents. 
                        Pocket books, like modern calendars, usually lost value after the beginning of the New Year, 
                        and it was to avoid this obsolescence that the almanac material was dropped from the early annuals 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HUNNISETTSTEELENGRAVED">Hunnisett, <hi rend="italic">Steel&#x2010;Engraved Book Illustration in England</hi></ref>, 139). 
                        For example, in an early volume of the annual, <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi>, the editor, <persName corresp="#TKH">T. K. Hervey</persName>, 
                        announced his intention to remove &#x201C;all those features which marked&#x201D; the publication &#x201C;as more peculiarly adapted 
                        for one season of the year than another&#x201D; and to raise the production above the annuals&#x02BC; &#x201C;toy&#x2010;like attributes&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliiography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1826">Hervey, ed., <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi> [1826]</ref>, vi).
                        Nonetheless, the annuals retained the pattern of publishing in the autumn of one year a title that was meant &#x201C;for&#x201D; the following year. 
                        Thus, the first <hi rend="italic">Forget Me Not: A Christmas and New Year&#x02BC;s Present for <date when="1823">1823</date></hi> was published in <date when="1822-10">October 1822</date> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FORDACKERMANN">Ford, <title type="bibliography" corresp="#FORDACKERMANN"><hi rend="italic">Ackermann</hi></title></ref>, 65).
                    </p>
                    <p>Another legacy of the pocket book was consumers&#x02BC; perception of this niche of print culture as representing elegant, but not costly mementos. 
                        In the case of a shrewdly produced and marketed pocket book, 
                        such as <title type="manual_guide" corresp="#ROYALENGAGEMENTPOCKETATLAS" rend="italic">The Royal Engagement Pocket Atlas</title> (<date when="1779">1779</date>&#x2013;<date when="1826">1826</date>), the ephemeral publication could anticipate the literary annual 
                        by being turned into permanent keepsakes. The publisher commissioned sophisticated, historical&#x2010; or literary&#x2010;themed engravings that were worth preserving, 
                        and the pocket book was available in a range of bindings, from functional to elegant. 
                        Owners, too, transformed the ephemeral publication into a keepsake, by dedicating the diary pages to memoranda more lasting than notes about engagements, 
                        and in some cases by decorating copies with precious handmade coverings, presumably to serve as personal gifts 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JUNGSTOTHARD">Jung, <title type="essay" corresp="#JUNGSTOTHARD">&#x201C;Print Culture, Marketing, and Thomas Stothard&#x02BC;s Illustrations for <hi rend="italic">The Royal Engagement Pocket Atlas</hi>, 1779&#x2013;1826&#x201D;</title></ref>, 34&#x2013;36). 
                        With the addition of embellishments to the diary pages, such as the vignettes on literary themes heading the otherwise blank pages of the 
                        <title type="manual_guide" corresp="#ROYALENGAGEMENTPOCKETATLAS" rend="italic">Royal Engagement Pocket Atlas</title>, pocket books of this class were produced well into the <date notBefore="1801" notAfter="1900">nineteenth century</date>, 
                        and they even began themselves to feature literary content in response to&#x2014;and even anticipating&#x2014;the impact of the annuals 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JUNGILLUSTRATED">Jung, <title type="essay" corresp="#JUNGILLUSTRATED">&#x201C;The Illustrated Pocket Diary&#x201D;</title></ref>, 25, 33, 36; 
                        and see <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="rogers_samuel_note.php">Samuel Rogers (<date when="1763">1763</date>&#x2013;<date when="1855">1855</date>)</ref>).
                    </p> 
                    <p>When adapting features of the <hi rend="italic">Taschenbuch</hi> from his native <placeName corresp="#GERMANY">Germany</placeName>, 
                        <persName corresp="#RAP">Ackermann</persName> drew on the popular Gothic and sentimental emphasis in these publications. 
                        As <persName corresp="#KDH">Harris</persName> has discovered, <persName corresp="#RAP">Ackermann</persName> modeled the <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title> 
                        more closely than he acknowledged on a particular <hi rend="italic">Taschenbuch</hi>, the <title type="annual" corresp="#VERGISSMEINNICHT" rend="italic">Vergissmeinnicht</title>, edited by 
                        <persName corresp="#HC">Heinrich Clauren</persName> (<persName corresp="#HC">Karl Heun</persName>, <date when="1771">1771</date>&#x2013;<date when="1854">1854</date>), 
                        whose popular story, &#x201C;<title type="prose" corresp="#MIMILI">Mimili,</title>&#x201D; appeared in the <title type="archive" corresp="#HARRISFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title> for <date when="1824">1824</date> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HARRISBORROWING">Harris, <title type="essay" corresp="#HARRISBARROWNING">&#x201C;Borrowing, Altering, and Perfecting the Literary Annual Form&#x201D;</title></ref>, 14&#x2013;16).
                        Based on the proven success of these formulas, the popularity of these first volumes of <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title> proved so overwhelming  
                        that the <orgName corresp="#ACKERMANN">Ackermann</orgName> firm diverted a major share of its resources into the books&#x02BC; production, 
                        consequently relinquishing experiments with lithography, 
                        a new method of reproducting images that the firm had recently helped to introduce to <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">Britain</placeName>. 
                        <persName corresp="#RAP">Ackermann</persName> turned over the opportunity to develop the new technology to <persName corresp="#CH">Charles Hullmandel</persName> (see 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="prout_samuel_note.php">Samuel Prout (<date when="1783">1783</date>&#x2013;<date when="1852">1852</date>)</ref>). 
                        Ackermann&#x02BC;s success and increased production immediately inspired other publishers to enter the field with their own annual. The first imitator was 
                        the firm of <orgName corresp="#RELFE">Lupton Relfe</orgName>, whose 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="friendships_offering_note.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref> 
                        appeared in <date when="1823">1823</date>&#x2013;<date when="1824">24</date>; 
                        and the second was <orgName corresp="#RH">Hurst, Robinson</orgName>, 
                        whose <title type="annual" corresp="#LITERARYSOUVENIR" rend="italic">Literary Souvenir</title> appeared in <date when="1824">1824</date>&#x2013;<date when="1825">25</date>. 
                        The latter was edited for a decade by the energetic <persName corresp="#AWEDITOR">Alaric Watts</persName> (<date when="1797">1797</date>&#x2013;<date when="1864">1864</date>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Hereafter, as shown in the &#x201C;Chronological Index of British Literary Annual Titles&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HARRISFORGETMENOT">Harris, ed., <hi rend="italic">&#x201C;Forget Me Not&#x201D; Archive</hi></ref>), 
                        new annuals proliferated exponentially, surviving the depression in the book trade caused not only by the panic of <date when="1826">1826</date> but also the Reform agitation 
                        of <date when="1826">1832</date>. While all this effort could be summed up by the poet laureate, <persName corresp="#RS">Robert Southey</persName> 
                        (<date when="1774">1774</date>&#x2013;<date when="1843">1843</date>), as &#x201C;picture&#x2010;books for grown children&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RENIERFRIENDSHIPSOFFERING">Renier, <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref>, 12&#x2013;13), 
                        the ekphrastic connection between picture and text was profoundly significant to the audiences&#x2014;child and adult, alike&#x2014;of the unfolding 
                        <date notBefore="1837-06-20" notAfter="1901-01-22">Victorian Era</date>. 
                        For example, copies of the three most important founding titles 
                        of the genre&#x2014;<title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title>, <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi>, and the <title type="annual" corresp="#LITERARYSOUVENIR" rend="italic">Literary Souvenir</title>&#x2014;were owned by 
                        the Bront&#x00EB; family, and it was the pictorial appeal of annuals that most influenced the siblings&#x02BC; imaginations 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ALEXANDERBRONTEANNUALS">Alexander, &#x201C;&#x2018;That Kingdom of Gloom&#x2019;&#x201D;</ref>, 414&#x2013;18). 
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> was captured by an engraving after <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="turner_j_m_w_note.php"><persName corresp="#JMWT">Turner</persName> (1775&#x2013;1851)</ref>, &#x201C;<title type="engraving" corresp="#TURNEREHRENBREITSTEINIMAGE">Ehrenbreitstein</title>,&#x201D; 
                        in the <hi rend="italic">Keepsake</hi> for <date when="1833">1833</date>, 
                        even before the boy began his long association with the annual 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="friendships_offering_note.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref> 
                        in <date when="1834">1834</date>.</p>
                    <p>Some successful aspects of marketing of the annuals, such as their time&#x2010;consuming method of <ref type="internal" target="#STEELENGRAVING">steel engravings</ref> 
                        and their extravagant <ref type="internal" target="#BINDINGS">bindings</ref>, ultimately proved the undoing of the annuals. 
                        For some publishers, the high cost of production, often combined with an expensive pursuit of celebrated contributors, became unsustainable by the <date notBefore="1840" notAfter="1849">1840s</date>, 
                        and the annuals died out altogether by the <date notBefore="1860" notAfter="1869">1860s</date> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#CURRIEINTROHOGGANNUALS">Currie, introduction to <title corresp="#CURRIEINTROHOGGANNUALS"><hi rend="italic">Contributions to Annuals and Gift&#x2010;Books</hi></title></ref>, xvii&#x2013;xviii).
                        After the reign of the annuals had passed, the later Victorians found it easy to mock the often run&#x2010;of&#x2010;the&#x2010;mill contents of these publications, 
                        which alternated between simpering sentiment and melodramatic horror, but the grown&#x2010;up Victorians could not so easily escape the influence of the annuals&#x02BC; images 
                        over their imagination in youth.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="STEELENGRAVING">
                    <head type="section">Steel Engraving</head>
                   <p>One great significance of <persName corresp="#AWEDITOR">Watts&#x02BC;s</persName> <title type="periodical" corresp="#LITERARYSOUVENIR" rend="italic">Literary Souvenir</title> lay in the introduction of steel engraving to the annuals&#x2014;that is, 
                       intaglio printing from a steel plate. Typically, the steel plate was covered with an etching ground, 
                       which was engraved by an etching needle in preparation for etching by acid, and then the image was further worked using a burin. 
                       Because steel is much harder than copper, its durability increased the viability of print runs to the thousands of impressions, 
                       compared to the few hundreds of impressions possible from a copper plate, 
                       which rapidly wore thin from the abrasion of wiping 
                       (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BENSONPRINTEDPICTURE">Benson, <title corresp="#BENSONPRINTEDPICTURE"><hi rend="italic">Printed Picture</hi></title>, 36</ref>; 
                       <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BAINGIFTBOOKILLUSTRATIONS">Bain, <title type="essay" corresp="#BAINGIFTBOOKILLUSTRATIONS">&#x201C;Gift Book and Annual Illustrations&#x201D;</title></ref>, 19&#x2013;21; and see 
                       <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="rogers_samuel_note.php">Samuel Rogers (<date when="1763">1763</date>&#x2013;<date when="1855">1855</date>)</ref>). 
                       While copper rapidly yields lighter and dimmer impressions, its more pliable surface is easier to engrave than stubborn steel; 
                       and therefore innovations were required to make steel practicable for this use, 
                       such as softening the steel for engraving and then hardening the plate. 
                       With these developments, the art grew rapidly in the <date notBefore="1820" notAfter="1829">1820s</date>  
                       (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HUNNISETTENGRAVEDONSTEEL">Hunnisett, <title corresp="#HUNNISETTENGRAVEDONSTEEL"><hi rend="italic">Engraved on Steel</hi></title></ref>, 63, 110, 121; 
                       and for detailed accounts of the processes of tracing the source image, etching and engraving the steel plate, taking proofs for checking, 
                       and printing from the plate, all of which typically required many weeks and even years for very ambitious projects, 
                       see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BAINGIFTBOOKILLUSTRATIONS">Bain, <title type="essay" corresp="#BAINGIFTBOOKILLUSTRATIONS">&#x201C;Gift Book and Annual Illustrations&#x201D;</title></ref>, 21&#x2013;23; 
                       and <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HUNNISETTSTEELENGRAVED">Hunnisett, <title type="essay" corresp="#HUNNESETTSTEELENGRAVED"><hi rend="italic">Steel&#x2010;Engraved Book Illustration in England</hi></title></ref>, 
                       42&#x2010;52).
                   </p>
                   <p>In book illustration, 
                       the literary annuals were among the first kinds of publications to profit from the new technique. 
                       <title type="periodical" corresp="#RAPFORGETMENOT" rend="italic">Forget Me Not</title> had been illustrated using copper etching for its first three volumes, until steel was adopted in the volume for <date when="1825">1825</date> 
                       (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FORDACKERMANN">Ford, <hi rend="italic">Ackermann</hi></ref>, 65). 
                       In this regard, the <title type="periodical" corresp="#LITERARYSOUVENIR" rend="italic">Literary Souvenir</title>, published by <orgName corresp="#RH">Hurst, Robinson</orgName>, raced alongside its famous competitor, 
                       producing fine results in the second year of <persName corresp="#AWEDITOR">Watts&#x02BC;s</persName> editorship. 
                       Unfortunately, the success coincided with the financial panic of <date when="1826">1826</date>, 
                       which brought down many publishers, including <orgName corresp="#RH">Hurst, Robinson</orgName>, yet <persName corresp="#AWEDITOR">Watts</persName> kept the <title type="periodical" corresp="#LITERARYSOUVENIR" rend="italic">Literary Souvenir</title> 
                       afloat under his own proprietorship as well as editorship. Payments to authors were not always substantial or regular, except in the cases of lavish fees offered to the most celebrated 
                       writers, such as <persName corresp="#WW">Wordsworth</persName>, or to the most sought-after artists, such as 
                       <persName corresp="#JMWT">Turner</persName>. 
                       (Privately, some editors, engravers, and publishers built up significant collections of paintings from the canvases and drawings commissioned for engraved images 
                       [<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HUNNISETTSTEELENGRAVED">Hunnisett, <hi rend="italic">Steel&#x2010;Engraved Book Illustration in England</hi></ref>, 
                       42&#x2010;41, 37&#x2010;38, 166; 
                       <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#CURRIEINTROHOGGANNUALS">Currie, introduction to <hi rend="italic">Contributions to Annuals and Gift&#x2010;Books</hi></ref>, 
                       xx&#x2013;xxi].)
                   </p> 
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="BINDINGS">
                    <head type="section">Bindings</head>
                    <p>Another feature of the annuals that set apart these publications as especially desirable consumer items was their rich bindings. 
                        The first annuals were covered with glazed paper boards that were printed with a design framing the title, 
                        and the volumes were protected by a slipcase of the same materials and printed design. By the 
                        <date notBefore="1827" notAfter="1829">final quarter of the 1820s</date>, these paper and cloth bindings were being outdone by silk, 
                        which was regarded as not only a luxurious and feminine material but also as supplanting the need for a slipcase. 
                        In <date when="1827">1827</date>, however, all this showiness was trumped by 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="friendships_offering_note.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref>, 
                        which announced itself as newly acquired by the firm of <orgName corresp="#SMITHELDER">Smith, Elder</orgName> by boasting embossed leather boards. 
                        As Eleanore Jamieson explains in 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JAMIESONBINDINGSTYLES">&#x201C;The Binding Styles of the Gift Books and Annuals&#x201D;</ref>, 
                        the stylized patterns used in embossed covers like that for 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="friendships_offering_note.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref> 
                        were called <hi rend="italic">arabesque</hi>, incorporating floral and other pictorial elements. The arabesque pattern 
                        was distinguished from <hi rend="italic">cathedral</hi> patterns, which were associated with devotional publications. 
                        A cheaper alternative means of embossing was to employ 
                        <hi rend="italic">engine&#x2010;turned</hi> designs, resulting in the fine&#x2010;lined ornaments developed originally for bank notes. 
                        But by the <date notBefore="1827" notAfter="1829">final quarter of the 1820s</date>, arabesque designs could as well be produced by machine 
                        (pp. 10&#x2013;13, and see 7&#x2013;14). 
                        Indeed, the flamboyance, yet relative inexpensiveness, of these bindings, which anticipate the ornate fancifulness 
                        achieved in the heyday of Victorian bookbinding, 
                        the <date notBefore="1860" notAfter="1879">1860s&#x2013;70s</date>, indicates how suddenly factory modes of production had transformed a cottage industry 
                        that, at the start of the nineteenth century, had remained essentially unchanged for centuries 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#STONEPICTURESANDPATTERNS">Stone, ed., <hi rend="italic">Pictures and Patterns</hi></ref>, 10).
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="LANDSCAPEANNUAL">
                    <head type="section">The Landscape Annual</head>
                    <p>A special class of the annual was the <hi rend="italic">landscape annual</hi>. The emergence of this subclass, when viewed from the perspective of the 
                        <date notBefore="1820" notAfter="1839">1820s&#x2013;30s</date>, can be understood as a project by a star entrepreneur of steel engraving, 
                        <persName corresp="#CTH">Charles Heath</persName> (<date notBefore="1785" notAfter="1848">1785&#x2013;1848</date>). <persName corresp="#CTH">Heath</persName> was associated 
                        with the founding of one of the earliest, showiest, and longest surviving of the annuals, the <hi rend="italic">Keepsake</hi> 
                        (<date notBefore="1828" notAfter="1857">1828&#x2013;57</date>). 
                        From the annual&#x02BC;s beginnings in <date when="1827">1827</date>, <persName corresp="#CTH">Heath</persName> showcased engravings after <persName corresp="#JMWT">Turner</persName>, 
                        and in the same year <persName corresp="#CTH">Heath</persName> also published 
                        <title type="periodical" corresp="#PICTURESQUEVIEWS" rend="italic">Picturesque Views in England and Wales</title> (<date when="1827">1827</date>), 
                        for which the engraver commissioned and purchased 120 watercolors by <persName corresp="#JMWT">Turner</persName>. 
                        In <date when="1828">1828</date>, <persName corresp="#CTH">Heath</persName> and his editor for the <hi rend="italic">Keepsake</hi>, 
                        <persName corresp="#FMR">Frederic Mansel Reynolds</persName> (ca. 1800&#x2013;1850), 
                        journeyed personally to the <geogName corresp="#SCOTTISHBORDERS">Scottish borders</geogName> and the <geogName corresp="#LAKEDISTRICT">Lake District</geogName>, 
                        aiming to solicit contributions from the celebrated poets associated with these landscapes, <persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName>, 
                        <persName corresp="#WW">Wordsworth</persName>, and <persName corresp="#RS">Southey</persName>.</p>
                        <p>The enticement of this class of annuals for the Ruskin family can be measured by an episode in <date when="1832">1832</date>, when the idea was floated 
                        of producing a new deluxe edition of <title type="collected_poems" corresp="#THEQUEENSWAKE" rend="italic">The Queen&#x02BC;s Wake</title> (<date notBefore="1813" notAfter="1819">1813&#x2013;19</date>) as a charitable scheme supporting the Scottish poet, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="hogg_james_note.php"><persName corresp="#JH">James Hogg</persName> (ca. <date notBefore="1770" notAfter="1835">1770&#x2013;1835</date>)</ref>. 
                            <persName corresp="#JH">Hogg</persName> urged that the gift book &#x201C;should be a work something like The Keepsake&#x201D;<!-- not italicized in original --> with landscape illustrations by 
                            <persName corresp="#JMARTIST">John Martin</persName> (<date when="1789" notAfter="1854">1789&#x2010;1854</date>)
                            &#x201C;so as to make it a drawing&#x2010;room book.&#x201D;  
                        To this effort, <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> subscribed generously 
                        with a donation of &#x00A3;20, pleading for the honor of being listed as the first subscriber 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HOGGWORKSLETTERSVOL3">Hughes, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Collected Letters: Volume 3, 1832&#x2010;1835</hi></ref>, 33, 32n.). 
                        It is significant that <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> sent the donation on <date when="1832-02-08">8 February 1832</date>, 
                        his son&#x02BC;s <date when="1832-02-08">thirteenth birthday</date>, when the boy is believed to have received another 
                        deluxe edition of an established modern landscape classic&#x2012;the <date when="1830">1830</date> edition of 
                        <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> by <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="rogers_samuel_note.php"><persName corresp="#SR">Samuel Rogers</persName> (<date when="1763">1763</date>&#x2013;<date when="1855">1855</date></ref>), 
                            illustrated by <persName corresp="#JMWT">Turner</persName> and others. The deluxe <hi rend="italic">The Queen&#x02BC;s Wake</hi> was never produced. 
                            Had it appeared, the book might have taken a place in the Ruskin family mythology alongside <persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>, 
                            since both <persName corresp="#JH">Hogg</persName> and <persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName> served personally as mentors to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                            in <date when="1834">1834</date>, when the youth published his own topographical poem to the accompaniment of a steel&#x2010;engraved landscape plate, 
                            <ref type="apparatus" target="saltzburg_apparatus.php">&#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;</ref>, in 
                            <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; and Winter&#x02BC;s Wreath: A Christmas and New Year&#x02BC;s Present for MDCCCXXXV</hi></ref> 
                            (see <ref type="apparatus" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_apparatus.php#MENTORS">Account of a Tour on the Continent: Discussion&#x2014;Mentors</ref>).
                    </p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#CTH">Heath</persName> secured famous poets&#x02BC; 
                        contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Keepsake</hi>, by enticing them with 
                        offers of cash that were so princely that he fatally strained relations with 
                        his publishers, the firms of <orgName corresp="#JENNINGS">Robert Jennings</orgName> and of 
                        <orgName corresp="#HURST">Hurst, Chance</orgName>. These ambitious schemes suggest that <persName corresp="#CTH">Heath</persName> was interested less in promoting 
                        landscape art per se than in promoting and rewarding himself, rather than 
                        publishers, with the proceeds of his talent for steel engraving; however, 
                        <persName corresp="#BH">Basil Hunnisett</persName> may be correct to credit <persName corresp="#CTH">Heath</persName> 
                        at least incidentally with the development of the 
                        landscape annual as a class (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HUNNISETTSTEELENGRAVED"><hi rend="italic">Steel&#x2010;Engraved Book Illustration in England</hi></ref>, 
                        142&#x2013;43, 146&#x2013;48, 163&#x2013;67; and see 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LEDBETTERHEATH">Ledbetter, &#x201C;&#x2018;The Copper and Steel Manufactory&#x2019; of Charles Heath&#x201D;</ref>). 
                        The landscape annuals produced in association with <persName corresp="#CTH">Heath&#x02BC;s</persName> large workshop
                        included the <title type="periodical" corresp="#RJLANDSCAPEANNUAL" rend="italic">Landscape Annual</title> (later retitled <title type="periodical" corresp="#RJLANDSCAPEANNUAL" rend="italic">Jennings&#x02BC; Landscape Annual</title>) 
                        (<date notBefore="1828" notAfter="1839">1828&#x2013;39</date>), the <title type="annual" corresp="#PICTURESQUEANNUAL" rend="italic">Picturesque Annual</title> 
                        (<date notBefore="1832" notAfter="1845">1832&#x2013;45</date>), and 
                        <title type="periodical" corresp="#TURNERSANNUALTOUR" rend="italic">Turner&#x02BC;s Annual Tour</title> (<date notBefore="1833" notAfter="1835">1833&#x2013;35</date>). These titles also prompted
                        imitators, such as the <title type="annual" corresp="#CONTINENTALANNUAL1832" rend="italic">Continental Annual and Romantic Cabinet</title>, published in <date when="1832">1832</date> by 
                        <orgName corresp="#SMITHELDER">Smith, Elder</orgName>, and illustrated by another favorite artist of the Ruskins&#x02BC;, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="prout_samuel_note.php"><persName corresp="#SP">Samuel Prout</persName> (<date when="1783">1783</date>&#x2013;<date when="1852">1852</date>)</ref>.
                    </p>
                    <p>At the same time, viewed in a longer perspective, 
                        the landscape annual can be situated in the broader context of travel writing and illustration, 
                        in which the steel&#x2010;engraved landscape annuals formed a stage between the British copper&#x2010;engraved topographical and antiquarian magazines 
                        published <date notBefore="1770" notAfter="1819">between the last three decades of the eighteenth century and first two decades of the nineteenth</date>, 
                        and the magazines promoting the etching revival <date notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">in the final three decades of the nineteenth century</date> 
                        (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ROBERTSBRITISHARTPERIODICALS">Roberts, &#x201C;British Art Periodicals of the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries&#x201D;</ref>, 3&#x2013;4). 
                        In this context, for the Ruskins, the landscape annuals belong to the category of topographical 
                        poetry and prose, such as <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> by 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="rogers_samuel_note.php"><persName corresp="#SR">Samuel Rogers</persName> (1763&#x2013;1855)</ref>; 
                        pictorial travelogues, with or without letterpress, such as 
                        <title type="collected_sketches" corresp="#PROUTSKETCHES" rend="italic">Facsimiles of Sketches Made in Flanders and Germany</title> by 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="prout_samuel_note.php"><persName corresp="#SP">Samuel Prout</persName> (<date when="1783">1783</date>&#x2013;<date when="1852">1852</date>)</ref>; 
                        and <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="travel_narratives_and_guidebooks_note.php">Travel Narratives and Guidebooks</ref>. 
                        Topographical poetry, travel narrative, and landscape illustration were often included in annuals that were not specifically landscape annuals; 
                        an example is <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> own first contribution to an annual, the poem 
                        <ref type="apparatus" target="saltzburg_apparatus.php">&#x201C;Saltzburg&#x201D;</ref>, published in <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi>. 
                        Unlike the illustrated literary annuals, however, which typically 
                        anthologized a miscellany of verse and prose along with illustrations of both landscapes and figures, which were contributed by a variety of writers and artists, 
                        the landscape annuals featured a single artist paired with a single writer of the letterpress. Although subordinated to the artist, 
                        the writer for a landscape annual could, like <persName corresp="#LR">Leitch Ritchie</persName>, 
                        see himself as contributing &#x201C;<hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> sketches of his own&#x201D; 
                        (qtd. in  <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HUNNISETTSTEELENGRAVED">Hunnisett, <hi rend="italic">Steel&#x2010;Engraved Book Illustration in England</hi></ref>, 147).
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="COLLECTEDEDITIONS">
                    <head type="section">Collected Editions</head>
                    <p>Another illustrated publication of the period, one that shared the medium of steel engraving with the annuals, but not their fancy bindings, 
                        was the collected edition of poetry or prose by a British author, gathered into uniformly bound volumes, which were solidly but inexpensively produced. 
                        The Ruskins had first&#x2010;hand experience of these editions in the <hi rend="italic">magnum opus</hi> of <persName corresp="#WS">Walter Scott</persName>>, 
                        which started the trend, and they witnessed the failed attempt by 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="hogg_james_note.php"><persName corresp="#JH">James Hogg</persName> (ca. <date notBefore="1770" notAfter="1835">1770&#x2013;1835</date>)</ref> 
                        to complete such an edition of the <title type="anthology" corresp="#ALTRIVETALES" rend="italic">Altrive Tales</title>. In order to economize, these editions featured only a few illustrations per volume, 
                        but publishers made up the deficiency by selling portfolios of prints, which collectors could bind either separately or along with the uniform edition in question 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HUNNISETTSTEELENGRAVED">Hunnisett, <hi rend="italic">Steel&#x2010;Engraved Book Illustration in England</hi></ref>, 135&#x2013;36).                    
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>