<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="glosses">
        <fileDesc xml:id="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_toc_glosses_contextual">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Plan for Continuation of the Account of a Tour on the Continent</title>
                <title type="sub">Glosses</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#AEH">Aimee E. Harris</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#LAL">Lauren A. Lambert</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2018-01-23">January 23, 2018</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Glasses Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="glosses">
                <note xml:id="FRANCFORTGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Francfort&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>The 
                    Ruskins arrived in Frankfurt am Main (anglicized as <hi rend="italic">Frankfort on the Main</hi> by Murray) on Saturday, 1 June 1833, and departed Tuesday, 4 June. 
                    Frankfurt was a free city of the Holy Roman Empire, its old fortifications replaced by public gardens. It was important as a banking and mercantile center, with a large Jewish population 
                    including such prosperous families as the Rothschilds. Ministers from Great Britain and Europe were stationed here, 
                    so Murray advised that "travellers going to Austria or Italy should not neglect . . . having their passport properly <hi rend="italic">vis&#x00E9;</hi>", 
                    Mary noting that the family's passports were sent to the Austrian ambassador for signature. They stayed in the Hotel de Russie, erected by a gentleman of property for his own use, according to Mary, 
                    and still recommended by Murray in 1836. On Sunday, all but Margaret attended Protestant services, and they were visited by a Mr. and Mrs. Koch (unidentified), who also received them in their home the next evening 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson, 1833</ref>, 28-30;
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKCONTINENT1836"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers on the Continent</hi></ref>, 402-5).
                    .</p>
                    
                    <p>On Monday, Mr. Koch drove the Ruskins to a cemetery, doubtless the <placeName type="building" corresp="#FRANKFURTNEWCEMETERY">New Cemetery (Neue Friedhof)</placeName> beyond the city walls, 
                        which Murray recommended for its "charming view of Frankfort, and the Taunus [River]". 
                        Opened in 1828, the New Cemetery presented an example of the public cemetery that was starting to replace church and churchyard burial, 
                        an antiquated custom that "deserve[d] to be abolished" in the view of <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="loudon_j_c_note.php">John Claudius Loudon</ref>, 
                        especially in "large and densely inhabited cities". 
                        Visiting the Frankfurt cemetery in about the same year as did the Ruskins, the English artist 
                        <persName corresp="#JML">James Mathews Leigh</persName> (<date notBefore="1808" notAfter="1860">1808&#x2013;60</date>) noted, like Loudon, the neoclassicism of the architecture, 
                        designed by Friedrich Rumpf (1795-1867), with grounds laid in English style by Sebastian Rinz (1782-1861). A Doric propylaeum formed the entrance, 
                        and a "simple colonnade . . . divided into fifty-five compartments" organized the plots, "each . . . devoted to a family vault". At each end of the colonnade stood a "handsome mausoleum". 
                        Mary Richardson, with her usual British pride, considered the Frankfurt cemetery inferior to one in Liverpool, 
                        likely referring to St. James's Cemetery, opened in 1829 as a pioneering British alternative to overcrowded urban churchyards. 
                        Designed by John Foster (1787-1846), this site likewise featured severe neoclassicism in the form of a Doric temple, the <placeName type="building" corresp="#LIVERPOOLORATORY">Oratory</placeName>. 
                        Thus, contemporary cemetery architecture and sepulchral monuments presented Ruskin with one notable experience of modern neoclassicism; see also 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="milan_architecture_note.php">Neoclassical and Napoleonic&#x2010;Era Architecture in Milan</ref>
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKCONTINENT1836">Murray, <hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers on the Continent</hi></ref>, 405; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LOUDONREVNEUFRIEDHOF">Loudon, review of <hi rend="italic">Der Neue Friedhof vom Frankfurt am Main</hi></ref>;
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson, 1833</ref>, 28-30;
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LIVERPOOLORATORY">&#x201C;The Oratory and St. James&#x02BC;s Cemetery&#x201D;</ref>).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="STRASBURGGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Strasburg&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>For 
                    the Ruskins' stay in Kehl and visit to Strasbourg, see 
                    <ref type="witness" target="oh_the_morn_looked_bright_on_hill_and_dale_poem_msviii.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JROHTHEMORNLOOKEDBRIGHT">&#x201C;Oh the morn looked bright on hill and dale&#x201D; [&#x201C;The Black Forest&#x201D;]</title></ref> 
                    and associated glosses. In Strasbourg, they visited the Gothic <placeName type="building" corresp="#NOTREDAMESTRASBOURG">cathedral</placeName>, and the 
                    <placeName type="building" corresp="#STTHOMASCHURCHSTRASBOURG">Lutheran Church of St. Thomas</placeName>, where they viewed the baroque 
                    <title type="artwork" corresp="PIGALLESAXEMAUSOLEUM">mausoleum of the <persName corresp="#MDESAXE">Mar&#x00E9;shal de Saxe</persName></title> (1753-76) 
                    by <persName corresp="#JPPIGALLE">Jean-Baptiste Pigalle</persName> (1714-85). Describing the monument in her travel diary, 
                    Mary Richardson describes how the allegorical figure of France strains to hold the figure of Death at bay as the military hero 
                    descends toward the tomb (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson, 1833</ref>, 34). 
                    Since Maurice de Saxe remained a Lutheran throughout his life, the commission of his elaborate tomb by the French crown 
                    was regarded as a symbol of tolerance of Protestantism in the province of Alsace.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="CONSTANCEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Constance&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Arriving 
                    on June 10, Mary Richardson laconically summed up the Ruskins' opinion of Constance as an ugly town but with a fine view of the lake. 
                    J. G. Ebel in his guidebook to Switzerland advised tourists that, "when this town was free [as an imperial city of the Holy Roman Empire], it was in a flourishing state; 
                    but it is now very much decayed, notwithstanding the efforts which Buonaparte made to re-establish it. 
                    The town is badly built, the houses filthy, and many of them uninhabited". As principal tourist sites, 
                    Ebel recommends places associated with the <date notBefore="1414" notAfter="1418">Council of Constance</date>, highlighting its condemnation for heresy and burning of the forerunners of Protestantism, 
                    <persName corresp="#JHUS">Jan Hus</persName> (1369-1415) and Jerome of Prague (1379-1416), and its anathematizing of the works of <persName corresp="#JWYCLIF">John Wyclif</persName> (d. 1384) 
                    and ordering the posthumous burning of his remains. Lake Constance, Ebel goes on, 
                    ranked as the largest in Switzerland, formed by the Rhine and lying in the foothills of the Alps, though its "prospects are not so picturesque as those of" Lake Geneva" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#EBELTRAVELLERSGUIDE"><persName corresp="#JGE">Ebel</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#EBELTRAVELLERSGUIDE"><hi rend="italic">Traveller&#x02BC;s Guide through Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 226&#x2013;27).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="WERDENBERGGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Werdenberg&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Mary Richardson 
                    mentions this village in passing on the route between Constance and <placeName corresp="#PFAFFERS">Bad Pf&#x00E4;fers</placeName>. John Murray III briefly describes 
                    the castle "in good preservation above the town" of Werdenberg, which "was the seat of a noble family . . . who played an important part in early Swiss history" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.hml#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><title type="guidebook" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838" rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</title></ref>, 173).</p></note>
                    
                <note xml:id="PFAFFERSGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Pfaffers&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Spelled 
                    <hi rend="italic">Pfeffers</hi> in nineteenth-century English guidebooks, and today known by <hi rend="italic">Pf&#x00E4;fers</hi>. Since the early Middle Ages 
                    Pf&#x00E4;fers was the site of Benedictine abbey, but the place was best known for its mineral springs, which John Murray III declared "one of the most extraordinary spots in Switzerland" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.hml#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><title type="guidebook" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838" rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</title></ref>, 173). 
                    The physician and travel writer, William Beattie (1793-1875), described Bad Pf&#x00E4;fers (today called the Tamina Gorge) as a "golden fleece guarded by a frightful dragon", 
                    approached through a "wild scene . . . without competitor among the many savage regions to which the human foot has found access", yet affording in its waters 
                    medicinal virtues that "in numerous cases . . . , in pharmaceutic principles, [are] . . . impossible to explain" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BEATTIESWITZERLANDILUSTRATED">Beattie, <title type="collected_art" corresp="#BEATTIESWITZERLANDILLUSTRATED" rend="italic">Switzerland Illustrated</title></ref>, 1:178, 179, 185). 
                    Mary Richardson begins her account with a sentence taken nearly verbatim from J. G. Ebel: "The waters have their source in an abyss from whence runs the Tamina, 
                    they are conducted to the bathing house by an aqueduct, raised about 200 feet above the river (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson, 1833</ref>, 39; 
                    see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#EBELTRAVELLERSGUIDE"><persName corresp="#JGE">Ebel</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#EBELTRAVELLERSGUIDE"><hi rend="italic">Traveller&#x02BC;s Guide through Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 233). 
                    She then describes their intrepid descent into the gorge, again borrowing on the following account in Ebel:</p>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <div>
                                <p>The most lively imagination could not describe the entrance of Tartarus, under so hideous a form as that which nature has displayed in framing the defile of the Tamina. 
                                    You enter it over a bridge composed of planks that rest on wedges beat into the rocks. This bridge is 6 or 700 paces long, which requires above a quarter of an hour 
                                    to get over, as you must proceed with great caution. It is suspended over the Tamina, which is heard to roll furiously beneath it thirty or forty feet deep. 
                                    Near to the bridge the defile is thirty feet wide, but lower down it straitens as it descends along the torrent. The lateral walls, cleft and torn in divers ways, 
                                    rise 200 feet high, bend towards each other in the shape of a dome, and are 290 feet in height at that part where they entirely join. The faint light which illumines 
                                    the entrance of the defile disappears in proportion as you proceed; and the damp cold that prevails increases the horror of the place. Sometimes the rocks 
                                    that overhang the bridge are so close, that they will not allow one to stand up; and at another time they are so distant from it, that they no longer serve as a support. 
                                    The bridge is narrow, often very slippery, and it will sometimes occur that one single plank stands between the traveller and the dark abyss of the Tamina. . . . 
                                    The best method of avoiding danger is to walk between two men, each of them holding the extremities of a pole on the side of the precipice, which will serve as a support 
                                    and a railing to the tourist. The spring is situated beyond the bridge. . . . I shall invite all such people, who are unwilling to expose themselves to the danger 
                                    of going as far as the spring, to advance at least fifty paces on the bridge, beyond the entrance of the defile, and to sit down there to view at leisure the terrific prospect 
                                    of that dreadful passage.</p>
                                
                                <p>(<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#EBELTRAVELLERSGUIDE"><persName corresp="#JGE">Ebel</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#EBELTRAVELLERSGUIDE"><hi rend="italic">Traveller&#x02BC;s Guide through Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 444&#x2013;45)</p>
                            </div>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <p>The Ruskins took this advice, Mary commenting: "We did not go quite to the end for it was so frightful, the rocks rise high above the shelf, and are so close to each other 
                        as almost to exclude daylight" (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson, 1833</ref>, 39).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="ITALIAGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Italia, Italia&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Presumably, 
                    this work or section would have functioned similarly to the poem <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALYPOEM">"Italy"</title> in Samuel Rogers's 
                    <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALY"><hi rend="italic">Italy</hi></title>, a poem that begins by posing the rhetorical question, "Am I in Italy?", which the narrator excitedly pursues 
                    with "Surprise, and doubt, and self-congratulation" (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ROGERSITALY1830">Rogers, <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALY1830"><hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> [1830]</title></ref>, 41). 
                    Rogers places his poem between two sets of poems, one pair about the lakes region, <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSCOMO">"Como"</title> and <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSBERGAMO">"Bergamo"</title>, 
                    and the series of poems about Venice, beginning with <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSCOLLALTO">"Coll'Alto"</title> and <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSVENICE">"Venice"</title>. 
                    Ruskin also follows Rogers in situating the poem conveying greetings to Italy following a poem about crossing the Alps--in Rogers's <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALY1830"><hi rend="italic">Italy</hi></title>, 
                    <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSTHEALPS">"The Alps"</title>, and in Ruskin's "Account", 
                    <ref type="witness" target="passing_the_alps_poem_msia_g2.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRPASSINGTHEALPSPOEM">&#x201C;Passing the Alps&#x201D;</title></ref>. 
                    See <ref type="apparatus" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_apparatus.php#ROGERSINFLUENCEONEXTENSION">The Influence of Rogers&#x02BC;s Poetry on Ruskin&#x02BC;s Planned Extension of the Composite&#x2010;Genre Travelogue to Italy and Switzerland</ref>.</p></note>
                    
                    
                <note xml:id="CORSOGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;The corso of Milan&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>In <date when="1847">1847</date>, the 
                    <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKNORTHERNITALY1847"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Northern Italy</hi></title> reported that, &#x201C;[d]uring the sumnmer, 
                    the fashionable evening drive is in the <placeName corresp="#PORTAVENEZIA">Corso di Porta Orientale</placeName>; most particularly on Sundays and Thursdays&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKNORTHERNITALY1847"><persName corresp="#GBM">Maule</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKNORTHERNITALY1847"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Northern Italy</hi></title></ref>, 142). 
                    Taking their drive on a <date when="1833-06-19">Wednesday, June 19</date>, <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName> remarked that the <placeName type="building" corresp="#PORTAVENEZIA">Corso</placeName> &#x201C;was full of carriages like our <placeName corresp="#HYDEPARK">Hyde Park</placeName>, but not half so splendid&#x201D;; 
                    and afterward, in &#x201C;Milanese fashion&#x201D;, they enjoyed an ice 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson</title>, <date when="1833">1833</date></ref>, 50). Nonplussed by these modern urban public spaces, <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary</persName> and <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName> 
                    responded enthusiastically to the Gothic cathedral, a preference that led early in the development of the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNT">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title> to <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s only completed poem about <placeName corresp="#MILAN">Milan</placeName>, 
                    <ref type="witness" target="milan_cathedral_poem_msia_g2.php"><title type="poem" corresp="#JRMILANCATHEDRAL">&#x201C;Milan Cathedral&#x201D;</title></ref>. 
                    In that poem, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> emphasizes the vertical thrust of the carthedral, comparing its spires to <geogName corresp="#MONTEROSA">Monte Rosa</geogName> rising on the city&#x02BC;s horizon, 
                    whereas he projected, but evidently failed to execute a poem or essay on the <placeName type="building" corresp="#PORTAVENEZIA">Corso</placeName>, which presumably would have directed attention to the horizontal axes and breadth of the <placeName corresp="#MILAN">Enlightenment city</placeName>. 
                    Nonetheless, the Ruskins did seek out monuments in <placeName corresp="#MILAN">Milan</placeName> that attested to <persName corresp="NBE">Napoleon</persName>&#x02BC;s thwarted plans 
                    to impress the stamp of imperial government on the city&#x02BC;s architecture; see <ref type="note" subtype="contextual" target="milan_architecture_note.php">Neoclassical and Napoleonic&#x2010;Era Architecture in Milan</ref>.</p></note>
                    
                    
                <note xml:id="CERTOSAGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;The certosa&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi><placeName type="building" corresp="#CERTOSADIPAVIA">The Certosa of Pavia</placeName>, 
                    which the <date when="1847">1847</date> <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKNORTHERNITALY1847"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Northern Italy</hi></title> 
                    describes as "the most splendid monastery in the world", founded by <persName corresp="#GGVISCONTI">Gian Galeazzo Visconti</persName>, the first duke of <placeName corresp="#MILAN">Milan</placeName>, "built by him as an atonement for guilt, to relieve his conscience 
                    of the murder of his uncle and father-in-law, <persName corresp="#BVISCONTI">Barnabo Visconti</persName>, and his family. . . . The foundation was laid the <date when="1396-08-08">8th September, 1396</date>. Twenty-five Carthusian monks 
                    were appointed to take charge of this sanctuary, and executed, down to their expulsion in <date when="1782">1782</date> [by order of the <persName corresp="#JOSEPHII">Emperor Joseph II</persName>, to shut down the monasteries of the contemplative orders], 
                    the task imposed on them, of augmenting the glory of the Madonna, by adding to the beauty of the <placeName type="building" corresp="#CERTOSADIPAVIA">Certosa</placeName>. . . . From <date notBefore="1782" notAfter="1810">1782 to 1810</date>, the <placeName type="building" corresp="#CERTOSADIPAVIA">Certosa</placeName> was occupied by other orders, 
                    and in the latter year it was finally closed. . . . The monks were re-established at Christmas, <date when="1843">1843</date>, and the building is now well cared for"
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKNORTHERNITALY1847"><persName corresp="#GBM">Maule</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKNORTHERNITALY1847"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Northern Italy</hi></title></ref>, 203). 
                    In <date when="1833">1833</date>, the <placeName type="buidling" corresp="#CERTOSADIPAVIA">Certosa</placeName> being still closed to religious orders, <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName> says that the family visited the cells of former monks and noted their wealth, the <placeName type="building" corresp="#CERTOSADIPAVIA">Certosa</placeName> being the &#x201C;heir . . . and son of a hundred fathers&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson</title>, <date when="1833">1833</date></ref>, 52).</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="HOUSEOFBYRONGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;The <unclear resp="#DCH">house</unclear> of <persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName>&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>Following 
                    the drowning of <persName corresp="#PBS">Percy Shelley</persName> in the <geogName corresp="#LIGURIANSEA">Ligurean Sea</geogName> off the coast of <placeName corresp="#LIVORNO">Leghorn</placeName> in <date when="1822-07">July 1822</date>, 
                    in <date when="1822-10">October</date> <persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName> moved his household to <placeName corresp="#GENOA">Genoa</placeName>, where <persName corresp="#MWS">Mary Shelley</persName> had already arrived. 
                    Joined by his lover, <persName corresp="#TGUICCIOLI">Teresa Guiccioli</persName>, and his companion, <persName corresp="#EJTRELAWNY">Edward John Trelawny</persName>, 
                    <persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName> leased <placeName type="building" corresp="#CASASALUZZO">Casa Saluzzo</placeName> in the suburb, <placeName corresp="#ALBARO">Albaro</placeName>. 
                    A mile away, <persName corresp="#MWS">Mary Shelley</persName> occupied <placeName type="building" corresp="#CASANEGROTO">Casa Negroto</placeName> along with <persName corresp="#JHLH">Leigh Hunt</persName> and his family. 
                    <persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName> lived in <placeName type="building" corresp="#CASASALUZZO">Casa Saluzzo</placeName> until he and <persName corresp="#EJTRELAWNY">Trelawny</persName> 
                    sailed for <placeName corresp="#GREECE">Greece</placeName> in <date when="1823-07">July 1823</date>
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HAWKINSBYRONCHRONOLOGY"><persName corresp="#AHAWKINS">Hawkins</persName>, ed., <title type="book" corresp="#HAWKINSBYRONCHRONOLOGY">&#x201C;The Byron Chronology&#x201D;</title></ref>, years <date notBefore="1822" notAfter="1823">1822&#x2013;23</date>).</p>
                    
                    <p>While the Ruskins were traveling the <geogName corresp="#CONTINENT">Continent</geogName>, <persName corresp="#MGBLESSINGTON">Marguerite Gardiner, Countess of Blessington</persName> (<date notBefore="1789" notAfter="1849">1789&#x2013;1849</date>), 
                        was continuing publication of her <title type="book" corresp="#BLESSINGTONBYRON"><hi rend="italic">Journal of Conversations with Lord Byron</hi></title> (<date notBefore="1832" notAfter="1833">1832&#x2013;33</date>) 
                        as installments in the <title type="periodical" corresp="#NEWMONTHLYMAGAZINE"><hi rend="italic">New Monthly Magazine</hi></title>. 
                        She based the <title type="book" corresp="#BLESSINGTONBYRON"><hi rend="italic">Conversations</hi></title> on visits exchanged with <persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName> 
                        during her stay in <placeName corresp="#GENOA">Genoa</placeName>, where she settled during travels with her husband and companions in <date notBefore="1823-04-01" notAfter="1823-06-30">April&#x2010;June 1823</date>. 
                        In the book, she describes <persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName>&#x02BC;s residence thus: 
                        &#x201C;<placeName corresp="#ALBARO">Albaro</placeName>, the village in which the <placeName type="building" corresp="#CASASALUZZO">Casa Saluzzo</placeName>, 
                        where he lives, is situated, is about a mile and a 
                        half distant from <placeName corresp="#GENOA">Genoa</placeName>; it is a fine old palazzo, 
                        commanding an extensive view, and with spacious 
                        apartments, the front looking into a court&#x2010;yard 
                        and the back into the garden&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BLESSINGTONBYRON"><persName corresp="#MGBLESSINGTON">Blessington</persName>, <title type="book" corresp="#BLESSINGTONBYRON"><hi rend="italic">Conversations of Lord Byron with the Countess of Blessington</hi></title></ref>, 4; and see 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BLESSINGTONDNB"><persName corresp="#WHSCHEUERLE">Scheuerle</persName>, <title type="essay" corresp="#BLESSINGTONDNB">&#x201C;Gardiner [n&#x00E9;e Power; other married name, Farmer], Marguerite [Margaret], countess of Blessington (1789&#x2013;1849)&#x201D;</title></ref>).
                    </p></note>
                <!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_toc_glosses_contextual#HOUSEOFBYRONGLOSS"/>.-->
                
                <note xml:id="MADONNADELMONTEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;The Madonna del monte&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>On 
                    <date when="1833-07-03">3 July</date>, <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName> recorded that the family, after visiting <placeName corresp="#ARONA">Arona</placeName> on <geogName corresp="#LAKEMAGGIORE">Lake Maggiore</geogName>, 
                    crossed to <placeName corresp="#VARESE">Varese</placeName> and ascended the <placeName type="building" corresp="#SACROMONTEDIVARESE">Madonna del Monte</placeName>&#x2014;the <placeName type="building" corresp="#SACROMONTEDIVARESE">Sacro Monte di Varese</placeName>, 
                    one of the nine <placeName type="building" corresp="#SACRIMONTI">Sacri Monti</placeName> of <placeName corresp="#PIEDMONT">Piedmont</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#LOMBARDY">Lombardy</placeName>. 
                    She mentions the chapels situated along the ascent, the <placeName type="building" corresp="#SACROMONTEDIVARESE">Via Sacra</placeName> (incorrectly associating the chapels with the stations of the cross), and the view from the summit, 
                    which she and <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName> enjoyed from a steeple that they ascended accompanied by <persName corresp="#SALVADOR">Salvador</persName> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#RFT48"><title type="mauscript" corresp="#RFT48">Diary of Mary Richardson</title>, 1833</ref>, 63&#x2013;64).</p>
                    
                    <p>According to the <date when="1847">1847</date> guidebook by <persName corresp="#GBM">G. B. Maule</persName>, 
                        &#x201C;The chief object of attraction at <placeName corresp="#VARESE">Varese</placeName> is the celebrated <placeName type="building" corresp="#SACROMONTEDIVARESE">Santuario of the Virgin</placeName>, 
                        caUed <placeName type="building" corresp="#SACROMONTEDIVARESE">La Madonna del Monte</placeName>, which is situated on a lofty hill about five miles to the north&#x2010;west of the city 
                        [<placeName corresp="#VARESE">Varese</placeName>]. It is said to have been founded in <date when="0397">397</date> by <persName corresp="#STAMBROSE">St. Ambrose</persName>, 
                        to commemorate a great victory,&#x2014;not in argument, but in arms,&#x2014;gained by him on this spot over the <orgName corresp="#ARIANS">Arians</orgName>. 
                        The slaughter is said to have been so great that the heterodox party were exterminated. It was dedicated to the <persName type="scriptural_person" corresp="#VIRGINMARY">Virgin</persName>, 
                        and her statue, which was consecrated by <persName corresp="#STAMBROSE">St. Ambrose</persName>, is still preserved. At the end of the <date notBefore="1500" notAfter="1599">16th century</date> 
                        <persName corresp="#AGAGGIARI">Agaggiari</persName>, a <orgName corresp="#CAPUCHINS">Capuchin</orgName> monk, built, out of funds raised by his exertions, the fourteen chapels 
                        which stand by the side of the road which leads to the church on the summit. . . . The fourteen chapels represent the fourteen mysteries of the Rosary. . . . They contain coloured statues 
                        in stucco, . . . and frescoes . . . of the painters of the Milanese school of the <date notBefore="1500" notAfter="1599">16th century</date>. Over the fountain, near the last chapel, 
                        is a fine <title type="artwork" corresp="#MONTIMOSES">colossal statue of <persName type="scriptual_person" corresp="#MOSES">Moses</persName></title>, 
                        by <persName corresp="#GMM">Gaetano [Matteo] Monti</persName> [<date notBefore="1776" notAfter="1847">1776&#x2013;1847</date>]. . . . Connected with the chureh is a convent of 
                        <orgName corresp="#AUGUSTINIANS">Augustinian</orgName> nuns. . . . Those who are not tempted by the religions objects may be perhaps induced to visit the 
                        <placeName type="building" corresp="#SACROMONTEDIVARESE">Santuario</placeName> by being told that the ascent affords the most magnificent views of the rich plain of 
                        <placeName corresp="#LOMBARDY">Lombardy</placeName> as far as the <geogName corresp="#APPENINES">Apennines</geogName>, of the higher and lower chains of the <geogName corresp="#ALPS">Alps</geogName>, 
                        and the lakes of <geogName corresp="#LAKEVARESE">Varese</geogName>, <geogName corresp="#LAKECOMABBIO">Comabbio</geogName>, <geogName corresp="#LAKEBIANDRONNO">Biandrone</geogName>, 
                        <geogName corresp="#LAKEMONATE">Monate</geogName>, <geogName corresp="#LAKEMAGGIORE">Maggiore</geogName>, and <geogName corresp="#LAKECOMO">Como</geogName>&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKNORTHERNITALY1847"><title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKNORTHERNITALY1847"><persName corresp="#GBM">Maule</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Northern Italy</hi></title></ref>, 201&#x2013;2).</p></note>
                <!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_toc_glosses_contextual#MADONNADELMONTEGLOSS"/>.-->
                
                <note xml:id="TURTMANNGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold"><placeName corresp="#TURTMANN">&#x201C;Tourtman&#x201D;</placeName> (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi><persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s cousin, 
                    <persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName>, does not mention the family visiting <placeName corresp="#TURTMANN">Turtmann</placeName> in her travel <title type="manuscript" corresp="#RFT48">diary</title>. In 
                    his <date when="1838">1838</date> <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838">guidebook</title> to <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Switzerland</placeName>, <persName corresp="#JM">John Murray III</persName> briefly mentions the village&#x2014;using the French spelling, 
                    <placeName corresp="#TURTMANN">Tourtemagne</placeName>&#x2014;and why it was held in &#x201C;some repute among tourists&#x201D;. A twenty&#x2010;minute walk behind the main inn brought the traveler to a cascade, of which the &#x201C;volume of water is considerable&#x201D;, 
                    though &#x201C;on the whole inferior to the <geogName corresp="#NANTARPENAZ">fall of the Sallenche</geogName> near <placeName corresp="#MARTIGNY">Martigny</placeName>&#x201D; [i.e., the <geogName corresp="#NANTARPENAZ">Nant d>&#x02BC;Arpenaz</geogName>]. 
                    <persName corresp="#JM">Murray</persName> recommended &#x201C;the scene . . . on account of its entire seclusion&#x201D;; however, 
                    he warned against a danger that always put Victorian travelers on their guard: &#x201C;The neighborhood is overspread with marshes and stagnant pools&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"> <title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 157).</p></note>
                <!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_toc_glosses_contextual#TURTMANNGLOSS"/>.-->
                
                <note xml:id="STMAURICEGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold"><placeName corresp="#SAINTMAURICE">&#x201C;St Maurice&#x201D;</placeName> (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi><persName corresp="#MRC">Mary Richardson</persName> 
                    also fails to mention <placeName corresp="#SAINTMAURICE">St. Maurice</placeName> in her travel <title type="manuscript" corresp="#RFT48">diary</title>, but the village is honored by a poem in <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALY"><hi rend="italic">Italy</hi></title> by 
                    <persName corresp="#SR">Samuel Rogers</persName>. Its speaker, traveling in the opposite direction from the Ruskins, by riding from <geogName corresp="#LAKEGENEVA">Lake Geneva</geogName> toward <placeName corresp="#ITALY">Italy</placeName>, 
                    rests in <placeName corresp="#SAINTMAURICE">St. Maurice</placeName> for the night and describes the place:</p>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <div>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>&#x02BC;Twas dusk; and, journeying upward by the <geogName corresp="#RHONE">Rhone</geogName>,</l>
                                    <l>That there came down, a torrent from the <geogName corresp="#ALPS">Alps</geogName>,</l>
                                    <l>I entered where a key unlocks a kingdom;</l>
                                    <l>The mountains closing, and the road, the river</l>
                                    <l>Filling the narrow pass. . . .</l>
                                </lg>
                            </div>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <lb/>
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ROGERSITALY1830"><persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>, <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALY1830"><hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> [1830]</title></ref>, 9&#x2013;10)
                    <lb/>
                    <p>In the <date when="1830">1830</date> illustrated <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALY"><hi rend="italic">Italy</hi></title>, <persName corresp="#JMWT">Turner</persName>&#x02BC;s engraved vignette 
                        for the poem features a bridge across the <geogName corresp="#RHONE">Rhone</geogName>, along with attendant structures, a scene that is explained and updated by 
                        <persName corresp="#MURRAY">Murray</persName>. Quoting these lines from <persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>, <persName corresp="#MURRAY">Murray</persName> explains: 
                        &#x201C;Such is the scene presented to the traveller at the <hi rend="italic"><placeName corresp="#SAINTMAURICEBRIDGE">Bridge of St. Maurice</placeName></hi>, 
                        which spans the rapid river with one bold arch, 70 ft. wide, leaning for support (appuy&#x00E9;) on the rt. side upon the <geogName corresp="#DENTDEMORCLES">Dent de Morcles</geogName> 
                        and on the l. upon the <geogName corresp="#DENTSDUMIDI">Dent de Midi</geogName> [i.e., <geogName corresp="#DENTSDUMIDI">Dents du Midi</geogName>], 
                        whose bases are pushed so far forward as barely to leave room for the river. The <placeName corresp="#SAINTMAURICEBRIDGE">bridge</placeName>, erroneously attributed to the Romans, 
                        is not older than the <date notBefore="1400" notAfter="1499">15th century</date>, but may possibly rest on Roman foundations. It unites the <placeName corresp="#CANTONVAUD">canton Vaud</placeName> 
                        with the <placeName corresp="#CANTONVALAIS">canton Vallais</placeName>; and a gate at one end, now removed, formerly served to close the passage up and down: 
                        a circumstance alluded to in the lines of <persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>. A small fort was erected by the Swiss in <date when="1832">1832</date>, above the road, 
                        to defend the pass&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 152). 
                        Similar text by <persName corresp="#TRT">Thomas Roscoe</persName> along with an engraved view of the bridge after a drawing by <persName corresp="#SP">Samuel Prout</persName> was also available in 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ROSCOETOURISTSWITZERLANDITALY"><hi rend="italic">The Tourist in Switzerland and Italy</hi></ref>, 52&#x2013;55.</p>
                    
                    <p>In <persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>&#x02BC;s <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALY1830">poem</title>, the speaker awakes to music&#x2014;preparations for the nuptials of the innkeeper&#x02BC;s daughter&#x2014;a reverie that attends him on his way:</p>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <div>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>. . . there I slept,</l>
                                    <l>And in my dreams wandered once more, well&#x2010;pleased.</l>
                                    <l>But now a charm was on the rocks, and woods,</l>
                                    <l>And waters; for, methought, I was with those</l>
                                    <l>I had at morn and even wished for there.</l>
                                </lg>
                            </div>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                    <lb/>
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#ROGERSITALY1830"><persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>, <title type="poem" corresp="#ROGERSITALY1830"><hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> [1830]</title></ref>, 10)
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Proceeding in the opposite direction across the bridge from <persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>&#x02BC;s speaker, <persName corresp="#MURRAY">Murray</persName>&#x02BC;s traveler 
                        emphasizes an invidious distinction typically made by British Victorian tourists between Protestant and Catholic Swiss cantons: 
                        &#x201C;No one can cross the <placeName corresp="#SAINTMAURICEBRIDGE">bridge of St. Maurice</placeName> without being struck with the change in the condition of the inhabitants of the two cantons. The neatness and industry 
                        of the <placeName corresp="#CANTONVAUD">Vaudois</placeName> are exchanged within the space of a few hundred yards for filth and beggary, equally apparent in the persons and habitations of the <placeName corresp="#CANTONVALAIS">Vallaisans</placeName>. 
                        Their physical condition is lamentable; no part of <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Switzerland</placeName> is afflicted to a greater extent with the maladies of go&#x00EE;tre and cretinism . . . , 
                        and the victims of them shock the traveller&#x02BC;s sight at every step&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><title type="book" corresp="#MURRAYSHANDBOOKSWITZERLAND1838"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers in Switzerland</hi></title></ref>, 152).</p></note>
                <!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_toc_glosses_contextual#STMAURICEGLOSS"/>.-->
                
                <note xml:id="AARTGLOSS" resp="#DCH"><p><hi rend="bold">&#x201C;Aart&#x201D; (<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>)&#x2014;</hi>I.e., <placeName corresp="#ARTH">Arth</placeName>.</p></note>
                <!--The pointer to this gloss would be <ref type="gloss" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_toc_glosses_contextual#AARTGLOSS"/>.-->
                
                
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>