<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Work</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Note subtypes include bibliographical, biographical, contextual, and geographical.-->
            <div type="note" subtype="subtype">
                <head type="title">Title of Note</head>
                <p>Starting in 1826,
                    the archive&#x02BC;s earliest documents reveal the Ruskin family&#x02BC;s
                    engagement with late-Enlightenment pedagogy for young children; extending to
                    1842, later documents open up the experiences of an early Victorian Oxonian and
                    the professionalization of a rising author.but, when complete, it will be the most comprehensive. Approximately a
                    third of its materials has never before been available in edited form, and a
                    large portion of the remainder has been available only in the problematically
                    edited form of late-nineteenth- and early-twentieth-century editions. The
                    archive also encourages awareness of the editorial, scholarly, and biographical
                    tradition in which it stands, inviting critical assessment of a tradition of
                    reflection on Ruskin&#x02BC;s youth and education.Among the most multifaceted thinkers
                    of the nineteenth century, Ruskin developed an approach to art criticism that
                    probed the social, religious, political, and economic implications of
                    appreciating beauty in the arts and the natural world. <hi rend="italic"
                        >ERM</hi> contains the records of his education leading to that career, </p>
                <p>In scope, the archive </p>
                <p>Once the task of organizing, annotating, and exhibiting this mass of material is
                    well underway, the archive also aims to facilitate study of how Ruskin became
                    seemingly the most proto-<hi rend="italic">hypertextual</hi> of Victorian
                    writers. Late in his career, Ruskin experimented with writing and publication
                    that anticipate modes later made possible by digital platforms. Straining the
                    publication resources of his day, he invented an unbounded and hypertextual, if
                    perhaps not quite nonlinear, series of monthly letters called <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fors Clavigera</hi>. It is a valuable question how far Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    innovations were grounded, for example, in a social-network methods of education
                    promoted by the Edgeworths, or in a Romantic-era alertness to the interrelation
                    of arts and disciplines.</p>
                <p>In such questions and in the ongoing digitization of Ruskin&#x02BC;s works, <hi
                    rend="italic">ERM</hi> joins other digital editions such as the <ref
                        target="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/depts/ruskinlib/eSoV/index.html"><hi
                            rend="italic">Ruskin&#x02BC;s Venetian Notebooks</hi></ref>, and <ref
                                target="http://ruskin.ashmus.ox.ac.uk/main.php"><hi rend="italic">The
                                    Elements of Drawing</hi></ref>. <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> most directly
                    complements the Lancaster University's <ref
                        target="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/depts/ruskinlib/Pages/welcome.html"
                        >Electronic Edition of <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters</hi> I</ref>, in
                    the sense that the present archive can be viewed as editing the works leading up
                    to that 1843 work, which established Ruskin&#x02BC;s reputation as a popular art
                    critic.</p>
                <p></p>
                
                <p>A complementary volume of early prose edited by Collingwood was planned but never
                    executed. Instead, Allen was responsible for a small, somewhat haphazard
                    miscellany of volumes of early prose writing, perhaps meant more to ply the
                    heated trade for fine editions of fugitive writing by &#x201C;modern
                    writers&#x201D; than to serve scholarship. </p>
                <p>Thus, the transmission of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early writing at the turn of the
                    twentieth century is bound up, on one hand, with Ruskin&#x02BC;s construction of
                    his youth in the autobiographical narratives of <hi rend="italic">Fors
                        Clavigera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>, and, on another hand,
                    with the cultural context of fine book collecting centering on modern authors
                    that flourished in the 1890s. <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> provides a means to
                    study these later contexts of transmission of the early Ruskin, which helped to
                    shape subsequent scholarship, as well as the contexts of the early
                    writing&#x02BC;s first creation. <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> also advances an
                    
                    Building on this tradition and (it is hoped) contributing new avenues of
                    scholarship, <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> assembles digital facsimiles of the
                    manuscripts along with transcripts encoded according to the standards of the
                    Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), allowing for expansion in content and
                    extensibility in markup unavailable to earlier editors. The edition is offered
                    as an interdisciplinary research site for a new generation of Romantic and
                    Victorian studies.</p>
                <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                <p>Body paragraph containing a list:
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">First item in the list.</item>
                        <item n="2">Second item.</item>
                        <item n="3">Third item.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Body paragraph.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>