<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject MANUSCRIPT followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "msi_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "msi_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_manuscript_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Manuscript</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#TPD">Isaiah Thomas</persName>
                    <resp>conributing transcription/encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>            
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
            <head type="title">Title of Manuscript</head>
                <!--A manuscript apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p><title type="manucript" corresp="MSV">MS V</title></p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood</persName> assigned the roman numeral V to this notebook in his <title type="biography_text" corresp="#COLLINGWOODPRELIMINARYNOTE">“Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems”</title> for Poems (<date when="1891">1891</date>) (Poems [4o, <date when="1891">1891</date>], 1:263; Poems [8o, <date when="1891">1891</date>], 1:264).
                        Apart from the editor’s numerical designation, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> title—intended, it appears, for the manuscript in its entirety—is <title type="anthology" corresp="#MISCELLANEOUSPOETRY">“MISCELLANEOUS POETRY.”</title> Unlike his full-page titles for <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title>, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIB">MS IB</title>, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title>, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIIIA">MS IIIA</title>, and <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIV">MS IV</title>, which <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> apparently intended to serve both for the manuscript in its entirety and for its single main work (despite the more or less miscellaneous contents that eventually filled out some of these manuscripts), his title for <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title> does not take up an entire page in imitation of a published book. Rather, he wrote it in capitals on p. 1, above the first of the poems in the anthology, which starts on the same page (see “Helvellyn”: Title).
                        A handmade pamphlet tipped in at the end of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title> (see Description) bears its own title by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> <title type="manuscript" corresp="#BATTLEOFWATERLOOMS">: “BATTLE OF WATERLOO / A PLAY / IN TWO ACT’S / WITH OTHER SMALL / POEMS / DEDICATED TO HIS FATHER / BY <persName corresp="#JR">JOHN RUSKIN</persName> / </title> <date when="1829">1829</date> / HERNHILL / DULWICH.”
                    See System of Title Citation for Major Manuscripts.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="LOCATION">
                    <head type="section">Location</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p><name type="building" corresp="#BEINECKELIBRARY">Beinecke Library</name>, <orgName corresp="#YALE">Yale University</orgName>. Cataloged as “Poems <date when="18291832">1829-1832</date>,” which is the title on the spine of the slip case containing the manuscript when purchased. The slip case is now preserved separately.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="PROVENANCE">
                    <head type="section">Provenance</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>See Provenance: Sotheby’s <date when="1930">1930</date>.</p>
                    
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DESCRIPTION">
                    <head type="section">Description</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>A 12 × 18.5 cm, pre-ruled notebook, covered with greenish marbled boards, half-bound in chocolate calf, and gilt (the same binding as that described by <persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood</persName> [Poems (4o, <date when="1891">1891</date>), 1:263; Poems (8o, <date when="1891">1891</date>), 1:264]). The leaves measure 11 × 17.7 cm.
                    Collation
                    Following and not including the marbled front endpaper: three blank leaves + 167 pp. as numbered by <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> (with p. 1 starting on a recto, and with p. 37 given twice) + 3 blank leaves + back marbled endpaper.
                    The three leaves at the beginning and end of the notebook are unruled and, unlike the ruled leaves that make up the main part of the notebook, bear the watermark “Smith &#x0026; A[(?)] / 18[(?)].” This difference in papers might suggest a rebinding of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>, but the worn marbled boards appear original, as do the leather corners. Also, the edges of the paper were marbled in a color that may once have matched the boards. It seems likely, therefore, that <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title> has come down to us in the same binding in which <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> first used it.
                    <title type="manuscript" corresp="#BATTLEOFWATERLOOMS">Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts, with Other Small Poems</title>
                    A handmade pamphlet with this title, its pages disassembled, is tipped in at the back of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>. Originally, the pamphlet formed no part of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>, and it must not have been inserted when <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> described <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>, as he does not mention it. (See <title type="drama" corresp="#JRBATTLEOFWATERLOOPLAY">“Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts”</title> for the likelihood that <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> was unaware of this pamphlet at all when compiling Poems [<date when="1891">1891</date>].)
                    The pamphlet was probably inserted by <persName corresp="#AW">Alexander Wedderburn</persName>, and no later than <date when="1903">1903</date>, since <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood's</persName> “<title type="bibliography_text" corresp="#COLLINGWOODPRELIMINARYNOTE">Notes on the Original MSS. of Poems,”</title> as elaborated in the Library Edition, adds to the description of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>: “In this book . . . are now inserted the leaves of a thin paper book” containing <title type="drama" corresp="#JRBATTLEOFWATERLOOPLAY">“Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts”</title> and other works (<persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>, Works, 2:531). The addition is mentioned also on a leaf tipped in between the marbled front endpapers of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>; like similar leaves in some of the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#REDBOOK"></title>Red Books</ref>, these hold a clipping from Poems (<date when="1891">1891</date>) describing <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>, along with brief remarks penned probably by <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName>. It is perplexing why this pamphlet was not included in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title>, a collection compiled after <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood's</persName> editing of Poems (<date when="1891">1891</date>), just as it is perplexing, and intriguing, why the contents of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIA">MS IA</title> were omitted from <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSXI">MS XI</title>.
                    The pamphlet requires a description of its own:
                    Most of the booklet’s leaves have been cut at the fold and tipped separately onto successive pages of the notebook. If nothing is lacking—and only a front portion of cover, made of heavier paper, has likely disappeared—the booklet consists of 8 leaves that were folded once to form 16 pp., 10 x 16 cm. The innermost fold, leaves 4–5, remains intact, tending to confirm how the booklet was constructed. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> numbered the pages 1–14, starting with 2r.
                        In addition to this gathering, a back cover remains that is white on the inside, facing p. 16, and bright pink on the outer side, and that looks to be the same age as the other leaves. No matching front cover is extant. Nothing is written on the back cover, but it presumably formed part of the pamphlet when the editors discovered the little anthology; otherwise, they would have had no reason to include it. There is no assurance, however, that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself was responsible for the pink cover, when he constructed the pamphlet in <date when="1829">1829</date>, and there is no way of knowing what, if anything, might have been written or drawn on the front cover.</p>
                    <!--The subsection that follows, Collation, is common to all manuscript apparatuses and was, accordingly, assigned an xml:id by
                        the Ruskin Project Team during work on the "First Twenty."-->
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="COLLATION">
                    <head type="subsection">Collation</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="CONTENTS">
                    <head type="section">Contents</head>
                    <!--Typically, this section will begin:-->
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <!--and continue with a list, which may group items according to type (e.g. prose, poetry) or other similiarity. Note: drawings
                        may be included as items in this list.-->
                    <list xml:id="LIST" type="ordered">
                        <item n="a">Item belonging to Group A.</item>
                        <item n="b.1">First item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.2">Second item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.3">Third item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="c">Item belonging to Group C.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>a. Fair copies of poems, most of them originally drafted in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSSVI">MSS VI</title> and <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">VIII</title>, but not necessarily fair-copied here in order of composition: “Helvellyn” (pp. 1–2), “The Moon” (pp. 2–3), “The Wood of Birches near Tunbridge” (pp. 3–4), “On Happiness” (p. 4), “The IX Psalm” (p. 5), “Sabbath Morning” (pp. 6–7), “Shagram’s Farewell to Shetland” (pp. 7–9), “Etna” (pp. 9–10), “Bosworth Field” (pp. 10–13), “Vesuvius” (pp. 13–16), “Trafalgar” (pp. 17–20), “Death” (pp. 20–23), “The Day of Judgement” (pp. 24–29), “Battle of Preston Pans” (pp. 29–35), “Revenge” (pp. 36–37[b] [i.e., the poem takes up a total of three pages, including the two pages that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> mistakenly numbered redundantly as p. 37: p. 37[a] and p. 37[b]]), “Despair” (pp. 38–46), “Love” (pp. 46–51), “Haddon Hall” (pp. 52–53), “My Dog Dash” (pp. 53–54), “On the Death of My Cousin Jessy” (pp. 54–55), “My Fishing Rod” (pp. 55–59), “The Ascent of Skiddaw” [book ?, lines ??–?? of “Iteriad”] (pp. 59–78), “Going to Covent Garden Theatre To See the £100 Note &#x0026; Harlequin Fat and Harlequin Bat” (pp. 78–83), “The Fairies” (pp. 84–86), “To My Heart” (pp. 86–88), “To Poesie” (pp. 88–90), “A Dirge for Nelson” (pp. 90–92), “To the Ocean Spirits” (pp. 92–94), “To the Fairies” (pp. 95–97), “To the Spirits of the Earth” (pp. 97–99), “To the Spirits of the Fire” (pp. 100–102), “To the Wind” (pp. 102–3), “Weep for the Dead” (pp. 103–4), “The Mariner’s Song” (pp. 105–6), “On the Want of a Subject” (pp. 106–8), “To the Spirit of Mount Pilate, Written on Reading the Description of That Mountain in Sir Walter Scott’s Novel of Anne of Gierstein” (pp. 109–11), “The Site of Babylon” (pp. 111–12), “The Repentance of Nineveh: A Fragment” (pp. 112–13), “Dash” (pp. 113–15), “Curtained in cloudy drapery” [“Moonlight on the Mountains”] (pp. 115–16), “Sonnet to a Cloud” (pp. 116–17), “Creation: A Fragment” (pp. 117–18), “??? first line” [book 1, lines 401–28 of “Iteriad”] (pp. 118–20), “Athens” [17 stanzas] (pp. 121–29), “Sonnet to the Morning” (pp. 129–30), “The Song of the Southern Breeze” (pp. 130–33).
                        b. Pp. 134–67 blank; of these, pp. 136–48 used to tip in the handmade booklet, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#BATTLEOFWATERLOOMS">Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts, with Other Small Poems</title> (see Description). Contents of the booklet: no. <title type="manuscript" corresp="#BATTLEOFWATERLOOMS">"Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts"</title> (title page, 1r; list of characters, 1v; text, pp. 1–7 [2r–5r]), “Ballad on Waterloo” (pp. 7–8), “Description of an Afternoon” (pp. 8–9), “May” (pp. 9–10) “Skiddaw and Derwent Water” (pp. 10–13).</p>
                    
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <p>Date of composition summer <date when="1829">1829</date> to early <date when="1832">1832</date>.
                    Beneath <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> main title for the anthology, <title type="anthology" corresp="#MISCELLANEOUSPOETRY">“Miscellaneous Poetry,”</title> and above the title of the first poem, <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> wrote,  “By <persName corresp="#JR">J. Ruskin</persName> from 10 years to 11 to 12 to of age,” with a long space left perhaps to allow for adding <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin's</persName> ages as the years went by. As it turned out, the fair-copied poems in the notebook did not extend quite far enough into <date when="1832">1832</date> to justify <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> entering age “13” into the space.
                    <persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood</persName> remarks: “The poems are nearly all dated, and range from June 28, <date when="1829">1829</date>, to February <date when="1832">1832</date>. The dates are probably those of production, for they are slightly inconsecutive; which would not be the case if they were dates of entry; and, when chronologically arranged, they tally with the order of the first drafts in No. VI” (Poems [4o, <date when="1891">1891</date>], 1:263; Poems [8o, <date when="1891">1891</date>], 1:264). See Discussion for speculation about why the anthology was not carried beyond <date when="1832">1832</date>.
                    The handmade booklet tipped in the back of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#BATTLEOFWATERLOOMS">Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts, with Other Small Poems</title>, dates from <date when="1829">1829</date>1829 in fair copy.
                    See System of Date Citation.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <p><title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title> is the earliest major manuscript that was originally neither a <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#REDBOOK"></title>Red Book</ref> nor a homemade booklet. Another new development that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> starts with <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title> is the practice of keeping one notebook for carefully copied presentation of his poetry, while drafting his poems in other notebooks—<title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVI">MS VI</title> and <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVIII">MS VIII</title>, especially. Some evidence suggests that he took both sorts of notebooks along with him on journeys (see “The Day of Judgement”), entering the fair copies in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title> on Sundays or other days when the family paused from traveling. Just so, the Diary of <date when="1830">1830</date> was “written up” from notes during a lengthened stop.
                    <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> did compile poetry anthologies prior to <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>, but they were comparatively brief and served to fill out <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php"><title type="manuscript" corresp="#REDBOOK"></title>Red Books</ref> whose main feature was the ongoing <title type="lesson" corresp="#JRHARRYANDLUCY">"Harry and Lucy"</title> narrative: see <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSI">MS I</title> Poetry Anthology, Poetry Descriptive, <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> Second Poetry Anthology, and <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIII">MS III</title> Poetry Anthology.
                    While no apparent logic governs completion of the anthology other than filling the notebook, it appears from <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin's</persName> open-ended record of his son’s age as the boy entered successive fair copies (see Description) that the father at least may have looked for completion on those terms. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>, however, left over thirty pages blank at the end of the manuscript (see Contents); and the likeliest explanation for this neglect may be that he was drawn to a grander project—the fair copy in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVII">MS VII</title> of “Iteriad” and “Athens.” Selections from these epic-length poems appear toward the end of <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title>, suggesting that <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> grew dissatisfied with their constrained appearance in <title type="anthology" corresp="#MISCELLANEOUSPOETRY">Miscellaneous Poetry</title> and abandoned the anthology for grander presentation in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVII">MS VII</title>. (Since <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> did not complete fair-copying “Athens” in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVII">MS VII</title>, however, it is also possible that he returned to <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSV">MS V</title> to enter 17 stanzas of that poem on a less ambitious scale than that begun in <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSVII">MS VII</title>.)
                    On p. 167—a verso, facing the first of the three blank final leaves (see Description)—<persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> wrote in ink, but then erased,  <title type="anthology" corresp="#MISCELLANEOUSPOETRY">MISCELLANEOUS POETRY</title> / HELVELLYN.  This is how the notebook begins on p. 1, so the reason for the erasure is not apparent. Since the erased material is upside down to the text coming from the other direction, perhaps it represents a false start.
                    On the back inside endpaper, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> scribbled some numbers.</p>
                    <!--The Discussion section may contain all or only some of the following subsections.-->
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Hand</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Composition &#x0026; Sources</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Domestic Scene</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>