<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject MANUSCRIPT followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "msi_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "msi_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_manuscript_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Title of Manuscript</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>            
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
            <head type="title">Title of Manuscript</head>
                <!--A manuscript apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    <p>MS IIIA
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="LOCATION">
                    <head type="section">Location</head>
                    <p>Yale (in slipcase  Harry & Lucy, Poems &c ). </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="PROVENANCE">
                    <head type="section">Provenance</head>
                    <p>Sotheby’s 1930..(described only in a footnote as "another similar red book contain[ing] the remainder of 'Harry and Lucy,' 
                        and some more notes of sermons" which Collingwood omitted from the "Note" because it contains 
                        no poetry.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DESCRIPTION">
                    <head type="section">Description</head>
                    <p>	Red book; 9.8 × 15.2 cm; 38 leaves (counting from Yale bookplate, and including final leaf or endpaper, which has been partially glued to back board), of which 2r-15r numbered by Ruskin as pp. 1-29; watermark 1823. The leaf 31r-v has been attached to 30v with tape, and a stub along the inside margin of 31v shows that a leaf has been torn out. Following 31v, the gathering 32r-37v is loose and could be missing outermost leaves.
                        The inside front board is blank except for Yale’s bookplate and, unlike the other Red Books in the slipcase  Harry & Lucy,  does not have glued or tipped in a brief description of the notebook penned by Wedderburn(?) with a clipping from PJR. MS IIIA was never described by the earlier editors, however, neither in PJR nor in Works. Wedderburn, or whoever was responsible for slipcasing the juvenilia, was evidently content to include MS IIIA in the  Harry and Lucy  slipcase, where it logically belonged.
                        Title page (1r):  HARRY AND LUCY / CONCLUDED / BEING / THE LAST PART / OF / EARLY LESSONS / BY / JOHN RUSKIN / IN FOUR VOLUMES / VOL III / HERNHILL / DULWICH.  On back of the title page (1v), Ruskin imitated a printed page of  ERRATA. 
                        Unlike the  Harry and Lucy  narratives in MS I and III, this volume of the tale is written entirely in ink; however, this volume contains no  plates,  for which pencil had been reserved in MS III, even when the text was ink. Later in MS IIIA, the mineralogy notes and sermon draft are written in pencil.
                        The pages following  Harry and Lucy  that are blank except for Ruskin’s page numbering (pp. 10-29) must have been intended for the continuation of the narrative, since Ruskin prepared the pages in the same way as pp. 1-9--i.e., with verticle rules in pencil near the inside and outside margins, serving as guides to  justify  Ruskin’s printing.
                        Viljoen misdated MS IIIA as autumn 1828, 1829-30, 1832. The mineralogy notes, no. 172, are presumably no earlier than the note on payment for the  Homer  and for  mineralogy articles,  which precedes the notes written from the end of the volume. Payment for Homer must refer to translating the Iliad (no. 160a) in late February 1832:  But Homer! I am happy to inform you, sir, that I have translated about 550 lines of the first book. . . . These however I do suppose are news to you extremely unwelcome --unwelcome owing to what John James will have to pay (RFL 268-69). The following mineralogy notes were entered considerably later, I believe, probably after December 1832 (see note to no. 172). Finally, following the mineralogical notes, the rough draft of the eighteenth Sermon on the Pentateuch could have been entered anytime in 1833 after sermons VIII-X were drafted early in that year (see nos. 174-75).</p>
                    <!--The subsection that follows, Collation, is common to all manuscript apparatuses and was, accordingly, assigned an xml:id by
                        the Ruskin Project Team during work on the "First Twenty."-->
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="COLLATION">
                    <head type="subsection">Collation</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="CONTENTS">
                    <head type="section">Contents</head>
                    <!--Typically, this section will begin:-->
                    <p>Forward from front of book:
                        a) Following title page (1r), a list of  errata  (1v).
                        b) Vol. 3 of  Harry and Lucy,  no. 32 (pp. 1-9 [2r-6r]). The end of the narrative (pp. 7-9 [5r-6r]), is nearly identical to its draft in MS II. The fair-copy text is broken off in the middle of a sentence.
                        c) Blank pp. 10-11 (6v-7r), presumably left open for continuation of  Harry and Lucy,  never completed.
                        d) Mineralogy notes, no. 172 (pp. 12-15 [7v-9r]), later composed on pp. originally set aside for continuation of  Harry and Lucy.  These notes appear roughly contemporaneous with j below.
                        e) Blank, 9v-24v (9v-15r numbered by Ruskin pp. 16-29, and 15v-23v left completely blank).
                        f) List of minerals keyed to numbers of unknown significance (24r).
                        g) Blank, 24v-25r.
                        Forward from back of book:
                        h) Mineral list, no. 186 (38r).
                        i) List of payments to Ruskin by John James (37v):
                        s.	d
                        To	80 Lines composition.	0	4
                        To	8. min. articles.		0	8
                        To	2. Pages homer		2.	0
                        _______
                        3.	0
                        To	2 ditto			2.	0
                        Lent					2.	6
                        _______
                        Paid	<1.	6>
                            Presumably, the total paid is crossed out, because Ruskin had short-changed himself a shilling. According to no. 148, Ruskin was getting a halfpenny per line for his  greek  in late 1831 and early 1832, presumably for his translation of the Iliad (see no. 160a). It is not clear what  lines  he is counting, but 24 lines to earn a shilling for a  page  appears a likely equation.
                            From this sum, we also discover that a mineralogical  article  earned a penny, and, at least at this time, poetry composition was paid a farthing per five lines of poetry (see no. 91).
                            j) Mineralology notes (36v, 35v, 34v), no. 172. These notes alternate with blank pages (37r, 36r, 35r, 34r; 37r contains a few words).
                            k) Draft of sermon 18, no. 182 (32v, 31v, 30v, 29v, 28v, 27v, 26v, 25v). As in j, the draft pages alternate with blank pages (32r, 30r, 29r, 28r, 27r, 26r).
                            l) Pen and ink sketch of group of trees on an outcropping of rock (31r, undatable).
                        <hi rend="italic">From front of book, the sequential order of contents:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <!--and continue with a list, which may group items according to type (e.g. prose, poetry) or other similiarity. Note: drawings
                        may be included as items in this list.-->
                    <list xml:id="LIST" type="ordered">
                        <item n="a">Item belonging to Group A.</item>
                        <item n="b.1">First item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.2">Second item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="b.3">Third item belonging to Group B.</item>
                        <item n="c">Item belonging to Group C.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DATE">
                    <head type="section">Date</head>
                    <p>Date of composition December 1828; 1833-34.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="DISCUSSION">
                    <head type="section">Discussion</head>
                    <!--The Discussion section may contain all or only some of the following subsections.-->
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Hand</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Composition &#x0026; Sources</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head type="subsection">Domestic Scene</head>
                        <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>