<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Juvenilia of Modern Authors</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-27">October 27, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">Introductory Essay on Childhood, Precocity, and Juvenilia</head>
                <p>In the later nineteenth century, there appears to have arisen an increased
                    interest in the childhoods and juvenilia of
                    &#x201C;modern&#x201D;&#x2014;that is, high Victorian authors. </p>
                
                <p>AsCommodification tied to sentiment in Collingwood owing to the essentially aesthetic orientation of his editing, 
                and that's because of the view of childhood as pristine, described in "Note."
                
                     
                        
                        <q>The early writings of Mr. Ruskin were carefully preserved by his parents, who encouraged, though they do not seem to have supervised, the production of his juvenile attempts. 
                            In only two or three instances a word has been crossed out, and an emendation substituted by his father; but in several places his father and mother have inserted dates into the note-books, 
                            or endorsed a loose sheet "John's Poetry (<hi rend="italic">Date</hi>)." There is no trace of subsequent revision on the aauthor's part of any poems, 
                            except those which actually appeared in print during his youth.</q><!-- give reference -->
                        As the editors of the Library Edition would later point out, this portrayal of the early manuscripts is misleading. Collingwood's view of the evidence was overborne, however, 
                        by a desire to see the juvenilia as both 
                        perfect in its "beautifully written . . . 'copperplate' or 'print' hand" and "spontaneous . . . almost improvisational" in invention. The mixture of sentiment and ownership in Collingwood's metaphors, 
                        shown earlier, is a logical outcome of an aesthetic view of childhood and juvenilia, readily joined to a bio-bibliographical approach to understanding authorship, yet, 
                        by virtue of that view of childhood, resistant to any taint 
                        of the commodification with which the editorial and bookmaking approach is nonetheless involved.</p>
               
                <p>See note on Shepherd re. contradiction between Atheneaum's espousal of author's authority, and its sentement for childhood.</p> 
                   <p>
                While collectors and author societies were keen to explore authors' childhoods, as evident in the venue for Axon's bibliography, the Manchester Literary Society, 
                whose publications included numerous studies of other authors' boyhoods, this "bio-bibliographical" approach clashed with the editorial authority maintained by 
                many Victorian writers, such as Tennyson and Browning, who suppressed juvenilia in particular and who discouraged a genetic approach to their works in general.
                    <!-- Refer here to Millgate etc. --> The bio-bibliographical approach, encouraged by collecting, combined with a view of authors' juvenilia (especially Ruskin's) as pristine, 
                    textually free of revision or need of emendation, and representable through an essentially aesthetic orientation to editing. </p>
                <p>In the early nineteenth century, the interest in juvenilia as such appears to
                    have been a private concern of families. As W. G. Collingwood remarks, John
                    James and Margaret Ruskin treasured virtually everything that they and their son
                    wrote during his youth (<hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="superscript"
                        >o</hi>, 1891], 1:262; <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="superscript"
                        >o</hi>, 1891], 1:261). Authors themselves took a more equivocal view of
                    their early work. Ruskin resented his father&#x02BC;s preoccupation with
                    his early poetry at the very time when the writer, in the preparation for <hi
                        rend="italic">Stones of Venice</hi> (1850, 1853), was crucially defining
                    himself more as a critic than as a poetic prose writer. Yet, at the same time,
                    in <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters III</hi> (1854<!--Correction needed here?-->), Ruskin adopted a
                    Wordsworthian approach to history by taking his own development from childhood
                    as an example of modern landscape sensibility. Robert Browning, whose boyhood
                    shared so many influences with Ruskin&#x02BC;s in the semirural lanes and
                    evangelical chapels of Camberwell, was more reticent, destroying nearly
                    everything of importance in connection with his early writing. Leigh Hunt. . . .
                    The Brontës <!--Entry needed here.-->.</p>
                <p>As a result, Ruskin&#x02BC;s early literary development has been as admired
                    and extensively documented and studied as that of the Brontës, while
                    Browning&#x02BC;s biographers have been forced to rely on more indirect
                    sources (see Maynard). Yet, whereas Browning, having disposed of the evidence,
                    proved surprisingly insouciant in the ultimate testamentary arrangements for his
                    literary estate (see Millgate), Ruskin and his later circle of editors and
                    secretaries at Brantwood were as cautious as Browning, if not as destructive,
                    about the impression posterity would form of his early writing. Their measures
                    persist through the still standard editions, W. G. Collingwood&#x02BC;s
                    1891 edition of the <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>, and E. T. Cook and Alexander
                    Wedderburn&#x02BC;s 1903&#x2013;12 Library Edition of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>; and, despite monumental
                    corrective editing by Helen Gill Viljoen (much of which remains unpublished),
                    James S. Dearden, and Van Akin Burd, the earlier bibliographies and editions
                    continue profoundly to influence how the early Ruskin has been read.
                    Fortunately, it is characteristic of Ruskin that, while he and his circle
                    guarded how his writing should be approached, apparently nothing of the early
                    writing&#x2014;unlike the later correspondence with Rose
                    LaTouche&#x2014;was deliberately committed to flame. The purpose of this
                    edition is to compile the first comprehensive and reliable descriptive
                    bibliography and chronology of the early Ruskin manuscripts and to publish what
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s first editors excluded from their editions. </p>
                <p>Even now, the dispersal of the early manuscripts forces reliance on the earlier
                    editions, with all their bibliographic errors and questionable editorial
                    policies by Collingwood and Cook and Wedderburn. More recent scholars, such as
                    Burd and Dearden, have overcome the early editors&#x02BC; influence to
                    compile reliable editions of selected portions of the early writing. Until now,
                    however, no comprehensive bibliographic reconsideration of the entirety of the
                    early manuscripts has been made available. Only by means of a comprehensively
                    revised chronology and descriptive bibliography, which form the foundation of
                    this edition, can we at last fully understand the later mythologizing of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s childhood and, behind that, the actual youthful writing in
                    all the complexity of its genius.</p>
                
                <p> Cook and Wedderburn must be given credit for correcting at least part of the
                    story about Ruskin&#x02BC;s first publication, since, by their time, the
                    mythologized transmission of Ruskin&#x02BC;s early writing had already
                    begun, influencing its treatment by the first bibliographers and editors. In the
                    1870s, in his Catalogue of the Rudimentary Series of drawings at the Oxford
                    schools, and in Deucalion, Ruskin confidently&#x2014;even with colorful
                    supporting anecdotes&#x2014;attributed his first appearance in print to
                    prose publications, his two 1834 papers for Loudon&#x02BC;s Magazine of
                    Natural History (Works, 21:243, 26:275; nos. 190&#x2013;91). In the 1870s,
                    in context of his writing on drawing, botany, and geology, Ruskin very likely
                    wanted to believe his first publications to have been scientific and factual,
                    rather than poetic, in nature. Ruskin&#x02BC;s faulty memory or wishful
                    thinking soon became &#x201C;fact,&#x201D; however, when his first
                    major bibliographers, Shepherd (9) and Wise (1:302&#x2013;3, 2:111),
                    depended on Ruskin&#x02BC;s remarks to award the distinction of his debut
                    to the 1834 papers for Loudon&#x02BC;s Magazine. So settled became the
                    prejudice that even Collingwood&#x2014;who ought to have known better,
                    since he discovered John James&#x02BC;s entry in MS IV on the Spiritual
                    Times publication and even printed it, without comment, in 1891 (PJR,
                    1:264)&#x2014;persisted in heading a chronological list of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s publications with the Magazine of Natural History papers.
                    In his 1893 Life of Ruskin, Collingwood maintained that Ruskin &#x201C;began
                    his literary career&#x201D; as the &#x201C;analytic John Ruskin . . .
                    already an enfant terrible&#x201D; of prose argument (1:233,
                    49&#x2013;50).</p>
                <p>Before the last decades of the century, when Ruskin and his editors summoned
                    faulty bibliography in support of a desired story about the young natural
                    scientist, John James, in the middle of the century, told his own story through
                    selection for the Poems by &#x201C;J.R.&#x201D; The pencil scoring
                    through John James&#x02BC;s mistaken entry in MS IV may indicate, not that
                    somebody in the family spotted its inaccuracy, but that the father had decided,
                    curiously, not to include his son&#x02BC;s very first
                    publications&#x2014;not even the 1830 &#x201C;On Skiddaw and Derwent
                    Water,&#x201D; which John James certainly remembered. Instead, he opened
                    the volume with &#x201C;Song&#x201D; (&#x201C;I weary for the
                    torrent leaping,&#x201D; no. 176), a previously unpublished poem of 1833
                    (misdated 1832 by Collingwood). Why did John James choose this manuscript poem,
                    and not the printed &#x201C;On Skiddaw and Derwent Water,&#x201D; when
                    an otherwise pervasive principle of selection in the 1850 Poems was to reprint
                    poems that had already been published? We may never know, since the fifty copies
                    of the 1850 Poems constituted a private and very personal enterprise by John
                    James, limited to circulation among family and friends; however, a suggestive
                    fact about the 1833 poem has emerged from the revised chronology. This is one of
                    the few poems Ruskin wrote in early 1833, when Margaret finally prevailed in
                    enforcing a ban on the boy&#x02BC;s poetic composition (&#x201C;My
                    harp is sunk to rest,&#x201D; the poem laments), and in redirecting his
                    energies into the Sermon Books (see nos. 176, 170)&#x2014;a verdict to
                    which the father, probably reluctantly, assented. Two decades later, in
                    retrieving this poem to open his collection, was John James belatedly repealing
                    the old prohibition, tenderly restoring the silenced harp to his son? Ruskin, in
                    Venice at the time and engaged in repudiating his adolescent Byronism, no longer
                    wanted the harp (Helsinger, Ruskin and the Art of the Beholder
                    140&#x2013;63). The additional ironies revealed by the revised dating and
                    circumstances of the 1833 poem tend to reinforce the view that, in compiling the
                    Poems of 1850, John James was living in the past; however, the facts also point
                    unexpectedly to the father&#x02BC;s solicitude for his son&#x02BC;s
                    feelings and resentments&#x2014;if ironically and irrelevantly outdated
                    ones.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>