<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="tite_of_work_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">ERM Homepage Introductory Essay on Editing</title>
                <title type="sub">Essay</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head type="title" xml:id="INTROESSAYEDITINGBIBLIOGRAPHY">Editing and Bibliography of the Early Ruskin Manuscripts</head>
                <p>A map of how webpages are organized in the archive is provided in <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="plan_of_archive_note.php">Plan of the Archive</ref>, 
                    and the planned contents of the archive are surveyed in <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="overview_of_mss_note.php">Overview of the Manuscripts</ref>. 
                    Justification of the archive's organization and contents is offered in 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="editorial_rationale_note.php">Editorial and Encoding Rationale and Methodology</ref>. 
                    Historical grounding for this justification is attempted in 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="history_of_bibliography_and_editing_note.php">History of the Bibliography and Editing of the Early Manuscripts</ref>.<!-- This note should be broken up into smaller notes and its overview folded into this essay DCH -->
                </p>
                <p>The present essay suggests pathways into the archive respecting the following topics:<!-- DCH: Shouldn't the following list be subordinated to the "History of Bibliograhy and Editing" note? -->
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1">Ruskin's First Editors and the Emergence of His Literary Personae</item>
                        <item n="2">The Role of Ruskin's Early Works in the Emerging Bibliography and Collected Editing of Ruskin as a Canonical Modern Author</item>
                        <item n="3">Ruskin's Autobiographical Uses of His Early Works and the Conception of Literary and Artistic Precocity</item>
                        <item n="3">The Study of Ruskin's Early Works in Twentieth and Twenty-First Century Biography and Criticism</item>
                    </list>
                </p>    
                
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Ruskin's First Editors and the Emergence of His Literary Personae</head>
                
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Public Editing and Bibliography of the Early Manuscripts and Published Early Writing in the Fin de Si&#x00E8;cle</head>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) In the 1880s, Ruskin proposed to print selected early poetry and prose as a &#x201C;supplement&#x201D; to his autobiography, <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>.<!-- citation needed -->
                    This link to the early writing was ultimately realized only in part, and not by Ruskin, but by his secretary, 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="collingwood_w_g_note.php"><persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName></ref>, 
                    and his publisher, <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="allen_george_note.php"><persName>George Allen</persName></ref>. 
                    Collingwood edited the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1891_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891)</ref>, and he intended to edit the early prose also, 
                    but this complementary edition of the prose was never carried forward. Instead, Allen produced a series of editions of early prose work titles: . . . .<!-- list needed --> For his original &#x201C;supplement,&#x201D; 
                    Ruskin presumably intended a more modest compilation, and one motivated in part, like the autobiography itself, as a testimonial to his parents, symbolically repairing one of his decades-old emotional rifts 
                    with his father&#x2014;his snubbing of the older men's project celebrating the &#x201C;poetic&#x201D; aspect of his writing, 
                    which was precisely what Ruskin was striving, in the 1850s, to displace with a more critical approach in <hi rend="italic">The Stones of Venice</hi> (1850, 1853).</p> 
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891), however, should not be understood solely a belated realization of Ruskin's autobiographical project; the edition was driven also by motivations 
                    and underlying assumptions derived from broader cultural contexts of the 1890s. Collingwood reflects this context in the metaphors that open his introduction: 
                    <q>&#x201C;There is always a peculiar interest in watching development, in witnessing growth. When we have seen a plant burst the soil, . . . <!-- is there no TEI for omission from quotation? --> 
                we love every leaf and petal of it: it is our own; and worth more to us than all the cut bouquets of a flower-show. And in the same way we delight in the early history of nations,--in the 
                early biography of great men. As we follow their first steps, . . . they become our own by sympathy: and when they reach the day of victory and coronation, we seem, like the loyal adherents 
                of a conqueror, to share the triumph; and, like intimate confidants, to understand the full significance of the achievement&#x201D;</q> 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:xix; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:???).<!-- reference needed --> 
                    In the odd mix of metaphors joining <hi rend="italic">sympathy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ownership</hi>, Collingwood reflects attitudes that were fueling the 
                    <ref type="essay" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.php">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>,  
                    a phenomenon that both stoked and responded to the market for acquiring first editions of works by modern authors. Especially valued were editions of authors' early works, 
                    preferably original first editions, but also facsimilie editions or fine, illustrated editions such as Collingwood's of Ruskin's poems, which was available in elegant &#x201C;large&#x201D; 
                    editions using special papers and bindings.</p> 
                <p>Thus, Ruskin's autobiographical project converges with cultural currents to produce the <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891) as well as Allen's editions of Ruskin's early prose works, 
                    but Collingwood's edition also marks what cannot necessarily be said of Allen's editions&#x2014;a significant step forward in scholarly treatment of Ruskin's work. 
                    It was no mean accomplishment that Collingwood built his edition on the first descriptive bibliography of Ruskin manuscripts, the &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&#x201D; 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:261&#x2013;67; 
                    <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:???).<!-- reference needed --> 
                    This, too, reflected a trend, for bibliographical scholarship on modern authors' published works had been burgeoning in recent decades, 
                    in response to the collecting phenomenon and to the needs of the author societies forming around Britain. By 1890, Collingwood could rely on three bibliographical projects on Ruskin, 
                    which were underway throughout the 1870s&#x2013;90s were:</p>
                    <list>
                    <item><ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="bibliography_of_ruskin_shepherd_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Bibliography of Ruskin</hi> (5 editions, 1878&#x2013;81)</ref> by
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="shepherd_r_h_note.php">Richard Herne Shepherd</ref>;</item> 
                    <item><ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="bibliography_of_ruskin_axon_note.php"><hi rend="italic">John Ruskin: A Bibliographical Biography</hi> (1879)</ref> by
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="axon_w_e_a_note.php">William E. A. Axon</ref>;</item>  
                    <item><ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="bibliography_of_ruskin_wise_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Complete Bibliography of . . . Ruskin</hi> (1893)</ref> by
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="smart_j_p_note.php">James P. Smart</ref> and 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="wise_t_j_note.php">Thomas J. Wise</ref>.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>This scholarship cannot be separated from the phenomena previously noted as influencing Collingwood's project--autobiographical or biographical interests, and the desires of collectors. 
                        As compiled for collectors, the bibliographies tended to be concerned with establishing what constituted a perfect copy of a given item; and even that much description 
                        may have been established rather arbitrarily, based on copies the bibliographer happened to have available. This approach, 
                        as remarked by the &#x201C;new bibliography&#x201D; of the 1930s&#x2013;40s, lacked historical awareness of &#x201C;the changing processes, trade customs, 
                        methods of distribution and book&#x2010;buyers&#x02BC; tastes which made [these books] what they are,&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#DEVELOPMENTBIBLIOGRAPHICALSTUDY">Sadleir, &#x201C;Development of Bibliographical Study&#x201D;</ref>, 147). 
                        A more historical approach would have required a self&#x2010;consciousness on the part of fin-de-si&#x00E8;cle collectors themselves much less a perspective on Ruskin's own practices in bookmaking 
                        and distribution. Despite their limitations, the modern author bibliographies of the last quarter of the century were careful scholarly achievements.</p>
                    <p>These bibliographies also were not only influenced by, but also helped to sponsor an interest in modern authors' 
                        <ref type="essay" subtype="bibliographical" target="childhoods_and_juvenilia_of_modern_authors_note.php">Childhood, Precocity, and Juvenilia</ref>.<!-- is @type "essay"? -->
                        Bibliographers and collectors of the 1870s-80s were keen to unearth scarce publications by famous maodern authors, since such 
                        discoveries bolstered claims to comprehensiveness. This archaeology favored juvenile and youthful publications by virtue of their scarcity, 
                        such works having been published prior to the author's achieving fame.</p>
                    <p>As explained in <ref type="essay" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.php">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>,
                        an interest in juvenilia or other &#x201C;minor&#x201D; works was, in the view of post-war bibliographers, an unscholarly &#x201C;sentiment&#x201D; that grew out of the late-Victorian 
                        collecting phenomenon. Collectors, it was later argued, were prone to rearing nostalgic, imaginary scenarios involving their "first editions," a sentimentality that distracted from rigorous scholarship. 
                        This self-serving narrative overlooks evidence that a taste for famous authors' juvenilia worked also in the opposite direction&#x2014;a sentiment for childhood sponsoring 
                        collectors' search for juvenilia. This tendency shows in the career 
                        of <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="shepherd_r_h_note.php">Richard Herne Shepherd</ref>, Ruskin's first major bibliographer, 
                        and this decades-old relation between sentiment for youth and the collecting market apparently buoyed prices for the early Ruskin manuscripts as well, 
                        when these became available at the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1930_note.php">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1930</ref> 
                        and the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_sothebys_1931_note.php">Sotheby's Sale of Ruskin Manuscripts and Library, 1931</ref>.</p>
                    <p>Thus, in the mix of metaphors opening the introduction 
                        to <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891), it is not that Collingwood's appeal to &#x201C;sympathy&#x201D; for the subject is betrayed by a desire to &#x201C;own&#x201D; the subject, 
                        but that sympathy justified and sponsored possession: "It is no idle curiosity . . . that prompts the admirers of Mr. Ruskin's works to collect his boyish writings 
                    and to learn the story of his youth." Collingwood argued that Ruskin "more than other writers" required "a preliminary understanding of his ways, and aims, and attitude: and in his case, 
                    more than with others, these conditions have been determined at an early age, and illustrated in his early writings" 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS8D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [8<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:???; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#POEMS4D1891">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [4<hi rend="super">o</hi>, 1891]</ref>, 1:xix&#x2013;xx).<!-- reference needed --> 
                        In fact, readers of the period appear to have been predisposed to approach writers in this fashion.</p>
                    <p>The new bibliographers' eagerness to condemn the &#x201C;sentiment&#x201D; and &#x201C;greed&#x201D; of collectors was colored by the revelation that the fever for collector's items 
                        had provided T. H. Wise his opening for exploitation, 
                        using the 1893 bibliography as a platform to stage descriptions of nonexistent Ruskinalia. These included Ruskin's alleged pamphlet-length reprintings of juvenile poems, 
                        which Wise manufactured and spirited into the market as scarce surviving copies. Using this ingenious scheme, Wise and Buxton Forman bedeviled the bibliography of numerous modern authors, 
                        but it was doubts raised in the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref> about the Ruskin pamphlets in particular 
                        that led to Carter and Pollard's expos&#x00E9; of wise. As explained in <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="forgery_and_piracy_note.php">Forgery and Piracy</ref>, this 
                        clandestine industry was intricately involved in the climate of rare book and facsimile collecting in the fin de si&#x00E8;cle, and not a linear outcome of collectors' sentimentality calling 
                        forth exploitation.</p>
                    <p>All these approaches to studying and collecting modern authors at fin de si&#x00E8;cle shared a biographical orientation to their subjects. Collectors believed that, by acquiring a comprehensive material record 
                        of an author's productions, one gained insight into the author's career; and literary men like 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="shepherd_r_h_note.php">Richard Herne Shepherd</ref> encouraged this conviction respecting Tennyson or Barrett Browning 
                        no less than for Ruskin, Shepherd arguing in his <hi rend="italic">Tennysoniana</hi> that study of "'the growth of a Poet's mind'" required acquaintance with the early 
                        <hi rend="italic">Poems by Two Brothers</hi> (1827), just as he maintained in <hi rend="italic">The Earlier Poems of Elizabeth Barrett Browning</hi> that time spent with 
                        <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Mind</hi> (1826) 
                        served as "an exquisite day of April" dawning on the "fervid day in August" in <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#TENNYSONIANA">Shepherd, <hi rend="italic">Tennysoniana</hi></ref>, v; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#BARRETTBROWNINGEARLIERPOEMS1878">Barrett Browning, <hi rend="italic">Earlier Poems</hi>, ed. Shepherd</ref>, viii). 
                        If Ruskin, as Collingwood argued, benefited "more than other authors" from an approach via his early work, this seemed true only because Ruskin himself had prompted the approach. 
                        Axon could start his <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="bibliography_of_ruskin_axon_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Bibliographical Biography</hi> (1879)</ref> of Ruskin with a juvenile poem
                        because Ruskin himself printed the poem in <hi rend="italic">Queen of the Air</hi>. In drawing attention to his juvenilia, Ruskin was indeed unusual among Victorian authors; nonetheless,  
                        the bio-bibliographical impulse could prevail over the wishes even of authors who were hostile to publication of early efforts and first states of their work. 
                        No literary executor could have been more vigilant in this regard than Hallam Tennyson, the poet's son; yet, as Michael Millgate has remarked, Hallam apparently 
                        "recognized no contradiction between his deliberate 
                        preservation and publication of juvenilia and rejected readings and his insistence upon [his father's] desire to be represented only by his authorized final canon in its final form" 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#TESTAMENTARYACTS">Millgate, <hi rend="italic">Testamentary Acts</hi></ref>, 61).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Library Edition and the Rise of a Documentary Approach to the Early Manuscripts</head>
                    <p>So far as scholarship surrounding the early writing is concerned, the next stage, the editing of the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref>, 
                        can in some respects be seen as an extension of the culture and achievements of the 1890s. Owing in part to George Allen's rush to publish the first two volumes (1903) of the new edition and 
                        to show subscribers an earnest of the publisher's promises, these volumes represented more a reprise, even a reprint, of previous efforts, rather than a new editorial approach. 
                        Allen's editions of the early prose works and Collingwood's <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891) respectively make up large parts of the volumes 
                        of <hi rend="italic">Early Prose</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>. Enough was done, however, to reflect the philosophy of the editors, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="cook_e_t_note.php"><persName>E. T. Cook</persName></ref> and 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="wedderburn_note.php"><persName>Alexander Wedderburn</persName></ref>, 
                        that a collected edition should be comprehensive, 
                        without suppressing previously published works, as Ruskin had done in the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="works_series_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Works Series</hi></ref>. 
                        The editors also planned to show previous states of texts that Ruskin had revised and to print previously unpublished material, including manuscript versions of published works, and private 
                        materials such as letters, diaries, and notes. While far more revealing than what late Victorian collected editions typically authorized, the Library Edition blended its ostensibly historical  
                        and documentary approach to editing with an essentially aesthetic orientation. The editors generally presented the final state of a text (although in some cases, they created an eclectic text) and 
                        relegated previous states, draft or alternate published versions, to notes. Their choice of the latter witnesses seems arbitrary, governed by what appealed to them for reasons that they leave unstated.</p>
                    <p>Cook and Wedderburn did make some advances over Collingwood, however, and delivered on their promise of greater comprehensiveness 
                        by extending Collingwood's &#x201C;Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems&#x201D; 
                        to include early prose manuscripts. As indicated by Cook and Wedderburn's manuscript descriptions enhancing 
                        &#x201C;Notes on the Original MSS. of the Poems  [Revised and Completed from the Edition of 1891],&#x201D; 
                        they were laying the basis for a more documentary approach with considerable sorting, describing, and preserving manuscripts at Brantwood 
                        (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="overview_of_mss_note.php">Overview of the Manuscripts</ref> and 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="provenance_note.php">Provenance</ref>). They also challenged the previous editor's portrayal of the early manuscripts as pristine, 
                        free of revision by the author and of emendation by his parents; rather, the new editors pointed to 
                        "a good deal of revision between draft and fair copy" 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 2:529n)</p>
                
                    <p>and, further, how this production might be
                    woven &#x201C;into the lives of their authors, producing as it were a
                    garment of biography with a texture of bibliography&#x201D; .
                    Still, Sadleir recognizes that the new taste for collecting moderns was informed
                    by a significant level of bibliographic research.</p></div>
            
                    <!--<p>because he deprecated what he considered the greedy motives of Ruskin's literary executors, anxious to extend the Ruskin copyrights. When 
                    justifying his own edition of the <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891), however, as sating the <q>curiosity . . . that prompts the admirers of Mr. Ruskin's works to collect his boyish writings</q>, 
                    Collingwood retained a rhetorical figure of possession but displaced it from book collecting. Thus, in the "Preliminary Note on the Original MSS. of the Poems," he places provenance of the early manuscripts 
                    first in the hands of Ruskin's parents, who <q>carefully preserved</q> the <q>early writings</q>, but then he figuratively places the juvenilia beyond ownership or in a sor to self-possession: 
                    parents <q>encouraged, though they do not seem to have supervised, the production of [Ruskin's] juvenile attempts</q>; Ruskin himself imparted and preserved the value of the precious manuscripts 
                    by writing <q>very beautifully . . . in "copperplate" or "print" hand</q>, <q>the fair-copying . . . hav[ing] been quite as important a business as the invention and versification.</q>
                    Similarly, despite Collingwood's alleged interest in development, his alignment of the spectator's "ownership" with a special "sympathy" extends this privilege over the growing child's productions, 
                    which come spontaneously and self-possessed into being available for appreciation but not, it seems, for change or influence: <q>invention and versification . . . were apparently spontaneous . . . almost 
                    improvisational</q>. Collingwood, one suspects, was invested in editing the juvenilia as a project in fine bookmaking; for him, however, the vellum octavo <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1891) was 
                    a metaphor for Ruskin's boyhood in the walled garden of Herne Hill, and it offended him to see the product subjected to speculation.</p>-->
                        <!--<item>In the twentieth century, following Ruskin's death, project initiated by <persName>Helen Gill
                    Viljoen</persName>, who started her scholarship early enough to have met
                Collingwood and to have examined the Ruskin manuscripts remaining in situ at
                <placeName>Brantwood</placeName>, Ruskin&#x02BC;s last house, across
                <placeName>Coniston Water</placeName> from the village of
                <placeName>Coniston</placeName> in <placeName>Cumbria</placeName>. Viljoen
                went on to track (and did her part to secure) the early manuscripts&#x02BC;
                subsequent fortunes, as they made their way from the 1930&#x2013;31 auctions and
                private sales, through the hands of collectors, to widely scattered
                depositories. Viljoen&#x02BC;s papers, recording her extensive bibliographic
                sleuthing that built on Collingwood&#x02BC;s foundations, have formed an
                important resource for the present edition. The papers, now deposited at the
                Pierpont Morgan Library should be regarded as forming an impressive archive in
                their own right.
                <p>Viljoen&#x02BC;s efforts were sustained throughout the second half of the
                    twentieth century by <persName>Van Akin Burd</persName> and <persName>James
                        Dearden</persName>, who continued to edit unpublished early manuscripts,
                    correct errors in the <hi rend="italic">Library Edition</hi>, and carry out
                    other original bibliographical research, including a key edition for the present
                    archive, Burd&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi> (1973).</p></item>-->
                
                </div>       
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>