<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Overview Major MS</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="HMT">Heidi M. Toloudis</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-25">October 25, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head>Overview of the Manuscripts</head>
                <p>introductory survey of the manuscripts presently comprised by <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> rather than how the collection was defined historically
                THIS SHOULD REALLY BE AN ESSAY, NOT A NOTE</p> 
                <!--starting point. The survey of manuscripts. . . . nd that brings together all the
                extant early manuscripts for the first time since the contents oAf the Brantwood
                study were dispersed (see Provenance; Overview of the Major Manuscripts). Prior
                to the dispersal of the early manuscripts in the years following Ruskin’s death,
                the manuscript bibliography that W. G. Collingwood prepared for Poems (1891) and
                that E. T. Cook and Alexander Wedderburn expanded for the Library Edition
                reflects the condition, compilation, and binding of the manuscripts during the
                final decade of Ruskin’s life and the decade after his death, not their
                subsequent dispersal, the descriptions and locations require updating as well as
                correction and expansion.-->
                
                <p>Ruskin&#x02BC;s earliest extant juvenilia dates from 1826, about age seven,
                    aside from probably earlier childish scrawls, simple drawings and tracings, and
                    practice writing of his name on the fly leaves of books. Most of the early
                    writing 1826&#x2013;31, apart from the letters, is contained in the Red
                    Books (MS I, MS III, MS IIIA, MS IV, Juvenilia MS A, Juvenilia MS B, Juvenilia
                    MS C). <hi rend="italic">Red Books</hi> was Ruskin&#x02BC;s own term, used
                    from boyhood, when referring to them in letters to his father, and in later
                    years. </p>
                <p>In 1829, Ruskin also began to refer to his <hi rend="italic">works</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi>, 187), a term that probably
                    comprised not only the Red Books but also handmade pamphlets like MS II, which
                    bears the heading &#x201C;Vol I&#x201D;&#x2014;possibly connected
                    with an arrangement of &#x201C;works.&#x201D; Besides MS II, these
                    handmade pamphlets include &#x201C;<hi rend="caps">Battle of Waterloo / A
                        Play / In Two Act&#x02BC;s / With Other Small / Poems / Dedicated to his Father /
                        By John Ruskin / 1829 / Hernhill / Dulwich</hi>&#x201D; (now tipped
                    into MS V) and possibly MS IB, which appears to have been professionally bound
                    at a later time. Ruskin constructed these (or they were constructed for him)
                    from plain paper cut to about the size of the Red Books, folded once and sewed.
                        &#x201C;<hi rend="caps">Battle of Waterloo</hi>&#x201D; is covered
                    with pink or violet paper, perhaps to make its color uniform with the Red Books. </p>
                <p>Ruskin&#x02BC;s compilation of these early &#x201C;works&#x201D;
                    can be described as bookmaking as much as writing. From the start in MS I,
                    although his pencil printing is still fairly crude, Ruskin thinks to
                    &#x201C;justify&#x201D; the margins, enclose his illustrations in
                    frames and number them as &#x201C;plates,&#x201D; and provide a title
                    page and even a colophon. In contents, the Red Books imitate a range of genres,
                    from children&#x02BC;s verse and didactic tales, to imitations of the
                    Edgeworths&#x02BC; lessons, to more adult forms such as travel narrative
                    and topographical verse. In this imitative bookmaking, Ruskin was probably not
                    unusual among Victorian and Edwardian children. Less famous childhoods also left
                    behind scientific &#x201C;monographs,&#x201D; derivative
                    &#x201C;histories,&#x201D; and diaries that include illustrated
                    poetry. Some families even privately circulated
                    &#x201C;magazines,&#x201D; with elaborate nursery pretenses to
                    real&#x2010;life editorship.<note n="1"
                        place="botwin" resp="#DCH" xml:id="overview_majorms_note001">Olivia Bell and Alan Bell, &#x201C;Children&#x02BC;s Manuscript
                        Magazines in the Bodleian Library,&#x201D; and A. O. J. Cockshut,
                        &#x201C;Children&#x02BC;s Diaries,&#x201D; both in Children
                        and Their Books: A Celebration of the Work of Iona and Peter Opie, ed.
                        Gillian Avery and Julia Briggs (Oxford: Clarendon, 1989),
                        399&#x2013;412, and 381&#x2013;98, esp. 404&#x2013;6,
                        388&#x2013;89, 392&#x2013;94, 408.</note><hi rend="superscript"
                        >1</hi> For example, a handmade magazine, &#x201C;The Beresford
                    Spy,&#x201D; was produced by the children of Edward Andrews, the family
                    clergyman and Ruskin&#x02BC;s tutor, to take the place of
                    Andrews&#x02BC;s erstwhile professional magazine, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Spiritual Times</hi>, which had printed the writing of the Andrews brood,
                    as well as Ruskin&#x02BC;s poetry. (Ian Anstruther, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Coventry Patmore&#x02BC;s Angel: A Study of Coventry Patmore, His Wife
                        Emily, and</hi> The Angel in the House (London: Haggerston, 1992),
                    17&#x2013;18.) Childhood authorship is encouraged in the stories of Maria
                    Edgeworth, which contains stories within stories ostensibly written by child
                    characters. (See, e.g., &#x201C;Rivuletta, A Dream&#x201D; by a girl
                    of thirteen, and &#x201C;The Injured Ass&#x201D; by a boy in eleven,
                    both in Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Rosamond</hi>, part 1, 26&#x2013;27,
                    49&#x2013;56. What sets apart Ruskin&#x02BC;s Red Books from this
                    common Victorian childhood pastime is the ambitious scope he set for himself,
                    and the genius and almost incredible pace and flexibility by which he was able
                    to live up to his ambitions. </p>
                <p>At the same time, the Red Books show how easily he was deflected from their
                    initial purposes. MS I, MS III, MS IIIA, and MS IV all begin with title pages
                    announcing works that Ruskin evidently meant to fill the notebook, but those
                    works steadily took up less and less of the available space. In 1826, on the
                    title page of MS I, he announced the first volume of his prose narrative,
                    &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; and he filled out the notebook with a
                    brief collection of poems, the MS I Poetry Anthology, which he followed with a
                    colophon to round out the whole. In 1827, he began MS III in the same manner,
                    with a title page for the second volume of &#x201C;Harry and
                    Lucy,&#x201D; and he probably nearly simultaneously entered the anthology,
                    Poetry Descriptive, to complement MS I. However, MS III grew more miscellaneous,
                    with the addition of the MS III Second Poetry Anthology, the narrative poem
                    &#x201C;The Monastery,&#x201D; and&#x2014;in 1829, in deference
                    to his mother&#x02BC;s criticism that he was prone to
                    &#x201C;beginning too eagerly and becoming careless towards the end of his
                    works as he calls them&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family
                        Letters</hi>, 187)&#x2014;the MS III Third Poetry Anthology. Prior to
                    this crisis, he started MS IV in 1828 with the title page for a
                    &#x201C;poem on the universe, &#x201C;Eudosia,&#x201D; but a
                    large portion of that Red Book was to remain blank, until Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    father used the pages two decades later to compile the first bibliography of the
                    published poetry. MS IIIA. . . .</p>
                <div type="subsection">
                <head type="subsection">Earliest Writing and Edgeworthian Education</head>
                <p>Ruskin&#x02BC;s earliest writing bears the stamp of the progressive methods
                    of education advocated by Richard and Maria Edgeworth. Famously, three of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s Red Books (MSS I, III, IIIA, and partial draft in MS II)
                    were initially used between 1826 and 1829 to contain fair copies of
                    &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; his adaptations of Maria
                    Edgeworth&#x02BC;s series of tales Early Lessons, separately titled <hi
                        rend="italic">The Parent&#x02BC;s Assistant</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Harry and Lucy</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Rosamond</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy Concluded</hi>.<note
                            n="2" place="botwin" resp="#DCH" xml:id="overview_majorms_note002">The
                        bibliography of the Edgeworths&#x02BC; children&#x02BC;s books is
                        notoriously confusing. The following is drawn from Marilyn Butler, <hi
                            rend="italic">Maria Edgewoth: A Literary Life</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon,
                        1972), 63&#x2013;64, 165&#x2013;68, and from the <hi rend="italic"
                            >New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature</hi>. <hi
                            rend="italic">Harry and Lucy</hi>, in its earliest version along with
                        its incipient theory of education, was originally devised by Richard Lovell
                        Edgeworth and his wife Honora in 1779&#x2013;80. This remained
                        unpublished, until revised by Richard and his daughter Maria for publication
                        in 1801, along with the other narratives, largely of Maria&#x02BC;s
                        composition. This first published <hi rend="italic">Early Lessons</hi>
                        consisted of <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy</hi>, pts. 1&#x2013;2
                        (1801); <hi rend="italic">Rosamond</hi>, pts. 1&#x2013;3 (1801); <hi
                            rend="italic">Frank</hi>, pts. 1&#x2013;4 (1801); and a volume of
                        stories, which completed the series in 1801&#x2013;2. Some of the
                        stories included in the <hi rend="italic">Early Lessons</hi> (not only
                        anthologized in the 1801&#x2013;2 volume but incorporated with the
                        other narratives) had been transferred from an earlier publication <hi
                            rend="italic">The Parent&#x02BC;s Assistant: or, Stories for
                            Children</hi> (1795 or 1796, 1800). <hi rend="italic">Continuation of
                            Early Lessons</hi> followed in 1814, and, after Richard&#x02BC;s
                        death, Maria carried on alone with <hi rend="italic">Rosamond: A Sequel to
                            Early Lessons</hi> (1821); <hi rend="italic">Frank: A Sequel to Frank in
                            Early Lessons</hi> (1822); and <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy
                            Concluded: Being the Last Part of Early Lessons</hi> (1825).</note>
                    Activities and experiments drawn from Edgeworth&#x02BC;s stories and from
                    Jeremiah Joyce&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Scientific Dialogues</hi> (1807;
                    see nos. 3, 20) are blended with the Ruskin family&#x02BC;s actual travels
                    and experiences. In his first two volumes of &#x201C;Harry and
                    Lucy&#x201D; (MSS I, III [1826&#x2013;28]), Ruskin probably identified
                    with either or both characters Harry and Lucy, although in the portions set at
                    his aunt&#x02BC;s home in Perth, Scotland, he may have associated
                    &#x201C;Lucy&#x201D; with his cousins Jessie and Mary Richardson. In
                    the third volume (MS IIIA, 1828), Ruskin concentrates less on travel adventures
                    and more on the family&#x02BC;s domestic activities at Herne Hill. Having
                    written this volume after his cousin Mary Richardson had come to live with the
                    family, Ruskin appears to identify more exclusively with Harry, who takes a
                    decidedly preceptorial role over Lucy, identified with Mary. Less impulsive than
                    in the two first volumes, and even priggishly strict with Lucy, Harry determines
                    the daily round as teaching Lucy the constellations before breakfast, lessons
                    after breakfast, drawing maps until dinner, correcting Virgil &#x201C;for
                    his papa&#x201D; and more mapmaking in the afternoon, and listening to papa
                    read <hi rend="italic">Don Quixote</hi> until bed (no. 32).</p>
                <p>Seen whole, the earlier juvenilia reveals how extensively the Ruskins invested in
                    the Edgeworths&#x02BC; program. Ruskin&#x02BC;s first extant poem and
                    slightly later works (nos. 1, ??) are drawn from <hi rend="italic">Evenings at
                        Home</hi> (1792&#x2013;96), by Anna Laetitia Barbauld and her brother
                    Dr. John Aiken. Mrs. Barbauld&#x02BC;s hymns and narratives were
                    recommended by Richard Edgeworth as a child&#x02BC;s first books, because
                    the pleasurable tales animate children with the desire to learn to read for
                    themselves. Another Edgeworth recommendation, Thomas Day&#x02BC;s <hi
                        rend="italic">Sandford and Merton</hi> (1783&#x2013;89) is declared
                    Harry&#x02BC;s &#x201C;favourite history&#x201D; in one of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s narratives (no. 20). Day was a close friend and associate
                    of the Edgeworths, although a more theoretical and committed Rousseauist than
                    they believed prudent.</p>
                <p>In another of Ruskin&#x02BC;s very first poems (no. 5), he imitates Erasmus
                    Darwin, the poet of the Lunar Society. This was the circle of scientists,
                    inventors, and industrialists, who stimulated the Edgeworths&#x02BC;
                    intellectual life.See Butler, Maria Edgewoth, 33&#x2013;35,
                    58&#x2013;61; and Robert E. Schofield, The Lunar Society of Birmingham: A
                    Social History of Provincial Science and Industry in Eighteenth&#x2010;Century England
                    (Oxford: Clarendon, 1963), 204&#x2013;10. Darwin&#x02BC;s heroic
                    couplets in <hi rend="italic">The Botanic Garden</hi> (1789&#x2013;91) may
                    also lie behind Ruskin&#x02BC;s catalog of plants in his
                    &#x201C;Eudosia, or a Poem on the Universe&#x201D; (no. 27), but the
                    title is taken from a production by Capell Lofft (1781), another poet of the
                    scientific enlightenment. Ruskin&#x02BC;s introduction to these poets
                    probably came through their frequent quotation in Jeremiah Joyce&#x02BC;s
                        <hi rend="italic">Scientific Dialogues</hi>, a systematic course in
                    mechanics, astronomy, hydrostatics, pneumatics, optics, and electricity.
                    Joyce&#x02BC;s prose is ornamented with extracts from this learned verse,
                    just as Darwin&#x02BC;s poem is annotated with extensive scientific notes.
                    Ruskin adopts this elegant manner, after his fashion, in his &#x201C;Harry
                    and Lucy.&#x201D; After imitating Joyce&#x02BC;s
                    experiments&#x2014;indeed, often copying them verbatim&#x2014;he caps
                    the prose with poems on natural history and the industrial sublime (MS I).</p>
                <p>Ruskin also imitates the conversational mode favored by the Edgeworths and by
                    Jeremiah Joyce, who, on his title page, attributes his
                    &#x201C;dialogue&#x201D; manner to the Edgeworths&#x02BC;
                    recommendations in <hi rend="italic">Practical Education</hi>
                    (1798&#x2013;1801). Dialogue promotes the fundamental premise of the
                    Edgeworth system, that appeals should be made to children&#x02BC;s reason,
                    and that they should be encouraged to think for themselves. Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    Harry and Lucy, much like Edgeworth&#x02BC;s Frank and the much beleaguered
                    Rosamond, are quizzed by Mamma, who treats ordinary events as opportunities to
                    admonish self&#x2010;discipline or to practice multiplication tables. Papa, in both
                    Ruskin and Edgeworth, is less prone to these Pumblechookian methods, and is
                    reserved for more exciting and brilliant experiments and excursions.</p>
                <p>If the boy was following approved Enlightenment models, the elder Ruskin was
                    nonetheless correct in <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> to detect gestures
                    characteristically his own, when, for example, at the close of his first
                    &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; (no. 3) he combines an electrical
                    experiment from Joyce, not just with elegant scientific verse, but with a
                    haunting image from Lord Byron. In part, the romance in Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    early writing shows merely that he possessed the materials to temper the
                    Edgeworth&#x02BC;s hostility to &#x201C;inflaming the imagination, or
                    exciting a restless spirit of adventure, by exhibiting false views of life, and
                    creating hopes which, in the ordinary course of things, cannot be
                    realized&#x201D; (preface to <hi rend="italic">Parent&#x02BC;s
                        Assistant</hi>). It is better for Rosamond to tour a cotton factory, even
                    though she is too young to understand the machinery, than to dream over
                    imaginary things (Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Rosamond</hi>, part 3, 149). That
                    Ruskin was untroubled by the fancy and fact dichotomy does not seem surprising
                    in a family that regularly read Scott and Byron. The more important division
                    indicated by Ruskin&#x02BC;s departures from Edgeworthian discipline is a
                    temperamental one between him and his mother.</p>
                <p> As Michael Brooks has remarked, the Edgeworths&#x02BC; educational program
                    may have been more congenial temperamentally to Margaret Ruskin than to her son.
                    Michael Brooks, &#x201C;Love and Possession in a Victorian Household: The
                    Example of the Ruskins,&#x201D; in The Victorian Family: Structure and
                    Stresses, ed. Anthony S. Wohl (New York: St. Martin&#x02BC;s, 1978), 92.
                    The Edgeworths provided a system, and method must have appealed to a woman,
                    whose nearly first words in Ruskin&#x02BC;s portrayal of her are to
                    &#x201C;do one thing at once&#x201D; (no. 3).</p>
                <p>Although rationalist mentors may have posed fundamental challenges to Margaret
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s evangelicalism&#x2014;just as Enlightenment and
                    Rousseauist approaches to education provoked Mrs. Sherwood, Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    favorite evangelical children&#x02BC;s writer&#x2014;the Edgeworths
                    were pragmatic enough that Margaret, like Mrs. Sherwood, was able to take what
                    she wanted from their stories, while disputing the Rousseauist premises. What
                    she wanted was system, reflected, as Brooks points out, in
                    Margaret&#x02BC;s constant and painstaking commitment to her
                    child&#x02BC;s education and her emphasis on children learning to reflect
                    on his own thought processes. These progressive aims, however, could be detached
                    from Rousseau&#x02BC;s fundamental conviction that the natural child should
                    be granted his birthright of freedom. Instead, the Edgeworthian system of
                    children thinking <emph rend="italic">for</emph> themselves could be urged
                    toward thinking <emph rend="italic">about</emph>
                    themselves&#x2014;Protestant self&#x2010;reflection. In that way, the sinful,
                    natural child would be curbed and made obedient to Christian, parental
                        authority.<note n="3"
                            place="botwin" resp="#DCH" xml:id="overview_majorms_note003">Brooks, 91. On Ruskin and Mrs. Sherwood, see my
                        &#x201C;Ruskin&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> and
                        Landscape in Evangelical Children&#x02BC;s Education,&#x201D; <hi
                            rend="italic">Nineteenth&#x2010;Century Literature</hi> 44, no. 1 (June 1989):
                        45&#x2013;66. There, I argue that Mrs. Sherwood, in
                        Ruskin&#x02BC;s favorite of the novels, <hi rend="italic">Henry
                            Milner</hi>, avoids pressing even the Protestant tradition of
                        self&#x2010;examination on her young audience, in favor of enforcing the
                        child&#x02BC;s trust and obedience&#x2014;a recourse that survives
                        partly in the strategies of deferring pain and conflict in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Praeterita</hi>, in favor of parental tribute. Now, I would confirm my
                        point about Ruskin&#x02BC;s childhood (and adulthood) evasion of
                        emotional distress, which the full spectacle of the early writing proves in
                        even more interesting ways psychologically; however, I would refine that
                        point to add that Ruskin was very early, and very precociously interested in
                        the processes of his own mind&#x2014;if, by that, one refers to what
                        Sheila Emerson has called &#x201C;the laws of motion&#x201D; that
                        Ruskin believed reflected both in his own mind on paper and in the outward
                        nature he beheld. Margaret Ruskin, for her part, was probably more prone
                        than Mrs. Sherwood to enforce on children, alongside obedience, the
                        Protestant duty of self&#x2010;examination; it was in such terms that she probably
                        understood the progressive Edgeworthian recommendation that children reason
                        their way to conclusions, rather than merely accept them. When she read to
                        the ten&#x2010;year&#x2010;old Ruskin and his cousin Mary from Adam Smith, that they may
                        &#x201C;observe something of the working of their own
                        minds,&#x201D; her ultimate aim was that they gain &#x201C;more
                        knowledge [of] themselves&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">RFL</hi>
                        186).</note></p>
                <p>What at times appears characteristic of Ruskin&#x02BC;s response to these
                    instructors, whether Edgeworthian or evangelical, are his wily dodges.
                    Joyce&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi> are carefully arranged for
                    the methodical acquisition of concepts, but Ruskin, in no. 3, begins in the
                    middle of Joyce&#x02BC;s course, with pneumatics, and then works backwards
                    even within that series of experiments. . . .</p>
                <p>Ruskin&#x02BC;s obedience or resistence to specific forms of training were
                    probably complex. When Ruskin declares in <hi rend="italic">Fors Clavigera</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> that he &#x201C;went on to amuse
                    myself, in my own way, learnt whole words at a time, as I did
                    patterns&#x201D; (28:274; 35:23), he may be remembering the stress on
                    acquisition of vocabulary in Joyce&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dialogues</hi> and in <hi rend="italic">Harry and Lucy</hi>, both of which
                    contain long glossaries and insist on a systematic accumulation of terms.
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s memory of solitary learning seems to counter the
                    Edgeworthians&#x02BC; contention that vocabulary, like all subjects,
                    &#x201C;should be made a subject of conversation&#x201D;; however,
                    Edgeworth also respected the child&#x02BC;s pleasure as the best arbiter of
                    what and how much should be read, and above all trained the child&#x02BC;s
                    &#x201C;habit of thinking for yourself&#x201D; (Edgeworth, <hi
                        rend="italic">Frank</hi>, 80, 104)....</p>
                <p>Questions of how Edgeworthian or any other system of education was adopted by the
                    elder Ruskins and how it was received cannot be considered apart from the
                    family&#x02BC;s psychology....</p>
                <p>The &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; books bear comparison with that
                    other celebrated body of Victorian juvenilia, the Brontë children&#x02BC;s
                    handmade books, in that both simulate in miniature the appearance of printed
                    works. In content also, Ruskin&#x02BC;s &#x201C;Harry and
                    Lucy&#x201D; narratives are comparable to the Brontë
                    &#x201C;sagas,&#x201D; in that the authors project themselves as
                    semireal, semifictional characters into fictive worlds modeled on their reading.
                    The Brontë children interact as &#x201C;little queens&#x201D; and
                    &#x201C;little king&#x201D; with characters derived from <hi
                        rend="italic">Blackwood&#x02BC;s</hi> and other fiction and with
                    current historical heroes such as the Duke of Wellington. Christine Alexander,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Early Writings of Charlotte Brontë</hi> (Buffalo,
                    N.Y.: Prometheus, 1983), 11&#x2013;26, 46. Similarly, Ruskin enters
                    imaginatively into the educational activities of Maria and Richard
                    Edgeworth&#x02BC;s Harry and Lucy.</p>
                <p>Unlike the Brontë sagas, Ruskin&#x02BC;s juvenilia did not continue to
                    develop a complex, ongoing fictive world. Charlotte Brontë lingered so long in
                    her childhood&#x02BC;s imaginative world that her first efforts at mature
                    fiction suffered from embroilment in the earlier sagas. Ibid.,
                    203&#x2013;12. Ruskin, on the other hand, began his
                    &#x201C;mature&#x201D; work in childhood. While the earlier
                    &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; books show charming (and
                    extraordinarily talented) imitations of children&#x02BC;s stories and
                    verse, within a few years the juvenilia so elaborately copies an adult library
                    that the pieces appear more to be a child&#x02BC;s offering in miniature of
                    adult productions beyond his years. In reading the Brontë sagas, one feels
                    oneself trespassing deeper and deeper into an arcane wonderland wrought by the
                    authors for their private adventuring&#x2014;an effect that would be
                    heightened, I assume, by the privilege of poring over Charlotte&#x02BC;s
                    microscopic handwriting and preciously tiny booklets. Ruskin&#x02BC;s hand
                    and booklets, too, are small enough to make reading uncomfortable at times, but
                    they do not begin to approach Charlotte&#x02BC;s feats. In reading the
                    early Ruskin, rather, one is invited to survey a public
                    spectacle&#x2014;from his paired epics &#x201C;Iteriad&#x201D;
                    and &#x201C;Athens&#x201D; to his &#x201C;Poem on the
                    Universe&#x201D; called &#x201C;Eudosia&#x201D;&#x2014;and
                    to admire the mere child who is showing off to his parents &#x201C;how well
                    he could do it&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, 35:72). At the same
                    time, the more one studies the early Ruskin especially of the rough&#x2010;draft
                    notebooks (MSS VI, VIII), the more one is struck by how, behind the public
                    performances and spilling into them, Ruskin reveals secrets, fantasies, and
                    emotional turmoil. Ruskin encoded these secrets in various ways, perhaps
                    concealing turmoil even from himself, but the emotions nonetheless continue to
                    trouble his characteristically ebullient voice.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; books are filled out with short poems.
                    In MS I, the verses are based partly on what he found in children&#x02BC;s
                    books, although some of these poems, such as the previously unpublished
                    &#x201C;On Papa&#x02BC;s Leaving Home&#x201D; (no. 8), already
                    display a highly inventive and interesting emotional response to his
                    father&#x02BC;s departures on business trips; other poems, such as
                    &#x201C;On Scotland&#x201D; (no. 6) may already show Ruskin responding
                    to family deaths. Loss, whether by death or absence, is a prominent theme in the
                    suppressed fragments; both &#x201C;The Monastery&#x201D; (no. 46) and
                    &#x201C;Athens&#x201D; (no. 135) break off with the despondent
                    farewells or the absences of older males.</p>
                <p>By 1827, in MS III, Ruskin is imitating adult polite verse in a section named
                    &#x201C;poetry discriptive&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>),
                    although, again, these poems already reveal an individualistic acuity in
                    perception of visual relationships, as Emerson has remarked. Another verse
                    grouping, also in MS III but dating from 1829, includes the versification of the
                    opening of Scott&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">The Monastery</hi>,
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s project for &#x201C;a novel&#x201D; (<hi
                        rend="italic">RFL</hi>, 185). Also from 1829, the handmade booklet
                    &#x201C;Battle of Waterloo . . . with Other Small Poems&#x201D;
                    imitates the verse drama publications of the period. At about the same time,
                    beginning in 1828, Ruskin exhibits a fine Augustan confidence in surveying the
                    creation by devoting a Red Book (MS IV) to &#x201C;Eudosia; or, a Poem on
                    the Universe.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Of the remainder of the earlier juvenilia, one Red Book was used in 1827 for
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s first Latin exercises, prior to Andrews&#x02BC;s
                    instruction (MS IVA). Another Red Book (MS IVB) was begun as a personalized
                    guidebook and itinerary for the family&#x02BC;s English tour of 1828.
                    Additionally, besides all these notebook productions, Ruskin celebrated his
                    father&#x02BC;s birthdays, New Year&#x02BC;s, and sometimes his own
                    birthday, by presenting John James with fancy copies of odes composed to
                    commemorate the occasions, along with other kinds of poems. For these he used
                    the most elaborate print or script that he could muster at the
                    time&#x2014;either his most careful early print in imitation of typeface or
                    a &#x201C;double&#x201D; print that, as a &#x201C;Harry and
                    Lucy&#x201D; episode records, cost him so much time that he rarely again
                    attempted it. Later, he employed a more rapid
                    &#x201C;copperplate&#x201D; hand, sometimes decorated with flourishes
                    drawn an arithmetic and orthography primer (see <hi rend="italic">RFL</hi>, 259,
                    261 n. 17). The presentation poems were copied on sheets folded vertically as a
                    folio; then the folios were sometimes folded twice horizontally, like a letter,
                    and a superscription added to the outside&#x2014;typically, &#x201C;To
                    My Father&#x201D; and a date. Many of these were bound later by Wedderburn
                    in MSS IA and XI along with other miscellaneous poems and letters.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Eudosia&#x201D; eventually faltered in 1830, with only one
                    volume on &#x201C;Botany&#x201D; (containing book 1 and part of book
                    2) carried from flowers through a catalog of trees. From here, Ruskin went on
                    undaunted to &#x201C;Iteriad&#x201D; (MS VII), a four&#x2010;book verse
                    account of the family tour to the Lakes in 1830, on which he worked until 1832.
                    When, in 1831, he had finished drafting (but not fair&#x2010;copying)
                    &#x201C;Iteriad,&#x201D; he began &#x201C;Athens,&#x201D; a
                    verse narrative of Xerxes&#x02BC; great march climaxing the Persian Wars.
                    Since Ruskin was translating the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> at the time, he no
                    doubt was inspired to attempt the ultimate epic achievement: to pair an epic on
                    travel adventure&#x2014;his own <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> in
                    &#x201C;Iteriad,&#x201D; as it were&#x2014;with an epic on
                    battle, his <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> in &#x201C;Athens.&#x201D;
                    Unlike &#x201C;Iteriad,&#x201D; however,
                    &#x201C;Athens&#x201D; was never finished, in its draft or its fair
                    copy. Meanwhile, between 1829 and 1832, Ruskin was using a smaller notebook (MS
                    V, not a Red Book) entitled &#x201C;Miscellaneous Poetry&#x201D; to
                    gather together fair copies of the shorter poems&#x2014;a sort of collected
                    minor poems.</p>
                <p>A change is noticeable from about 1831, age twelve, when Ruskin was engaged in
                    fair&#x2010;copying &#x201C;Iteriad&#x201D; and in drafting
                    &#x201C;Athens,&#x201D; and when his home studies were extended to
                    include modern languages, mathematics, more advanced Latin and Greek, and
                    drawing tutelage.See Tim Hilton, <hi rend="italic">John Ruskin: The Early Years,
                        1819&#x2013;1859</hi> (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press, 1985),
                    22&#x2013;24. Now the Red Books were set aside for grander notebooks in
                    half&#x2010;calf or half&#x2010;roan and marbled boards. As he would boast in early 1833, he
                    required &#x201C;additional space&#x201D; for &#x201C;greater
                    freedom &#38; play of cogitation&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">RFL</hi>,
                    274). In MS VII, he fair&#x2010;copied his &#x201C;Iteriad&#x201D; between
                    1831 and 1832 and started fair&#x2010;copying &#x201C;Athens.&#x201D; During
                    the same period, 1831&#x2013;32, he kept his first separate sketchbooks,
                    earlier drawings appearing mainly as &#x201C;plates&#x201D; in the Red
                    Books. The two sketchbooks exhibit picturesque sketches taken during tours of
                    the southeast of England. Later, in 1833&#x2013;34, the remarkable Account
                    of a Tour on the Continent (MS IX) imitates with astonishing fidelity the
                    engraved plates and letterpress of Samuel Rogers&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Italy</hi> and of the professional gift annuals to which Ruskin would soon
                    be contributing verse.</p>
                <p>Besides the epics and poetic travelogues of this period, Ruskin&#x02BC;s
                    lessons are worked up as his own &#x201C;published&#x201D; textbooks.
                    In place of the 1827 Latin vocabulary lists in a Red Book, his 1832 translation
                    of the first few books of the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> is presented in an
                    elegant double&#x2010;column pamphlet. A &#x201C;Practical Geometry&#x201D;
                    belonging to &#x201C;Mast<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ruskin Jan<hi
                        rend="superscript">y</hi> 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                    1833&#x201D;&#x2014;so inscribed probably when it was started (MS XIA)
                    and elaborately handlettered in Gothic and copperplate
                    scripts&#x2014;devotes each page to an elegant statement of a
                    &#x201C;problem&#x201D; and its solution in a neatly ruled geometric
                    figure.</p>
                <p>Whether owing to the accident of preservation or to Ruskin&#x02BC;s now
                    regarding himself as a more workmanlike poet, there survive from this time two
                    notebooks that serve for rough&#x2010;drafting poetry before it was copied elsewhere
                    (MSS VI, VIII). MS VIII, kept in continuous use between 1831 and 1836 or 1837,
                    is the primary source for poetry, stories, and drama related to
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s tormented and unrequited first love affair, Adèle Domecq.
                    Also starting about this time, the earlier Red Books are recycled as workbooks
                    (perhaps at the behest of John James, who was economical with paper).<note
                        n="4" place="botwin" resp="#DCH" xml:id="overview_majorms_note004">See <hi
                            rend="italic">TLC</hi>, 19. Some of the features of the juvenilia
                        manuscripts, such as the slightest indications of paragraph breaks and the
                        haphazard word divisions in the Sermon Books, may be partly explained by
                        John James&#x02BC;s frugality with paper.</note> Turned upside down and
                    started anew from the end opposite to the earlier &#x201C;Harry and
                    Lucy&#x201D; narratives, their remaining blank leaves and endboards
                    exploited, or their newer entries even crossing the earlier material, the Red
                    Books were now made to serve diverse interests&#x2014;articles on
                    mineralogy, algebra and geometry exercises, and sketches that turn up in
                    finished form as &#x201C;plates&#x201D; in MS IX. The mineralogy notes
                    and catalogs, which begin about 1830&#x2013;31 with a Red Book devoted to
                    the subject (MS IVC), evolve into the ambitious Mineralogical Dictionary (MS IVD
                    [1831&#x2013;36]), Ruskin&#x02BC;s own redaction of primers on
                    geological identification and classification, such as Jameson&#x02BC;s <hi
                        rend="italic">System of Mineralogy</hi> or the geological articles in
                    Loudon&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Magazine of Natural History</hi>, to
                    which Ruskin himself would contribute brief scientific papers in 1834.</p>
                <p>By their appearance, the Sermon Books (MSS IIA&#x2013;E) seem positioned
                    between the earlier juvenile Red Books and the later aspirations of the young
                    scholar. By their date also, the sermons&#x02BC; composition belong to a
                    transitional period, 1832&#x2013;34. In some physical respects, the Sermon
                    Books are similar to the earlier pamphlets constructed to conform with the Red
                    Books. Handmade and miniature, the pamphlets measure only 9.5 by 15.5
                    centimeters, with a text space of only 7.5 by 15 centimeters, into which Ruskin
                    packed roughly fifty lines and even seventy&#x2010;five on some pages. By this time,
                    however, the Red Books themselves were in their recycled stage of use, and in
                    fact some of the Red Books were reused to draft the sermons. Moreover, the
                    Sermon Books, despite their precious dimensions, appear more sober than the
                    &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; books, linking them to the formal
                    textbook presentations of contemporaneous and later prose&#x2014;the <hi
                        rend="italic">Iliad</hi> translation, the Mineralogical Dictionary, and,
                    later, the first critical essays (MSS XB, no. 270; MS XIB). The ink script is
                    studiously neat longhand, rather than the printing meant to imitate typeface
                    that had been used for poetry before the &#x201C;Iteriad.&#x201D;
                    Title headings follow a consistent pattern and, appropriate to the solemn
                    contents, show minimal ornamentation. The margins are
                    &#x201C;justified&#x201D; so rigorously that, rather than spoil the
                    effect, words are divided according to how much fits on the line rather than by
                    syllable; hyphens are omitted if space disallows; curlicues, commas, and dots
                    are <emph rend="italic">added</emph> to bring a short line to the margin (easily
                    misread as punctuation by the unwary); and paragraphs are indicated with only
                    the barest indentation or with only a slight line space.</p>
                <p> In content as well, the Sermon Books are especially interesting as reflecting
                    both a self&#x2010;conscious childishness and a rapidly maturing thought and learning.
                    Although the persona most frequently impersonates an elder, learned divine
                    expositing scripture to his congregation, the writer also speaks as a pious
                    child when the occasion demands, such as when commenting on the Fifth
                    Commandment. The boy&#x02BC;s perspective on the doctrine of his church is
                    invaluable, especially as a source for understanding the foundations of
                    Ruskin&#x02BC;s mature religious thought.</p>
                    
                    <!--<p>manuscriptsThis category comprises a range of circumstances accounting for gathering and
                        binding, so various that the category would seem pointless, save for its being
                        hallowed by usage starting with Collingwood, &#x201C;Preliminary
                        Note.&#x201D; Thus, a major manuscript in this traditional usage may be
                        (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) a notebook that was professionally bound and
                        purchased as such, given to or coopted by Ruskin and used at the time of
                        composition to contain his draft and/or fair copy; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) a
                        homemade gathering of leaves, folded and sewn at or near the time of
                        composition, and used for draft or fair copy; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) a
                        compilation of leaves and/or of gatherings of leaves (e.g., single&#x2010;sheet fair
                        copies of poems, holograph letters, etc.) that were originally unbound and
                        separate from one another, but long after the time of composition assembled
                        (with or without Ruskin&#x02BC;s oversight) by a member of
                        Ruskin&#x02BC;s circle (e.g., W. G. Collingwood or Alexander Wedderburn)
                        and sent to a professional binder. The category is further complicated by some
                        of these compilations subsequently being disassembled owing to damage. </p>
                    <p>Despite the awkward variety comprised in the category of <hi rend="italic">major
                        manuscripts</hi>, an awkwardness compounded by its relation to the category
                        of <hi rend="italic">manuscripts</hi>,
                    <p>Thus, the &#x201C;Note&#x201D; remains indispensable and survives in
                    one of the main portals to the archive. To name just one as an example, the
                    handmade booklet Battle of Waterloo: A Play in Two Acts, with Other Small Poems
                    and its traditional classifications of the major manuscripts are indispensable,
                    however, it can be supplemented by a tabular manuscript survey. This is
                    undertaken as part of the Overview of Manuscripts. </p>-->
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>