<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Education: Overview</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of
                    America, Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents,
                    National Endowment for the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South
                    Central Modern Language Association, and Southeastern Louisiana
                    University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-25">October 25, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department
                        of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">Education</head>
                <div type="section" xml:id="OVERVIEW"><!-- subhead used in POETRY is "Lesson"-->
                    <head type="section">Overview</head>
                
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="PRACTICAL_EDUCATION">
                    <head type="title">Practical Education</head>
                    <p>his earliest writings, 
                        preserved largely in his <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="red_book_note.php">Red Books</ref>, reflect the influence 
                        of <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="edgeworth_maria_note.php">Maria Edgeworth</ref> and her father,
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="edgeworth_richard_lovell_note.php">R. L. Edgeworth</ref>. The presence of this progressive, Enlightenment approach to education 
                        in an Evangelical household is less surprising than the models presented by some writers carried in the Edgeworths&#x02BC; wake&#x2014;writers 
                        such as <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="joyce_jeremiah_note.php">Jeremiah Joyce</ref>, and 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="lofft_capel_note.php">Capel Lofft</ref>, whose scientific writings Ruskin imitates closely, 
                        but whose radical politics surely would have been unacceptable to the Ruskins. These influences disappear abruptly after 1829, when Ruskin&#x02BC;s religious education appears perceptively
                        in the archive. One can only speculate whether the displacement reflects an alarm of the elder Ruskins&#x02BC; discovery of these writers&#x02BC; politics 
                        or their plan to confine and control a rational educational program that they regarded as useful and up&#x2010;to&#x2010;date but as politically and spiritually problematic.</p>
                     <p>prational e perceived as u of<persName>Marilyn Butler</persName> divides <persName>Maria
                            Edgeworth</persName>&#x02BC;s works for children into tales, which
                        Butler regards as "virtually an original literary form" invented by Maria,
                        and lessons, devised "for the purpose of teaching facts about chemistry,
                        physics, mechanics, and other sciences, as well as certain specific
                        injunctions about behaviour--truth-telling, obedience to parents, and so on"
                        (168). The foundations for the two genres were laid, respectively, in the
                        collection of tales The Parent's Assistant (1796; 2d ed., 1800) and in the
                        theoretical treatise (not lessons aimed directly at children) Practical
                        Education (1798; 2d ed., 1801). Butler's distinction in genres is useful in
                        understanding the Ruskin family's uses of Edgeworth's works. Despite
                        Ruskin's later admiration for Edgeworth's tales and novels, it appears in
                        boyhood that he was either given the books of lessons by his parents or more
                        personally drawn to that genre--or both--as compared with tales. Lessons are
                        prominently and steadily represented in the juvenilia by Harry and Lucy I,
                        II, and III, whereas tales are limited to . . . Ruskin did not make his
                        first sustained attempt at writing tales until much later, around age ?, and
                        then the more immediate model was not Maria Edgeworth but George Croly (see
                        MS ?).</p>
<p>Question of JR's precocity. Dating of Needless as 26 reflects attempt to get with the program?</p>
                    <p>Practical Education The Edgeworths' program for education, as developed in
                        Practical Education, was to approach it as an empirical and experimental
                        science, based on what children actually do and say and not on theoretical
                        system. Children should be allowed to acquire knowledge by their own
                        experience, without apprehension of being directed by "the dictatorial
                        anathematizing tone . . . of a theorist" (Edgeworth, Practical Education,
                        15). To promote experimentation, the Edgeworths advocated, for example,
                        replacing mechanical and gilt toys, which can only be passively admired,
                        with "pieces of wood of various shapes and sizes, which they may build up
                        and pull down, and put in a variety of different forms and positions"
                        (ibid., 16). [Develop toys issue with Hanson and Emerson] To prevent
                        children from being stymied in their experimental efforts, the Edgeworths
                        emphasize gradated learning. In Practical Education, Maria ridicules
                        assigning young children elaborate tasks in gardening and carpentering
                        before they are capable of handling specialized tools. Materials should be
                        kept simple in order to retain the focus on "simple facts" that the mind can
                        "reason upon," inducing the child "to judge of the different conclusions
                        which are drawn from [the facts] by different people" (26). But Ruskin's
                        orrery and puppet theater. . . . The order in which the lessons were meant
                        to be read, which did not correspond to the order in which they were
                        written, had been laid out by Richard Lovell Edgeworth in the "Address to
                        Mothers" (1801)--so far, at least, as the lessons had been written: "Frank
                        is the easiest to be understood; and should therefore have come first; after
                        Frank, the first part of Harry and Lucy; then Rosamond; and, lastly, the
                        second part of Harry and Lucy. . . . This latter part should not be put into
                        the hands of pupils before they are eight years old" (???). All these had
                        first been published in 1801??? as Early Lessons. After this, Continuation
                        of Early Lessons, published in 1813??, contained more parts of Harry and
                        Lucy, Frank, and Rosamond. Further parts of Rosamond and Frank, published in
                        1821 and 1822 respectively, were directed at ten- to thirteen-year-olds.
                        Finally, Harry and Lucy Concluded, released in 1825, brought the heroes
                        along with their readers to age fourteen. Ruskin starts at the wrong end of
                        the lessons, taking the last ones first, which were intended for elder
                        children. Similarly, he starts with the most advanced experiments in Joyce.
                        Dialogue While in Butler's view the Edgeworthian lesson was a less original
                        creation than Maria's tales, the form can be seen as supplying a framework,
                        however loosely, for the exchange between Ruskin and his parents that lies
                        at the core of his education. The form was originally developed by Maria's
                        father, Richard Lovell Edgeworth, and his second wife, Honora; and, while
                        Edgeworth scholars are justifiably anxious now to credit Maria with the
                        form's realization in Early Lessons, which included Harry and Lucy, Frank,
                        and Rosamond, Maria's own insistence on her father's contribution highlights
                        the importance of collaboration and exchange. As Richard Lovell Edgeworth
                        acknowledges in ????, Mrs. Barbauld developed the basis of the genre in ????
                        by writing a dialogue form of instruction that employs simple language
                        accessible to a child. Science and Religion In 1820, a year after Ruskin was
                        born, the reception of the Edgeworths' educational ideas reached a nadir.
                        With the publication of Memoirs of Richard Lovell Edgeworth, written by
                        himself and Maria, conservative and religious reviewers refused to condone
                        the absence of religion in the Edgeworths' writings as mere avoidance of
                        controversy, instead pronouncing the works atheistic and subversive (Manly,
                        introduction to Edgeworth, Practical Education, 11:xvi-xvii). . . . [See
                        happiness, practical ed 28] Butler treats the Edgeworths' employment of the
                        lesson form to instruct the practical science favored by the Lunar Society
                        of scientists and industrialists presented young readers with a unique and
                        more timely experience of the emerging nineteenth-century industrialized
                        world--an original and significant development as compared with the form's
                        employment by Barbauld, Mrs. Trimmer, and Dorothy Kilner to teach morality
                        and religion (Maria Edgeworth 165n.). The originality as such of the
                        Edgeworths' contribution is, however, perhaps less relevant to understanding
                        the Ruskins' employment of these works than the family's timely and
                        progressive interest in the early Victorian industrialized world. Evidence
                        of Ruskin's engagement with morality and religion--although certainly
                        present in ??? and ???--pales by comparison. The emphasis suggests that the
                        boy's reading was governed by parents ambitious "to follow . . . a programme
                        of education" (168) that the elder Edgeworths had developed in context of
                        theory. Think about Butler's point that the Edgeworths were in the end more
                        influenced by the Scottish emphasis on economic and civic man than by
                        Rousseau's idea of natural man. (see notes) Butler's view of ME as an
                        unconscious realist, one attracted to empirical reality but who was unlikely
                        to formulate realism as a conscious literary objective. Nonetheless, because
                        (or if) JR started with Harry and Lucy Concluded instead of the earlier
                        books in the series, the contest between imagination and truth was in his
                        mind. Ruskin’s earliest extant juvenilia dates from 1826, about age seven,
                        aside from probably earlier childish scrawls, simple drawings, and practice
                        writing of his name on the flyleaves of his books. Most of the writing from
                        1826, when Ruskin was seven, through about 1831 is contained in the “Red
                        Books” (MSS I, III, IIIA, IV, IVA, IVB, IVC), a uniform set of seven
                        store-bought notebooks with reddish-brown, flexible leather covers
                        (described as roan in Sotheby Cat. 1930), each approximately ten by fifteen
                        centimeters. Red Books was Ruskin’s own term, used both in childhood, when
                        referring to them in letters to his father (e.g., RFL 192), and in later
                        years, when reoccupying his old nursery rooms atop the Herne Hill house and
                        meditating on his childhood for Fors and Praeterita (Ruskin’s Camberwell,
                        13–14). Perhaps it was on one of the latter occasions that he wrote Red Book
                        and an assigned number inside some of these. Contemporaneous and in
                        conformity with the Red Books, there also survive three handmade pamphlets
                        (MSS IB, II, and one containing no. 57 now cut apart and its leaves tipped
                        into MS V; MS IB was later professionally bound). Ruskin constructed these
                        from plain paper cut to about the size of the Red Books, folded once and
                        sewed. One pamphlet (see no. 57) was covered with pinkish violet paper,
                        perhaps to make its color uniform with the Red Books. Another (MS II) bears
                        the heading “Vol I,” connecting it with what he called his series of “works”
                        (RFL, 187). These early “works” might be described as bookmaking as much as
                        writing. From the start in MS I, although Ruskin’s pencil printing is still
                        fairly crude, he thinks to “justify” the margins, enclose his illustrations
                        in frames and number them as “plates,” and provide title pages and even
                        colophons. In contents, the Red Books imitate a range of genres, from
                        children’s verse and didactic tales to such adult forms as travel narrative
                        and topographic verse. In this imitative bookmaking, Ruskin was probably not
                        unusual among Victorian and Edwardian children. Less famous childhoods also
                        left behind scientific “monographs,” derivative “histories,” and diaries
                        that include illustrated poetry. Some families even privately circulated
                        “magazines,” with elaborate nursery pretenses to real-life editorship. For
                        example, a handmade magazine, “The Beresford Spy,” was produced by the
                        children of Reverend Edward Andrews, Ruskin’s tutor, to take the place of
                        Andrews’s erstwhile professional magazine, the Spiritual Times, which had
                        printed the writing of the Andrews brood, as well as Ruskin’s poetry.
                        Childhood authorship is encouraged in the stories of Maria Edgeworth, which
                        contains stories within stories ostensibly written by child characters. The
                        distinction setting apart Ruskin’s Red Books from this common Victorian
                        childhood pastime lay in the ambitious scope he set for himself, and the
                        genius and almost incredible pace and flexibility by which he was able to
                        live up to his ambitions. Ruskin’s earliest writing bears the stamp of the
                        progressive methods of education advocated by Richard and Maria Edgeworth.
                        Famously, three of Ruskin’s Red Books (MSS I, III, IIIA, and partial draft
                        in MS II) were initially used between 1826 and 1829 to contain fair copies
                        of “Harry and Lucy,” his adaptations of Maria Edgeworth’s series of tales
                        Early Lessons, separately titled The Parent’s Assistant, Harry and Lucy,
                        Frank, Rosamond, and Harry and Lucy Concluded. Activities and experiments
                        drawn from Edgeworth’s stories and from Jeremiah Joyce’s Scientific
                        Dialogues (1807; see nos. 3, 20) are blended with the Ruskin family’s actual
                        travels and experiences. In his first two volumes of “Harry and Lucy” (MSS
                        I, III [1826–28]), Ruskin probably identified with either or both characters
                        Harry and Lucy, although in the portions set at his aunt’s home in Perth,
                        Scotland, he may have associated “Lucy” with his cousins Jessie and Mary
                        Richardson. In the third volume (MS IIIA, 1828), Ruskin concentrates less on
                        travel adventures and more on the family’s domestic activities at Herne
                        Hill. Having written this volume after his cousin Mary Richardson had come
                        to live with the family, Ruskin appears to identify more exclusively with
                        Harry, who takes a decidedly preceptorial role over Lucy, identified with
                        Mary. Less impulsive than in the two first volumes, and even priggishly
                        strict with Lucy, Harry determines the daily round as teaching Lucy the
                        constellations before breakfast, lessons after breakfast, drawing maps until
                        dinner, correcting Virgil “for his papa” and more mapmaking in the
                        afternoon, and listening to papa read Don Quixote until bed (no. 32). Seen
                        whole, the earlier juvenilia reveals how extensively the Ruskins invested in
                        the Edgeworths’ program. Ruskin’s first extant poem and slightly later works
                        (nos. 1, ??) are drawn from Evenings at Home (1792–96), by Anna Laetitia
                        Barbauld and her brother Dr. John Aiken. Mrs. Barbauld’s hymns and
                        narratives were recommended by Richard Edgeworth as a child’s first books,
                        because the pleasurable tales animate children with the desire to learn to
                        read for themselves. Another Edgeworth recommendation, Thomas Day’s Sandford
                        and Merton (1783–89) is declared Harry’s “favourite history” in one of
                        Ruskin’s narratives (no. 20). Day was a close friend and associate of the
                        Edgeworths, although a more theoretical and committed Rousseauist than they
                        believed prudent. In another of Ruskin’s very first poems (no. 5), he
                        imitates Erasmus Darwin, the poet of the Lunar Society. This was the circle
                        of scientists, inventors, and industrialists, who stimulated the Edgeworths’
                        intellectual life. Darwin’s heroic couplets in The Botanic Garden (1789–91)
                        may also lie behind Ruskin’s catalog of plants in his “Eudosia, or a Poem on
                        the Universe” (no. 27), but the title is taken from a production by Capell
                        Lofft (1781), another poet of the scientific enlightenment. Ruskin’s
                        introduction to these poets probably came through their frequent quotation
                        in Jeremiah Joyce’s Scientific Dialogues, a systematic course in mechanics,
                        astronomy, hydrostatics, pneumatics, optics, and electricity. Joyce’s prose
                        is ornamented with extracts from this learned verse, just as Darwin’s poem
                        is annotated with extensive scientific notes. Ruskin adopts this elegant
                        manner, after his fashion, in his “Harry and Lucy.” After imitating Joyce’s
                        experiments—indeed, often copying them verbatim—he caps the prose with poems
                        on natural history and the industrial sublime (MS I). Ruskin also imitates
                        the conversational mode favored by the Edgeworths and by Jeremiah Joyce,
                        who, on his title page, attributes his “dialogue” manner to the Edgeworths’
                        recommendations in Practical Education (1798–1801). Dialogue promotes the
                        fundamental premise of the Edgeworth system, that appeals should be made to
                        children’s reason, and that they should be encouraged to think for
                        themselves. Ruskin’s Harry and Lucy, much like Edgeworth’s Frank and the
                        much beleaguered Rosamond, are quizzed by Mamma, who treats ordinary events
                        as opportunities to admonish self-discipline or to practice multiplication
                        tables. Papa, in both Ruskin and Edgeworth, is less prone to these
                        Pumblechookian methods, and is reserved for more exciting and brilliant
                        experiments and excursions. If the boy was following approved Enlightenment
                        models, the elder Ruskin was nonetheless correct in Praeterita to detect
                        gestures characteristically his own, when, for example, at the close of his
                        first “Harry and Lucy” (no. 3) he combines an electrical experiment from
                        Joyce, not just with elegant scientific verse, but with a haunting image
                        from Lord Byron. In part, the romance in Ruskin’s early writing shows merely
                        that he possessed the materials to temper the Edgeworth’s hostility to
                        “inflaming the imagination, or exciting a restless spirit of adventure, by
                        exhibiting false views of life, and creating hopes which, in the ordinary
                        course of things, cannot be realized” (preface to Parent’s Assistant). It is
                        better for Rosamond to tour a cotton factory, even though she is too young
                        to understand the machinery, than to dream over imaginary things (Edgeworth,
                        Rosamond, part 3, 149). That Ruskin was untroubled by the fancy and fact
                        dichotomy does not seem surprising in a family that regularly read Scott and
                        Byron. The more important division indicated by Ruskin’s departures from
                        Edgeworthian discipline is a temperamental one between him and his mother.
                        As Michael Brooks has remarked, the Edgeworths’ educational program may have
                        been more congenial temperamentally to Margaret Ruskin than to her son. The
                        Edgeworths provided a system, and method must have appealed to a woman,
                        whose nearly first words in Ruskin’s portrayal of her are to “do one thing
                        at once” (no. 3). Although rationalist mentors may have posed fundamental
                        challenges to Margaret Ruskin’s evangelicalism—just as Enlightenment and
                        Rousseauist approaches to education provoked Mrs. Sherwood, Ruskin’s
                        favorite evangelical children’s writer—the Edgeworths were pragmatic enough
                        that Margaret, like Mrs. Sherwood, was able to take what she wanted from
                        their stories, while disputing the Rousseauist premises. What she wanted was
                        system, reflected, as Brooks points out, in Margaret’s constant and
                        painstaking commitment to her child’s education and her emphasis on children
                        learning to reflect on his own thought processes. These progressive aims,
                        however, could be detached from Rousseau’s fundamental conviction that the
                        natural child should be granted his birthright of freedom. Instead, the
                        Edgeworthian system of children thinking for themselves could be urged
                        toward thinking about themselves—Protestant self-reflection. In that way,
                        the sinful, natural child would be curbed and made obedient to Christian,
                        parental authority. What at times appears characteristic of Ruskin’s
                        response to these instructors, whether Edgeworthian or evangelical, are his
                        wily dodges. Joyce’s Dialogues are carefully arranged for the methodical
                        acquisition of concepts, but Ruskin, in no. 3, begins in the middle of
                        Joyce’s course, with pneumatics, and then works backwards even within that
                        series of experiments. . . . Ruskin’s obedience or resistence to specific
                        forms of training were probably complex. When Ruskin declares in Fors
                        Clavigera and Praeterita that he “went on to amuse myself, in my own way,
                        learnt whole words at a time, as I did patterns” (28:274; 35:23), he may be
                        remembering the stress on acquisition of vocabulary in Joyce’s Dialogues and
                        in Harry and Lucy, both of which contain long glossaries and insist on a
                        systematic accumulation of terms. Ruskin’s memory of solitary learning seems
                        to counter the Edgeworthians’ contention that vocabulary, like all subjects,
                        “should be made a subject of conversation”; however, Edgeworth also
                        respected the child’s pleasure as the best arbiter of what and how much
                        should be read, and above all trained the child’s “habit of thinking for
                        yourself” (Edgeworth, Frank, 80, 104).... Questions of how Edgeworthian or
                        any other system of education was adopted by the elder Ruskins and how it
                        was received cannot be considered apart from the family’s psychology.... The
                        “Harry and Lucy” books bear comparison with that other celebrated body of
                        Victorian juvenilia, the Brontë children’s handmade books, in that both
                        simulate in miniature the appearance of printed works. In content also,
                        Ruskin’s “Harry and Lucy” narratives are comparable to the Brontë “sagas,”
                        in that the authors project themselves as semireal, semifictional characters
                        into fictive worlds modeled on their reading. The Brontë children interact
                        as “little queens” and “little king” with characters derived from
                        Blackwood’s and other fiction and with current historical heroes such as the
                        Duke of Wellington. Similarly, Ruskin enters imaginatively into the
                        educational activities of Maria and Richard Edgeworth’s Harry and Lucy.
                        Unlike the Brontë sagas, Ruskin’s juvenilia did not continue to develop a
                        complex, ongoing fictive world. Charlotte Brontë lingered so long in her
                        childhood’s imaginative world that her first efforts at mature fiction
                        suffered from embroilment in the earlier sagas. Ruskin, on the other hand,
                        began his “mature” work in childhood. While the earlier “Harry and Lucy”
                        books show charming (and extraordinarily talented) imitations of children’s
                        stories and verse, within a few years the juvenilia so elaborately copies an
                        adult library that the pieces appear more to be a child’s offering in
                        miniature of adult productions beyond his years. In reading the Brontë
                        sagas, one feels oneself trespassing deeper and deeper into an arcane
                        wonderland wrought by the authors for their private adventuring—an effect
                        that would be heightened, I assume, by the privilege of poring over
                        Charlotte’s microscopic handwriting and preciously tiny booklets. Ruskin’s
                        hand and booklets, too, are small enough to make reading uncomfortable at
                        times, but they do not begin to approach Charlotte’s feats. In reading the
                        early Ruskin, rather, one is invited to survey a public spectacle—from his
                        paired epics “Iteriad” and “Athens” to his “Poem on the Universe” called
                        “Eudosia”—and to admire the mere child who is showing off to his parents
                        “how well he could do it” (Works, 35:72). At the same time, the more one
                        studies the early Ruskin especially of the rough-draft notebooks (MSS VI,
                        VIII), the more one is struck by how, behind the public performances and
                        spilling into them, Ruskin reveals secrets, fantasies, and emotional
                        turmoil. Ruskin encoded these secrets in various ways, perhaps concealing
                        turmoil even from himself, but the emotions nonetheless continue to trouble
                        his characteristically ebullient voice. The “Harry and Lucy” books are
                        filled out with short poems. In MS I, the verses are based partly on what he
                        found in children’s books, although some of these poems, such as the
                        previously unpublished “On Papa’s Leaving Home” (no. 8), already display a
                        highly inventive and interesting emotional response to his father’s
                        departures on business trips; other poems, such as “On Scotland” (no. 6) may
                        already show Ruskin responding to family deaths. Loss, whether by death or
                        absence, is a prominent theme in the suppressed fragments; both “The
                        Monastery” (no. 46) and “Athens” (no. 135) break off with the despondent
                        farewells or the absences of older males. By 1827, in MS III, Ruskin is
                        imitating adult polite verse in a section named “poetry discriptive” (sic),
                        although, again, these poems already reveal an individualistic acuity in
                        perception of visual relationships, as Emerson has remarked. Another verse
                        grouping, also in MS III but dating from 1829, includes the versification of
                        the opening of Scott’s The Monastery, Ruskin’s project for “a novel” (RFL,
                        185). Also from 1829, the handmade booklet “Battle of Waterloo . . . with
                        Other Small Poems” imitates the verse drama publications of the period. At
                        about the same time, beginning in 1828, Ruskin exhibits a fine Augustan
                        confidence in surveying the creation by devoting a Red Book (MS IV) to
                        “Eudosia; or, a Poem on the Universe.” Of the remainder of the earlier
                        juvenilia, one Red Book was used in 1827 for Ruskin’s first Latin exercises,
                        prior to Andrews’s instruction (MS IVA). Another Red Book (MS IVB) was begun
                        as a personalized guidebook and itinerary for the family’s English tour of
                        1828. Additionally, besides all these notebook productions, Ruskin
                        celebrated his father’s birthdays, New Year’s, and sometimes his own
                        birthday, by presenting John James with fancy copies of odes composed to
                        commemorate the occasions, along with other kinds of poems. For these he
                        used the most elaborate print or script that he could muster at the
                        time—either his most careful early print in imitation of typeface or a
                        “double” print that, as a “Harry and Lucy” episode records, cost him so much
                        time that he rarely again attempted it. Later, he employed a more rapid
                        “copperplate” hand, sometimes decorated with flourishes drawn an arithmetic
                        and orthography primer (see RFL, 259, 261 n. 17). The presentation poems
                        were copied on sheets folded vertically as a folio; then the folios were
                        sometimes folded twice horizontally, like a letter, and a superscription
                        added to the outside—typically, “To My Father” and a date. Many of these
                        were bound later by Wedderburn in MSS IA and XI along with other
                        miscellaneous poems and letters. “Eudosia” eventually faltered in 1830, with
                        only one volume on “Botany” (containing book 1 and part of book 2) carried
                        from flowers through a catalog of trees. From here, Ruskin went on undaunted
                        to “Iteriad” (MS VII), a four-book verse account of the family tour to the
                        Lakes in 1830, on which he worked until 1832. When, in 1831, he had finished
                        drafting (but not fair-copying) “Iteriad,” he began “Athens,” a verse
                        narrative of Xerxes’ great march climaxing the Persian Wars. Since Ruskin
                        was translating the Iliad at the time, he no doubt was inspired to attempt
                        the ultimate epic achievement: to pair an epic on travel adventure—his own
                        Odyssey in “Iteriad,” as it were—with an epic on battle, his Iliad in
                        “Athens.” Unlike “Iteriad,” however, “Athens” was never finished, in its
                        draft or its fair copy. Meanwhile, between 1829 and 1832, Ruskin was using a
                        smaller notebook (MS V, not a Red Book) entitled “Miscellaneous Poetry” to
                        gather together fair copies of the shorter poems—a sort of collected minor
                        poems. A change is noticeable from about 1831, age twelve, when Ruskin was
                        engaged in fair-copying “Iteriad” and in drafting “Athens,” and when his
                        home studies were extended to include modern languages, mathematics, more
                        advanced Latin and Greek, and drawing tutelage. Now the Red Books were set
                        aside for grander notebooks in half-calf or half-roan and marbled boards. As
                        he would boast in early 1833, he required “additional space” for “greater
                        freedom ampersand play of cogitation” (RFL, 274). In MS VII, he fair-copied
                        his “Iteriad” between 1831 and 1832 and started fair-copying “Athens.”
                        During the same period, 1831–32, he kept his first separate sketchbooks,
                        earlier drawings appearing mainly as “plates” in the Red Books. The two
                        sketchbooks exhibit picturesque sketches taken during tours of the southeast
                        of England. Later, in 1833–34, the remarkable Account of a Tour on the
                        Continent (MS IX) imitates with astonishing fidelity the engraved plates and
                        letterpress of Samuel Rogers’s Italy and of the professional gift annuals to
                        which Ruskin would soon be contributing verse. Besides the epics and poetic
                        travelogues of this period, Ruskin’s lessons are worked up as his own
                        “published” textbooks. In place of the 1827 Latin vocabulary lists in a Red
                        Book, his 1832 translation of the first few books of the Iliad is presented
                        in an elegant double-column pamphlet. A “Practical Geometry” belonging to
                        “Mastr Ruskin Jany 21st 1833”—so inscribed probably when it was started (MS
                        XIA) and elaborately handlettered in Gothic and copperplate scripts—devotes
                        each page to an elegant statement of a “problem” and its solution in a
                        neatly ruled geometric figure. Whether owing to the accident of preservation
                        or to Ruskin’s now regarding himself as a more workmanlike poet, there
                        survive from this time two notebooks that serve for rough-drafting poetry
                        before it was copied elsewhere (MSS VI, VIII). MS VIII, kept in continuous
                        use between 1831 and 1836 or 1837, is the primary source for poetry,
                        stories, and drama related to Ruskin’s tormented and unrequited first love
                        affair, Adèle Domecq. Also starting about this time, the earlier Red Books
                        are recycled as workbooks (perhaps at the behest of John James, who was
                        economical with paper). Turned upside down and started anew from the end
                        opposite to the earlier “Harry and Lucy” narratives, their remaining blank
                        leaves and endboards exploited, or their newer entries even crossing the
                        earlier material, the Red Books were now made to serve diverse
                        interests—articles on mineralogy, algebra and geometry exercises, and
                        sketches that turn up in finished form as “plates” in MS IX. The mineralogy
                        notes and catalogs, which begin about 1830–31 with a Red Book devoted to the
                        subject (MS IVC), evolve into the ambitious Mineralogical Dictionary (MS IVD
                        [1831–36]), Ruskin’s own redaction of primers on geological identification
                        and classification, such as Jameson’s System of Mineralogy or the geological
                        articles in Loudon’s Magazine of Natural History, to which Ruskin himself
                        would contribute brief scientific papers in 1834. By their appearance, the
                        Sermon Books (MSS IIA–E) seem positioned between the earlier juvenile Red
                        Books and the later aspirations of the young scholar. By their date also,
                        the sermons’ composition belong to a transitional period, 1832–34. In some
                        physical respects, the Sermon Books are similar to the earlier pamphlets
                        constructed to conform with the Red Books. Handmade and miniature, the
                        pamphlets measure only 9.5 by 15.5 centimeters, with a text space of only
                        7.5 by 15 centimeters, into which Ruskin packed roughly fifty lines and even
                        seventy-five on some pages. By this time, however, the Red Books themselves
                        were in their recycled stage of use, and in fact some of the Red Books were
                        reused to draft the sermons. Moreover, the Sermon Books, despite their
                        precious dimensions, appear more sober than the “Harry and Lucy” books,
                        linking them to the formal textbook presentations of contemporaneous and
                        later prose—the Iliad translation, the Mineralogical Dictionary, and, later,
                        the first critical essays (MSS XB, no. 270; MS XIB). The ink script is
                        studiously neat longhand, rather than the printing meant to imitate typeface
                        that had been used for poetry before the “Iteriad.” Title headings follow a
                        consistent pattern and, appropriate to the solemn contents, show minimal
                        ornamentation. The margins are “justified” so rigorously that, rather than
                        spoil the effect, words are divided according to how much fits on the line
                        rather than by syllable; hyphens are omitted if space disallows; curlicues,
                        commas, and dots are added to bring a short line to the margin (easily
                        misread as punctuation by the unwary); and paragraphs are indicated with
                        only the barest indentation or with only a slight line space. In content as
                        well, the Sermon Books are especially interesting as reflecting both a
                        self-conscious childishness and a rapidly maturing thought and learning.
                        Although the persona most frequently impersonates an elder, learned divine
                        expositing scripture to his congregation, the writer also speaks as a pious
                        child when the occasion demands, such as when commenting on the Fifth
                        Commandment. The boy’s perspective on the doctrine of his church is
                        invaluable, especially as a source for understanding the foundations of
                        Ruskin’s mature religious thought.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
