<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="note">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the NOTE followed by "note", for example, "red_book_note".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "red_book_note.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="runciman_charles_note">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Charles Runciman (1798-1864)</title>
                <title type="sub">Note</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2012-09-04">September 4, 2011</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note" subtype="biographical">
                <head type="title"><persName corresp="#CR">Charles Runciman</persName> (<date notBefore="1798" notAfter="1864">1798&#x2013;1864</date>)</head>
                <p>Ruskin's first drawing master from ???? to ???? (see Burd's discussion of this 261). Runciman was employed initially to teach Ruskin's cousin, Mary Richardson. . . .</p>
                <p>In <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#GRAVESDICTIONARY">Graves, <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Artists</hi></ref> (1884), 
                    Runciman is assigned the specialty of a historical painter, and he is credited with 57 exhibitions between 1825 and 1867, of which 16 were at the Royal Academy,
                    25 at the British Institution, and 16 at the Suffolk Street Exhibitions (i.e., the Society of British Artists) (p. 203). [check ref works in harris]. Walton 
                    says that Runciman "tried unsuccessfully for years to attract favourable attention as a painter of landscapes, genre scenes, and historical subjects" (9).</p>
                <p>Runciman's metier was teaching of perspective (RFL 261 n. 13), reflected in Ruskin's description of a lesson: "I took my paper &#x0026; I fixed my points, 
                    &#x0026; I drew my perspective, &#x0026; then as Mr Runciman bid me, I began to invent a scene". 
                    Working within this method, Ruskin constructed a scene by means of what he termed "patch[ing] . . . together": "I examined one of Mary's pictures, 
                    to see how the rocks were done, &#x0026; then another to see how the woods were done, &#x0026; another to see how the moutains were done, 
                    and another to see how the cottages were done, and I patched them all together, &#x0026; I made such a lovely scene (John Ruskin to John James Ruskin, 20 February 1832 [RFL 262-63]). 
                    Although Ruskin expected to be scolded for this patchwork approach to invention, but the master's response was that "patch[ing] up . . . was not copying," 
                    and that "there was something in" Ruskin's picture "that would make him totally change the method he had hitherto pursued with me." Forthwith, Runciman 
                    instructed Ruskin to use watercolor on grey paper, beginning "with a few of the simplest colours, in order to teach me better the effects of light &#x0026; shade." 
                    The aim was "to teach me water colour painting, but . . . only as a basis for oil" (John Ruskin to John James Ruskin, 27 February 1832 [RFL 267].</p>
                <p>Paul H. Walton speculates this change in approach signifies that Runciman "believed that he had encountered a boy who would one day bring lustre to his teacher's name through his success as a professional 
                    artist in the exhibitions of the Royal Academy," but that such ambitions were foiled by the elder Ruskins' plans of a more gentlemanly profession for their son, 
                    for which "advanced training in the techniques and materials of art" such as oils "would introduce an unnecessary and inappropriate degree of specialization" (9. 11). 
                    In due course, as Walton points out, Ruskin came to dislike oil painting, complaining in an 1835 rhymed letter to his father of its smell and messiness. Instead, 
                    "C. Fieldings tints alone for me," Ruskin declared, having begun his lessons with Copley Fielding in this year, the same year in which he appears to have ended 
                    his instruction with Runciman (John Ruskin to John James Ruskin, 11 March 1835 [RFL 312, and see 261 n 13, 314 n. 3]). If snobbery about an ungentlemanly dirtying 
                    of one's hands was a factor in Ruskin's rejection of Runciman's course of instruction, 
                    so was the time involved in "some fifty coats to be / Splashed on each spot successively" (RFL 312). From the start, however, even when Ruskin was still 
                    "patching together" his pictures, the quality that perhaps gained Runciman's attention was a Wordsworthian combining of memory and spontaneity. When constructing 
                    his first scene for Runciman, Ruskin was not entirely copying, because he "thought . . . [his] model resembled" his memory of "the cottage that we saw, 
                    as we went to Rhaidyr Dhu, near Maentwrog where the old woman lived whose grandson went with us to the fall, so very silently" (RFL 262); and the 
                    painting that he had in prospect to learn from Runciman seemed to Ruskin a "superior" art, because he would be able to "carry off Derwent Water &#x0026; Skiddaw 
                    in my pocket" (RFL 268). When graduating to Fielding's instruction, Ruskin was still looking to capture the ephemeral, "To sketch the scenes that pass me by" in 
                    the "lovely world" of "the heavens high" that remind him of other places, such as an illusory "heap of Alpine snow" over the Norwood hills (RFL311, 310_.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>