<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/E:/exercise.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Leoni</title>
                <title type="sub">etext generated from a transcription of a manuscript</title>
                <author><persName>John Ruskin</persName></author>
                <editor><persName>David Hanson</persName></editor>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>Louisiana Board of Regents</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>ERM version 1.0 encoded Oct. 2009</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>###########</idno>
                <date when="2010-01-14">January 29 2010</date>
                <distributor>The Early Ruskin Manuscripts Project</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>###INSERT COPYRIGHT STATEMENT###</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="influence">###Insert notation of poetic influences here###</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><!-- possibly change to <msDesc> tag-->
                    <author>John Ruskin</author>
                    <title>Leoni</title>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from original manuscript</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head>LEONI</head>
            <!-- Syd says front matter should only be used for acurately representing the manuscript being transcribed... 
                not to display a heading in the website.... If we want to do this Syd suggests letting Mike handle it on the programming end-->
        </front>
    V
    LEONI
    A LEGEND OF ITALY
    (1836)
    LEONI
    A LEGEND OF ITALY1
    
    The lord of Castel Alto is old and gray-headed; fourscore years have flitted silently over him, and the dream of his life is nigh to its awaking, and his ear is dull, and his eye is dim, and his heart is weary.
    The old man reclines on a couch in the hall of his ancestors, beside an open casement, and the balmy air that floats over the deep blue waters of the broad sea, passes softly through his thin hair, and his weary eye rests on the brightness of a lovely landscape; for the olive, and the orange, and the myrtle, are green by the shore of the still waters; and the city lies whitely beneath the glance of the sun, as he rides through the cloudless azure of the heaven; while the purple mountains clasp the ocean in their arms, and fade away into the horizon in long lines of misty blue. Alas! the springtime of nature is a mockery to the winter of age, and Amalfiero turns away in sadness. His vassals are waiting around him to do him pleasure; the minstrel is there with his harp, the maiden with her song; but no music is so sweet to the old man’s ear as the voice of his daughter Giulietta.
    Giulietta, when a babe, was a thing of smiles and loveliness, like a happy thought dancing over the mind. Giulietta, when a child, was like the orange blossom in the groves of Friuli, and gladness floated around her like the fragrance of
    1 [The second title was added by the editor of Friendship’s Offering; see below, p. 303.]
    289
    I.	T
    
    the flower. Giulietta, in her youth, was1 the fairest maiden of Italy,—she glanced among the myrtle bowers like the winged zephyr: the evening star, when it rises gleaming out of the sea into the darkness of the glorious night of Italy, is not so bright as the beam that flashed from her large eye through the night of her lovely eyelashes. Giulietta’s mind was love—all love—to each and every thing.
    Like music to the sadness of the soul, was Giulietta to the old age of her father. As she passed before him, a light came into the coldness of his eye; and his ear, when it was dead to other sound, awoke to the murmur of her gentle voice.2 As an angel watches over the last days of a saint upon the earth, when the tumult of the battle of his life is over, and sheds peace around his hours, and bids his days pass sweetly and holily, so Giulietta watched over Amalfiero like an influence of good, and was the sun of his thoughts, and the light of his rejoicing.
    Giulietta had a brother. Garcio d’Amalfiero was a man of a dark countenance, and the shadows of his evil passions passed over it, like clouds over the luridness of the stormy heaven, and his look withered those upon whom it fell, and his wrath, once excited, raged like a pestilence, and would not be appeased. He was loved by few, and had many enemies, none of whom he hated as he did the bandit Leoni, for him only he feared.3
    Leoni’s better nature had been borne down by the violence of his passions, and he became what he abhorred, and widely was the fear of his name spread; for he passed over the land like a meteor, and left desolation behind him in the palaces
    
    of the great and the powerful, but not in the hamlets of the poor.1
    Returning from a successful attack on the castle of a neighbouring baron, Leoni had been once tracked to the fastnesses of the Apennines by Garcio, with a chosen troop of his followers. The bandit gave him battle, and was, as usual, victorious; the followers of Garcio cowered back from his thunderbolt charge, and Garcio himself was struck from his horse by the sword of Leoni. It had been said of the bandit, that he had never deserted a friend, nor spared an enemy; but, as his sabre waved over the head of his prostrate foe, the beaver of Garcio’s helmet fell open; Leoni’s arm was arrested as if by the hand of an invisible being, a smile of scorn passed over his lip, and then a mildness came into his eye; he turned clamly away; and, to the astonishment of his followers, sounded a retreat in the very flush of victory, while Garcio and his disheartened and vanquished band were suffered to retire unmolested. From that time the hatred of Garcio to Leoni was inextinguishable. The shame of defeat and the thirst of revenge gnawed into his heart like vultures, for he had rather have been laid dead by the sword of Leoni, than have owed his life to the clemency of his conqueror.
    *	*	*	*	*2
    Giulietta sat in her chamber in the eastern tower of Castel
    1 [In the MS. this paragraph runs:—
    “There are spirits moving on the earth, which are not of a like order with their fellows, which will rise above the ordinary dust of mortality, whether it be in greatness of evil or of good; and it depends upon the accident of impulse, upon the treatment of their fellowmen, whether that greatness be a blessing or a curse; and such was Leoni, and he was what he abhorred. His noble nature had been borne down by the violence of his passions, but yet his name was pronounced with fear, not with scorn or contumely, and widely was the fear of that name spread; for he passed,” etc.]
    2 [Long passages in the MS. are here omitted both in Friendship’s Offering and in the privately printed edition. The passages consist of three scenes: (1) Between Giulietta and her father; (2) between Leoni and the bandits; (3) Leoni’s serenading of Giulietta. Ruskin’s criticisms upon the editor’s omission of these scenes are given in the letter printed at p. 302. The passages in the MS. are as follows:—
    (1)
    “Giulietta, Giulietta,” said the old man.
    And Giulietta came forth from among her maidens like the moon when it is bright among the pale stars, and she knelt down softly beside her parent,
    
    Alto. The evening star rose out of the sea, and climbed slowly up into the sky, and Giulietta’s dark eye rested sadly upon it. She was waiting for a voice that rose, every evening, from the myrtle grove below the castle, as the star disappeared behind
    
    and lifted up her large dark eyes full of love. And a blessing passed silently over the heart of her father, and descended upon her like the dew.
    “Giulietta,” said the old man, “there is a dark spirit upon me to-day, a shadow that is felt, a dread stillness of the mind like the fearful hush of the air before the desolation of the earthquake; a chill is upon my soul as if the hand of death was lying cold even upon my mind.”
    “Nay, my father,” said Giulietta, “thou art weary,” and she bent over him and kissed his cheek.
    “I am not weary when thou art beside me, Giulietta; this gloom that is brooding over my heart is not weakness or disease, it is a presentiment of evil which the invisible beings who are round us and in us, and who watch over our feelings and turn them to good or evil, have power to infuse into our souls as a warning. Such there are, Giulietta, I have spoken with them in my mind. I have felt their power ruling over my life. I have felt them busy about my heart-strings in joy or in sorrow.”
    “My father,” said Giulietta, “the evil spirits have no power over us without our own consent, and this midnight of the soul is not of the good.”
    “I know not,” returned the old man; “I have felt it once before: it was followed by the death of those whom I loved.”
    Giulietta looked up, and his countenance was exceeding pale, and there was a horror upon it of great fear.
    “My father, my father, you are ill,” said the maiden.
    “That sun will soon set, Giulietta, and to me, I believe, for ever,” said the old man; “but this is not death, nor the fear of death that sits so heavily on me. What is it to one like me to fall asleep from weariness of life? Why should I fear resting from trouble and turmoil and grief—why should gloom come over me from the dread of repose?”
    “What do you fear, my father?” said Giulietta.
    “I know not what I fear; but I fear for thee only, my daughter,” said the old man. “The only blow which can now reach my heart must be struck through thee. Leave me, Giulietta.”
    “Not thus, not thus,” said the maiden, for the countenance of her father grew still paler.
    “Yes, leave me. Thy presence but increases the horror that has bound me.”
    And the maiden kissed her father’s brow, and it was very cold, and his frame trembled strongly, and she left him and sought her chamber in sorrow.
    (2)
    The sun is low in the heaven, and the tall rocks on the sea shore are reddened with his rays, and the columns of the ruined temple on the summit throw their shadows lengthily along the sward. By a narrow path on the face of the grey rocks a band of warriors was defiling, man by man, and the warm rays glanced gaily on their crested helms. High was the brow and lofty the glance of their leader, and a pride sat upon his lip; for the countenance of Leoni was not as the countenance of other men, the emotions which passed over his heart like whirlwinds were not reflected in the stillness of his brow—none when they looked on Leoni could have known what thoughts were working in the deep secret places of his soul. Neither hope, nor fear, nor anger had ever been seen on his countenance, but the pride of spirit sat there ever, and when he spoke, even in the. . . . . . . (sic)
    One of his followers was beside him, privileged by superior age, one whom
    
    the peak of a distant mountain. Giulietta hardly knew how very sweet the voice was to her listening ear, for it was the voice of one who loved her with a more than common love. They had first met when Giulietta was young, very young,
    
    Leoni allowed to speak familiarly to him as a friend, and the old man’s tone was querulous and complaining.
    “So we are to wait here for you again half the night, are we? I love not these solitary rambles of yours, Leoni; what can you have to do alone at the Castle of——every evening?”
    “Trouble not yourself about that, Anselmo,” said Leoni.
    “But I do trouble myself,” returned Anselmo; “I love not to be left here sprawling on this damp grass every night, while you go pushing your head into the Lion’s mouth in this way. I can’t imagine what makes you keep lurking alone about that Castle of——, unless it be to let Garcio catch you, and then you would lose your head, and we our Captain.”
    “Fear not for me,” said Leoni; “my doom is not to die by his coward sword.”
    “I don’t know that, Leoni,” replied the old man. “That was another fool’s trick of yours—you should have known better, when he fell before you in the battle, than to think that he would ever have forgiven his defeat. Why did you let him live to plot revenge as a reward for your most wise clemency?”
    Leoni smiled in scorn.
    “I knew him then as I know him now,” he said, “let him plot against me as he will—think you that I care for his meanly devised revenge and impotent wrath? Garcio is to me as the wave that dashes its weak spray on the forehead of younder stern and unyielding crag.”
    “Nevertheless, Leoni, if he were to catch you near his castle without your followers, I fancy our next charge would be without a leader. You had better stay here out of his den or take us with you. I’ll follow you to the castle with the utmost possible pleasure, providing you don’t sound a retreat as you so prudently did once when we were about to give the rascals a lesson how they dared to attack the band of Leoni: you were possessed that day, Leoni—mad, quite mad. Some of them would have remembered it as long as their heads stood on their shoulders.”
    “You must not follow me,” said Leoni, “you must remain here this evening, at least—but keep your carbines loaded, and sleep not. I may have need of you this night.”
    “It’s high time, I know,” muttered Anselmo, “to have need of us; we might as well be fishermen or Lazzaroni at once as lie here like moon calves all night, not a blow to be struck nor a shot fired. Well, if he will go, he must, I suppose—he’ll be tired of this in time, or Garcio will teach him the imprudence of solitary contemplation.” And with a low, discontented kind of growl, Anselmo couched sulkily behind a fallen column, looked to the priming of his carbine, turned his sword belt round that the hilt might be near his hand, etc. . . . (sic). The rest of the band had soon disappeared into various places of concealment, and Leoni, leaping down lightly from the rocks, moved rapidly along the sea shore towards the Castle of——.
    (3)
    And a change came over his countenance, and it grew mild, and a gladness rested on it, and the haughtiness of his lip faded away.
    Giulietta sat in her chamber, in the eastern tower of the Castle of ——, and the evening was sinking down upon the shores of the deep sea—and the evening star rose up out of the deep and climbed slowly up into the darkening sky, and far through the deep blue air gleamed its melancholy
    
    and Francesco just verging into manhood. From that hour she was the light of his path, and the joy of his heart. Her father knew not of his child’s love for Francesco, who pleaded
    
    ray, and shone paly on the quivering countenance of the moving waters. And Giulietta’s large dark eye rested sadly on the star, and what were Giulietta’s thoughts? And now, fast waned the twilight away, and the glow of the sky that was shed o’er it by the departing sun became cold, and the shadow of the pervading starlight became visible on the chequered floor and carved walls of the chamber. And the night came glorious down upon the sea.
    And the star climbed higher and higher, and as it touched the summit of the mountain, the night breeze came balmily over the deep, and as it died away, the voice was heard singing below the castle. And Giulietta drew near the window and listened, and the sounds rose softly up upon the wings of the night wind, and the moon looked down and saw a blush pass over Giulietta’s lovely cheek—and thus the voice sang:—
    1
    “There was a tower within my heart,
    The tower was strong and high;
    But oh, its walls they fell before
    The glance of thy bright eye.
    A throne of love within the tower,
    A lofty throne, was seen,
    And there thou sittest on the throne,
    Indisputable queen.
    2
    Full high upon the Apennine
    Is set my mountain tower,
    And there with gems and marble fine
    I’ve decked a lady’s bower.
    The lady’s bower is fair to see,
    No lady’s there, I ween;
    Oh, maiden, wend away with me,
    And thou shalt be its queen.
    3
    And far among the mountains blue
    I have a trusty band;
    My band is bold, my band is true,
    They wait for my command.
    Their hands are strong, their hearts are free,
    Their swords are bright and keen;
    Oh, maiden, wend away with me,
    And thou shalt be their queen.”
    
    And the voice died away, and the tones passed drearily into the stillness of the night.
    At the end of the MS. there is a revised version of the omitted scene, numbered (3) above. This version reads as follows:—
    And where were Giulietta’s thoughts? She was waiting for a voice that rose every evening as the star disappeared behind the summit of a distant peaked mountain from the myrtle grove beneath the castle. Giulietta hardly knew how very sweet the voice was to her ear, for it was the voice of one who loved her with a more than common love—even with a love like to that of a spirit. They had first met when Giulietta was young, very young, and
    
    to Giulietta some ancient feud of their families, as an excuse for maintaining his secrecy.
    When the star touched the misty summit of the mountain, and Giulietta drew near to the window, a blush passed over her fair cheek as a minstrel’s song floated upon the breeze:—
    
    “Full broad and bright is the silver light
    Of moon and stars, on flood and fell;
    But in my breast is starless night,
    For I am come to say farewell.
    How glad, how swift was wont to be
    The step that bore me back to thee;
    Now coldly comes upon my heart
    The meeting that is but to part.
    
    I do not ask a tear, but while
    I linger where I must not stay,
    O, give me but a parting smile,
    To light me on my lonely way.
    To shine, a brilliant beacon star,
    To my reverted glance, afar,
    Through midnight, which can have no morrow
    O’er the deep, silent, surge of sorrow.”1
    
    Francesco a youth just verging into manhood. From that hour she had been like a halo of glory in the life of Francesco. Giulietta knew it—she could not help loving him whose thoughts, whose hopes, whose being were centred in her only.
    The thought of her came over his soul like the morning on dark mountains, when absent from her. Francesco had two lives, and one was cold and dead and dark and cheerless, but the other was the dreamy life of the mind, beautiful exceedingly, full of light and loveliness, for the vision of her was there. . . . . . .  (sic).
    Her father knew not of the love of his child. Francesco had seen her only for moments, by stealth, pleading to Giulietta some ancient feud of their families as an excuse for maintaining his love in secret. Several times in the masque or the dance at the Castle of——a knight had mingled of more graceful form and noble bearing: none knew him, unless there was recognition in the brightness of Giulietta’s eye. Several times, when she had gone forth with her father and a retinue of fifty knights, the ranks had been thrown into confusion as if by a supernumerary individual. Giulietta only knew how. Several times when the minstrels were singing in the hall had one come forward of haughtier glance and loftier brow, and all bent forward to listen to his lay of love, charming all ears, intended only for one.
    Here is a blank of half a page. Then on the next page:—
    The song ceased for a moment; then again the perfumed night breeze became vocal; but now the sounds were low and sad, and fell melancholy on Giulietta’s ear:—
    “Now broad and brilliant,” etc.]
    1 [In the MS. the first line reads, “Now broad and brilliant lies the light,” and a third stanza is added:—
    “An ardent fire within me burns,
    And though my heart consumed may be,
    There is a Phænix in its ashes;
    Oh, how I love the love of thee!
    
    Giulietta opened a secret door, and descended, and Francesco saw her come forth in her beauty.1
    “What meant thy song to-night, Francesco?” said the maiden.
    “What can a farewell to thee mean, Giulietta, but misery?”2
    “Nay, this is madness, Francesco,” replied the maiden; “wherefore must we part?”
    “Thou sayest well, Giulietta, we will not part,—fly with me,—night is on the mountains, my band is near. Ere the dawn we shall be far hence, in safety, in honour, and—if thou wilt, in power.”
    “Thy band!” repeated Giulietta; “fly with thee! With whom? What meanest thou? What art thou, Francesco?”
    “I know not, maiden!” said Francesco. “I have not been what I seem to be, yet thou couldst make me so. With thee,
    
    Although my hope and joy be chill,
    That constant flame will flicker still;
    And round my broken heart will play
    With mocking melancholy grey.”
    
    The first two stanzas, as given in Friendship’s Offering, were included in the privately printed Poems of 1850 (p. 45), and in the edition of 1891.]
    1 [In the MS.: “come forth into the night in her beauty robed as in a robe of light.”]
    2 [The MS. at this point inserts the following further dialogue, the omission of which by the editor was challenged by the author (see p. 304):—
    “And why farewell?” said Giulietta, and she looked enquiringly at her lover, and there was agony passing over his countenance, and the damp, death-like dew hung upon his forehead.
    “Why farewell,” he repeated, “ay, why farewell between thee and me? It cannot, shall not be.”
    “Why this agony, Francesco? Whither wouldest thou go?” said Giulietta.
    “Ask the withered leaf that is quivering from its bough and drifted at the will of the winter wind; ask the meteor that is hurled irregularly down among the stars; ask the spray of the ocean when the tempest whirls it along the shore, where they would go; for withered as the autumn leaf, and vain as the ocean spray, and desolating and feared as the influences of the fires of the night, shall I be, Giulietta, when parted from thee.”
    “This is madness, Francesco,” replied the maiden. “Wherefore must we part, or if we must, how canst thou, noble and true as I have known thee, become the thing thou hast described?”
    “Thou knowest me not, Giulietta—I am not noble; I am not true.”
    “Mock me not, Francesco,” said the maiden.
    “I could be, I will be, Giulietta, we will not part; fly with me, the night is down on the mountains, my band is near, ere the day dawns we shall be far hence in safety—in honour, ay, if thou wilt, in power.”
    “Thy band,” repeated Giulietta; “fly with thee; with whom?” etc.]
    
    I am Francesco; without thee, I am a pestilence, a scourge,—in a word,1 without thee, I am—Leoni.”
    And the name struck through to the maiden’s heart with a coldness as of death; the cry she would have uttered died upon her lips, and she fainted in the arms of her lover.2
    A hectic flush passed over her cheek, and she woke from the partial death with a deep gasp as of one in pain, and her dark eye was filled with a vague horror. “Francesco, Francesco!” she said, “thou toldest me something,—it was terrible, —tell it me again. Francesco!—thou art not Francesco,” and she paused for a moment. “I know now,” she said; “I remember well, very well, Francesco is dead, and thou—thou art not, thou canst not, thou shalt not be Leoni,—the bandit Leoni,—my brother’s enemy. O Francesco! say thou mockest me!”
    “I was once Leoni,” he replied;—“they brother’s enemy never, or Garcio had not now lived. Could I be the enemy of your brother, Giulietta!”3
    And Giulietta felt that it was Francesco and not Leoni who spoke, and she paused in deep agony.
    *	*	*	*	*
    Great was the tumult at Castel Alto. An old fisherman of Pozzuolo had informed Garcio that he had seen two figures
    1 [The MS. reads: “without thee, I am a walking misery, the curse of others, an embodied fear of reckless madness, the pestilence, the scourge, the deeper curse of my own heart, in one word . . .”]
    2 [The MS. here inserts a passage the omission of which was regretted by the author (see p. 304):—
    “Oh, how beautiful was the fear upon Giulietta’s face, as she lay in the lifeless sleep—pale as the snow that lies beneath the moon upon the high Apennine, and the terror on her countenance was as the terror of troublous slumber. Then the hectic . . .”]
    3 [The MS. here continues:—
    “He is thine,” she replied; “oh fly, fly for thy life, Leoni. I love thee yet; Garcio will find thee, will kill thee; my brother will kill thee, Francesco.”
    “Let him,” said Leoni bitterly; “fly without thee, Giulietta, I will not, I could not. Die! how I could thank death for the blow, if it were not that beyond the grave I know not if there might not be forgetfulness, forgetfulness of thee, Giulietta.”—He paused.—“That were worse than life without thee—but death could not do that; no, no, my spirit would be with thee, Giulietta, upon earth; the evening breeze that fanned thy cheek should be Leoni; the nightingale should sing in the orange grove, and Leoni should bear the sound to thy ear; the fragrance of the wild rose should be brought thee by Leoni—the wreath of the morning mist, the light of the noonday sun, the beam of the
    
    passing down westward on the sea-shore, at the foot of the castle. One was a maiden of exceeding beauty, the countenance of the other, he said, was one which he knew well, and which, once seen, was not easily forgotten,—that of the bandit Leoni. Then Garcio was wild with rage, and he called his followers together, and the clash of arms was loud in the hall, and then, from the gate of Castel Alto issued a troop of warriors, and their mail shone cold in the starlight, and Garcio spurred on his bloody war-horse in the van. His countenance was pale with wrath, and he dashed madly forward along the winding shore.
    But one of the maidens of Giulietta, when she heard the peasant’s1 tale, went and sought for her in her father’s hall, and she was not there; and in her chamber, and she was not there; and she descended by the secret staircase, and she saw footsteps in the dew on the grassy ground. Then she returned weeping, and came to Amalfiero, and told him that Leoni the bandit had carried away Giulietta. And the old man was very feeble, and he bowed his head gently upon his breast and died.
    *	*	*	*	*2
    “Heardest thou nothing?” Giulietta said to Leoni.
    “Nothing, Giulietta,” he replied. “Nay, now that I listen,
    
    evening star should all be full of Leoni, and who should separate thee from these. Would not this be happiness, Giulietta? O Giulietta, either fly with me this night, or I will remain here and the sword of Garcio shall unite me with thee for ever. Who shall slay an invisible? Who shall part thee from the air?”
    Great was the tumult in the Castle of——. An old peasant had come to Garcio saying that he had seen . . .]
    1 [So in the MS. It should have been altered to “fisherman’s.”]
    2 [The MS. here inserts:—
    “And the spirit went forth with a complaining, and passed moaning on the night wind in search of those whom it loved. And it went fast like a wreath of sea mist along the shore and came and hovered over the head of Giulietta, as she fled with Leoni, and as the spirit came near unto [her] she remembered her father, and how he had said that the sun would not rise to him. And she stopped in great misery, exclaiming, ‘Oh, my father, my father, surely I have murdered thee, my father! ’ Then she heard through her weeping the noise of a soft sigh beside her, and she started and looked round: it was not like the voice of the wind among the laurel leaves, neither like the murmur of the little waves upon the shore. ‘Heardest thou nothing? ’ she said to Leoni.”]
    
    methinks I hear a sound, far away, like the tramp of steeds along the sand.” And Giulietta listened, and she was filled with great fear.
    “Oh! fly, Leoni!” she said; “it is Garcio! Fly, and leave me here!” But Leoni raised her in his arms, and bare her softly forward.1
    And now the rocks were seen rising high from the sea-shore, with the columns of a ruined temple upon their summit, and Leoni knew that his band was near.
    “On, on, Giulietta!” he exclaimed; “one effort more, and we are safe.” And now the tramp of the galloping horses came nearer and nearer, and the voices of the men were heard urging them on. Louder and louder became the sound, and Giulietta made one last struggle forward, and having gained the rocks, the lovers stood beneath the ruins.2
    “Anselmo! Anselmo!” cried Leoni; and he was answered by a shout from the rocks, and the banditti leaped from their concealment; but ere they gained the shore, the foremost horseman of the opposite troop dashed into view. It was Garcio. A shout of triumph burst from his lips when he saw Leoni. Giulietta saw him level his carbine, and with a shriek of agony she threw herself before Leoni, and fell dead into his arms.3
    The band of Leoni heard the shot, and were around him in an instant: and lo! their leader was standing inactive beside the body of a maiden.4 There was a stillness in his eye, and on his features; but it was as the stillness of the volcano before it bursts forth into desolation. His troops stood round him in a fearful silence, and there was a pause, until, like a whirlwind over the quietness of deep waters, came the madness
    
    upon the soul of Leoni. He looked up, and saw that his band was beside him.
    “Stand by me this night,” he said, “and revenge the loss of your leader.” Then he shouted his war-cry, and the banditti swelled the sound with eager voices. The followers of Garcio replied, and Leoni dashed at them like a thunderbolt. Then loudly into the quietness of the heaven rose the roar of the battle, and the echoes rolled heavily over the sea.1
    Leoni burst his path through the mass of battle, and his bloodshot eye was on the crest of Garcio,2 and, whether it were foe or friend whom he met in his frenzy, he dashed the combatants aside, and clove his way to that one plume. With the implacable wrath of an avenging spirit3 Leoni sought his single foe. The followers of Garcio shrunk from his glance, and, as he broke through the front of their battle, some turned and fled, and the rest hung back in disorder and dismay.4
    Then Garcio saw Leoni come upon him with the swoop of an eagle, and his eye quailed before the despair of his foe.
    “Wretch,” cried Leoni, “lovest thou life?—Oh, would that I could make life to thee, what thou hast made it to me, and thou shouldst live! I spared thee once, for her sake,—thou
    
    hast well rewarded me!—thy sister strikes thee, Garcio.” And he smote him dead.
    And the voice of battle drifted away towards Castel Alto, and the shouts of the victorious banditti were heard echoing along the cliffs. But Leoni was no longer at their head;—in their victory they were without a leader,—they remembered that he had commanded them to revenge his loss, and few, very few, of the followers of Garcio escaped the slaughter of that night. The banditti met1 and sought for Leoni among the dead, and they found the body of Garcio, and the sword of their leader lying beside it; but him they found not. And they retired silently, under cover of the night, to their fastness among the mountains.
    Oh, calmly, brightly, beautifully rose the morning out of the eastern sea, and widely spread the rosy dawn over the deep! Gloriously the radiance stole up into the high heaven, where the white clouds waved their light wings in the deepness of the infinite blue, and looked out eastward, rejoicing, as they met the morning breeze that sprung upward from its repose in the grove of silver olives.2 And the sun lifted his head majestically out of the sea, and the mists passed away before his glance, from its surface, and the waves rolled onward, singing, with sweet low voices, and a long golden path was thrown upon them, even unto the shore.3
    Oh, the radiance of that morning was unconscious of the desolation of the night! There was no sadness in the dawn that shone on the ruins of Castel Alto. The surges that, in the night, had dashed away the blood from the shore, now broke clear and white on the unstained pebbles.4 A figure
    
    was leaning against a rock on the strand.1 Few, very few, could have recognized in the haggard face and withered form the once haughty and fiery Leoni. The fishermen of Pozzuolo affirm that, for years after that terrible night, the same figure was seen pacing the shore, with the unequal step, and wild gestures of a maniac.2
    
    A LETTER ON LEONI
    
    The following letter, referring to alterations made in Leoni, was written by Ruskin to W. H. Harrison, the editor of Friendship’s Offering:—
    Herne Hill, 30th June 1836.
    My dear Sir,—I have great pleasure in receiving your kind note, with enclosed proofs, which I have looked over and compared with the manuscript with great care, and am much gratified to observe that if there has been considerable curtailing, there has been no alteration, and that all that is, is mine. I have known some little poems come back to me with such a “change come o’er the spirit of their dream” that I had great difficulty in recognizing my old acquaintances till I had perused the letter of introduction. In the present case I am happy to perceive no change in my friends’ countenance, even though he may have grown a little shorter—I will not say the wrong way—on the contrary, I feel that the greatest part of the exits are very beneficial, and that all the verbal alterations are great improvements. Will you, however, excuse me, if I venture, with all diffidence, to intercede for one or two bits. I do not allege, in their defence, that they cost me some trouble to compose—that is no proof that they were worth it; neither that I myself like them, because everybody is a bad judge of what he has himself written; but I think that they form links of connexion, the absence of which would be missed. I will mention them, and the reasons which occur to me for retaining them, and if you still think their room preferable to their company, I, having all confidence in your judgment and experience, shall know that it is so. The scene between Leoni and his bandits3 is certainly not necessary, and I feel its change of style to be an interruption: its exit, therefore, is desirable; but then in the end of the piece, the definite articles, the rocks, the ruined temple, must be got rid of, and Leoni must not call for a person whom nobody knows
    1 [The MS. adds:—
    “and wan and haggard was its countenance, as if it had been withered away by the devouring fire that flickered madly in the eye.”]
    2 [The MS. adds a “wind up,” the omission of which was regretted by the author (see p. 304):—
    “Wandering among the rocks upon the shore, with sleepless eye and weary limbs, and walking among the crags as if seeking something, he knew not what, with the restlessness of madness, passing hither and thither at all times, whether the night winds were singing sadly, or the stars gleaming tearfully, or the moon breaking lightly, or the sun setting silently over the resting-place place of the Bandit’s bride.”]
    3 [The scene numbered (2) on p. 292, above.]
    
    was leaning against a rock on the strand.1 Few, very few, could have recognized in the haggard face and withered form the once haughty and fiery Leoni. The fishermen of Pozzuolo affirm that, for years after that terrible night, the same figure was seen pacing the shore, with the unequal step, and wild gestures of a maniac.2
    
    A LETTER ON LEONI
    
    The following letter, referring to alterations made in Leoni, was written by Ruskin to W. H. Harrison, the editor of Friendship’s Offering:—
    Herne Hill, 30th June 1836.
    My dear Sir,—I have great pleasure in receiving your kind note, with enclosed proofs, which I have looked over and compared with the manuscript with great care, and am much gratified to observe that if there has been considerable curtailing, there has been no alteration, and that all that is, is mine. I have known some little poems come back to me with such a “change come o’er the spirit of their dream” that I had great difficulty in recognizing my old acquaintances till I had perused the letter of introduction. In the present case I am happy to perceive no change in my friends’ countenance, even though he may have grown a little shorter—I will not say the wrong way—on the contrary, I feel that the greatest part of the exits are very beneficial, and that all the verbal alterations are great improvements. Will you, however, excuse me, if I venture, with all diffidence, to intercede for one or two bits. I do not allege, in their defence, that they cost me some trouble to compose—that is no proof that they were worth it; neither that I myself like them, because everybody is a bad judge of what he has himself written; but I think that they form links of connexion, the absence of which would be missed. I will mention them, and the reasons which occur to me for retaining them, and if you still think their room preferable to their company, I, having all confidence in your judgment and experience, shall know that it is so. The scene between Leoni and his bandits3 is certainly not necessary, and I feel its change of style to be an interruption: its exit, therefore, is desirable; but then in the end of the piece, the definite articles, the rocks, the ruined temple, must be got rid of, and Leoni must not call for a person whom nobody knows
    1 [The MS. adds:—
    “and wan and haggard was its countenance, as if it had been withered away by the devouring fire that flickered madly in the eye.”]
    2 [The MS. adds a “wind up,” the omission of which was regretted by the author (see p. 304):—
    “Wandering among the rocks upon the shore, with sleepless eye and weary limbs, and walking among the crags as if seeking something, he knew not what, with the restlessness of madness, passing hither and thither at all times, whether the night winds were singing sadly, or the stars gleaming tearfully, or the moon breaking lightly, or the sun setting silently over the resting-place place of the Bandit’s bride.”]
    3 [The scene numbered (2) on p. 292, above.]
    
    anything about; and as the introduction of Leoni (his better nature had been borne down by the—etc., page 31) sounds incomplete, and looks rather short in print, might it not be improved by the addition of the description of him in the omitted scene, beginning, “His countenance was not as the countenance of other men,” etc.2
    But with regard to the other omitted scene,3 unless we have only set Mr. Amalfiero at the window in his easy-chair, that he may take a digestive nap after dinner, I think we might as well let him speechify a little to his daughter, more especially as the old fellow’s feelings are a very good preparation to the reader for coming horrors; and if they appear rather supernatural, the excellent addition to the title, an Italian legend, may, I think, very well excuse a little Italian superstition. I will also confess to you that I think the young lady’s behaviour rather graceful, kneeling down, kissing, etc., etc., etc., and her father’s speeches, though there is a good deal of nonsense in them, appear to me, nevertheless, somewhat sublime; in fact, the scene was a favourite, and cost me much pains, and I feel, on missing it, a good deal as the clown in the pantomime may be supposed to feel, when the delicious morsel he is about to taste is whisked out of his hand, up to the ceiling; or like the child whose bubble has burst; or like the old lady who, going down into her cellar for a bottle of cider, discovered her exploded bottles had, like the baseless fabric of a vision, left but a rack behind.
    En passant, allow me to say that I do not quite see the reason for the cutting out what I fancied was a tol lol bit of Italian description, after the asterisks—page 4—only to end the sentence with the little, short, unmeaning word “it.” This, however, is not of the least consequence.4
    But I think the only thing a bandit can do to ingratiate himself with a lady is to be desperately over head and ears in love. I have therefore spouted some nonsense about morning on dark mountains, and likened the rascal to a cat, in giving him a more than ordinary number of lives, i.e. two. “Joy of his heart” is rather a commonplace expression, and suggests the idea of the fellow’s being only reasonably in love; which wouldn’t do; he ought to be as mad as a March hare. I do not quite perceive the reason for dismissing this bit, or even that which follows,5 and for this reason—it seems to me quite as dangerous to make a lady much in love as a gentleman little. Now, as Miss G., in this very scene, elopes with her blackguard of a lover without requiring much persuasion, it is necessary to show some reason for her being so violently in love with him, besides the palpable one of its being the very thing she ought not to have been. Now, the bo-peep sort of a way in which they have enjoyed each other’s society, and which, as I thought, I had very neatly described in this paragraph, is just the thing to occasion such a result.
    The first person is not required, and therefore better out.
    But in the next scene Mr. Leoni ought to be very eloquent. He has a ticklish affair on his hands: first, to inform the young lady that he is a confounded knave; and second, to persuade her to run away with him.
    1 [P. 290, last line but four, here.]
    2 [See beginning of omitted scene numbered (2) on p. 292, above.]
    3 [The scene numbered (1) on p. 291, above.]
    4 [The sentence on p. 292, line 2, here. The “tol lol bit of Italian description” is at the beginning of the omitted scene numbered (3) on p. 293.]
    5 [This refers to the omitted scene numbered (3) on pp. 293–294, above.]
    
    
    
    The first must have been disagreeable, and the second ought to have been difficult.
    If, in addition to this, he be properly in love, he cannot talk too great a quantity of nonsense, or come over her with too much gammon. Why, therefore, eject his speech about meteors and leaves, etc.,1 which indeed is required to account for Miss G.’s charging him with being mad; you know, she would not have done that only because he said it would be misery to part from her. Again, I think the bits2 about “how beautiful was the fear,” and the comparison about hands and clouds and moon and brows, are picturesque, and serve to keep up the readers’ estimation of the lady’s charms. With regard to the wandering of the spirit of the old buck after death,3 out it very properly goes, because I say positively “it did,” which is a bounce; but permit me to intercede for Leoni’s speech of the same kind.4 We are to suppose that the young lady manifests some reluctance to take a step so shocking, improper, romantic, undutiful, and indecorous as an elopement, particularly with a person of so suspicious a character. He therefore, besides flattering her with the promise of eternal affection (a likely and common thing on the part of a lover, and liable to no animadversion), frightened her out of her wits with this dexterously introduced bit of ghostification, for no lady would particularly relish the idea of being so assiduously attended by a ghost, even of a lover. And, besides, she could not tell but the ghost of a bandit might be accompanied by other ghosts not at all so agreeable, or even respectable. Therefore I think this speech alone a very sufficient excuse to the reader for the young lady’s conduct, and, allow me to say, a very necessary one.
    I thought my wind up jingled in prettily, but that does not signify.
    On looking over this letter, it puts me in mind of the landlord in Sterne, whose “Tout ce que vous voulez”—dwindled down into a solitary chop, to be pulled out of the mouth of the house dog, i.e. me. Thus, I find my “Tout ce que vous voulez,” with regard to curtailing, has been reduced to two scenes,5 but I hope you will believe me when I tell you, that, even if you were to cut out all these passages, I should believe, though I might not feel, that the piece was improved by it.—I remain, my dear sir, yours respectfully,
    J. RUSKIN.
    
    
</TEI>
