<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/E:/exercise.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Leoni</title>
                <title type="sub">etext generated from a transcription of a manuscript</title>
                <author><persName>John Ruskin</persName></author>
                <editor><persName>David Hanson</persName></editor>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>Louisiana Board of Regents</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>ERM version 1.0 encoded Oct. 2009</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>###########</idno>
                <date when="2010-01-14">January 29 2010</date>
                <distributor>The Early Ruskin Manuscripts Project</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>###INSERT COPYRIGHT STATEMENT###</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="influence">###Insert notation of poetic influences here###</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><!-- possibly change to <msDesc> tag-->
                    <author>John Ruskin</author>
                    <title>Leoni</title>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from original manuscript</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head>LEONI</head>
            <!-- Syd says front matter should only be used for acurately representing the manuscript being transcribed... 
                not to display a heading in the website.... If we want to do this Syd suggests letting Mike handle it on the programming end-->
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="prose" subtype="tale">
                <!-- Simple Prose -->
                
                <head>
                    Leoni: A Legend of Italy<ptr target="targetneeded"/>
                </head>

                <p>
                    The Lord of the castle of<ptr target="targetneeded"/>
                    <gap><desc>castle's name</desc></gap> is old, and grey headed 
                    Fourscore years have <add place="supralinear"><del>past</del>flitted</add> over him, 
                    <add place="supralinear">silently and anawares</add> and the dream of life is nigh to its awaking,
                    and his ear is dull, and his eye is dim, and his heart is weary.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The old man reclines on a couch in the hall of his ancestors. <del>and</del>
                    beside an open casement, and the balmy air that <del>dri</del> floats over the
                    deep blue waters of the broad sea passes softly over his gleaming hair; and his
                    weary eye rests on the brightness of an exceeding lovely landscape for the olive
                    and the orange and the myrtle are green by the shore of the still waters, and
                    the city gleams whitely beneath the glance of the sun as he rides through the
                    cloudless azure of the <del><unclear reason="crossout"/></del> heaven, and the
                    purple mountains clasp the ocean in their arms, and fade away into the horizon
                    in long lines of misty blue.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Alas, the spring time of nature is a mockery to the winter of <del>old</del> age,
                    and the old man turns away in sadness <del>He is begirt by</del> His vassals are
                    waiting around him to do his pleasure, the minstrel is there with his harp. the
                    maiden with her song, but no music is so sweet to the old mans ear as the voice
                    of his daughter <persName>Giulietta</persName>. <persName>Giulietta</persName> ,
                    when a babe, was a thing of smiles and loveliness like a happy thought dancing
                    over the mind------ <persName>Giulietta</persName>, when a child, was like the
                    orange blossom in the groves of <placeName>Friuli</placeName>, and gladness
                    floated around her like the fragrance of the flower.
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName> in her youth is the fairest maiden of
                    <placeName>Italy</placeName>, she glance<add><del>d</del>s</add> among the
                    myrtle bowers like the <add place="supralinear"><del>wayward</del>winged</add>
                    zephyr, the evening star when it <del>trembles over</del> rises gleaming out of
                    the sea into the darkness of the glorious night of <placeName>Italy</placeName>
                    is not so bright as the <del>lig</del> beam that flashes from her large eye
                    through the night of her lovely eye lashes.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Like music to the sadness of the soul, so was <persName>Giulietta</persName> to
                    the old age of her Father, as she passed before him a light came into the
                    coldness of his eye, and his ear when it was dead to other sound, awoke to the
                    murmur of her gentle voice. (<persName>Giuliettas</persName> mind was love, all
                    love continual love to each and every thing, the birds knew
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName>, (the nightingale sang at her chamber window
                    his song to the stars,) <del>and</del> (as she walked among the flowers they
                    fluttered beside her. and stooped their glossy necks to her hand) nay, the
                    flowers seemed to know <persName>Giulietta</persName> and to be gladdened into
                    brightness as she past, and <persName>Giulietta</persName> loved them all.)
                    <del>To her father</del> --as an angel watches over the last days of a saint
                    upon the earth, when the tumult of the battle of his life is oer, and sheds
                    peace around his hours and bids his days pass sweetly and holily, so Giulietta
                    watched over the old man like an influence of good and was the sun of his
                    thoughts, and the light of his rejoicing.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Giulietta had a brother; <persName>Garcio<ptr target="targetneeded"/></persName>
                    <gap/>
                    was a man of a dark countenances
                    and the shadows of his evil passions past over it like clouds over the luridness
                    of the stormy heaven; and his look withered those upon whom it fell, and his
                    wrath once excited raged like a pestilence, and would not be appeased, he was
                    feared by all, hated by many, loved by few, but <del>his arm was restless in the
                    battle, and his fame was bright amoung the proud names of the warriors of
                    Italy</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Among his many enemies. <persName>Garcio</persName> hated none as he did the
                    bandit <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, for him only he feared;
                </p>
                <p>
                    There are spirits moving on the earth, which are not of a like order with their
                    fellows, which will rise above the ordinary dust of mortality, whether it be in
                    greatness of evil, or of good, and it depends upon the accident of impulse, upon
                    the treatment of their fellow men, whether their greatness 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>is</del>be</add> a blessing or a curse. and such
                    was <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, 
                    (&amp; <unclear/> was what he abhorred,)
                    <del>for</del> (his noble nature had been borne down by the violence of his
                    passions), <add place="supralinear">but yet</add> his name was pronounced with
                    fear, <del>but</del> not with scorn or contumely, and widely was the fear of
                    that name spread. for he passed over the land like a meteor and left desolation
                    behind him in the halls of the great and the poweful, but not in the hamlets of
                    the poor.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Returning from a successful attack on the castle of a neighbouring baron,
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> had been once tracked to the fastnesses of the
                    <placeName>Apennines</placeName> by <persName>Garcio</persName>, with a
                    chosen troop of his followers. the bandit gave him battle, and was as usual
                    victorious, the followers of <persName>Garcio</persName> cowered back from 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>the charge of the bandit</del>his thunderbolt
                    charge</add><del>Garcio</del><del>and he</del>
                    <add place="sublinear">and</add><restore>Garcio</restore> himself was struck from his horse by the
                    sword of <del>of their leader</del><persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> 
                    It had been said of <persName ref="Francesco">Leoni</persName> 
                    that he had never <del>spared</del> deserted a
                    friend, or spared an enemy. but suddenly as his sword waved over the head of his
                    prostrate foe, <add place="supralinear">the beaver of
                    <persName>Garcios</persName> helmet fell open</add> his arm was checked
                    as if by the hand of an invisible being* and to the astonishment of his
                    followers, <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> sounded a retreat in the very flush of
                    victory and <del>the</del><persName>Garcio</persName> and his <del>band w</del>
                    disheartened and vanquished band were suffered to retire unmolested.
                </p>
                <addSpan spanTo="addEnd01"/>
                <p>
                    *a smile of scorn passed over his lip, and then a mildness came into the flash of
                    his eye, a mildness <add place="supralinear"><del>never</del>never before</add>
                    seen on the features of <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>; 
                    he turned calmly away, and to the astonishment &amp;c
                </p>
                <anchor xml:id="addEnd01"/>
                <p>
                    From that time the hatred of <persName>Garcio</persName> to
                    <persName ref="Francesco">Leoni</persName> was as a consuming fire, and the shame of defeat
                    and the thirst of revenge gnawed into his heart like vultures--he had rather
                    have been laid dead by the sword of <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> than suffered to
                    live a monument of the clemency of <del>t</del>his bandit conqueror
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Lord of Castle Alto">Giulietta. Giulietta.</said> said the old man
                </p>
                <p>
                    And <persName>Giulietta</persName> came forth from among her maidens like the
                    when it is bright among the pale stars and she knelt down 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>silently</del>softly</add> beside<del>s</del> her
                    parent, and lifted up her large eyes full of love. And a blessing past silently
                    over the heart of her father <del>in</del> and descended upon her like the dew
                    <del>of C<unclear/></del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Lord of Castle Alto"><persName>Giulietta</persName></said> , said the
                    old man, <said who="Lord of Castle Alto"> there is a dark spirit upon me to day,
                    a shadow <add place="supralinear">that</add> is felt, a dread stillness of
                    the mind like the fearful hush of the air before the desolation of the
                    earthquake, a chill is upon my soul as if the hand of death was or were
                    lying cold even upon my mind</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">Nay, my father</said>, said <persName>Giulietta</persName>,
                    <said who="Guilietta">thou art weary, and she bent over him and kissed his
                    cheek</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Lord of Castle Alto">I am not weary when thou art beside me
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName>, this gloom that sits brooding over my
                    heart is not weakness or disease, it is a presentiment of evil which the
                    invisible beings who are round us <del>in the air</del> and in us, and who
                    watch over our feelings and turn them to good or to evil, have power to
                    infuse into our souls as a warning--Such there are,
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName>, I have spoken with them 
                    <add place="supralinear">in</add> my mind. I have felt their power ruling
                    over my life. I have felt them busy about my heartstrings in Joy or in
                    sorrow--</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">My father,</said> said Giulietta, <said who="Giulietta">the
                    evil spirits have no power over us without our own consent, and this
                    midnight of the soul is not of the good.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Lord of Castle Alto">I know not</said>, returned the old man, <said
                    who="Lord of Castle Alto">I have felt it once before it was followed by the
                    death of those whom I loved.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName> looked up, and <add place="supralinear"><del>her
                    fathers</del>his</add> countenance was exceeding pale, and there was a
                    horror upon it of great fear.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">My Father, my Father, <del>said Giulietta speak not
                    so</del> you are ill</said> said <del>Giulietta</del>the maiden
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Lord of Castle Alto"><del>No, Giulietta</del>
                    <del>I believe I shall not see that sun 
                    <unclear reason="crossout">set</unclear></del>
                    <add place="supralinear">That sun will soon set I believe
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName>, and to me I believe</add></said>
                    said the old man, <said who="Lord of Castle Alto">but this is not 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>the</del> for ever</add> death, nor the fear of
                    death, that sits so heavily on me. What is it to one like me to fall asleep
                    from weariness of life--why should I fear resting from trouble and
                    <del>grief</del>turmoil and grief, why should a gloom come over me from
                    the dread of repose.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">What do you fear, my father</said>, said Giulietta
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Lord of Castle Alto"><add place="supralinear">I know not what I fear
                    but</add> I fear for thee only, my daughter</said>, said the old man,
                    <said who="Lord of Castle Alto">the only blow which can now reach my old
                    heart, must be struck through thee. Leave
                    me--<persName>Giulietta</persName>.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">Not thus, not thus</said>. said the maiden, for the
                    countenance of her father grew still paler.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Lord of Castle Alto">Yes--Ieave me, thy presence but increases this
                    horror that has bound me--<del>farewell</del></said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    And the maiden kissed her fathers brow. and it was very cold. and his frame
                    trembled strongly. and she left him, and sought her chamber in sorrow.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The sun is low in the heaven, and the tall rocks on the sea shore are reddened
                    with his rays, and the columns of the ruined temple on their summit throw their
                    shadows lengthily along the<del>ir</del> sward By a narrow path on the face of
                    the grey rocks a band of warriors was defiling man by man, and the warm rays
                    glanced gaily on their crested helms. High was the brow and lofty the glance of
                    their leader. and a pride sat upon his lip; <del>sus</del> for the countenance
                    of <persName>Leoni</persName> was not as the countenance of other men, the
                    emotions which passed over his heart like whirlwinds, <del>mo</del> were not
                    reflected in the stillness of his brow none when they looked upon
                    <persName>Leoni</persName> could have known what thoughts were <del>passing
                    over</del> working in the deep secret places of his soul. Neither hope, nor
                    fear, nor anger had ever been seen on his countenance, <del>and when</del> but
                    the pride of spirit sat there ever, <s rend="underline"> and when he spoke, even
                    in the</s>
                </p>
                <p>
                    One of his followers was beside him, privileged by superior age, one whom
                    <persName>Leoni</persName>
                    <del>had</del> allowed to speak familiarly to him and as a friend. and the old
                    mans tone was querulous and complaining.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Anselmo">Lo, we are to wait here for you again half the night
                    <del>we</del> are we. I love not these solitary rambles of yours,
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, what can <add place="supralinear">you</add>
                    have to do <add place="supralinear">alone</add> at the castle of <gap>
                    <desc>castle's name</desc></gap> every evening;</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Leoni">Trouble not yourself about 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>me</del>that</add>, <persName>Anselmo</persName></said>, 
                    said  <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName><del>, kindly</del>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Anselmo">But I do trouble myself,</said> returned Anselmo, <said
                    who="Anselmo">I love not to be left here sprawling <del>idle</del> on this
                    damp grass every night while you go pushing your head into the Lions mouth
                    in this way I can't imagine what makes you keep lurking alone about that
                    castle of <gap><desc>castle's name</desc>
                    </gap> unless it be to let <persName>Garcio</persName> catch you. and then
                    you would lose your head, and we our captain</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Leoni">Fear not for me,</said> said Leoni, <said who="Leoni">my doom
                    is not to die by his coward sword--</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Anselmo">I don't know that <persName>Leoni</persName>,</said> replied
                    the old man. <said who="Anselmo">that was another fools trick of yours, you
                    should have known better, when he fell before you in the battle, than to
                    think that <add place="supralinear"><del>a coward</del> he</add> would ever
                    have forgiven his defeat Why did you let him live to plot <del>means
                    of</del> revenge as a reward for your 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>very</del>most</add> wise clemency;</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> smiled in scorn.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Leoni">I knew him then as I know him now,</said> he said 
                    <said who="Leoni">Let him plot against me as he will--think you I care for his
                    <del>coward wrath</del> meanly devised revenge or coward and impotent
                    wrath. <persName>Garcio</persName> is to me as the wave that dashes its weak
                    spray on the forehead of yonder stern and unyielding crag.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Anselmo">Nevertheless <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, 
                    if he were to catch
                    you near his castle without your followers, I fancy our next charge <del>on
                    him</del> would <del>not be unheaded by you</del> be without a leader
                    You had better stay here out of <add place="supralinear"><del>the
                    Lions</del>his</add> den. or take us with you--Ill follow you to the
                    castle with the utmost possible pleasure-- <del>and when hes down here</del>
                    providing you don't sound a retreat as you so prudently did once when we
                    were about to give the rascals a lesson how they 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>tracked the</del>dared to attack the</add> band of
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> --you were possessed that day
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, mad, quite mad. 
                    <add place="supralinear">some of them</add> would have remembered it as long as their heads
                    stood on their shoulders</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Leoni"><add place="supralinear"><del>Not yet</del>You must not follow
                    me</add>, </said> said Leoni, <said who="Leoni">you <del>may have
                    an</del> must remain here <del>one</del> this evening at least but keep
                    your carbines loaded, and sleep not. I may have need of you this
                    night.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Anselmo">Its high time I know,</said> muttered Anselmo, 
                    <said who="Anselmo">to have need of us, we might as well be fishermen or 
                    <foreign xml:id="it">Lazzaroni</foreign> at once as lie here like moon calves all
                    <del>th</del> night, not a blow to be struck nor a shot fired. Well, if
                    he will go he <del>will--</del> must, I suppose. he'll be tired of this in
                    time or <del>somebody</del> Garcio will teach him the imprudence of solitary
                    contemplation.</said> And with a low discontented kind of growl
                    <persName>Anselmo</persName> couched sulkily behind a fallen column looked
                    to the priming of his carbine, turned his sword belt round that the hilt might
                    be near his hand, and (etc) The rest of the band 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>were</del>had</add> soon disappeared into various places of
                    concealment. and <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> leaping down 
                    <add place="supralinear">lightly</add> from the rocks, <del>with a light step
                    purs</del> moved rapidly along the seashore towards the castle of--<gap>
                    <desc>castle's name</desc>
                    </gap> And <add place="supralinear">a change came over</add> his countenance and
                    <add place="supralinear">it grew mild</add>. and a gladness rested on it.
                    and the haughtiness of his lip faded away
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName> sat in her chamber, in the eastern tower of the
                    castle of <gap><desc>castle's name</desc>
                    </gap> and the evening was sinking down upon the shores of the deep sea.
                    <del>And Giulietta's eye rested</del> and the evening star <del>as it</del>
                    rose up out of the deep and climbed slowly up into the darkening sky. and far
                    through the deep blue air gleamed its melancholy ray. and shone paly on the
                    quivering countenance of the moving waters And <persName>Giuliettas</persName>
                    large dark eye rested <add place="supralinear">sadly</add> on the star, and what
                    were <persName>Giuliettas</persName> thoughts. and <add place="supralinear">now
                    fast</add> waned the daylight away and the glow of the sky that was shed oer
                    it by the departing sun became cold, and the shadow of the pervading starlight
                    became visible on the chequered floor and <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>marble</del>carved</add> walls <del>and carved ceilin</del> of the
                    chamber. And the <del>objects beneath</del> night came glorious down upon the
                    sea.
                </p>
                <p>
                    And the star climbed higher and higher. and as it 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>vanished behind</del>touched</add> the summit of
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>a distant</del>the</add> mountain the night breeze
                    came balmily over the deep. and as it <del>balm</del> died away 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>a</del>the</add> voice was heard singing below the
                    castle. And <persName>Giulietta</persName> drew near the window and listened,
                    and the sounds <add place="supralinear"><del>came</del>rose</add> softly up upon
                    the wings of the night wind and <del>G</del> the moon and the stars <del>were
                    the only witnesses of the</del> looked down, and saw a blush <del>that</del>
                    passed over <persName>Giuliettas</persName> lovely cheek, <del>for the voice was
                    Francesco</del> and thus it sang. the voice
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poetry">
                <lg type="stanza" n="1">
                    <l>There was a tower within my heart</l>
                    <l>The tower was <del>high and</del> strong and high</l>
                    <l>But oh, its walls they fell before</l>
                    <l>The glance of thy bright eye</l>
                    <l>A throne of love within<del>g</del> the tower</l>
                    <l> A lofty throne, was seen</l>
                    <l>And there thou sittest on the throne</l>
                    <l>Indisputable queen</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" n="2">
                    <l>Full high upon the <placeName>Apennine</placeName></l>
                    <l>Is set my mountain town</l>
                    <l>And there with gems and marble fine</l>
                    <l>I've decked a lady's bower</l>
                    <l>The lady's bower is fair to see</l>
                    <l>No Ladys there I ween</l>
                    <l>Oh maiden, wend away with me</l>
                    <l>And thou shalt be its queen.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" n="3">
                    <l>And far among the mountains blue</l>
                    <l>I have a trusty band</l>
                    <l>My band is bold, my band is true</l>
                    <l>They wait for my command</l>
                    <l>Their hands are strong their hearts are free</l>
                    <l>Their swords are bright and keen</l>
                    <l>Oh maiden, wend away with me</l>
                    <l>And thou shalt be their queen </l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prose" subtype="tale">
                <p>
                    And the voice <add place="supralinear"><del>faded away</del>died</add>
                    <restore>away</restore>, and the tones passed <del>away <unclear/></del>
                    drearily into the stillness of the night <gap/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>And the voice <del>song</del> ceased, and the tones passed away into the
                    stillness of the night;</del>
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName> opened a secret door and descended, and
                    <persName>Francesco</persName> saw her come forth into the night in her
                    beauty; robed <del>all</del> in a robe of light. <said who="Giulietta">What
                    meant thy song to night <persName>Francesco</persName></said>said the maiden
                    <said who="Francesco"> What can a farewell to thee mean
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName>, but misery--</said>
                    <said who="Giulietta">And why farewell,</said> said
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName>, and she looked enquiringly at her lover, and
                    there was an agony passing over his <add place="supralinear"><del>high
                    forehead</del>countenance</add>, and the damp <add place="supralinear">
                    deathlike</add> dew <del>sat</del> hung upon his forehead. <said
                    who="Francesco">Why farewell,</said> he repeated, <said who="Francesco">ay.
                    why farewell between thee and me, <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>this</del>it</add> cannot shall not be.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta"><add place="supralinear">Why this,
                    <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName></add>. Whither wouldest thou go
                    <del>Francesco</del></said> said <persName>Giulietta</persName>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Francesco">Ask the withered leaf that is torn quivering from its bough
                    and drifted at the will of the winters wind--ask the meteor that is hurled
                    irregularly down <add place="supralinear">among</add> the stars--ask the
                    pray of the ocean when the tempest whirls it along the shore where they
                    would go, for withered as the autumn leaf and vain as the ocean spray, and
                    desolating and feared as the influence of the fires of the night, shall I be
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName>, when parted from thee</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">This is madness <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>,
                    </said> replied the maiden, 
                    <said who="Giulietta">wherefore must we part, or if we must, how canst thou noble
                    and true as I have known thee, become the thing thou hast described.</said>
                    <said who="Francesco">Thou knowest me not <persName>Giulietta</persName>--I am
                    not noble--I am not true</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">Mock me not--<del>thou art</del>
                    <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName></said>
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>Giulietta</del>the maiden</add>--
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Francesco">I could be. I will be, <persName>Giulietta</persName>. we
                    will not part--fly with me--the night is down on the mountains--my band is
                    near--ere the day dawns we shall be far hence in safety--in honour, ay if
                    thou wilt--in power.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">Thy band,</said>
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>the maiden</del>
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName></add>repeated <said who="Giulietta">--fly
                    with thee-- with whom What art thou <add place="supralinear">what mean
                    you</add>, <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Francesco"> I know not, maiden,</said> said
                    <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>
                    <said who="Francesco"><del>and he laughed</del> I have not been what
                    <del>not</del> I seem to be--yet thou could'st make me so. With thee I
                    am <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>--without thee <del>I am</del> a walking
                    misery. the curse of others, <del>and a deeper curse of my own heart</del>
                    --<s rend="underline">an <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>corporeal</del>embodied</add> fever of reckless madness</s>
                    the pestilence, the scourge, the deeper curse of my own heart--in one word,
                    without thee I am <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>.</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    And the word struck through to the maidens heart with a coldness as of death, and
                    the cry she <add place="supralinear"><del>formed</del>would have uttered</add>
                    died upon her lips, and she fainted in the arms of her Lover Oh how beautiful
                    was the fear upon <persName>Giuliettas</persName> face<del>s</del>--as she lay
                    in the lifeless sleep, pale as the snow that lies beneath the moon upon the high
                    <placeName>Apennine</placeName> and the terror on <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>a</del>her</add> countenance was as the terror of troubled
                    slumber--
                </p>
                <p>
                    Then the hectic flush passed over her cheek, and she woke from the partial death
                    with a deep gasp <add place="supralinear">as</add> of <add place="supralinear">
                    one in</add> pain and her dark eye gleamed with a vague uncertain
                    horror--And she passed her hand over her pale brow. and lo--it was as the silver
                    cloud that passeth over the <del><unclear>brow</unclear> of Monte Rosa</del>
                    --brightness of the midnight moon-- <said who="Giulietta"><persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco.
                    Francesco</persName>,</said> she said, <said who="Giulietta">thou
                    toldest me something--it was terrible--tell it me again-- 
                    <add place="margin-right"><persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName> where art thou</add>
                    thou art not <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>--<del>you said you were
                    not--Francesco is dead--dead--she not</del></said> And she paused for a
                    moment. <said who="Giulietta">I know now,</said> she said. <said who="Giulietta">
                    I remember--well--very well. <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName> is dead. and
                    thou <add place="supralinear"><del>art Leoni--the bandit Leoni</del>*</add>.
                    Oh fly--<del>fly</del> for thy life <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>--I love thee
                    yet-- <persName>Garcio</persName> will find thee will kill thee--my brother
                    will kill thee <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>.</said>
                </p>
                <addSpan spanTo="#addEnd02"/>
                <p>
                    <said who="Giulietta">Thou art not, thou canst not--thou shalt not be
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> the bandit 
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>. my
                    brothers enemy to the death--Oh <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName> --say thou
                    mockest me.</said>
                    <said who="Leoni">I was once <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName></said>, he replied--
                    <said who="Leoni">thy brothers enemy never--had I been
                    <persName>Garcio</persName> had now not
                    lived--<persName>Giulietta</persName>, you cannot believe I could be the
                    enemy of your brother--</said>
                    <said who="Giulietta">He is thine</said> she replied, <said who="Giulietta">oh
                    fly, fly for--&amp;c</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Leoni">Let him,</said> said Leoni--bitterly--<said who="Leoni"> fly
                    without thee--<persName>Giulietta</persName> I will not I could not. Die--
                    how I could thank death for the blow if it were not that beyond the grave
                    <del>there might</del> I know not if there might not be
                    forgetfulness--forgetfulness of thee <persName>Giulietta</persName>--he
                    paused--that were worse than the life without thee- -but death could not do
                    that no. no. my spirit would be with thee then <persName>Giuletta</persName>
                    [sic} upon earth. the <add place="supralinear"><del>air</del> evening
                    breeze</add> that fanned thy cheek should be
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>--the nightingale should sing <add
                    place="supralinear"><del>by</del>in</add> the orange grove, and
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> should bear the sound to thy
                    ear--<del>and</del> the fragrance of the wild rose should be brought
                    thee by <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>--the wreath of the morning mist the <add
                    place="supralinear"><del>light</del><del>bea</del></add><restore>light</restore> of the noonday
                    sun, the beam of the evening star should all be full of
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, and who should separate thee from
                    these--Would not this be happiness, <persName>Giulietta</persName> Oh
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName>, either fly with me this night, or I will
                    remain here, and the Sword of <persName>Garcio</persName> shall unite me
                    with thee for ever--Who shall slay an invisible--who shall part thee from
                    the air</said> And <persName>Giulietta</persName>
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>knew</del>felt</add> that it was
                    <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>, and not 
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, who
                    spoke, and she paused in very great agony.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Great was the tumult in the castle of <gap><desc>castle's name</desc>
                    </gap> an old peasant <del>(who had been gathering sticks amid the thickets on
                    the sea shore at the foot of the castle)</del> had come to
                    <persName>Garcio</persName> saying that he seen [sic] (, one of 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>which</del>them</add> was a maiden of exceeding
                    beauty,) two figures passing down westward <del>towar</del> on the
                    <add place="supralinear">sea</add> shore, <add place="supralinear"><del>they had
                    passed him</del>at the foot of the castle</add> he had seen them pass
                    unobserved, the countenance of the other he said was one which he knew well, one
                    which once seen was not easily forgotten, that of 
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> the
                    bandit Then <persName>Garcio</persName> was wild with rage 
                    <add place="supralinear">&amp; he</add> he called his followers together, and the
                    clash of arms was loud in the hall--and then from the gate issued a troop of
                    <del>armed men</del> warriors, and their arms gleamed coldly in the 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>pale moon</del>star</add>light--and
                    <persName>Garcio</persName> spurred on his bloody warhorse in the van--and
                    his countenance was pale with <del>the</del> wrath, and he dashed madly forward
                    along the winding shore
                </p>
                <p>
                    But one of the maidens of <persName>Giulietta</persName>, when she heard the
                    peasants tale, went and sought for <persName>Giulietta</persName> in her 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>chamber</del>fathers hall</add> and she was not
                    there, and in her <del>fathers</del> chamber, and she was not there. and she
                    descended by the secret staircase and she saw footsteps in the dew on the grassy
                    ground. Then she returned weeping--and she came to <del>the old m her</del>
                    father of <persName>Giulietta</persName>, and she told him that
                    <persName>Leoni</persName> the bandit had carried <add place="supralinear">
                    her</add> away <del>Giulietta</del> And the old man was weak, and very
                    feeble-- and he could not grieve and h<del>is</del>e bowed his head gently upon
                    his breast and died.
                </p>
                <p>
                    And the spirit went forth with a complaining, and passed moaning on the night
                    wind in search of those whom it loved--And it <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>fled</del>went</add> fast like a wreath of sea mist along the
                    shore and came and hovered over the head of <persName>Giulietta</persName>, as
                    she fled with <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, and as the spirit came near unto her
                    she remembered her father and how he had said that the sun would not rise to
                    him-And she stopped in great misery, exclaiming--<said who="Giulietta">oh my
                    father, my father surely I have murdered thee my father</said>--Then she
                    heard <del>her</del> through her weeping the noise of a soft sigh beside her-and
                    she started and looked round--it was not like the voice of the wind among the
                    <del>mur</del> laurel leaves, neither like the murmer of the little waves
                    upon the shore <del>And she said to Leoni</del>
                    <said who="Giulietta">Heardest thou nothing</said> she said to
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Leoni">Nothing. <persName>Giulietta</persName>,</said> he replied--
                    <said who="Leoni">nay--now that I listen, methinks I hear 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>the tra</del>a</add> sound far away like the
                    tramp of steeds along the sand.</said> And <del>she</del>
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName> listened, and she was filled with great fear. ah
                    fly <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, she said, <said who="Giulietta">
                    it is <persName>Garcio</persName>. fly, and leave me here--</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    But <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> raised her in his arms, and bore her softly
                    forward. and <persName>Giulietta</persName> overcame her faintness, and
                    struggled onward, and they fled. And now the rocks were seen rising high from
                    the sea shore, and the columns of the ruined temple were seen upon this summit,
                    and <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> knew that his band was near. <said who="Leoni">
                    <add place="supralinear">On. On.</add> One effort more
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName></said> he <del>said</del> exclaimed,
                    <said who="Leoni"> and we are safe.</said> And now the tramp of the
                    galloping horses came nearer and nearer and the voices of men were heard urging
                    them on. Louder and louder became the sound, and <del>Leoni</del>
                    <persName>Giulietta</persName> made one last struggle forward--and they gained
                    the rocks, they stood beneath the ruined temple-- <said who="Leoni">
                    Anselmo--Anselmo,</said> cried Leoni aloud and he was answered by a shout
                    from the cliffs, and the bandits leaped from their concealment but
                    <unclear>as</unclear> they gained the shore the foremost horseman of the
                    opposite troop dashed like lightning into view--it was
                    <persName>Garcio</persName> --a shout of triumph burst from his lips when he
                    saw <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>--<persName>Giulietta</persName> saw him level his
                    carbine--with a shriek of agony she threw herself before
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> , and fell dead into his arms, and the 
                    <add place="supralinear">dying</add> sigh that came from her lips sounded
                    like--<persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>--
                </p>
                <p>
                    The<del><unclear reason="crossout"/></del> band of 
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>
                    heard the shot, and were round him in an instant, and lo their leader was
                    standing beside the body of a maiden and the calm upon his countenance was
                    dreadful. and there was a smile upon his lips like the grinning of the dry bones
                    of a withered skull. and there was a stillness in his eye, and on his features,
                    but it was as the stillness of the volcano before it bursts forth into
                    desolation And his troops stood round him in a fearful silence--
                </p>
                <p>
                    There was a pause until, like a whirlwind over the quietness of deep waters came
                    the madness over the soul of <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>--and he looked, and saw
                    that his band was beside him--. <del>and he said</del><said who="Leoni">Stand by
                    me this night,</said> he said, <said who="Leoni"> and revenge <del>you</del>
                    the loss of your leader</said>--<del>And</del> Then he shouted his warshout
                    aloud, and the bandits swelled the sound with eager voices, and as the followers
                    of <persName>Garcio</persName> replied <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> dashed at them
                    like a thunderbolt.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Then loudly into the quietness of the heaven rose the roar of the battle, and the
                    echoes rolled heavily over the sea. On came the bandits like the tornado in its
                    power, and the banner of Garcio bore backward shivering, but he cheered them
                    again to the onset, and the tumult bellowed along the shore <del>as the</del>
                    and the shots rang loud and thick from among the volumes of smoke lit by
                    <del><unclear/></del> the death flashes that coiled its heavy and sulphurous
                    mass into the choked <del>sky</del> heaven-- Like the light that trembles along
                    the <add place="supralinear">rippled</add> waters of the ocean with 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>its</del>a</add> thousand sparkles, gleamed
                    <del>sabre</del> the flashing sabres amid the darkness of the war--but the
                    clash of the weapons and the roar of the fire were not mingled with any
                    voice--for the combatants could not shout in the madness of the struggle, and
                    the wounded fell in indignant silence and gasped out their souls without a
                    groan--
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>With the inveterate wrath of <add place="supralinear"><del>an</del>the</add>
                    avenging spirit of the victim pursing its murderer, did</del>
                    &amp;<persName>Leoni</persName> burst his path through the <del>ba</del>
                    mass of battle, and h<add><del>e</del></add>is <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>watched the</del>bloodshot eye</add> was on the crest of
                    <persName>Garcio</persName> as it rose and fell on the billowy burst of the
                    war, and whether it were friend or foe whom he met in his madness, he dashed the
                    combatants aside in death and clove his way onward toward that 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>high helmet of his one enemy</del>plume</add> And
                    with the inveterate wrath of an avenging spirit, when the dark ghost of the
                    victim walks the earth in the pursuit of its murderer,
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>
                    <del>follo</del> sought his single foe-- And the followers of 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>Leoni</del>
                    <persName>Garcio</persName></add> shrunk back even from his glance, and as
                    he broke <del>into the</del> through the fore-front of their battle some turned
                    <del>their backs</del> and fled, and the rest hung back in disorder and
                    dismay. Then the bandits drew backward out of the rush of the battle like the
                    dark reflux of a mighty billow before it breaks upon the shore, they paused for
                    a moment, a murmur <del>so came</del> rose from their ranks, louder and louder
                    became the voice, and then with a shout that startled the very stars they broke
                    down upon their hesitating opponents.
                </p>
                <p>
                    And the shock was as the shock of an ocean, and irresistible, and the ranks of
                    <persName>Garcio</persName> were overwhelmed <add place="supralinear">and
                    broken</add>, in an instant, and wild was the tumult as they were driven
                    backwards and struck down. Then <persName>Garcio</persName> saw
                    <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> come upon with the swoop of an eagle. and his eye
                    quailed and his limb quivered, before the despair of his <del>op</del> foe--
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Leoni">Wretch,</said> cried <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName>, 
                    <said who="Leoni">lovest thou life--Oh, would that I could make thy life to thee
                    what thou hast made it to me--and thou shouldst live--</said>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <said who="Leoni">I spared thee once, for her sake--thou hast well rewarded
                    me--Thy sister strikes thee--<persName>Garcio</persName></said>--And he
                    smote him dead.
                </p>
                <p>And the voice of battle drifted away towards the castle of <gap>
                   <desc>castle's name</desc>
                   </gap> and the shouts of the victorious bandits were heard echoing along the
                   cliffs. but <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> was no longer at their head--in their
                   victory they were without a leader--they remembered how he had commanded them to
                   avenge his loss; and few, very few of the followers of
                   <persName>Garcio</persName> escaped the slaughter of that night--and the
                   flames soon <add place="supralinear"><del>rose redly from</del> wrapt themselves
                   round</add> the towers of the castle, <del>and wrapt it round</del> and
                   shone redly and far over the darkness of the ocean And the bandits met by the
                   <add place="supralinear">lurid</add> light of the rushing fire and sought
                   for <persName ref="#Francesco">Leoni</persName> among the dead, and they found the body of
                   <persName>Garcio</persName>--and the sword of their leader lying beside
                   it--but him they found not, and they retired <add place="supralinear">
                   silently</add> under cover of the night to their fastness among the
                   mountains.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Oh, calmly <add place="supralinear">brightly</add> beautifully the morning rose
                    up out of the eastern sea--and widely spread the rosy <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>glory</del>dawn</add> over the deep--Gloriously the radiance stole
                    up into the high heaven--and the white clouds waved their light wings in the
                    deepness of its infinite blue, and looked out eastward rejoicing as they met the
                    morning breeze that sprang upward from its repose in the <del>olive</del> grove
                    of silver olives--and it breathed on the pale clouds and 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>it</del>they</add> passed silently on their path to
                    meet the sun
                </p>
                <p>
                    And the sun lifted his head majestically out of the sea, and looked forth upon
                    the world, and the mists rolled away before <del>the</del> his glance from the
                    surface of the sea--and the waters walked in light, and the waves passed onward
                    surging with sweet low voices, and the sun laid along the surges a long golden
                    path even unto the shore
                </p>
                <p>
                    And the mountains saw his glory and were gladdened--and their steeps were bathed
                    in brightness--
                </p>
                <p>
                    Oh the radiance of that morning <add place="supralinear">was</add> unconscious of
                    the desolation of the night, there was no sadness in the brilliancy of the dawn
                    <add place="supralinear">that <del><unclear reason="crossout"/></del> shone
                    on the ruins of the castle</add> and the voices of the winds and the waters
                    was gay, and the surges that <add place="supralinear">had</add> dashed away the
                    blood from the shore through the night <add place="supralinear">now</add> broke
                    clear and white on the unstained pebbles And the columns of the ruined temple on
                    the <add place="supralinear"><del>shore</del>rocks</add> stood tall in the beam,
                    and broadly and darkly against the gleaming sky rose the tall trunks and
                    spreading foliage of the ancient trees. A figure was leaning against one of the
                    rocks on the sea shore, and wan and haggard was <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>the</del>its</add> countenance as if it had been withered
                    <del>th</del> away by the devouring fire that flickered <del>in</del> madly
                    in the eye; Few, very few, could have recognized in the weary face and withered
                    form the <del>once</del> bearing of the haughty and fiery Leoni-- and the
                    fishermen of <placeName>Pozuolo</placeName> affirm that for years after that
                    terrible night the same figure was seen wandering among the rocks upon the shore
                    with sleepless eye and weary limb, and <add place="margin-right"><del>with w
                    looking</del>walking</add> among the crags as if seeking something, he
                    know not what with the restlessness of madness passing hither and thither at all
                    times, whether the night winds were singing <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>mournfully</del>sadly</add> or the stars gleaming tearfully, or
                    the morn breaking brightly, or the sun setting silently over the resting place
                    of the Bandits bride.
                </p>
                <p>
                    And when were [sic] <persName>Giulietta's</persName> thoughts. She was
                    <del>listening f</del> waiting for a voice that rose every evening as the
                    star disappeared behind the summit of a distant peaked mountain from the myrtle
                    Grove beneath the castles [sic]. <persName>Giulietta</persName> hardly knew how
                    very sweet the voice was to her ear--for it was the voice of one who loved her
                    with a more than common love--even with a love like that of spirits. They had
                    first met when <persName>Giulietta</persName> was young, very young, and
                    <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName> a youth just verging into manhood--From that
                    hour she had been like a halo of glory in the life of
                    <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName>--<persName>Giulietta</persName> knew it, she
                    could not help loving <del>one</del> him whose thoughts whose hopes, whose being
                    were centred in her only-- <del>she <add><del>the thought of her</del></add> she
                    came upon his <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>spirit</del><del>soul</del></add> like the morning on
                    <del>the</del> dark mountains --Francesco thought not how black would be
                    the midnight if that sun should ever set</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The thought of her came over his soul like the morning on dark
                    mountains--<del>and</del> when absent from her,
                    <persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName> had two lives, and one was cold, and dead,
                    and <add place="supralinear">dark, &amp;</add> cheerless, but the other was 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>a visionary</del>the dreamy</add> life 
                    <add place="supralinear">of the mind</add>, beautiful exceedingly, full of light
                    and loveliness, for the vision of her was there <del>always</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Her father knew not of the love of his child--<persName ref="#Leoni">Francesco</persName> had
                    seen <add place="supralinear">her</add> only <del>at intervals</del> for
                    moments, by stealth, pleading to <persName>Giulietta</persName> some ancient
                    feud of their families as an excuse for maintaining <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>the</del> his love</add> in secret <del><unclear reason="crossout"/>
                    </del> --Several times in the masque or the dance at the castle of--<gap/>
                    a knight had mingled of more graceful form and nobler bearinq--none knew
                    him--unless there was recognition in the brightness of
                    <persName>Giuliettas</persName> eye-several times when 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>her father</del>she</add> had gone forth with her
                    <add place="margin-right">father</add>
                    <add place="supralinear">&amp; a</add> retinue of fifty knights the ranks had
                    been thrown into confusion as if by a supernumerary
                    individual<del>ly</del>--<persName>Giulietta</persName> only knew
                    how--several times when the minstrels were singing in the hall had one come
                    forward of haughtier glance and loftier brow, and all bent forward to 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>hear</del>listen to</add> his 
                    <add place="supralinear"><del>strain, but the</del></add> lay of love, charming
                    all ears, intended only for one--
                </p>
                <p>The song ceased for a moment, <add place="supralinear">and</add> then again the
                    perfumed night breeze became vocal--but <add place="supralinear">now</add> the
                    sounds were low and sad-- and fell <add place="supralinear">
                    <del>coldly</del>melancholy</add> on <persName>Giuliettas</persName>
                    ear--
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poetry">
                <lg type="stanza" n="1">
                    <l>Now broad and brilliant lies the light</l>
                    <l>Of <del>moon and</del> stars on flood and fell</l>
                    <l>But in my breast is starless night</l>
                    <l>For I have come to say farewell--</l>
                    <l>How glad, how swift was wont to be</l>
                    <l>The step that bore me back to thee</l>
                    <l>Now coldly comes upon my heart</l>
                    <l>The meeting that is but to part--</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" n="2">
                    <l>I do not ask a tear. but while</l>
                    <l>I linger where I must not stay,</l>
                    <l>Oh, give me but a parting smile</l>
                    <l>Eleven lines, to the bottom of the page, are left blank; the</l>
                    <l>remaining text begins at the top of the following recto.</l>
                    <l>To light me on my lonely way</l>
                    <l>To shine, a brilliant beacon star</l>
                    <l>To my reverted glance afar--</l>
                    <l>Through midnight, which can have no morrow</l>
                    <l>Oer the deep, silent surge of sorrow</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" n="3">
                    <l><del>The</del> ardent fire within me flashes-And</l>
                    <l>though my heart consumed may be</l>
                    <l>There is a Phoenix in its ashes--</l>
                    <l>Oh how I love the love of thee--</l>
                    <l>Although my hope <del>an</del><del>be chill</del> and joy be chill</l>
                    <l>That constant flame will flicker still</l>
                    <l>And round my broken heart will play</l>
                    <l>With mocking melancholy ray</l>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="personography">
                <listPerson type="Ruskins">
                    <person xml:id="John_Ruskin">
                        <persName>John Ruskin</persName>
                        <birth when="1819-02-12">
                            <placeName>London, England</placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <residence from="1819" to="1834"/>
                        <death when="1900-01-20">
                            <placeName>Coniston, England</placeName>
                        </death>
                        <state type="mentally_ill" from="1878-06" to="1878-08">
                            <desc>Period of apparent schizophrenia</desc>
                        </state>
                        <event type="institutionalized" notBefore="1878-05-25" notAfter="1878-08-05">
                            <desc>committed</desc>
                        </event>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Effie_Ruskin">
                        <persName>Effie Ruskin</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Margaret_Ruskin">
                        <persName>Margaret Ruskin</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="John_James_Ruskin">
                        <persName>John James Ruskin</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <listPerson type="editor">
                    <person xml:id="DH">
                        <persName>David Hanson</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <listPerson type="encoder">
                    <person xml:id="JKB">
                        <persName>Jaime Barrilleaux</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="SGH">
                        <persName>Stephen Haddad</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="MS">
                        <persName>Michael Stevenson</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="WW">
                        <persName>William Woodard</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="HT">
                        <persName>Heidi Toloudis</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="JR">
                        <persName>Jessica Rushing</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="BF">
                        <persName>Beth Fox</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="SH">
                        <persName>Simone Hamilton</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <listPerson type="historical">
                    <person xml:id="Homer">
                        <persName>Homer</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Hystaspes">
                        <persName>Hystaspes</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Scamander">
                        <persName>Scamander</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Xerxes">
                        <persName>Xerxes</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Wordsworth">
                        <persName>Wordsworth</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Rollin">
                        <persName>Rollin</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Herodotus">
                        <persName>Herodotus</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Byron">
                        <persName>Byron</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Walter_Scott">
                        <persName>Walter Scott</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Collingwood">
                        <persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <listPerson type="mythological">
                    <person xml:id="Achilles">
                        <persName>Achilles</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Apollo">
                        <persName>Apollo</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Phoebus">
                        <persName>Phoebus</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <listPerson type="fictional">
                    <person xml:id="Moriartes">
                        <persName>Moriartes</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Harry">
                        <persName>Harry</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Lucy">
                        <persName>Lucy</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="mamma">
                        <persName>mamma</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="papa">
                        <persName>papa</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Harold">
                        <persName>Harold</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Elaira">
                        <persName>Elaira</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Francesco">
                        <persName>Francesco</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Leoni">
                        <persName>Leoni</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Giulietta">
                        <persName>Giulietta</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Garcio">
                        <persName>Garcio</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Anselmo">
                        <persName>Anselmo</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </div>
            <div type="places">
                <listPlace type="geographical">
                    <place xml:id="Athens">
                        <placeName>Athens</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="The_City">
                        <placeName>Financial district of London</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Greece">
                        <placeName>Greece</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="India">
                        <placeName>India</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="London">
                        <placeName>London</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="London_Docks">
                        <placeName>London Docks</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Marathon">
                        <placeName>Marathon</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Parnassus">
                        <placeName>Mount Parnassus</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Persia">
                        <placeName>Persia</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Salamis">
                        <placeName>Salamis</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Scythia">
                        <placeName>Scythia</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Sparta">
                        <placeName>Sparta</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Thebes">
                        <placeName>Thebes</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Morat">
                        <placeName>Morat</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Sunium">
                        <placeName>Sunium</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Dover">
                        <placeName>Dover</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Hastings">
                        <placeName>Hastings</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="England">
                        <placeName>England</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Tyres">
                        <placeName>Phoenicia</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Helle">
                        <placeName/>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Egean">
                        <placeName>Aegean Sea</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Appennines">
                        <placeName>Appennine Mountains</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Friuli">
                        <placeName>Friuli</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Italy">
                        <placeName>Italy</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="Pozuolo">
                        <placeName>Pozuolo</placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
                <listPlace type="mythological">
                    <place xml:id="Troy">
                        <placeName>Troy</placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>