<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">A Rhyming Letter</title>
                <title type="sub">etext generated from a transcription of a manuscript</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>Louisiana Board of Regents</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>ERM version 1.0 encoded Oct. 2009</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>000012</idno>
                <date when="2010-06-08">June 8 2010</date>
                <distributor>The Early Ruskin Manuscripts Project</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>###INSERT COPYRIGHT STATEMENT###</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="influence">###Insert notation of poetic influences here###</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <!-- possibly change to <msDesc> tag-->
                    <author>John Ruskin</author>
                    <title>Rhyming Letter</title>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from original manuscript</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
                <div type="poem">
                    <!-- Simple verse -->
                    <head rend="caps">A Rhyming Letter<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded1" n="1" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></head>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>My dearest Richard,&#x02014;<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note
                                xml:id="xmlidneeded2" n="2" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                                Needed</note></l>
                        <l>I hope you will not (moved by the delay</l>
                        <l>Of mine epistle to this distant day)</l>
                        <l>Accuse me of neglect; for if you do,</l>
                        <l>I can retort an equal blame on you:</l>
                        <l>For I, who in my study&#x02019;s height sublime</l>
                        <l>See every wave of calmly passing time</l>
                        <l>Flow softly onward in one beaten track&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>My only journies into town and back,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>Horace or Homer, all I choose between,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>Dulwich or Norwood my sole change of scene,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>Find every hour exactly like its brother,</l>
                        <l>And scarce can tell the days from one another;</l>
                        <l>And cannot find a single circumstance,</l>
                        <l>As I review, with a reverted glance,</l>
                        <l>The fast flown autumn months from end to end,</l>
                        <l>To fill a page, or interest ev&#x02019;n a friend;</l>
                        <l>While you, whose distant wandering steps have trod</l>
                        <l>The blue lake&#x02019;s glittering shingle and the
                            sod&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>The short, crisp sod, which on the mountains high</l>
                        <l>Braves the unkindness of their cloudy sky,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>Whose velvet tuftings most I love to feel</l>
                        <l>Result elastic underneath my heel&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>You, sir, I say, whose eye hath wandered o&#x02019;er</l>
                        <l>Bala&#x02019;s blue wave and Harlech&#x02019;s golden shore,</l>
                        <l>And seen the sun declining towards the west</l>
                        <l>Light the lone crags of Idris&#x02019; triple crest,</l>
                        <l>And watched the restless waters dash and swell</l>
                        <l>By Pont y Monach,&#x02014;should have much to tell.</l>
                        <l>You said, you know, that you would keep a journal</l>
                        <l>Wherein t&#x02019; insert the quintessence or kernel</l>
                        <l>Of your day&#x02019;s doings, like to that of Crusoe.</l>
                        <l>I hope, but don&#x02019;t believe you have. To do so</l>
                        <l>Is the severest test of the stern quality</l>
                        <l>Of a man&#x02019;s powers; for it needs punctuality,</l>
                        <l>Steadiness, firmness, and determination,</l>
                        <l>And perseverance&#x02014;the continuation</l>
                        <l>Of such a thing is really quite laborious,</l>
                        <l>And its performance actually glorious;</l>
                        <l>Which if you&#x02019;ve not performed, I hope you&#x02019;ll
                            send</l>
                        <l>Me a large sheet, close written to the end&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>Crossed if you like,&#x02014;containing full details</l>
                        <l>Of all you saw, and did, and heard in Wales;</l>
                        <l>Of your adventures and perambulations,</l>
                        <l>Delights and hardships, pleasures and vexations,</l>
                        <l>With all the changes of your tasks and rule,</l>
                        <l>And all the new varieties of school.</l>
                        <l>As to myself&#x02014;a fortnight almost gone</l>
                        <l>Since I went up to put my toga on&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>That learned toga, whose important grace</l>
                        <l>Befits the studious mien and thoughtful pace</l>
                        <l>Of those who by the banks of Isis dwell,</l>
                        <l>In classic hall or philosophic cell.</l>
                        <l>The winter mists were dark as we were dragged all in</l>
                        <l>Over the nobly-arching bridge of Magdalen,</l>
                        <l>And twilight sunk, borne by the bat-winged hours,</l>
                        <l>Down softly on the still, majestic towers;</l>
                        <l>The calmly passing river held its breath</l>
                        <l>Among the bending sedges by its path,</l>
                        <l>As every wave kissed with its lips so cold</l>
                        <l>Some sculptured stone or fretwork rich and old;</l>
                        <l>A moveless light, as from some sacred flame,</l>
                        <l>Through the grey Gothic of the casements came;</l>
                        <l>(My fancy heard the air, so still, so dim,</l>
                        <l>Made soft and holy by the vesper hymn;)</l>
                        <l>The varied form of every gorgeous stain</l>
                        <l>Shone, brightly burning, on the illumined pane;</l>
                        <l>And as a gentle dream comes calm and kind</l>
                        <l>O&#x02019;er the dark slumber of the lonely mind,</l>
                        <l>When, through the night of grief that knows no morrow,</l>
                        <l>Pale visions mock the fevered sleep of sorrow,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>And fill the brain with brightness, and the ear</l>
                        <l>With long-lost music that it starts to hear&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>So through the dimness of the silent night</l>
                        <l>Floated that stream of soft and sacred light,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>Fell on the sculptures grey, and touched with gold</l>
                        <l>The stone made living by hands long since cold,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>And showed where, twisted in fantastic wreath,</l>
                        <l>Strange features grinned, and stone eyes glanced beneath,</l>
                        <l>Flushed by the flame and by a life in death;</l>
                        <l>Then fitful o&#x02019;er the waters danced the ray,</l>
                        <l>And &#x02019;midst the dim reflection died away.</l>
                        <l>In Oxford there are two hotels&#x02014;which are</l>
                        <l>(Perchance you know) the &#x0201C;Angel&#x0201D; and the
                                &#x0201C;Star;&#x0201D;<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                                xml:id="xmlidneeded3" n="3" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                                Needed</note></l>
                        <l>The landlord has contrived (oh, avarice horrid!)</l>
                        <l>To put the star upon the angel&#x02019;s forehead,</l>
                        <l>Which, as I think, both businesses may mar;</l>
                        <l>&#x02019;Twill then be falling Angel,&#x02014;shooting star.</l>
                        <l>The &#x0201C;Angel&#x0201D; was our choice&#x02014;we always
                            went</l>
                        <l>To that&#x02014;we like an old establishment.</l>
                        <l>A night, a day past o&#x02019;er&#x02014;the time drew
                            near,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>The morning came&#x02014;I felt a little queer;</l>
                        <l>Came to the push; paid some tremendous fees;</l>
                        <l>Past; and was capped and gowned with marvellous ease;</l>
                        <l>Then went to the Vice-Chancellor to swear</l>
                        <l>Not to wear boots, nor cut or comb my hair</l>
                        <l>Fantastically,&#x02014;to shun all such sins</l>
                        <l>As playing marbles or frequenting inns,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>Always to walk with breeches black or brown on,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>When I go out, to put my cap and gown on,&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>With other regulations of the sort, meant</l>
                        <l>For the just ordering of my comportment;</l>
                        <l>Which done, in less time than I can rehearse it, I</l>
                        <l>Found myself member of the University.</l>
                        <l>Believe me, sir, it made me quite ecstatical</l>
                        <l>To hear you had become so mathematical,</l>
                        <l>And passed the bridge, so strangely named from those</l>
                        <l>Who cannot pass it. At this half-year&#x02019;s close</l>
                        <l>I hope such geometrical employment</l>
                        <l>Will furnish us with profit and enjoyment.</l>
                        <l>My father and my mother (hang it!&#x02014;join&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>Won&#x02019;t join with any rhyme that I can coin)&#x02014;</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Mother and cousin beg to join in kind</l>
                        <l>Love,&#x02014;and I do remain as undersigned,</l>
                        <l>With a most loving friendship in my mind,</l>
                        <l>Remaining based on a firm pediment,</l>
                        <l>Your most devoted&#x02014;most obedient&#x02014;</l>
                        <l>And most affectionate</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
