<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"The Steam Engine"</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from a Transcription of the Library Edition</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-09-28">September 28, 2010</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                    <!--Example entries have been provided for the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <country type="nation">United States of America</country>
                        <region type="state">Connecticut</region>
                        <settlement type="city">New Haven</settlement>
                        <institution>Yale University</institution>
                        <repository>Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</repository>
                        <collection>MS Vault Ruskin</collection>
                        <idno>Miscellaneous Ruskin MSS</idno>
                        <msName>Early Poems IA</msName>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno>"Ruskin MS. Early Poems. IA. This has been bound since the publication of the Poems in 1891 and may be added to the list of MS given there, as IA. See The Library Edition II.530."</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!--Front matter should acurately represent the manuscript being transcribed - not display the the title/heading of the Web site/page.-->
            <head>Steam Engine</head>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="poem">
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabb">
                    <l>When furious up from mines the water pours,</l>
                    <l>And clears from rusty moisture all the ores;</l>
                    <l>Then may clouds gather, then may thunder roar</l>
                    <l>Then may the lightnings flash and rain may pour,</l>
                    <l>Yet undisturbed the power alone will raise</l>
                    <l>The water from the engine might be formed a phrase,</l>
                    <l>When as it drags the weight of fragments large,</l>
                    <l>It also drags the weight of smokey barge,</l>
                    <l>Called by us steamboat, and a steamboat saves</l>
                    <l>The beings scattered on the furious waters</l>
                    <l>By boilers bursting, but a steamboat can</l>
                    <l>Be the most useful engine brought to man</l>
                    <l>The grinding stones that by its force are whirled,</l>
                    <l>And by their force the yellow grains are twirled,</l>
                    <l>Bruised, ground, and thrown away in boxes small,</l>
                    <l>While it doth thunder near the echoing wall,</l>
                    <l>The whirling wheels arranged in whirling rows</l>
                    <l>And on the wheels the spinner cotton throws;</l>
                    <l>Next moves the noisy beam ; the wheels do whirl,</l>
                    <l>And next the wheels the cotton fibres twirl;</l>
                    <l>The moving bellows that are made to roar</l>
                    <l>By its huge strength that melt the red hot ore;</l>
                    <l>The copper mines that by it emptied are;</l>
                    <l>And their blue metal now is brought from far;</l>
                    <l>Then it puts forth its power that rollers squeeze</l>
                    <l>The metal, then another part doth seize</l>
                    <l>The flattened metal; quick flies the circle round,</l>
                    <l>And all is stamped at once Brittannia and the ground,</l>
                    <l>Then showers the water from the reservoir,</l>
                    <l>And round the town it rushing now doth pour;</l>
                    <l>Then runs to cisterns large and fills them all</l>
                    <l>And turns back homeward in quantity but small;</l>
                    <l>Then forms the lengthening and putting link to link,</l>
                    <l>Makes a small chain and leaves of that flower the pink.</l>
                    <l>And so I end.</l>
                    <l>[My interpolation]</l>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>