<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Tour Through France</title>
                <title type="sub">etext generated from a transcription of a manuscript</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>Louisiana Board of Regents</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>ERM version 1.0 encoded Oct. 2009</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>000018</idno>
                <date when="2010-06-08">June 8 2010</date>
                <distributor>The Early Ruskin Manuscripts Project</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>###INSERT COPYRIGHT STATEMENT###</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="influence">###Insert notation of poetic influences here###</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <!-- possibly change to <msDesc> tag-->
                    <author>John Ruskin</author>
                    <title>Tour Through France</title>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from original manuscript</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="poem">
                <head rend="caps">A Tour Through France</head>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="ababcc">
                    <l>Steward, some brandy; No, that an&#x02019;t enough.</l>
                    <l>Ask him&#x02014;Oh dear! I thought I should have died.</l>
                    <l>Call you that brandy&#x02014;never saw such stuff.</l>
                    <l>Then poke your head over the vessel&#x02019;s side.</l>
                    <l>One rates the cabin stairs, which he can&#x02019;t go up,</l>
                    <l>Another hopes the boiler will not blow up.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="3">
                    <!-- there is one source online that says this scheme is a fishhook sonnet-->
                    <head>3</head>
                    <l>I&#x02019;m sure enough to fluster any body &#x02019;tis</l>
                    <l>To step upon the stones of Calais quay;</l>
                    <l>You meet with such a set of oddities;</l>
                    <l>This way and that you turn yourself to see,</l>
                    <l>And then you bawl out, &#x0201C;Dear! how hot it is!&#x0201D;</l>
                    <l>Then you&#x02019;re hauled off&#x02014;for they make very free,</l>
                    <l>Those interfering officers of custom&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>For they will search, ay, and they will examine;</l>
                    <l>&#x02014;It&#x02019;s very impolite, but then, they must,
                        ma&#x02019;am!</l>
                    <l>&#x0201C;They should not be so rough, and rout, and ram in</l>
                    <l>My things so!&#x0201D;&#x02014;but they&#x02019;re used to it; only trust
                        ‘em;</l>
                    <l>You will make all things right by dint of cramming.</l>
                    <l>&#x02014;Now, sir, I hope you&#x02019;ve finished with that box;</l>
                    <l>See, here&#x02019;s the key; and that&#x02019;s the way it locks!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="4">
                    <head>3</head>
                    <l>There is a monument beneath the wall</l>
                    <l>Of Calais, as you pass along the pier,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>A plain, unsculptured, low memorial;</l>
                    <l>Yet pass not by it, stranger; for &#x02019;tis dear&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>A thing most precious in the sight of all</l>
                    <l>Who dwell upon the deep. There lie not here</l>
                    <l>The bones of those whose names thereon you see;</l>
                    <l>But &#x02019;tis a tomb for such as have no tomb,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Memory of those who have no memory,</l>
                    <l>Nor even a burial-place, except the gloom</l>
                    <l>And ceaseless roll of the relentless sea;</l>
                    <l>For whom no hymn was sung except the boom</l>
                    <l>Of waves innumerable, and the roar</l>
                    <l>That their grave makes upon their native shore.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="5">
                    <head>5</head>
                    <l>Weep not for those who in their honours die,</l>
                    <l>Whom fame forbids to perish,&#x02014;for the brave,</l>
                    <l>The mighty and the glorious, all pass by,</l>
                    <l>All must go down into the voiceless grave.</l>
                    <l>Weep not for those for whom whole nations sigh,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>But we will weep for those who died to save</l>

                    <l>The stranger perishing. Approach and read!</l>
                    <l>There&#x02019;s not a name upon you simple stone</l>
                    <l>But of a hero. What although the dead</l>
                    <l>Have all gone down into the deep unknown,</l>
                    <l>And what although their bones be scattered</l>
                    <l>All underneath the deep, salt surges thrown?</l>
                    <l>They speak, for whom their being was surrendered:</l>
                    <l>They have been wept, and they shall be remembered.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="6">
                    <head>6</head>
                    <l>Now as I stood beside the tomb, thus thinking,</l>
                    <l>There came some perfumes o&#x02019;er the pier&#x02014;thinks
                        I&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>This is not very sweet, I won&#x02019;t say stinking,</l>
                    <l>Then as I saw some ancient fish close by,</l>
                    <l>I sentimentally departed winking,</l>
                    <l>There was a tear, or something, in my eye;</l>
                    <l>Perhaps the wind had blown the dust into it,</l>
                    <l>It broke upon my train of sentiment,</l>
                    <l>I saw the ancient portal, and walked through it;</l>
                    <l>I need not say to which hotel we went,</l>
                    <l>But ‘twas the best in Calais, and we knew it;</l>
                    <l>Our trunks were from the custom houses sent,</l>
                    <l>And then we dined on many a savoury stew</l>
                    <l>And then we&#x02014;what is what we did to you?</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="7">
                    <head>7</head>
                    <l>Then by Montreuil to Abbeville we went,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>An ancient place, and picturesque indeed all;</l>
                    <l>The ramparts round enclose a large extent.</l>
                    <l>We put our noses into the cathedral</l>
                    <l>(Much tempted by the outside) with intent</l>
                    <l>To wander through the naves,<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded1" resp="#DH" n="1" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note> and see it all;</l>
                    <l>But started back, and instant sought the door,</l>
                    <l>Nought seeing there but dirt and dirty people.</l>
                    <l>&#x02014;The marble chequers of the ancient floor,</l>
                    <l>Oh, citizens of Abbeville, why not sweep well?</l>
                    <l>We stared about, the Gothic front before,</l>
                    <l>Surveyed the porch, and criticised the steeple,</l>
                    <l>Marvelled to see the carving rich, and talked of</l>
                    <l>The figures standing with their noses knocked off.2<note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded2" resp="#DH" n="2" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="8">
                    <head>8</head>
                    <l>And so we wandered on, until the Seine</l>
                    <l>Glistened along the distance mistily,</l>
                    <l>Floating among the azure of the plain</l>
                    <l>Like milky way along the midnight sky;</l>
                    <l>Which wooded hills surrounded with a chain</l>
                    <l>Of silver cliffs; and Rouen&#x02019;s minster high,</l>
                    <l>Uplifted in the air its Gothic light1<note xml:id="xmlidneeded3" resp="#DH"
                            n="3" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>In rich array of spiry pinnacle.</l>
                    <l>The river, that we looked on from the height</l>
                    <l>Was full of islands green, and wooded well,</l>
                    <l>Like fairy dwellings in the misty light</l>
                    <l>That o&#x02019;er the city and the waters fell,</l>
                    <l>Throwing a beautifully golden shower</l>
                    <l>On minster grey and tall St. Ouen&#x02019;s fretted tower.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="9">
                    <head>9</head>
                    <l>Now, every street in Rouen without fail is</l>
                    <l>Traversed by gutters of enormous size;</l>
                    <l>(The joke about the Grecian quite stale is),</l>
                    <l>But, in such occupation of your eyes</l>
                    <l>Beware lest you endure the fate of Thales</l>
                    <l>&#x02014;Ditched in philosophizing on the skies.</l>
                    <l>For, as you pass each antiquated street</l>
                    <l>Diverging from the Place de la Pucelle,</l>
                    <l>Over your head the Norman houses meet,</l>
                    <l>Black with old beams, and ornamented well</l>
                    <l>With huge, broad roofs to shade them from the heat;</l>
                    <l>And you enjoy variety of smell</l>
                    <l>Quite infinite,&#x02014;in fact, you can&#x02019;t suppose</l>
                    <l>Better amusement for the eyes and nose!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="10">
                    <head>10</head>
                    <l>Rouen is full of holes and corners curious;</l>
                    <l>What thing you are to see next, there&#x02019;s no knowing;</l>
                    <l>And churches two, applied to use injurious,</l>
                    <l>Sounded with anvil stroke and bellows blowing.</l>
                    <l>The rascally canaille!&#x02014;it makes one furious!</l>
                    <l>What English mob would ever think of stowing</l>
                    <l>Old iron ‘neath the Gothic portals grey</l>
                    <l>Of holy shrine, whose niches, statueless,</l>

                    <l>But carved and sculptured in a wondrous way,</l>
                    <l>Remained to tell how sacred once the place?</l>
                    <l>Indignant at the deed, we turned away</l>
                    <l>Towards the huge Cathedral&#x02019;s western face.</l>
                    <l>I stood, upstaring at the lofty steeple</l>
                    <l>&#x02014;And ran against a dozen market people!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="11">
                    <head>11</head>
                    <l>It is a marvel, though the statues cramp are,</l>
                    <l>How beautifully rich the tower is!</l>
                    <l>But ‘tis amazing what a sudden damper</l>
                    <l>Of all enthusiasm a shower is!</l>
                    <l>Down came a thunder-cloud, which made us scamper</l>
                    <l>Under the arch that shows what hour it is.</l>
                    <l>&#x02014;I don&#x02019;t admire the plan of elevating</l>
                    <l>A clock upon a steeple huge and high,</l>
                    <l>Where really nobody can see it, bating</l>
                    <l>Those who have got a very practised eye;</l>
                    <l>And people in a hurry can&#x02019;t stand waiting</l>
                    <l>Until the clappers tell how time goes by:</l>
                    <l>Besides, on Gothic work, the great, flat face</l>
                    <l>Looks quite incongruous, and out of place.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="12">
                    <head>12</head>
                    <l>So, as the Rouen architects thought fit</l>
                    <l>To go upon a plan entirely new,</l>
                    <l>They built an arch on purpose every bit;</l>
                    <l>Chiselled it over, till gay garlands grew</l>
                    <l>Beneath their hands, where&#x02019;er their mallets hit,</l>
                    <l>And open flowers along the granite blew</l>
                    <l>Unwitheringly. On the arching wide</l>
                    <l>Stood up the dial, bridging over quite</l>
                    <l>The narrow Norman street from side to side.</l>
                    <l>Long distance down the street the dial white</l>
                    <l>By every passer-by might be espied,</l>
                    <l>And looked exceeding picturesque and light.</l>
                    <l>In fact, there never was a plan projected</l>
                    <l>By which a clock could better be erected.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="13">
                    <head>13</head>
                    <l>So, as I said before, past this we ran,</l>
                    <l>(For, in this clime, when thunder-clouds come blowing,</l>
                    <l>Always retire as quickly as you can);</l>
                    <l>Reached the hotel, and scarce had time to go in</l>
                    <l>Before the thunder and the rain began;</l>
                    <l>So we sat at the window, and cried &#x0201C;Oh!&#x0201D; when</l>
                    <l>There came a brilliant flash along the sky.</l>
                    <l>We, from the next day&#x02019;s morn till day departed,</l>
                    <l>Went up and down in Rouen constantly;</l>
                    <l>Admired, and wondered that in every part it</l>
                    <l>Presented rich street-pictures to the eye.</l>
                    <l>And then we ordered horses, and we darted</l>
                    <l>Many a long look at beautiful St. Ouen,</l>
                    <l>Climbing a verdant hill, the last that looks on Rouen.1<note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded4" resp="#DH" n="4" place="botwin">Notation Needed
                        </note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="14">
                    <head>14</head>
                    <l>St. Germain is a pleasant place to mope at&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Uninteresting as a place may be.</l>
                    <l>There&#x02019;s a fine view &#x02019;twould be as well to stop at</l>
                    <l>Near the old palace; and they say you see</l>
                    <l>Beyond the spires of Paris; and I hope that</l>
                    <l>It&#x02019;s true, but it is only an &#x0201C;on dit.&#x0201D;</l>
                    <l>When you&#x02019;ve walked up the Rue la Paix at Paris,</l>
                    <l>Been to the Louvre, and the Tuileries,</l>
                    <l>And to Versailles, although to go so far is</l>
                    <l>A thing not quite consistent with your ease,</l>
                    <l>And&#x02014;but the mass of objects quite a bar is</l>
                    <l>To my describing what the traveller sees.</l>
                    <l>You who have ever been to Paris, know:</l>
                    <l>And you who have not been to Paris,&#x02014;go!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="15">
                    <head>15</head>
                    <l>By Soissons, and by Rheims,&#x02014;which is much spoken of;</l>
                    <l>There&#x02019;s very little in it to admire,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The statues&#x02019; heads [indeed] are not all broken
                        off,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The thing is well preserved, from porch to spire;</l>
                    <l>And clean and neat, which is a [welcome]<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note
                            resp="#DH" xml:id="xmlidneeded5" n="5" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note> token of</l>
                    <l>Good order here. But many spires are higher:</l>
                    <l>The carving is not rich, the Gothic heavy;</l>
                    <l>The statues miserable,&#x02014;not a fold</l>
                    <l>Of drapery well-disposed in all the bevy</l>
                    <l>Of saints, and bishops, and archbishops old</l>
                    <l>That line the porches grey. But in the nave I</l>
                    <l>Stared at the windows, purple, blue, and gold:</l>
                    <l>And the perspective&#x02019;s wonderfully fine,</l>
                    <l>When you look down the long columnar line.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded6" resp="#DH" n="6" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="16">
                    <head>16</head>
                    <l>So on by Chalons, where no lions are</l>
                    <l>Save four on the Hôtel de Ville, we past</l>
                    <l>Plains in abominable flatness far</l>
                    <l>Extending westward, till we dropped at last</l>
                    <l>Down in a hole upon the town of Bar.2<note xml:id="xmlidneeded7" resp="#DH"
                            n="7" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>I love to see a streamlet flashing past</l>
                    <l>Down some still valley, in a sportive mood;</l>
                    <l>Where the winds come to bathe themselves, and sing,</l>
                    <l>And dip their breezy tresses in the flood.</l>
                    <l>&#x02019;Tis sweet to stand and watch the quivering</l>
                    <l>Of wave-embarrassed beams, where pebbles strewed</l>
                    <l>Brightly along the bottom of the spring</l>
                    <l>Fling back and forward flashes&#x02014;constant play</l>
                    <l>Of silver sunbeams that have lost their way.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="17">
                    <head>17</head>
                    <l>Therefore we went along the river&#x02019;s bank</l>
                    <l>Shaded by many a broad tree, branching wide</l>
                    <l>Where the cool ripple made the borders dank.</l>
                    <l>And everywhere along the valley-side</l>
                    <l>The hill, upon its brown and sunburnt flank,</l>
                    <l>Bore full and verdant vineyards in the pride</l>
                    <l>Of fruitfulness. But though we hear a deal of</l>
                    <l>Italian vineyards, and the juice delightful</l>
                    <l>Which Spanish peasantry make every meal of;</l>
                    <l>And though a glass looks pretty when ‘tis quite full</l>
                    <l>Of sparkling wine; and though we like the feel of</l>
                    <l>A bunch of grapes just gathered with a slight pull;</l>
                    <l>And though the Grecian poets praised a foamer</l>
                    <l>Of wine, when they were thirsty (witness Homer);&#x02014;</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="18">
                    <head>18</head>
                    <l>Yet, sir, you would by no means think it fun,</l>
                    <l>And all your fine romantic feelings fly off,</l>
                    <l>When you are stewed beneath a burning sun</l>
                    <l>Panting with heat which you are like to die of,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The stones beneath you scorching, every one,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The walls around you white and hot,&#x02014;a sky of</l>
                    <l>Untempered, sultry, and continual blue,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The air without a motion or a sound;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>&#x02019;Twould put a salamander in a stew</l>
                    <l>To feel the dry reflection from the ground!</l>
                    <l>Vine, vine, still vine,&#x02014;the only thing in view,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>All vine, monotonously roasting round!</l>
                    <l>&#x02019;Twould make you cry, as up the hills you scramble,</l>
                    <l>&#x0201C;Oh, for an English hedge of shady bramble!&#x0201D;</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="19">
                    <head>19</head>
                    <l>From Bar-le-Duc we made a dash at Nancy,</l>
                    <l>Whose beautiful arcades we walked about.</l>
                    <l>Its buildings are, as any body can see,</l>
                    <l>By revolutionists much knocked about.</l>
                    <l>There are two fountains spouting on a plan we</l>
                    <l>Admired, and the triumphal arch is talked about.<hi rend="superscript"
                            >1</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded8" n="8" resp="#DH" place="botwin"
                            >Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>But if you wish to see a foreign town,</l>
                    <l>Look out for every narrow, dirty street,</l>
                    <l>As you walk diligently up and down;</l>
                    <l>Pop into it directly; you will meet</l>
                    <l>Such combinations,&#x02014;houses tumbling down,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Old fragments,&#x02014;Gothic morsels, quite a treat,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Columns and cloisters,&#x02014;old boutiques which stink of</l>
                    <l>Garlic, and everything that you can think of!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abab" n="20">
                    <head>20</head>
                    <l>Thus here, there&#x02019;s such a bit, in such a lane</l>
                    <l>A gate, with curious carved Gothic niches</l>
                    <l>Where statues were, but where they don&#x02019;t remain,</l>
                    <l>Those men of taste, those Gemmen without breeches</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcacacaee" n="22">
                    <head>22</head>
                    <l>We saw them all the way to Plombières,</l>
                    <l>Which is a pretty place; but it is not that</l>
                    <l>Which makes the crowds of invalids go there.</l>
                    <l>The springs are so abominably hot, that</l>
                    <l>They steam and bubble in the open air,</l>
                    <l>Which makes the place look like a boiling pot, that</l>
                    <l>Smokes from the valley. There the baths are seen,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The water, through distilling drop by drop there,</l>
                    <l>Fills four1<note xml:id="xmlidneeded9" n="9" resp="#DH" place="botwin"
                            >Notation Needed</note>large tubs with liquid warm and green.</l>
                    <l>There sit the social invalids and pop their</l>
                    <l>Thin yellow noses out like lobsters lean</l>
                    <l>Boiling for dinner. Hour to hour they stop there,</l>
                    <l>Sleeping an[d] reading,&#x02014;subjects lean and bony,</l>
                    <l>Engaging in a conversazione.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="23">
                    <head>23</head>
                    <l>I&#x02019;m on the Jura. Lo! the rocks are dun,</l>
                    <l>Although the opposite of heaven [is]2<note xml:id="xmlidneeded10" n="10"
                            resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note> bright,</l>
                    <l>And all the glare of gaudy day [is] done;</l>
                    <l>And there is shadow mingled with the light.</l>
                    <l>The dazzled world is weary of the sun;</l>
                    <l>Her eyes are shaded by the hand of night.</l>
                    <l>Yet beautiful, oh! beautiful the beam</l>
                    <l>Along the azure of the plain [is] sleeping:</l>
                    <l>The distant hills are veiled as with a dream</l>
                    <l>Of mist, of dewy mist, their foreheads steeping.</l>
                    <l>The heaven is parting with the dying gleam,</l>
                    <l>And lo! the heaven is sad, the heaven is weeping.</l>
                    <l>The voice of streams is hushed3 upon the hill;</l>
                    <l>No murmur from the plain, and all the world is still.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="24">
                    <head>24</head>
                    <l>Farewell, ye plains; ye champaigns wide, farewell!</l>
                    <l>The cloud, the storm, the mountain now for me!</l>
                    <l>Mine be the deserts where the chamois dwell,</l>
                    <l>And the wild eagle soars at liberty!</l>
                    <l>For meditation on the pinnacle</l>
                    <l>Of the lone mountain sits, and loves to see</l>
                    <l>The beauty of the living solitude;</l>
                    <l>And music floats around; the mountain air</l>
                    <l>With a rich spirit of music is imbued;</l>
                    <l>And every sound becomes harmonious there;</l>
                    <l>The streamlet&#x02019;s plash, the thunder of the flood,</l>
                    <l>The flock&#x02019;s low tinkle o&#x02019;er the pastures bare,</l>
                    <l>And the long roar and echo never ending</l>
                    <l>Of distant avalanches terrible descending.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="25">
                    <head>25</head>
                    <l>This isn&#x02019;t humbug; no, you feel quite odd when</l>
                    <l>You climb an elevation hugely high;</l>
                    <l>Step after step goes hop upon the sod then,</l>
                    <l>Lightly as if you were about to fly;</l>
                    <l>Mile after mile with merry heart is trod then,</l>
                    <l>Enjoying all things with unwearied eye.</l>
                    <l>Then you feel hungry, eat a double ration</l>
                    <l>Of viands, don&#x02019;t despise your what you call it,</l>
                    <l>It is a member of imagination,</l>
                    <l>And of much sentiment, and, after all, it</l>
                    <l>Is pleasant in romantic situation</l>
                    <l>To fall upon your dinner or forestall it</l>
                    <l>With half-a-dozen breakfasts, rolls and eggs</l>
                    <l>To vivify your mind, and fortify your legs.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababacacacdd" n="26">
                    <head>26</head>
                    <l>So, on the heights of Jura, as I said,</l>
                    <l>I stood, admiring much the setting sun</l>
                    <l>Taking a bath before he went to bed</l>
                    <l>Out of the mists, that, indistinct and dun,</l>
                    <l>And dark, and grey, and colourless as lead</l>
                    <l>Along the horizon&#x02019;s farthest outline run</l>
                    <l>Like velvet cushions for his weary head;</l>
                    <l>Or like a sort of scene, for him to slip off</l>
                    <l>Behind: and a long line of ruby red</l>
                    <l>Zigzag&#x02019;d along their summits, like a strip of</l>
                    <l>Dutch gold upon a piece of gingerbread</l>
                    <l>After the happy urchin&#x02019;s gnawed the tip off</l>
                    <l>The finger, after long deliberation</l>
                    <l>Between his appetite and admiration.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="27">
                    <head>27</head>
                    <l>So, on the heights of Jura, as I said,</l>
                    <l>I stood, and rocks around in quantities,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>In cliffs quite high enough to turn your head,</l>
                    <l>And make you cry &#x0201C;how very grand it is!&#x0201D;</l>
                    <l>Especially after coming through the dead</l>
                    <l>And stupid plains of France, where scant it is1<note xml:id="xmlidneeded11"
                            n="11" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>Of beauty, and monotonously low.</l>
                    <l>These are those famous rocks by which the stone-</l>
                    <l>Examiners have all been puzzled so.</l>
                    <l>For here and there the granite blocks are strown</l>
                    <l>Over the bending mountain&#x02019;s softer brow;</l>
                    <l>And some affirm that here they have been thrown</l>
                    <l>By mighty floods, quite large enough to heave a</l>
                    <l>Mountain across the valley of Geneva!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="28">
                    <head>28</head>
                    <l>When o&#x02019;er the world the conquering deluge ran,1<note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded12" n="12" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>Rolling its monster surges, far and wide,</l>
                    <l>O&#x02019;er many an ancient mountain&#x02019;s lordly2<note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded13" n="13" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note> span,</l>
                    <l>And when upon the all devouring tide</l>
                    <l>Wallowed the bulk of the leviathan</l>
                    <l>Where cultivated plains are now descried;3<note xml:id="xmlidneeded14" n="14"
                            resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>And when the toppling peaks of mountains old</l>
                    <l>Were shook from their foundations into ruin,</l>
                    <l>Like shingle at the ocean&#x02019;s mercy rolled,</l>
                    <l>That worked, and worked,&#x02014;ever its work undoing,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Heaping up hills beneath its bosom cold,</l>
                    <l>Then wide again the devastation strewing,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Then the dark waves, with nothing to obstruct &#x02019;em,</l>
                    <l>Carried these blocks from far, and here it chucked &#x02019;em!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababacacacdd" n="29">
                    <head>29</head>
                    <l>Such are the dreams of the geologist!</l>
                    <l>He sees past ages of the world arise;</l>
                    <l>Strange sounds salute his ears, prepared to list,</l>
                    <l>And wondrous sights, his rock inspired eyes.</l>
                    <l>Before him solid mountains wave and twist,</l>
                    <l>And forms of life within them fossilize;</l>
                    <l>The flint invades each member as it dies,</l>
                    <l>And through the quivering crose on creeps the stone,</l>
                    <l>Till in the mountain&#x02019;s hardened heart it lies,</l>
                    <l>In nature, rock,&#x02014;in form, a skeleton;</l>
                    <l>Much for the feature valued by the wise,</l>
                    <l>Or in some huge museum to be shown,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>A mystery, as wonderful, at least,</l>
                    <l>As that of apples conjured into paste!4<note xml:id="xmlidneeded15" n="15"
                            resp="#DH" place="Notation Needed">Notation Needed</note></l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="30">
                    <head>30</head>
                    <l>Thus on the Jura dreamed I, with nice touch</l>
                    <l>Discriminating stones; till, which was teasing,</l>
                    <l>The evening mists rolled round, with dampness such,</l>
                    <l>That, though they brought a coolness not unpleasing,</l>
                    <l>They made me sneeze! Now, nothing half so much</l>
                    <l>Disturbs a person&#x02019;s sentiment as sneezing:</l>
                    <l>It takes you impudently by the nose;</l>
                    <l>Throws your component parts into confusion;</l>
                    <l>And shakes you up, as doctors shake a dose</l>
                    <l>In which they&#x02019;ve put some villainous infusion;</l>
                    <l>And the shrill echo in at both ears goes</l>
                    <l>With such a sharp and1 startling an intrusion,</l>
                    <l>Like a fell thunder clap by tempest brought,</l>
                    <l>Breaking the deep, still silence of your thought.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="31">
                    <head>31</head>
                    <l>And so I wished myself good luck, you know,</l>
                    <l>As many people do on like occasion:&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The Swiss takes off his hat with a low bow</l>
                    <l>To you, though in the midst of conversation;</l>
                    <l>And if you&#x02019;ve caught a little cold or so,</l>
                    <l>You keep your friend just in the situation</l>
                    <l>Of the caparisoned dragoon, with sword on</l>
                    <l>His side, well carved in wood, with wooden steed,</l>
                    <l>Placed the extremest limit of a board on:</l>
                    <l>Still up and down he goes, by ball of lead</l>
                    <l>Which slowly swings beneath him, ever spurred on:&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Thus at each sneeze your friend still bows his head;</l>
                    <l>In fact, the courteous Swiss puts off and on his</l>
                    <l>Hat, like a master of the ceremonies.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="32">
                    <head>32</head>
                    <l>A mountain walk by moonlight, people say,</l>
                    <l>Is interesting and poetical.</l>
                    <l>Some like to walk while twilight wastes away;</l>
                    <l>Some choose to be a peripatetic all</l>
                    <l>Night, and a very Stoic during day.</l>
                    <l>I am not given to be ecstatical</l>
                    <l>When I can&#x02019;t see, and therefore I descended;</l>
                    <l>Although the night that came was scarcely night,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>So softly with the air was starlight blended,</l>
                    <l>Like the sea&#x02019;s phosphor lustre, coldly bright;</l>
                    <l>The peaks above me, as I downward wended,</l>
                    <l>Grew misty in the ray so faint and white;</l>
                    <l>You could have thought, as, veil-like, you did view them,</l>
                    <l>That the moonbeams were shining through and through them.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="33">
                    <head>33</head>
                    <l>O redly broke the morn, and Jura smiled,</l>
                    <l>And all the plains awoke them from their slumber.</l>
                    <l>The morn! the morn! I heard along the wild</l>
                    <l>The torrents shouting with a voice of thunder.</l>
                    <l>Under the cliffs fantastically piled</l>
                    <l>We wound and left the city couching under:</l>
                    <l>Up on the mountain where the breeze is free,</l>
                    <l>Up on the mountain where the wild flowers grow,</l>
                    <l>Up on the mountain where with melody</l>
                    <l>The cataracts sing and tempests loudly blow,</l>
                    <l>Up on the mountain, where quick rushing by</l>
                    <l>Leaps like a lion the lavange,1<note xml:id="xmlidneeded16" n="16" resp="#DH"
                            place="botwin">Notation Needed</note> we go.</l>
                    <l>Farewell, ye plains, the rocks around I see,</l>
                    <l>The cloud, the storm, the mountain now for me!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="34">
                    <head>34</head>
                    <l>Thus did we leave Poligny, and to Morez</l>
                    <l>We went, which is an odd place in a hole,</l>
                    <l>Under huge cliffs built in successive stories</l>
                    <l>Of limestone, very pretty on the whole,</l>
                    <l>Swiss-ish, and picturesque, and so on: nor is</l>
                    <l>It far from the green summit of the Dôle</l>
                    <l>Which groves of tall and spiry pine embrace,</l>
                    <l>Which2<note xml:id="xmlidneeded17" n="17" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note> like a mantle of the deepest green,</l>
                    <l>Shadow its sides and darken round its base:</l>
                    <l>But grassily doth rise its crest; between</l>
                    <l>Its ridges and in every sheltered place</l>
                    <l>The wavy lines of whitest snow are seen:</l>
                    <l>Through the first summer months it wears them yet,</l>
                    <l>Like a large emerald in silver set.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="35">
                    <head>35</head>
                    <l>Reader, if you are trigonome&#x02014;, no! I</l>
                    <l>Can&#x02019;t manage that long word, which is a bother;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Trigonometrical, I&#x02019;ll tell you how high</l>
                    <l>It is above the Medi&#x02014;, there&#x02019;s
                        another!&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Mediterranean; and that will show why</l>
                    <l>The snow, although it melts some time or other,</l>
                    <l>Continues there so long. I&#x02019;ve calculated</l>
                    <l>It is [five] thousand and [five] hundred feet1<note xml:id="xmlidneeded18"
                            n="18" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>Above the sea: a summit, insulated</l>
                    <l>So high, is seldom subject to much heat,</l>
                    <l>And therefore, as above I have related,</l>
                    <l>Although the sun&#x02019;s rays may appear to beat</l>
                    <l>Warmly upon the grass with two&#x02019; ring glow,</l>
                    <l>They cannot melt the hard heart of the snow.2<note xml:id="xmlidneeded19"
                            n="19" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="36">
                    <head>36</head>
                    <l>And when the day is hot, at two o&#x02019;clock,</l>
                    <l>And trees and flowers are loaded with the heat,</l>
                    <l>And walnuts tall give shelter to the flock</l>
                    <l>That crowds3<note xml:id="xmlidneeded20" n="20" resp="#DH" place="botwin"
                            >Notation Needed</note> beneath their branches, then ‘tis sweet</l>
                    <l>To seek the shadow of some lofty rock</l>
                    <l>With a cool streamlet gurgling at your feet;</l>
                    <l>And when you&#x02019;ve scaped the power and the might</l>
                    <l>Of the fierce sun, and coolness fills your breast,</l>
                    <l>Then, to look up to some enormous height</l>
                    <l>Where winter sits for ever, and whose crest</l>
                    <l>Is lovely with the kisses of the light,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The ruby light that loves on it to rest,</l>
                    <l>And to feel breezes o&#x02019;er your features blown, is</l>
                    <l>Like eating raspberry ices at Tortoni&#x02019;s!4<note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded21" n="21" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdeefgfgfgcc" n="37">
                    <head>37</head>
                    <l>The meadows of these hills are like the robe,</l>
                    <l>Bedight with gems, of some high emperor:</l>
                    <l>There&#x02019;s not a spot in all this lovely globe</l>
                    <l>That&#x02019;s more abundant in its flowery store.</l>
                    <l>The Alpine rose along its ridges glowed,</l>
                    <l>The mountains burning with the fiery flower.</l>
                    <l>Queen of the blossoms in the fields below,</l>
                    <l>The silver lily lifted its pale head,</l>
                    <l>The emulation of the mountain snow.</l>
                    <l>Fresh emerald moss along the rocks was spread,</l>
                    <l>And hare bells trembling as the breezes blow,</l>
                    <l>And many another flower, of blue and red,</l>
                    <l>Purple and gold, too numerous to mention,</l>
                    <l>Half-drowned in dew, solicited attention.</l>
                    <l>Continues there so long. I&#x02019;ve calculated</l>
                    <l>It is [five] thousand and [five] hundred feet1<note xml:id="xmlidneeded22"
                            n="22" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>Above the sea: a summit, insulated</l>
                    <l>So high, is seldom subject to much heat,</l>
                    <l>And therefore, as above I have related,</l>
                    <l>Although the sun&#x02019;s rays may appear to beat</l>
                    <l>Warmly upon the grass with two&#x02019; ring glow,</l>
                    <l>They cannot melt the hard heart of the snow.2<note xml:id="xmlidneeded23"
                            n="23" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="36">
                    <head>36</head>
                    <l>And when the day is hot, at two o&#x02019;clock,</l>
                    <l>And trees and flowers are loaded with the heat,</l>
                    <l>And walnuts tall give shelter to the flock</l>
                    <l>That crowds3<note xml:id="xmlidneeded24" n="24" resp="#DH" place="botwin"
                            >Notation Needed</note> beneath their branches, then ‘tis sweet</l>
                    <l>To seek the shadow of some lofty rock</l>
                    <l>With a cool streamlet gurgling at your feet;</l>
                    <l>And when you&#x02019;ve scaped the power and the might</l>
                    <l>Of the fierce sun, and coolness fills your breast,</l>
                    <l>Then, to look up to some enormous height</l>
                    <l>Where winter sits for ever, and whose crest</l>
                    <l>Is lovely with the kisses of the light,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The ruby light that loves on it to rest,</l>
                    <l>And to feel breezes o&#x02019;er your features blown, is</l>
                    <l>Like eating raspberry ices at Tortoni&#x02019;s!4<note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded25" n="25" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="37">
                    <head>37</head>
                    <l>The meadows of these hills are like the robe,</l>
                    <l>Bedight with gems, of some high emperor:</l>
                    <l>There&#x02019;s not a spot in all this lovely globe</l>
                    <l>That&#x02019;s more abundant in its flowery store.</l>
                    <l>The Alpine rose along its ridges glowed,</l>
                    <l>The mountains burning with the fiery flower.</l>
                    <l>Queen of the blossoms in the fields below,</l>
                    <l>The silver lily lifted its pale head,</l>
                    <l>The emulation of the mountain snow.</l>
                    <l>Fresh emerald moss along the rocks was spread,</l>
                    <l>And hare bells trembling as the breezes blow,</l>
                    <l>And many another flower, of blue and red,</l>
                    <l>Purple and gold, too numerous to mention,</l>
                    <l>Half-drowned in dew, solicited attention.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="38">
                    <head>38</head>
                    <l>&#x02014;Attention difficult to give, when we</l>
                    <l>Saw such a scene of loveliness around;</l>
                    <l>Yet ‘twas not much amiss to stoop, and see</l>
                    <l>The beauty of that flower enamelled ground:</l>
                    <l>First, to behold the mountain&#x02019;s majesty,</l>
                    <l>Then, the fresh green of yonder mossy mound.</l>
                    <l>As when you enter some enormous pile&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Gothic cathedral very ancient,</l>
                    <l>First, you admire what people call the style</l>
                    <l>And massive wholeness of the monument,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Magnificent effect of done and aisle,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>And next, you view the lavish ornament</l>
                    <l>That&#x02019;s carved on every part, but all intended</l>
                    <l>To make the general effect more splendid.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="39">
                    <head>39</head>
                    <l>Thus on the Jura did we gaze, beholding</l>
                    <l>A monument enormous everywhere:</l>
                    <l>The hills, that on their shoulders seemed upholding</l>
                    <l>The high blue dome that looked above the air;</l>
                    <l>Groves of dark pines their scarped crags enfolding;</l>
                    <l>Rocks raised like castles from their summits bare,</l>
                    <l>In many a varied form: and then did look</l>
                    <l>At the most rich and intricate detail;</l>
                    <l>The coloured marks in yonder marble rock,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The green moss that hangs o&#x02019;er it like a veil,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The turf inlaid with flowers,&#x02014;the crystal brook</l>
                    <l>That ever tells its never varied tale</l>
                    <l>Unto the air, that sporteth with its spray,</l>
                    <l>And sings, and sings, [and sings]1 to it all day.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="40">
                    <head>40</head>
                    <l>Give me a broken rock, a little moss,</l>
                    <l>A barberry tree with fixed branches clinging,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>A stream that clearly at its bottom shows</l>
                    <l>The polished pebbles with its ripples ringing;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>These to be placed at nature&#x02019;s sweet dispose,</l>
                    <l>And decked with grass and flowers of her bringing;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>And I would ask no more; for I would dream</l>
                    <l>Of greater things associated with these,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Would see a mighty river in my stream,</l>
                    <l>And, in my rock, a mountain clothed with trees.</l>
                    <l>For nature&#x02019;s work is lovely to be seen;</l>
                    <l>Her finished part as finished whole will please;</l>
                    <l>And this should be a mountain-scene to me&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>My broken rock, my stream, and barberry tree.1<note xml:id="xmlidneeded26"
                            n="26" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="41">
                    <head>41</head>
                    <l>I&#x02019;m going to turn a corner,&#x02014;which I&#x02019;ve
                        done</l>
                    <l>A hundred or a thousand times before!</l>
                    <l>But this is really a distinguished one,</l>
                    <l>And needs a little preparation, for</l>
                    <l>The shock of it is quite enough to stun</l>
                    <l>You, like a box upon the ear, and floor</l>
                    <l>Your very feelings, that you will not move</l>
                    <l>A muscle of your body, nor will dare</l>
                    <l>To breathe the breezes that about you rove.</l>
                    <l>You could chastise the movement of the air</l>
                    <l>While drinking in the beauty that you love!</l>
                    <l>Some cannot that delicious rapture share;</l>
                    <l>Those who feel little, talk, and rant, and vapour,</l>
                    <l>Kick up their heels, prance, frisk, curvet, and caper.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdeefghihihijj" n="42">
                    <head>42</head>
                    <l>Mighty Mont Blanc, thou hast been with me still</l>
                    <l>Wherever I have been! In the dark night</l>
                    <l>I&#x02019;ve walked upon thy visionary hill,</l>
                    <l>And have been filled with infinte delight:</l>
                    <l>And when I woke, it was against my will.</l>
                    <l>Though then I did not have thee in my sight,</l>
                    <l>Still wert thou like a guiding star, and all</l>
                    <l>My hope was to be with thee once again,</l>
                    <l>Hearing thy avalanches&#x02019; fearful fall.</l>
                    <l>I was bound to thee by a pleasant chain,</l>
                    <l>And I am here in answer to thy call!</l>
                    <l>I see thee rise o&#x02019;er younder lordly plain,</l>
                    <l>Like nothing else i&#x02019; the world; for thou hast stood</l>
                    <l>Unrivalled still, thine own similitude!<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded27" n="27" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>Splintered, and crushed,&#x02014;a direful token of</l>
                    <l>Ancient convulsions of their majesty.</l>
                    <l>There is Jorasse, Midi, and spiry Dru,</l>
                    <l>And the Géant, and high Argentière:</l>
                    <l>And dark and scowlingly they look at you.</l>
                    <l>There&#x02019;s not a spot of vegetation there&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Even where the hand of winter cannot strew</l>
                    <l>Snows on the sides, so splintered and so bare,</l>
                    <l>With granite points upon their rugged flanks,</l>
                    <l>Like spears of the archangels&#x02019; military ranks.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="52">
                    <head>52</head>
                    <l>But on your left a softer scene appears,</l>
                    <l>Where the lake spreads out its metallic glow.</l>
                    <l>No mountain there its scraggy outline rears,</l>
                    <l>But all is peaceful,&#x02014;beautifully so!</l>
                    <l>Some little bark in distance fades, or nears</l>
                    <l>With forked canvass flitting to and fro</l>
                    <l>Over the dimples of its polished face.</l>
                    <l>Many a field and many a garden gay</l>
                    <l>Bedeck the Voirons&#x02019; gently sloping base;</l>
                    <l>At these you look and wonder, day by day,</l>
                    <l>So that Geneva is a pleasant place</l>
                    <l>Whereat to make a week&#x02019;s or fortnight&#x02019;s stay,</l>
                    <l>To rest and to enjoy yourself at; and to</l>
                    <l>End a long journey, and a tiresome canto.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="1">
                    <head rend="caps">CANTO II</head>
                    <head>1</head>
                    <l>You who are tired of journeying with me</l>
                    <l>May stick here if you like, nor read my rhyme.</l>
                    <l>You who desire a few more sights to see,</l>
                    <l>Cities more splendid, scenery more sublime,</l>
                    <l>Come on, I&#x02019;m going to start, and instantly&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>No stopping, no delaying, I&#x02019;ve no time.</l>
                    <l>I will invoke no muses: I can do</l>
                    <l>Without &#x02019;em, and my Pegasus goes first;</l>
                    <l>I&#x02019;m not upon Parnassus, it is true,</l>
                    <l>But soon midst higher mountains shall be lost.</l>
                    <l>And, gentle reader, I will carry you</l>
                    <l>Where upon frozen ocean&#x02019;s Alpine coast</l>
                    <l>Are streams as sweet as any Heliconian,</l>
                    <l>Fit to inspire the soul of a Maronian.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded28" n="28" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="2">
                    <head>2</head>
                    <l>We left Geneva. &#x02019;Tis against the grain</l>
                    <l>From such a lovely place yourself to sever,</l>
                    <l>Knowing that you will not be there again</l>
                    <l>For a long time at least,&#x02014;and perhaps never.</l>
                    <l>I must confess I crossed the bridge with pain,</l>
                    <l>The bridge that arches o&#x02019;er a rushing river.</l>
                    <l>But up my heart leaped with a bound once more</l>
                    <l>When, full in front, increasing as we went,</l>
                    <l>The ancient mountain stood, with glaciers hoar.</l>
                    <l>And entering the valley, which is rent</l>
                    <l>Between the Môle and Brezon (I before</l>
                    <l>Have spoken of it<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded29"
                            n="29" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note>), I grew quite
                        content,</l>
                    <l>And ceased to sigh, though I no more could see of</l>
                    <l>Geneva&#x02019;s spires, which there are two or three of.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="3">
                    <head>3</head>
                    <l>Our road fast brings us nearer to the Môle,</l>
                    <l>And we shall pass beneath it presently.</l>
                    <l>The Môle&#x02014;now don&#x02019;t confuse it with the
                        Dôle,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>There is a difference between M and D&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The Môle, I say, sir, is upon the whole</l>
                    <l>A lovely mountain as you&#x02019;d wish to see.</l>
                    <l>Those who for height alone inclined to stickle are</l>
                    <l>May say that it is nothing of a height;<hi rend="superscript">3</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded30" n="30" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>[Six] thousand feet, or something, perpendicular:</l>
                    <l>That&#x02019;s quite contemptible!&#x02014;and they are right!</l>
                    <l>But I<hi rend="superscript">4</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded31" n="31"
                            resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note> am not at all
                        particular,</l>
                    <l>So that a mountain&#x02019;s aspect please the sight;</l>
                    <l>And even to look up so high makes one feel</l>
                    <l>Stiff i&#x02019; the neck, from such a place as Bonneville.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="4">
                    <head>4</head>
                    <l>They told me things about the Môle, on which</l>
                    <l>I was incredulous, and quite refractory.</l>
                    <l>They said &#x02019;twas shaped exactly like the ridge</l>
                    <l>Of some spare, lean old gentleman&#x02019;s olfactory&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>A sharp and regular and well-formed ridge,</l>
                    <l>You scarcely could believe the fact, nor I.</l>
                    <l>Seen from Geneva, ‘tis a pyramid,</l>
                    <l>Sharp, high, and pointed, for beheld from thence</l>
                    <l>Its back by its extremity is hid.</l>
                    <l>But here the ridge is lengthened and immense,</l>
                    <l>Furrowed by avalanches, which have slid</l>
                    <l>Down its steep sides, and with magnificence</l>
                    <l>Of verdure robed; indeed, there&#x02019;s not a spot on</l>
                    <l>Its sloping flanks of snow from top to bottom.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="5">
                    <head>5</head>
                    <l>And on the other side appears the Brezon,<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded32" n="32" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>A lofty precipice of limestone hoar.</l>
                    <l>Monsieur Saussure, who used to lay much stress on</l>
                    <l>Necessity of practising, before</l>
                    <l>You venture into danger (and with reason),</l>
                    <l>Used to climb up, and poke his numskull o&#x02019;er</l>
                    <l>Couched on his breast,&#x02014;a ticklish situation</l>
                    <l>For those who are not thorough mountain bred!</l>
                    <l>Oh, Shakespeare! when the paltry elevation</l>
                    <l>Of Dover&#x02019;s promontory filled thy head</l>
                    <l>With dizziness and instant inspiration,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Oh, Master Shakespeare, what would&#x02019;st thou have said</l>
                    <l>If, &#x02019;stead of poor four hundred, as at Dover</l>
                    <l>Thou hadst looked down four thousand feet, and over?</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="6">
                    <head>6</head>
                    <l>Tell me of crows and choughs,&#x02014;a pretty thing!</l>
                    <l>Why, man, you could not see a flying cow</l>
                    <l>A quarter down!&#x02014;or samphire gatherer swing,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Such nonsense!&#x02014;here were room and height enow</l>
                    <l>To hang a dozen of &#x02019;em in a string,</l>
                    <l>Nor see the topmost from the mountain&#x02019;s brow.</l>
                    <l>&#x0201C;Not leap aloft<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded33"
                            n="33" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note> for all beneath
                        the moon?&#x0201D;</l>
                    <l>&#x02014;No, nor leap backward from the verge of fear</l>
                    <l>For all beneath the shine of stars of sun.</l>
                    <l>&#x0201C;Not hear the sea?&#x0201D;<hi rend="superscript">3</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded34"
                            n="34" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note> why, here you
                        could not hear</l>
                    <l>The echo of the chamois hunter&#x02019;s gun</l>
                    <l>Fired at the bottom of the cliff so sheer!</l>
                    <l>The vallies lying in the mountain&#x02019;s lap</l>
                    <l>Look like a pretty little pocket-map!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="7">
                    <head>7</head>
                    <l>Onward we went; and as we went, the cloud</l>
                    <l>Fretted the sunny sky with silver white,</l>
                    <l>Like Gothic carving on a temple proud;</l>
                    <l>Pale at the first, and shadowy, and light;</l>
                    <l>Then darker and distincter, like a shroud</l>
                    <l>Stooped upon each surrounding wintry height.</l>
                    <l>For these, where&#x02019;er in heaven the clouds are tost,<hi
                            rend="superscript">1</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded35" n="35" resp="#DH"
                            place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>Do gather them together, and wrap over</l>
                    <l>Their naked sides, all comfortless with frost.</l>
                    <l>Above us, wreathed like smoke the cloudy cover,</l>
                    <l>And half-way down the higher hills were lost;</l>
                    <l>But here and there by chance you might discover</l>
                    <l>A spire of ice, incredibly on high,</l>
                    <l>Start like a meteor through the misty sky.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="8">
                    <head>8</head>
                    <l>Onward we went, in&#x02014;what&#x02019;s the name of
                        it?&#x02014;I</l>
                    <l>Really don&#x02019;t know if it has any name,</l>
                    <l>The vale &#x02019;twixt Cluse and Bonneville, which looks pretty</l>
                    <l>At summer&#x02019;s early glow; though at the same</l>
                    <l>Time it is liable&#x02014;which is a pity&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>To the attacks of water, wind, and flame.</l>
                    <l>You ask, at its wild beauty wondering,</l>
                    <l>How can the place be such a flat as to</l>
                    <l>Permit the Arve its turbid waves to fling</l>
                    <l>Over its greenest fields, and to renew</l>
                    <l>An annual devastation? till some king<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded36" n="36" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>(A monument&#x02019;s built to him) passing through</l>
                    <l>Bonneville (just at the bridge-end mark you it?)</l>
                    <l>&#x0201C;Aggeribus haec flumina coercuit.&#x0201D;</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="9">
                    <head>9</head>
                    <l>But when the fierce and unrelenting heat</l>
                    <l>Of summer doth oppress the weary stream,</l>
                    <l>Along the hills the rays, all burning, beat,</l>
                    <l>And the hot valley pants beneath the beam.</l>
                    <l>The glowing soil beneath you fires your feet</l>
                    <l>And tires your eyesight with an arid gleam.</l>
                    <l>Once,&#x02014;&#x02019;twas a marvellous and fearful
                        thing,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The trees took fire beneath the glowing soil;</l>
                    <l>Wide Conflagration spread his purple wing:</l>
                    <l>Vainly the frighted peasants pant and toil,</l>
                    <l>Vainly dig channels for the crystal spring;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The helpless waters in their channel[boil],<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded37" n="37" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>And a red Autumn in an instant came,</l>
                    <l>And Nature withered &#x02019;neath her glance of flame.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="10">
                    <head>10</head>
                    <l>But when, in furry robe of whitest snow,</l>
                    <l>The Winter spreads his desolate dominion,</l>
                    <l>Forth come the winds, and loudly do they blow,</l>
                    <l>And, like an eagle poised on threatening pinion,</l>
                    <l>Swoop in wide circles round the plain below.</l>
                    <l>And when a tempest once begins within one</l>
                    <l>Of these low mountain-vallies, many a tree</l>
                    <l>That long firm-rooted in their earth have stood</l>
                    <l>Bow their old heads<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded38"
                            n="38" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note> before it
                        painfully;</l>
                    <l>And all the plain, obscured with hoary wood,</l>
                    <l>Undulates like the variable sea:</l>
                    <l>The very river backward rolls his flood,</l>
                    <l>Shakes the far mountains with his echoing roar,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Heaves his white crest on high, and deluges his shore.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="11">
                    <head>11</head>
                    <l>And now the bridge of Cluse is gained and past:</l>
                    <l>Sharp turns the road to enter the ravine</l>
                    <l>Cloven in the hills as by some weapon vast.</l>
                    <l>The river takes his rushing path between;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>I would not be the Arve, to fly so fast</l>
                    <l>Through the variety of such a scene!</l>
                    <l>From side to side, from crag to crag rebounding,</l>
                    <l>Sheeted with foam, as is the spurred war-horse,</l>
                    <l>So leaps the river, that the rocks around him<hi rend="superscript"
                            >3</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded39" n="39" resp="#DH" place="botwin"
                            >Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>Are formed and chiselled by his constant force.</l>
                    <l>With bursting echoes quake the cliffs resounding,</l>
                    <l>No deepness stills, no barrier checks his course;</l>
                    <l>On, ever on, the maddened billows sweep,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Rest in no pool, nor by their border sleep.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="12">
                    <head>12</head>
                    <l>The castellated cliffs stand o&#x02019;er your head</l>
                    <l>Broken, as is the war worn battlement.</l>
                    <l>But, as if its defenders were not fled,</l>
                    <l>Bristle the pines above their summits rent</l>
                    <l>Like a well-ordered army. Bare and red</l>
                    <l>Gleam their high flanks, and beautifully blent</l>
                    <l>Are moss, and turf, and crag, wet with the spray</l>
                    <l>Of yon aërial stream, which long ago</l>
                    <l>We saw in distance glittering down, and gay</l>
                    <l>With its broad, beautiful, perpetual bow</l>
                    <l>Belted about its column, as the ray</l>
                    <l>Shoots through the dissipated drops below,</l>
                    <l>Like dew descending, or soft April showers</l>
                    <l>Bathing in sunshine the delighted flowers.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded40" n="40" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="13">
                    <head>13</head>
                    <l>Oh, gently sinks the eve, and red [doth]<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded41" n="41" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note> set</l>
                    <l>The sun above Sallenches&#x02019; mountains blue;</l>
                    <l>Like regal robes, the purple clouds beset</l>
                    <l>Mont Blanc; but on his crest, still breaking through,</l>
                    <l>The last bright western rays are lingering yet,</l>
                    <l>And the white snow glows with a rosy hue.</l>
                    <l>And now it fades, and now is past away;</l>
                    <l>The highest dome among the stars is white;</l>
                    <l>It seems to wake, and watch the night away<hi rend="superscript">3</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded42" n="42" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>And kindle at the first gleam of the light,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>A mighty beacon, to proclaim the day,</l>
                    <l>A beacon fit to meet the gladdened sight</l>
                    <l>Of half the world, from Gallia&#x02019;s plains of vine</l>
                    <l>Unto the distant ridge of the blue Apennine.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdefghghghii" n="14">
                    <head>14</head>
                    <l>The morning came; delightful was the weather.</l>
                    <l>Up to the door with rattling rumble daundered</l>
                    <l>Those very strange compounds of wood and leather:&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Oh, char-à-banc, thou vehicle most honoured</l>
                    <l>Of all the vehicles e&#x02019;er put together!</l>
                    <l>What though thy cushions be to sit upon hard,</l>
                    <l>And though they scarce can hold their well-squeezed three,</l>
                    <l>And though thou lookest ancient, worn and brown,</l>
                    <l>Want, or may possibly require: twines cracking, too,</l>
                    <l>Things tumbling down because they cannot stand well:&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>And &#x0201C;tie that there,&#x0201D; and then, &#x0201C;tie that thing to it,</l>
                    <l>And tie this on the top of them; and that thing</l>
                    <l>Must go between your legs;&#x02014;ay, so you&#x02019;ll do
                        it;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>And this behind your back, it is a flat thing;</l>
                    <l>This on your knee.&#x0201D;&#x02014;No, thank ye; I&#x02019;ll give you
                        it!&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>&#x0201C;This in your pocket.&#x0201D;&#x02014;How that bottle&#x02019;s
                        rattling!</l>
                    <l>&#x0201C;Dear me, it&#x02019;s loose; how lucky you have spoken!&#x0201D;</l>
                    <l>Smash! &#x0201C;That&#x02019;s the tumbler; hope it is not broken!&#x0201D;</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="18">
                    <head>18</head>
                    <l>We&#x02019;d sixteen miles to go, or thereabout.</l>
                    <l>That, among hills, is something appetising.</l>
                    <l>Hadst seen us, you&#x02019;d have said, I make no doubt,</l>
                    <l>Our provend preparation was surprising:</l>
                    <l>With lemonade (you cannot get brown stout,</l>
                    <l>The creamy bubbles through its crystal rising),</l>
                    <l>Bottles of wine and brandy, butter, bread,</l>
                    <l>Cheese of the finest,&#x02014;cream and rich Gruyère;</l>
                    <l>Strawberry jam upon our crusts to spread,</l>
                    <l>And many a purple plum, and golden pear,</l>
                    <l>And polished apples, blushing rosy red;</l>
                    <l>Ham, beef, and bacon, slices rich and rare;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>We found our knives and dishes useful; you</l>
                    <l>On carrying them may find them useful too.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcee" n="19">
                    <head>19</head>
                    <l>Thus from St. Martin&#x02019;s gate we made our start, I</l>
                    <l>Following in the second char-à-banc.</l>
                    <l>Behind us in a third there came a party</l>
                    <l>Who, dashing down for Italy point blank,</l>
                    <l>Here from their route had ventured to depart; we</l>
                    <l>Found them agreeable, and free, and frank.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded43" n="43" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>There was a sort of middle-aged old lady,</l>
                    <l>And a not very young young lady too;</l>
                    <l>A miss beginning to be sage and steady,</l>
                    <l>And advice-giving, and her brother, who</l>
                    <l>Was younger, had a great deal in his head; he</l>
                    <l>Knew Greek, French, Latin, had not time to dally in</l>
                    <l>What he left to the ladies&#x02014;the Italian.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="20">
                    <head>20</head>
                    <l>Thus from St. Martin&#x02019;s gate we rolled away;</l>
                    <l>We found at first the motion rather tiring,</l>
                    <l>Loquacious we as crickets are, and gay,</l>
                    <l>Arranging, rearranging, and admiring.</l>
                    <l>Poking our heads this, that, and every way,</l>
                    <l>Murmuring and pushing, packing and perspiring.</l>
                    <l>The day was very hot, and quite a smotherer,</l>
                    <l>That makes one drowsy, which is very odd.</l>
                    <l>[Some of us,]<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded44" n="44"
                            resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation Needed</note> who inclined to make a
                        pother were,</l>
                    <l>Quite disturbed those who were inclined to nod</l>
                    <l>By playing at bopeep with those in t&#x02019;other char,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Popping behind the leathern curtains broad.</l>
                    <l>I was ashamed, and told them&#x02014;&#x0201C;no more gammon! I</l>
                    <l>Think that a shocking way of going to Chamouni!&#x0201D;</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="21">
                    <head>21</head>
                    <l>There is a little and a quiet lake,<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded45" n="45" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>And lovely are its waters, hardly seen,</l>
                    <l>Lying beneath the shelter of a brake,</l>
                    <l>Like the spring turf beneath its foliage green;</l>
                    <l>And where the sunbeams through the leavage break</l>
                    <l>They dive beneath its waters, with a sheen</l>
                    <l>Such as the moon sheds on the midnight deep,</l>
                    <l>When mermaids, issuing from their coral caves,</l>
                    <l>With shelly voices sing the seas to sleep,</l>
                    <l>And scatter wayward lustre o&#x02019;er the waves.</l>
                    <l>Forth the stream issues with a hurried leap</l>
                    <l>Down its rock-girded channel, which it paves</l>
                    <l>With many a ball of alabaster white,</l>
                    <l>And marble gay, and crystal clear and bright:&#x02014;</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="22">
                    <head>22</head>
                    <l>Not clearer than its waters, which receive</l>
                    <l>The image of Mont Blanc upon their breast,</l>
                    <l>Nor, with the motion of one ripple, heave</l>
                    <l>The quiet snow on his reversed crest,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>So beautiful the scene, you might believe</l>
                    <l>A limner, &#x02019;mid the fairies deemed the best,</l>
                    <l>Had painted it with natural colours fair,</l>
                    <l>And put the water o&#x02019;er it for a glass,</l>
                    <l>And framed it in, with fretwork rich and rare</l>
                    <l>Of jewel-flowers, and moss, and daisied grass.</l>
                    <l>How sweetly sounds the gurgle through the air</l>
                    <l>Of the cool, dancing streamlet, as you pass:</l>
                    <l>There is no music pleases you so truly</l>
                    <l>As gush of waters in the heat of July.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="23">
                    <head>23</head>
                    <l>By slow degrees and winding pathway mounting,</l>
                    <l>Onward we went the ancient pines among;</l>
                    <l>By many a trickling stream and gushing fountain</l>
                    <l>O&#x02019;er the rough bed of many a torrent strong,</l>
                    <l>Amid the wreck of Servoz&#x02019; ruined mountain,<hi rend="superscript"
                            >1</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded46" n="46" resp="#DH" place="botwin"
                            >Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>So beautiful in ruins. Far along,</l>
                    <l>And up the ridge, amid whose granites grey</l>
                    <l>Struggles the Arve, you hear the constant cry</l>
                    <l>Of waters, though unseen they wind their way</l>
                    <l>A hundred fathom down. In front, on high</l>
                    <l>The glacier flashes in the noontide ray,</l>
                    <l>In the deep azure of the Alpine sky.</l>
                    <l>And now the ridge is won: rest, rest, and see</l>
                    <l>What lies beneath you now; for there is Chamouni!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="24">
                    <head>24</head>
                    <l>Like the Elysian fields where rove the blest,</l>
                    <l>Though round them reaches the Tartarean wild,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Thus lies the enchanted vale, and all that&#x02019;s best</l>
                    <l>Of spring and summer&#x02019;s lavished on their child.<hi
                            rend="superscript">2</hi><note xml:id="xmlidneeded47" n="47" resp="#DH"
                            place="botwin">Notation Needed</note></l>
                    <l>While, round the space where those green meadows rest,</l>
                    <l>Is mountain chaos, like a barrier, piled,</l>
                    <l>And Winter holds an undisputed reign;</l>
                    <l>The chilly fingered tempest winds that go</l>
                    <l>On waving wings along the hills amain</l>
                    <l>Shake not a blossom in the fields below;</l>
                    <l>And every sunbeam that, with effort vain,</l>
                    <l>Strikes on the cold and unrelenting snow,</l>
                    <l>Seeks the sweet covert of the sheltered plain,</l>
                    <l>And lies delighted upon flowers again.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdee" n="25">
                    <head>25</head>
                    <l>The King of mountains, clothed in cloudy veil,</l>
                    <l>Asserts his rule upon the meadows green,</l>
                    <l>And lays his sceptre on the subject dale&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Sceptre of silver ice, whose spires were seen</l>
                    <l>And many a minaret of crystal pale</l>
                    <l>Rising above the pines with silver sheen.</l>
                    <l>Oh, beautiful, how beautiful to see</l>
                    <l>The summer sun on tower and bastion beaming,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Their bases beaten by a frozen sea,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>The moveless foam upon its breakers gleaming;</l>
                    <l>And from a mighty portal constantly</l>
                    <l>A sparkling river through the valley streaming;</l>
                    <l>For here&#x02019;s the company of glaciers, that is</l>
                    <l>Supplying all the world with water, gratis!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abababcdcdcdeefgfgii" n="26">
                    <head>26</head>
                    <l>Then we descended, through the valley going,</l>
                    <l>Till the small village in the front was seen</l>
                    <l>With its low spire conspicuously glowing,</l>
                    <l>(For here they cover all their spires with tin,</l>
                    <l>Which makes them sparkle in the distance, showing</l>
                    <l>Like diamond in gentleman&#x02019;s breast-pin).</l>
                    <l>Here there are several hotels; but which of them</l>
                    <l>May be the best, is difficult to say.</l>
                    <l>Accommodation may be found at each of them;</l>
                    <l>But don&#x02019;t believe those fellows on the way,&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>They&#x02019;ll recommend the worst, if you trust speech of them!</l>
                    <l>The Union seems the largest and most gay;</l>
                    <l>Of which I&#x02019;ll give you an exact description,</l>
                    <l>Because it was the place of our reception.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded48" n="48" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    <l>Up went the casement: there I took my stand,</l>
                    <l>Stupidly of the scene to take my fill:</l>
                    <l>My head dropped somehow down upon my hand</l>
                    <l>Sleep-like; and I became exceeding still.</l>
                    <l>Sometimes, when such a glory you espy,</l>
                    <l>The body seems to sleep,&#x02014;the soul goes to the eye.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aba" n="30">
                    <head>30</head>
                    <l>The noonday clouds across the heaven were rolled,</l>
                    <l>With many a lengthened vista opening through,</l>
                    <l>Where many a gorgeous wave of white and gold</l>
                </lg>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
