<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Walk in Chamouni</title>
                <title type="sub">etext generated from a transcription of a manuscript</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>Louisiana Board of Regents</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>ERM version 1.0 encoded Oct. 2009</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>000019</idno>
                <date when="2010-06-08">June 8 2010</date>
                <distributor>The Early Ruskin Manuscripts Project</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>###INSERT COPYRIGHT STATEMENT###</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="influence">###Insert notation of poetic influences here###</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <!-- possibly change to <msDesc> tag-->
                    <author>John Ruskin</author>
                    <title>Walk in Chamouni</title>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from original manuscript</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
          <body>
            <div type="poem">
                <head rend="caps">A Walk In Chamouni<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><ptr
                        target="targetneeded"/></head>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abaabcdcdd" n="1">
                    <l>Together on the valley, white and sweet,</l>
                    <l>The dew and silence of the morning lay:</l>
                    <l>Only the tread of my disturbing feet</l>
                    <l>Did break, with printed shade and patient beat,</l>
                    <l>The crispèd stillness of the meadow way;</l>
                    <l>And frequent mountain waters, welling up</l>
                    <l>In crystal gloom beneath some mouldering stone,</l>
                    <l>Curdled in many a flower-enamelled cup,</l>
                    <l>Whose soft and purple border, scarcely blown,</l>
                    <l>Budded beneath their touch, and trembled to their tone.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abaabcdcddefeef" n="2">
                    <l>The fringèd branches of the swinging pines</l>
                    <l>Closed o&#x02019;er my path; a darkness in the sky,</l>
                    <l>That barred its dappled vault with rugged lines,</l>
                    <l>And silver network,*&#x02014;interwoven signs</l>
                    <l>Of dateless age and deathless infancy;</l>
                    <l>Then through their aisles a motion and a brightness</l>
                    <l>Kindled and shook&#x02014;the weight of shade they bore</l>
                    <l>On their broad arms was lifted by the lightness</l>
                    <l>Of a soft, shuddering wind, and what they wore</l>
                    <l>Of jewelled dew, was strewed about the forest floor.</l>
                    <l>That thrill of gushing wind and glittering rain</l>
                    <l>Onward amid the woodland hollows went;</l>
                    <l>And bade by turns the drooping boughs complain</l>
                    <l>O&#x02019;er the brown earth, that drank in lightless stain</l>
                    <l>The beauty of their burning ornament;</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="ababbcdccdefeffghiihjkjkklmnnm" n="3">
                    <l>And then the roar of an enormous river</l>
                    <l>Came on the intermittent air uplifted,</l>
                    <l>Broken with haste, I saw its sharp waves shiver,</l>
                    <l>And its wild weight in white disorder drifted,</l>
                    <l>Where by its beaten shore the rocks lay heaped and rifted.</l>
                    <l>But yet unshattered, from an azure arch*</l>
                    <l>Came forth the nodding waters, wave by wave,</l>
                    <l>In silver lines of modulated march,</l>
                    <l>Through a broad desert, which the frost-winds parch</l>
                    <l>Like fire, and the resounding ice-falls pave</l>
                    <l>With pallid ruin&#x02014;wastes of rock&#x02014;that share</l>
                    <l>Earth&#x02019;s calm and ocean&#x02019;s fruitlessness.† Undone</l>
                    <l>The work of ages lies,&#x02014;through whose despair</l>
                    <l>Their swift procession dancing in the sun,</l>
                    <l>The white and whirling waves pass mocking one by one.</l>
                    <l>And with their voice&#x02014;unquiet melody&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>Is filled the hollow of their mighty portal,</l>
                    <l>As shells are with remembrance of the sea;</l>
                    <l>So might the eternal arch of Eden be</l>
                    <l>With angels&#x02019; wail for those whose crowns immortal</l>
                    <l>The grave-dust dimmed in passing. There are here,</l>
                    <l>With azure wings and scimitars of fire,</l>
                    <l>Forms as of heaven, to guard the gate, and rear</l>
                    <l>Their burning arms afar,&#x02014;a boundless choir</l>
                    <l>Beneath the sacred shafts of many a mountain spire.</l>
                    <l>Countless as clouds, dome, prism, and pyramid</l>
                    <l>Pierced through the mist of morning scarce withdrawn,</l>
                    <l>Signing the gloom like beacon fires, half hid</l>
                    <l>By storm&#x02014;part quenched in billows&#x02014;or forbid</l>
                    <l>Their function by the fulness of the dawn:</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="ababacdccddedeefgffghihiijkj" n="4">
                    <l>And melting mists and threads of purple rain</l>
                    <l>Fretted the fair sky where the east was red,</l>
                    <l>Gliding like ghosts along the voiceless plain,</l>
                    <l>In rainbow hues around its coldness shed,</l>
                    <l>Like thoughts of loving hearts that haunt about the dead.</l>
                    <l>And over these, as pure as if the breath</l>
                    <l>Of God had called them newly into light,</l>
                    <l>Free from all stamp of sin, or shade of death,</l>
                    <l>With which the old creation travaileth,</l>
                    <l>Rose the white mountains, through the infinite</l>
                    <l>Of the calm, concave heaven; inly bright</l>
                    <l>With lustre everlasting and intense;</l>
                    <l>Serene and universal as the night,</l>
                    <l>But yet more solemn with pervading sense</l>
                    <l>Of the deep stillness of Omnipotence.</l>
                    <l>Deep stillness! for the throbs of human thought</l>
                    <l>Count not the lonely night that pauses here;</l>
                    <l>And the white arch of morning findeth not,</l>
                    <l>By chasm or alp, a spirit, or a spot</l>
                    <l>Its call can waken or its beams can cheer:</l>
                    <l>There are no eyes to watch, no lips to meet</l>
                    <l>Its messages with prayer&#x02014;no matin bell</l>
                    <l>Touches the delicate air with summons sweet;&#x02014;</l>
                    <l>That smoke was of the avalanche;* that knell</l>
                    <l>Came from a tower of ice that into fragments fell.</l>
                    <l>Ah! why should that be comfortless&#x02014;why cold,</l>
                    <l>Which is so near to heaven? The lowly earth,</l>
                    <l>Out of the blackness of its charnel mould,</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza" rhyme="abbcbcc" n="5">
                    <l>Feeds its fresh life, and lights its banks with gold;</l>
                    <l>But these proud summits, in eternal dearth,</l>
                    <l>Whose solitudes nor mourning know, nor mirth,</l>
                    <l>Rise passionless and pure, but all unblest:</l>
                    <l>Corruption&#x02014;must it root the brightest birth?</l>
                    <l>And is the life that bears its fruitage best,</l>
                    <l>One neither of supremacy nor rest?</l>
                    <l>[Age 24.]</l>
                    <!--this is not a line in the poem... what would it be...?  a signature?-->
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
