<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;Title of Work&#x201d;</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from a Transcription of the MS Draft/Fair Copy Name/Number</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                    <!--Example entries have been provided for MS I from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <country type="nation">United States of America</country>
                        <region type="state">Connecticut</region>
                        <settlement type="city">New Haven</settlement>
                        <institution>Yale University</institution>
                        <repository>Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</repository>
                        <collection>MS Vault Ruskin</collection>
                        <idno>"Harry &#x0026; Lucy, Poems &#x0026;c"</idno>
                        <msName>MS I</msName>
                        <msName>"Red book No. 3"</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <locus facs="image.jpg image.jpg">pp. ##-##</locus>
                            <note>For a discussion of foliation, see <ref type="apparatus" target="tite_of_apparatus.html#MAJORMS">"Title of Work": Manuscripts</ref>.</note>
                            <filiation><!--Entry needed here.--></filiation>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <!--If additional entries are made below, the hands count must be increased.-->
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote corresp="#HANDJR1826-27" scribe="JR">
                                <p>John Ruskin's early boyhood hand, circa <date notBefore="1826" notAfter="1827">1826-27</date>,
                                    examples of which can be found in MS I, pages <locus from="##" to="##">##-##</locus>.</p>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="witness" subtype="poem" rhyme="ababbcbcc">
                <head type="title"><handShift new="#HANDJR1833-34" script="cursive" medium="pencil"/><placeName corresp="#ATHENS">Athens</placeName></head>
                <lg type="strophe">
                    <l>Thou muse who once from <hi rend="underline">fair</hi> <placeName corresp="#PARNASSUS">Parnassus</placeName> height</l>
                    <l>Fanned agèd <persName corresp="#HOMER">Homer</persName> with thy plumy wings</l>
                    <l><hi rend="underline">Who</hi> told of <placeName corresp="#GREECE">Greece</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#TROY">Trojas</placeName> ancient might</l>
                    <l><del rend="strikethrough">And fierce <persName type="fictional" corresp="#ACHILLES">Achilles</persName> anger! Thou, that</del><add place="below">&#x2038;</add> <add place="above">O thou whose lyre all wild resounding</add> sings</l>
                    <l>Of the war field where the broad banner flings</l>
                    <l>Its folds oer many a corse of heroes slain</l>
                    <l><del rend="strikethrough">Sing</del>Now sing once more of ancient Græcias kings</l>
                    <l>Who fought against a haughty tyrants chain</l>
                    <l>Take up thy lyre, awake its <add place="below">&#x2038;</add><add place="above">slumbring</add> voice again</l></lg>
                        
                <lg n="2" type="strophe">
                    <head type="strophe_number">2</head>
                    <l><add place="above">Oer the <unclear resp="#CJL">wide</unclear> fi</add>
                            <delSpan rend="strikethrough"></delSpan>
                            O ancient <placeName corresp="#ATHENS">Athens</placeName> thou who once didst reign</l>
                    <l>Oer the wide fields of sea encircled <placeName corresp="#GREECE">Greece</placeName></l>
                    <l>Ruler of <placeName corresp="#THEBES">Thebes</placeName> 
                            and rugged <placeName corresp="#SPARTA">Spa</placeName></l>
                    </lg>
                        
                <lg>    
                    <l>Oer the wide fields of sea encircled <placeName corresp="#GREECE">Greece</placeName></l>
                    <l>Oh ancient <placeName corresp="#ATHENS">Athens</placeName> thou who once didst reign</l>
                    <l>In gory war or olive bearing peace</l>
                    <l>Ruler of <placeName corresp="#THEBES">Thebes</placeName> and Rugged <placeName corresp="#SPARTA">Sparta's</placeName> bane</l>
                    <l>I sing thee now in a less noble strain</l>
                    <pb/>
                    <l>Than formerly when white haired HOMER gave</l>
                    <l>His living lay at bright Apollo’s fane</l>
                    <l>That sung the dirges of thy young and brave,</l>
                    <l>Who found at Trojas wide and sandy plain a grave</l></lg>
                        
                <lg n="3" type="strophe">
                    <head type="strophe_number">3</head>
                    <l>Oh ruined Athens where thy glory now</l>
                    <l>Ist hovering oer thy ruins stern and grey</l>
                    <l>Thou who didst tear from Xerxes haughty brow</l>
                    <l>The wreath that he so late had grasped of bay</l>
                    <l>Spite of his golden crested stern array</l>
                    <l>Where is thy glory that so dearly won</l>
                    <l>And bought by blood upon that glorious day</l>
                    <l>Where is thy might thy power thy grandeur gone</l>
                    <l>Let their proud spirits tell who died at Marathon</l></lg>
                        
                <lg n="4" type="strophe">
                    <head type="strophe_number">4</head>
                    <l>And art thou gone for ever  Oer the deep</l>
                    <l>Echoes the voice of armies now no more</l>
                    <l>Now only on the breezes sullen sweep</l>
                    <l>The ocean which erst while those armies bore</l>
                    <l>Pours forth its angry everlasting roar</l>
                    <l>As to the rocks the sounding waters glide</l>
                    <l>Not now their billows blush with heroes gore</l>
                    <l>Now only beats in briny foam the tide</l>
                    <l>And snowy crests upon its wild waves ride</l></lg>
                        
                <lg n="5" type="strophe">
                    <l>Oh ye wild winds that oer their watery grave</l>
                    <l>In hoarse, and hollow soundings onwards sweep</l>
                    <l>Howl not so loudly oer their bosoms brave</l>
                    <l>Break not their slumber, that entrancing sleep</l>
                    <l>That waits the dead when pillowed on the deep</l>
                    <l>They rest, lulled softly by the oceans sigh</l>
                    <l>The eagle circling round the seabeat steep</l>
                    <l>May make the billows answer to its cry</l>
                    <l>But wake not those below their foam who lie.</l>
                            
                    <l>O Persia they fell in fight with thee</l>
                    <l>When first thy proud thy angry monarch came</l>
                    <l>And Xerxes led his gallies oer the sea</l>
                    <l>To make the Grecian glory but a name</l>
                    <l>Then was not Greece forgetful of her fame</l>
                    <l>And first thou haughty one began thy woes</l>
                    <l>When thy unnumbered armament in vain</l>
                    <l>Her heroes to their countrys battle fight arose [fight written above battle]</l>
                    <l>And bent before <!--all--> old Greca her humbled foes</l></lg>
                                
                <lg n="6" type="strophe">
                    <head type="strophe_number">VI</head>
                    <l>Little the young and mighty Xerxes thought</l>
                    <l>When first he counted all his myriads oer</l>
                    <l>And scarcely told their sum, a time how short</l>
                    <l>Should see him flying from the Grecian shore</l>
                    <l>And him the same who once nor long before</l>
                    <l>Had driven Scamander back unto his head</l>
                    <l>And dried his channel now one galley bore</l>
                    <l>His pride together with his power twas fled</l>
                    <l>And where his pristine glory? With the dead</l></lg>
                <lg n="7" type="strophe">
                    <head type="strophe_number">VII</head>
                    <l>And such the force that Persias king could boast</l>
                    <l>Ay thousands millions myriads indeed</l>
                    <l>He might be proud who looked on such a host</l>
                    <l>And marked them for his own his eager steed</l>
                    <l>Pawing the ground impatient he might lead</l>
                    <l>That sea of plumes to battle  They were doomed</l>
                    <l>On deep Salamis ocean fields to bleed</l>
                    <l>And in its yawning gulph to be entombed</l>
                    <l>While the relentless wave above them boomed</l></lg>
                <lg n="8" type="strophe">
                    <head type="strophe_number">VIII</head>
                    <l>They came the plumes upon their helmets dancing</l>
                    <l>Their young and eager monarch at their head</l>
                    <l>Their golden armour in the sunbeams glancing</l>
                    <l>A sea of bright translucent splendour shed</l>
                    <l>And earth all trembling shook beneath their tread</l>
                    <l>As when some gloomy vast and boundless deep</l>
                    <l>Heaps wave on wave with all its murmurs dread</l>
                    <l>Billow on billow with successive sweep</l>
                    <l>So pressed the warriors on a plumy foaming sheet</l></lg>
                <lg n="9" type="strophe">
                    <head type="strophe_number">IX</head>
                    <l>They past, but on their track behind them prest</l>
                    <l>Riding upon the swift wings of the gale</l>
                    <l>The demon desolation  Horrid guest</l>
                    <l>Attending wars red footsteps. Famine pale</l>
                    <l>Did follow. Shrouded in his cloudy veil</l>
                    <l>Death like some lurking monster glaring down</l>
                    <l>All in his fiery chariot seemed to sail</l>
                    <l>And night back trembling started at the frown</l>
                    <l>That marked his bony brow, seared by his lightning crown</l></lg>
                <lg n="10" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">X</subhead>
                    <l>And is it thus that pomp and pageantry</l>
                    <l>Must leave behind them such a gloomy train</l>
                    <l>And must it be that purple luxury</l>
                    <l>And royal grandeur shall be all in vain</l>
                    <l>Is this that kingly pomp  But neer again</l>
                    <l>Shall Xerxes lead those legions  He shall mourn</l>
                    <l>The time for ever past with grief and shame</l>
                    <l>All oer the lonely deep from Graecia borne</l>
                    <l>And like an exile king unpitied and forlorn</l></lg>
                <lg n="11" type="strope">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XI</subhead>
                    <l>But leave my muse this melancholy lay</l>
                    <l>Full soon shalt thou resume the mournful knell</l>
                    <l>Alas too quickly comes the blood stained day</l>
                    <l>That weeps for heroes dead But take thy shell</l>
                    <l>And all in softer mellower numbers tell</l>
                    <l>Till flinty rocks shall list the flowing strain</l>
                    <l>What forces Xerxes led what heroes fell</l>
                    <l>Those chieftains birth and eke from whence they came</l>
                    <l>Their fathers ancient deeds their lineage and their name</l></lg>
                <lg n="12" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XII</subhead>
                    <l>And first thou young Hydaspes3  What although</l>
                    <l>Thy parents came not of a kingly line</l>
                    <l>For oh a long futurity shall show</l>
                    <l>That natures proud nobility was thine</l>
                    <l>And not ancestral honours drowned in time</l>
                    <l>A mighty mind as innocent as pure</l>
                    <l>That through the mists of lowliness would shine</l>
                    <l>Humble not abject, rich although obscure</l>
                    <l>He had a virtuous mind the riches of the poor4</l></lg>
                <lg n="13" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XIII</subhead>
                    <l>He had a brother.5 They were kindred souls</l>
                    <l>For they were twins in age and mind the same</l>
                    <l>And where the wave of bright Hydaspes rolls</l>
                    <l>The Indian stream that gave to him his name</l>
                    <l>They learned the tigers savageness to tame</l>
                    <l>Or the dread hooded serpents folds to press</l>
                    <l>When hissed her head on high with eyes of flame</l>
                    <l>And as before them fled the lioness</l>
                    <l>Fearless and scatheless walked the wilderness</l></lg>
                <lg n="14" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XIV</subhead>
                    <l>And they had trod the stormy mountains ridge</l>
                    <l>To all the tribes of man a mighty bar</l>
                    <l>Or on the cliffs upraised and giddy edge</l>
                    <l>Looked down triumphant on the scene afar</l>
                    <l>Where the proud battlements of many a scar</l>
                    <l>Confusedly rising round them clove the sky</l>
                    <l>Where nature seemed to wage a mountain war</l>
                    <l>Long time they often lingered upon high</l>
                    <l>Where the snow wreaths hung round eternally</l></lg>
                <lg n="15" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XV</subhead>
                    <l>And hordes they led as swift as is the breeze</l>
                    <l>That flies across the oceans foam so light</l>
                    <l>Or as the mountain elk that challenges</l>
                    <l>The Scythian arrow to outstrip his flight</l>
                    <l>But firm and slow retreating from the fight</l>
                    <l>Strong as their native lion bathed in gore</l>
                    <l>Pawing the earth exulting in his might</l>
                    <l>And the wide forest echoing to his roar</l>
                    <l>Like sound of winter waves that bellow on the shore</l></lg>
                <lg n="16" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XVI</subhead>
                    <l>And he the born upon the battle field</l>
                    <l>Young Moriartes6 who upon a heap</l>
                    <l>Of gory corses on a warriors shield</l>
                    <l>Resting while war was raging round did sleep</l>
                    <l>High pillowed on the crest of that famed steep</l>
                    <l>That looks on Marathon with infant eye</l>
                    <l>Saw the rude tide of battle onwards sweep</l>
                    <l>As on the rugged mountain he did lie</l>
                    <l>And born in Greece in Greece was doomed to die</l></lg>
                <lg n="17" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XVII</subhead>
                    <l>(O Marathon thou field of victory</l>
                    <l>If ever Greece should cease to be a slave</l>
                    <l>Let her look back to ancient deeds and sigh</l>
                    <l>For loss of glory which her fathers gave</l>
                    <l>Bought with their noble lives or will her brave</l>
                    <l>Burst from the fetters of the narrow bed</l>
                    <l>Breaking the sods which clasp their gory grave</l>
                    <l>And tell old Greece that they for her have bled</l>
                    <l>And deep reproaching her forgetful of the dead7</l></lg>
                <lg n="18" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XVIII</subhead>
                    <l>Oh if this sad and simple lay of mine</l>
                    <l>Could give thee down unto posterity</l>
                    <l>Thou should’st have ridden on the wings of time</l>
                    <l>And only with creations self should die</l>
                    <l>Let not thy parent oer thine ashes sigh</l>
                    <l>For thou shalt live through many distant days</l>
                    <l>Though neath the ocean now thy corse may lie</l>
                    <l>Again thy name shall shine in future lays</l>
                    <l>And harps of nobler string record a warriors praise</l></lg>
                <lg n="19" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">XIX8</subhead>
                    <l>His was a <!--mighty--> gloomy and sequestered mind</l>
                    <l>Men say that on the night when he was born</l>
                    <l>There was a strange sad sighing in the wind</l>
                    <l>And many an ominous and awful form</l>
                    <l>Rode the dark clouds that bore the bursting storm</l>
                    <l>As the red lightning those wide heavens spanned</l>
                    <l>And sounds of wailing as of those that mourn</l>
                    <l>Ever for the dead and many a spectre hand</l>
                    <l>Seemed lifting high the [(?)] battle brand</l></lg>
                <lg n="20" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">20</subhead>
                    <l>His was a soul of solitude His ear</l>
                    <l>Liked not the hum of thousands He would pace</l>
                    <l>(At midnight when the azure heavens were clear</l>
                    <l>The paths of some wild desert wilderness</l>
                    <l>As if his soul would haste to seek its place</l>
                    <l>Winging its <!--way through--> vast and its aerial way</l>
                    <l>To that bright home of light and loveliness9</l>
                    <l>Breaking the bands of its confining clay</l>
                    <l>That shackled it on earth and haste to spring away</l></lg>
                <lg n="21" type="strophe">
                    <subhead type="strophe_number">2110</subhead>
                    <l>There was a sad and settled gloominess</l>
                    <l>That brooded oer his features, and if eer</l>
                    <l>He smiled twas not <!--the--> a smile of happiness</l>
                    <l>He never could forget the secret care</l>
                    <l>That weighed upon his bosom rooted there</l>
                    <l>Too deep for consolation <!--One young boy [these(?) . . . wild(?)]--> One young <!--child--> boy</l>
                    <l>Had followed him from far and he would share</l>
                    <l>His [fits(?)] of grief<!--s--> with purest sympathy.11</l>
                    <l>He loved him much, <!--but loved none else save--> but none save him loved her</l></lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>[unnumbered stanza]12</l>
                    <l>The sunset shone upon the isles of Greece</l>
                    <l>And ocean where the heavens misty blue</l>
                    <l>Was mingling with the deep which lay, in peace</l>
                    <l>Far to the west its world of waters threw</l>
                    <l>To those <!--[peace(?)]--> fair isles, that seemed as if they grew</l>
                    <l>Each in itself one [or an] Oasis. the waste</l>
                    <l>Stretching around, beyond them, and light<!--ly--> blew</l>
                    <l>The evening zephyr on the deep and <!--[(?)]--> cast</l>
                    <l>White foam upon the wave as murmuring it past.</l></lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>