<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from a Transcription of the MS Draft/Fair Copy Name/Number</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                    <!--Example entries have been provided for MS I from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <country type="nation">United States of America</country>
                        <region type="state">Connecticut</region>
                        <settlement type="city">New Haven</settlement>
                        <institution>Yale University</institution>
                        <repository>Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</repository>
                        <collection>MS Vault Ruskin</collection>
                        <idno>"Harry &#x0026; Lucy, Poems &#x0026;c"</idno>
                        <msName>MS I</msName>
                        <msName>"Red book No. 3"</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <locus facs="image.jpg image.jpg">pp. ##-##</locus>
                            <note>For a discussion of foliation, see <ref type="apparatus" target="tite_of_apparatus.php#MAJORMS">"Title of Work": Manuscripts</ref>.</note>
                            <filiation><!--Entry needed here.--></filiation>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <!--If additional entries are made below, the hands count must be increased.-->
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote corresp="#HANDJR1826-27" scribe="JR">
                                <p>John Ruskin's early boyhood hand, circa <date notBefore="1826" notAfter="1827">1826-27</date>,
                                    examples of which can be found in MS I, pages <locus from="##" to="##">##-##</locus>.</p>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="prose">
                <head type="title"><handShift new="#HANDJR1826-27" script="print" medium="pencil"/>Title of Prose Piece</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter">chap I</head>
                    <p>
                        THE REST of the noon was so foggy that Harry could not see more than four yards before him. But he amused himself with drawing the rest of the noon and took dinner.
                        After dinner Harry had to learn his lessons because the electrical phenomenon had quite driven them out of his head  But he learned them so quickly that he had from three to nine to play but he did not play he spent from three to half past it in learning his lessons for tomorrow and spent the rest in drawing took tea and went to bed.
                        Next morning a strange adventure befel Harry. As he was walking upon the beach with Lucy he called out here’s a fine place of shell’s for you and he heard you you you you you repeated five times and on looking about found a hollow in the rock and saw that it was an echo[—]’
                        But on going home he found them packing up for off for they had staid a week in Hastings”
                        Harry said he was sorry to leave it.’
                        But we must leave it said his mother’
                        Why must we mother.
                        Because we have not time to stay longer in it[—]
                        Where are we going next mother
                        To scotland Harry.
                        To scotland what a long travel but I like it the better.”
                        But I can tell you you’ll be very sleepy and tired by the way
                        I don’t care for that said Harry
                        But you’ll see such frightfull precipices[—]
                        So much the better said Harry
                        But by this time the carriage had got to the door and all getting in drove off[—]”
                        First they came to a common public road with hedges on each side of it till at last they came to a beautiful road sometimes hedges sometimes none at all sometimes landscapes sometimes none at all hills hillocks mounts rivulets rivers ponds lakes all in profusion sometimes high on a hill sometimes low in a valley and all along the same
                        Harry and Lucys mother had a certain friend living near this place and they went to see him here they saw many pretty and useful flowers such as the mimosa the papyrus and the coffee tree and after having had a good run they got into the carriage and drove into salt hill[—] 
                        But here they stayed only to dinner or else Harry would have had a fine swing there being a nice one in the ground  But such little disappointments must be put up with and they went on.”
                        Soon after this they came to the [same(?)]1 road again and after riding on for a very very very long time and changing horses often they reached oxford[—]
                        But it was so very late when they arrived at oxford that they could not see any thing but they were told that they were to stay all night at the hotel and in the morning went to see the colleges. They might have seen the inside if they had time but they had not so that they only went round them looked at their architecture and went home[—]”
                        Their father and mother thought very much of it but they had not much time to think about it for harry asked what the distance might be from gloster which he was told they were going to next  his father told him that he did not know and [now(?)]2 the carriage drove to the door.”
                        But just as they were passing a fine elm they saw a large pond perhaps a mile broad going complet{e}ly3 across the road without any bridge and the horses plunged into it  whats this cried Harry  Where are we going now cried Lucy they went on on deeper and deeper into the water and at length they went completely through the pond and went forward on their journey[—]”
                        For some time the road was very hilly chalky sandy and watery but soon it grew very dusty and such a fine day that they all got out and walked a good way they had intended to walk very quick but they did not for they were attracted by such a variety of objects such as the white major convolvolus in the hedges the black and white broad beans the butterfly like pea’s4 the sparkling rivulets and winding rivers all combined their forces to make them walk slowly  But on turning a corner such a beautiful waterfall presented itself to their view that they stood for above four minutes looking at it and harry just as he turned to look at the glittering diamond like bubbles in the stream he saw something leap up the waterfall and on looking at it he saw that it was a salmon the time passed so very quickly in looking at the waterfall that when harrys father looked at his watch they had been an hour looking at it  when they again got into the carriage harry said that if lucy liked he would give her a drawing of charles’s wain as an introduction to astronomy. Lucy said she would like it very much and we shall here put it down. [plates]5
                        Though Lucy liked astronomy very much yet she asked harry why he did not go on with pneumatics.6 Scarcely was this said than they found themselves at the inn and such was the bustle occasioned by packing and unpacking that harry could not answer Lucys question.
                        There was very little to be seen at glocester and so they only staid to dine. There was also nothing remarkable in their ride.
                        When they got to monmouth harry went out for a walk with his father  they went by the side of the river Wye which was rather full of projecting banks and peninsulas at that place and they staid so long that when they got home they found tea was waiting for them and after tea there was much much deliberation about going to tintern abbey next day  harrys mother was against going to it harrys father was for going to it at length mamma yielded and they went to tintern abbey next day.
                        <head type="chapter">CHAP II</head>
                        WHEN they had reached the place where tintern abbey was to be seen they got out and walked to it  in so doing they saw some beehives and scarcely had harry turned round from looking at them than he saw tintern abbey. It had a most beautiful window for first there was an arch and then by its sides and top there were all kinds of figures. The door was in this shape [diagram] and when their guide had opened it they found themselves in a large abbey with two rows of pillars one on each side of them but broken and ruined. Their guide showed them some keystones of the arches that had fallen down and harry wondered why the arches did not fall with them  He looked up and saw no gap in the arch and he asked his father what was the reason of all this but his father was busy looking at other things and so Harry was obliged to go to the same ones. After looking for a good while at these Harry and Lucy began to get tired but soon their guide took them through a passage which led them past several ruined rooms. Going through one of these they found themselves on a little green with a hillock [diagram?] on one side of it  from the green nothing was seen but a stone wall but when harry ascended the hillock no view could be more beautiful  they then went out of the abbey and went on to windcliff having gone through a cottage they saw a high rock as perpendicular as the wall of a house full of crags and white  harry was rather puzzled when he was told that he was to climb up this rock but the man who led them carried them by gentle sloping walks which carried them up to the top of the rock without the least difficulty
                        They thought that the coming down would not be so easy but it was much easier because it was a gentle slope  when they were safe down they jumped into the carriage and drove off
                        In a few minutes they saw the sea and presently they came to the side of it  they were presently aboard a steamboat and soon they arrived at the other side7 they then jumped into the carriage and drove off  they soon arrived at kinross here they took tea and drove off to Perth  Harry and Lucy were so sleepy that they were forced to go to bed whenever they arrived in Perth  their house chanced to be directly opposite the tay with the north inch completely between them and the tay  so when they arose in the morning they thought they would like to go out and take a walk and Harry took his little boat with him thinking it would take a nice sail in the tay but he was disappointed for the tay was so rough that his vessel immediately turned topsy turvy  seeing that to sail his vessel was impossible he took a nice walk with Lucy[,] and then returned home. They had seen some fine ups and downs on the inch so they thought they would hav{e}8 some play on them  Harry then determined to give Lucy a lesson of science so he thought he would show her this experiment.
                        Harry then took an ale glass[,] [plate]9 and plunged it with the mouth downwards into a jar of water and very little water entered into it.
                        Lucy enquired the reason of this and harry said that the air in the glass was compressed into the smaller space and would not let the water come in farther10
                        chap III
                        HARRYS mother now said to him that it was time to go out so Harry and Lucy put on their things and went out upon the inch they went to the ups and downs which they had seen the last time they were out  and first of all Harry first proposed running up and down the upandowns but lucy proposed breaking spars which harry agreed to and they got many beautiful spars by lucys plan when they came home they showed their spars to their mother who said that there were some different metals in them which Harry and Lucy were very well pleased at.  it was now dinner time and after dinner Harry drew till teatime then wrote a letter for his mother an went to bed.
                        This was the second day they had been at perth and on the morrow they were to march off	
                        When harry arose in the morning he found all busy with packing and soon they jumped into the carriage and drove off to kinross
                        Here Harry went out to see the lake of lochleven and when he came in his shoes were thoroughly wet through he had been so near the lake  he now drew a copy of a church that was close to the inn where they were and then got into the carriage and drove off to Queens ferry.
                        While crossing the water the steamboat pitched so that harry could hardly keep upon his legs but when harry got to edinburgh he had such a comfortable room comfortable dinner and comfortable tea that he quite forgot all pitching and travelling.
                        Whenever harry got up in the morning he went out to the top of the carlton hill with his papa and when he came in he found the carriage waiting for him into which he jumped and in a few minutes they came in sight of the sea  they travelled by the sea a long while and then going away from it they came to haddington where harry expected to see the sea very well
                        But when harry came to haddington they saw nothing but a long street which rather disappointed harry but when they came to berwick they saw the sea finely
                        In the morning harry went out on the walls with his father and when he came in jumped into the carriage and drove off to alnwick here harry went with his father to see the castle and then drove off to newcastle  it here began snowing very fast so that harry could not get out nor could Lucy for if they had gone out they would have tumbled every five minutes but when they set off they soon got to durham where they changed horses and went on to darlington here they slept and in the morning went on to boroughbridge.  the reason it was called so was that a very beautiful bridge was in the town the room which they had got had a bookcase in it and harry met with his favourite history of sandford and merton which he had not finished before he was forced to go on to ferrybridge which he was rather sorry for but it was made up at ferrybridge for there they had a complete view of the river which flowed through the town.
                        Here they slept and in the morning went off for doncaster this was a beautiful town there was an avenue of trees through which they passed to go into the town  well from this avenue the high towers of the cathedral gilded by the rays of the sun and the mountains at a distance looked so beautiful that people must see it to comprehend it even the great bass with its multitudes of seafowl could not equal this and what made the bass the more charming was that the bass was seen at sunset while this was seen at noon  But I will put them on to scarthing moor in another chapter.
                    </p>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>