<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from a Transcription of the MS Draft/Fair Copy Name/Number</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#GMS">Gabriella M. Smith</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Isabella Bairnsfather</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Jazmin Adams</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                    <!--Example entries have been provided for MS I from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <country type="nation">United States of America</country>
                        <region type="state">Connecticut</region>
                        <settlement type="city">New Haven</settlement>
                        <institution>Yale University</institution>
                        <repository>Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</repository>
                        <collection>MS Vault Ruskin</collection>
                        <idno>"Harry &#x0026; Lucy, Poems &#x0026;c"</idno>
                        <msName>MS I</msName>
                        <msName>"Red book No. 3"</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <locus facs="image.jpg image.jpg">pp. ##-##</locus>
                            <note>For a discussion of foliation, see <ref type="apparatus" target="tite_of_apparatus.php#MAJORMS">"Title of Work": Manuscripts</ref>.</note>
                            <filiation><!--Entry needed here.--></filiation>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <!--If additional entries are made below, the hands count must be increased.-->
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote corresp="#HANDJR1826-27" scribe="JR">
                                <p>John Ruskin's early boyhood hand, circa <date notBefore="1826" notAfter="1827">1826-27</date>,
                                    examples of which can be found in MS I, pages <locus from="##" to="##">##-##</locus>.</p>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Example entries have been provided from MS I in the <handShift/>s below. Actual entries may vary.-->
            <!--Simple Prose. Delete this <div/> if not used.-->
            <div type="prose">
                <head type="title"><handShift new="#HANDJR1826-27" script="print" medium="pencil"/>LEONI</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="subhead">A Legend of Italy.</head>
                    <p>The lord of <placeName type="fictional" corresp="#CASTELALTO-LEONI">Castel Alto</placeName> is old and grayheaded silently and unaware;<lb/>
                        fourscore years have <add place="above">flitted</add><del rend="strikethrough">past</del>over him, and the dream of<lb/>
                        life is nigh to its awaking, and his ear is dull, and his<lb/>
                        eye is dim, and his heart is weary.<lb/>
                        
                        The old man reclines on a couch in the hall of his<lb/>
                        ancestors, <del rend="strikethrough">and</del> beside an open casement, and the balmy<lb/>
                        air that floats over the deep blue waters of the broad sea,<lb/>
                        passes softly over his gleaming hair; and his weary<lb/>
                        eye rests on the brightness of an exceeding lovely landscape<lb/>
                        for the olive and the orange and the myrtle are green<lb/>
                        by the shore of the still waters, and the city gleams whitely<lb/>
                        beneath the glance of the sun as he rides through the<lb/>
                        cloudless azure of the heaven, and the purple mountains<lb/>
                        clasp the ocean in their arms, and fade away into the horizon<lb/>
                        in long lines of misty blue.<lb/>
                        Alas, the spring time of nature is a mockery to the<lb/>
                        winter of <del rend="strikethrough">old</del> age, and the old man turns away in sadness<lb/>
                        <del rend="strikethrough">He is begins by</del>His vassals are waiting around him to<lb/>
                        do him pleasure; the minstrel is there with his harp, the<lb/>
                        maiden with her song, but no music is so sweet to<lb/>
                        the old mans ear ear as the voice of his daughter <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GIULIETTA-LEONI">Giulietta</persName>.<lb/><pb/>

                        * * * *

                        <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GIULIETTA-LEONI">Giulietta</persName>, when a babe, was a thing of smiles and loveliness<lb/>
                        like a happy thought dancing over the mind&#x2019;<lb/>
                        <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GIULIETTA-LEONI">Giulietta</persName>, when a child, was like the orange blossom in<lb/>
                        the groves of <placeName corresp="#FRIULI">Friuli</placeName>, and gladness floated around her like the<lb/>
                        fragrance of the flower. <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GIULIETTA-LEONI">Giulietta</persName>, in her youth, is the<lb/>
                        fairest maiden of <placeName corresp="#ITALY">Italy</placeName>, she glanced among the myrtle<lb/>
                        bowers like the winged zephyr, the evening star, when<lb/>
                        it rises gleaming out of the sea into <lb/>
                        the darkness of the glorious night of Italy, is not so<lb/>
                        bright as the beam that flashed from her large<lb/>
                        eye through the night of her lovely eyelashes.<lb/>
                        Like music to the sadness of the soul, was Giulietta<lb/>
                        to the old age of her father. As she passed before him<lb/>
                        a light came into the coldness of his eye; and his ear,<lb/>
                        when it was dead to other sound, awoke to the murmur<lb/>
                        of her gentle voice (Giulietta&#x02BC;s mind was love, all love<lb/>
                        continual love to each and every&#x2010;thing, the birds<lb/>
                        knew Giulietta, (the nightingale sang at the chamber windows<lb/>
                        his song to the stars.)<del rend="strikethrough">and</del> (as she walked among the<lb/>
                        flowers theynflustered beside her and stooped their glady? mers<lb/>
                        to the land) nay, the flowers seemed to know Guilietta<lb/>
                        and to be gladdened into brighteness as she past, and Giulietta<lb/>
                        loved them all.) <del rend="strikethrough">To her father</del> as an angel watches<lb/>
                        over the last days of a saint upon the earth, when the tumult<lb/>
                        of the battle of his life is oer, and sheds peace around his hours<lb/>
                        and bids his days pass sweetly and holily,<gap reason="omission" unit="chars" quantity="2"/>so Giulietta watched<lb/>
                        over the old man like an influence of good, and was the sun of his<lb/>
                        thoughts, and the light of his rejoicing<gap reason="omission" unit="chars" quantity="1"/>.<lb/>
                        Giulietta had a brother; <gap reason="omission" unit="chars" quantity="3"/>Garcio<gap reason="omission" unit="chars" quantity="5"/>was feared by many<lb/>
                        <hi rend="underline">and loved by few</hi>was a man of a dark countenance<lb/><pb/> 
                        and the shadows of his evil passions passed over it like clouds<lb/>
                        over the luridness of the stormy heaven, and his look withered<lb/>                        
                        those upon whom it fell, and his wrath, once excited raged<lb/>
                        like a pestilence, and would not be appeased, he was feared by<lb/>
                        all, hated by many, loved by few, but his<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#RESTLESS"/>arm was restless in the<lb/>
                        battle, and his faire? was bright among the proud and<lb/><!--can't read what it says here, it doesnt look like and-->
                        of the warriors of Italy.<lb/>
                        <!--from "his arm was restless to "Italy." there seems to be a strikethrough, but it is very faint like it was written in pencil, possible editors note?-->
                        
                        Among his many enemies Garcio hated none of as he did<lb/>
                        the bandit Leoni, for him only he feared;<lb/>
                        There are spirits moving on the earth, which are not of<lb/>he
                        a like order with their fellows, which will rise above the<lb/>
                        ordinary dust of mortality, whether it be ingreatness of evil,<lb/>
                        of good and it depends from the accident of impulse,<lb/><!--??-->
                        from the treatment of their fellowmen, whether their greatness<lb/>
                        <add place="above">be</add><del rend="strikethrough">is</del> a blessing or a curse. and such was Leoni, &#x0026; he was<lb/>
                        what he abhorred, &#x3009; <del rend="strikethrough">for</del> &#x3008;his whole nature had been <!--can't read this--> driven<lb/>
                        by the violence of his patterns&#x3009; <add place="above">not yet</add>his name was pronounced<lb/>
                        with fear, <del rend="strikethrough">but</del>not with <!--not sure what this says--> or ___ , and widely<lb/>
                        was the fear of that name spread. for he passed over<lb/>
                        the land like a meteor and left destination behind him<lb/>
                        in the halls of the great and the powerful, but not in<lb/>
                        the hamlets of the poor.<lb/>
                        Returning from a successful attack on the castle of a<lb/>
                        neighboring baron, Leoni had been once tracked to the<lb/>
                        fastnesses of the Apennines by Garcio, with a chosen<lb/>
                        troop of his followers. The bandit gave him battle, and<lb/>
                        was as ___ victorious, the followers of Garcio cowered<lb/>
                        back from <add place="above">his thunderbolt charge</add><del rend="strikethrough">The charge of the bandit and Garcio</del><add place="above">and his</add><del rend="strikethrough">and his</del>himself was<lb/>
                        struck from his home by the sword of <del rend="strikethrough">this<!--??--></del>, Leoni<lb/>
                        It had been said of Leoni that he had never <del rend="strikethrough">stranded</del>deserted<lb/>
                        a friend, or spared an enemy. but suddenly as his sword wound<lb/>
                        over the head of his <!--???--> for, <add place="above">the ___ of Garcios helmet fell open</add> his aim was checked and if<lb/>
                        by the hand of an invisible being <add place="above">&#x002A;</add> and to the astonishment<lb/>
                        of his followers, Leoni rounded a retreat in very flush of victory<lb/>
                        and <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> Garcio and his <del rend="strikethrough">land as</del>dishearted and ____ wished<lb/>
                        loud were suffered to retire unnoticed.<lb/><!--not sure this is what it says-->
                        a smile of ___ passed over his eyes, and then a wildness came<lb/>
                        into the flush of his eye, a wildness <add place="above">never before</add><del rend="strikethrough">ready</del> seen on the features of<lb/>
                        Leoni; he turnedcalmly away, and to the allowed helmet&#x002A;<lb/>
                        From that time the hatred of Garcio to Leoni was as<lb/>
                        as a continuing fill <!-- not sure this is what is says-->, and the shame of defeat and the<lb/>
                        thirst of revenge gather into his heart like vultures&#x2013;<lb/>
                        he had rather have been laid dead by the sword of Leoni<lb/>
                        than suffered to live a monument of the clemency of this<lb/>
                        bandit conqueror<lb/>
                       
                        * * * * *
                        
                        Guilietta. Guilietta, said the old man<lb/>
                        And Guilietta cameforth from among her maidened<lb/>
                        like the moon when it is night among the pale stars<lb/>
                        and she knelt down <add place="above">softly</add><del rend="strikethrough">silently</del>beside her parent, and lifted<lb/>
                        up his large dark eyes full of love. And a blessing <!--not sure what this says--> silently<lb/>
                        over the heart of her father <!--not sure what is struck through here--> and descended from her like the<lb/>
                        dew <del rend="strikethrough">of Garcio?</del><lb/>
                        Giulietta, said the old man, there is a dark spirit upon<lb/>
                        me to day, a shadow <add place="above">that</add> is felt, a dread stillness of the mind<lb/>
                        like the fearful heat of the air before the desolation of<lb/>
                        the earthquake, a child is upon my soul as I the hand.<lb/>
                        of death ___ lying cold even upon my mind<lb/>
                        Nay, my father, said Giulietta, thou art weary,<lb/>
                        she bent over him and kissed his cheek<lb/>
                        I am not weary when thou art beside me Giulietta,<lb/>
                        this glow that sits hooding over my heart is not weakness<lb/>
                        or dislike, it is ____ of evil which the invisible beings<lb/>
                        who are around us <del rend="strikethrough">in the air</del>and in us, and who watch over our feelings<lb/>
                        and turn them <del rend="strikethrough">into</del> good to evil, have power conjure into<lb/>
                        our souls as a warning &#x2013; Such there are, Giulietta, I have<lb/>
                        spoken with them <add place="above">in</add> my mind, I havefelt their power sway<lb/>
                        over my life, I have felt their ___ about my hearts strings<lb/>
                        in day or in sorry&#x2013;<lb/>
                        My father, said Giulietta, the evil spirits have no power<lb/>
                        over us without our own consent, and this ____<lb/>
                        the soul is not of the good.<lb/>
                        I know not, returned the old man, I have felt it once before<lb/>
                        it was followed by the death of those whom I loved.<lb/>
                        Giulietta looked up, and <del rend="strikethrough">her father</del> his countenance was exceeding<lb/>
                        pale, and there was a horror upon it of great fear.<lb/>
                        My father, My Father, <del rend="strikethrough">said Giulietta</del> you<lb/>
                        are ill said <del rend="strikethrough">Giulietta</del>the maiden Giulietta, and to me that fear will soon set I believe<lb/> <!--conditional query here-->
                        <add place="above"><del rend="strikethrough">I believe I shall not see that</del></add><del rend="strikethrough">No, Giulietta,</del> said the old man, but this is not <add place="above">for ever</add><del rend="strikethrough">the</del> death, save the<lb/>
                        fear of death, that sits so heavily on me. What is it to one like<lb/>
                        me to fall asleep from weariness of life &#x2013; why should I fear<lb/>
                        resting from trouble and <del rend="strikethrough">grief</del> turmoil and grief, why should a<lb/>
                        gloom come over me from the dread of repose<lb/>
                        What do you fear, my father, said Giulietta<lb/>
                        <add place="above">I know not what I fear but</add> fear for thee<add place="above">only</add>my daughter, said the old man; the only<lb/>
                        blow which can now reach my old heart, must be struck through<lb/>
                        thee, Leave me &#x2013; Giulietta.<lb/>
                        Not thees, not thees, said the maiden, for the <del rend="strikethrough">far</del> countenance<lb/>
                        of her father grew still pale.<lb/>
                        Yes &#x2013; leave me, Thy presence but increases this horror that<lb/>
                        has bound me&#x2013; <del rend="strikethrough">farewell.</del><lb/>
<!--page break-->
                        And the maiden kissed her fathers brow. and it was very cold.<lb/>
                        and his ____ trembled strongly. and she left him, and sought<lb/>
                        her chamber in sorrow.<lb/>
                        The sun is low in the heaven, and the tal rocks on the<lb/>
                        sea shore are reddewed with his rays, and the columns of the<lb/>
                        ruined temple on their summit throw their shadows lengthly<lb/>
                        along the<del rend="strikethrough">ir</del> sword. By a narrow path on the face of the<lb/>
                        grey rocks a band of warriors was <!--not sure what this word is--> near by man, and<lb/>
                        the ___ rays glanced gaily on this crested island. High was<lb/>
                        the shore and lofty the glance of thisleader, and a pride sat upon<lb/>
                        his lip; <del rend="strikethrough">see</del> for the countenance of Leoni was not as the countenance<lb/>
                        of other men, the emotions which passed over his heart like<lb/>
                        whirlwinds <del rend="strikethrough">no</del> were not neglected in the stillness of his brow<lb/>
                        more when they looked upon Leoni could have known what<lb/>
                        thought<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> were <del rend="strikethrough">taking over</del> working in the deep secret places<lb/>
                        of his soul. Neither hope, nor fear, nor anger had ever<lb/>
                        been seen on his countenance <del rend="strikethrough">and when</del>but the <!--not sure what this says here--><lb/>
                        of music sat there ever, <add rend="underline">and when he spoke, even in the</add><lb/><!--note here unfinished thought?-->
                        One of his followers was beside him, privileged by <!--unsure--><lb/>
                        age, one whom Leoni <del rend="strikethrough">had</del> allowed to speak familarily <!--frequently?--><lb/>
                        to him. and as a friend. and the old mans tone <!--ink blob here?-->was<lb/>
                        querulous and complaining.<lb/>
                        Lo, we are to wait here for you again holy the night <del rend="strikethrough">and</del><lb/><!--might?-->
                        are we. I love not these sobstory rambles of yours, Leoni,<lb/>
                        what can <add place="above">you</add> have to do <add place="above">alone</add> at the castle of<lb/>
                        every evening;<lb/>
                        Trouble not yourself about <add place="above">that,</add><del rend="strikethrough">see</del><!--no clue what that says--> said Leoni, <del rend="strikethrough">kindly</del><lb/>
                        But I do trouble myself, returned Amalfiero I love not to be<lb/>
                        left here sprawling <del rend="strikethrough">idle</del> on this damp grass every night while<lb/>
                        you go pushing your head into the Lions mouth in the way<lb/><pb/>
                        I can&#x02BC;t imagine what makes you keep lurking alone<lb/>
                        that castle of<gap reason="omission" unit="chars" quantity="3"/><!--note here--> unless if he to let Garcio catch<lb/>
                        you. and then you would lose your head,and we are <!--?--><lb/>
                        Fear not for me, said Leoni, my doom is not to die by<lb/>
                        his coward sword&#x2013;<lb/>
                        I don&#x02BC;t know that Leoni, replied the old man. that was another<lb/>
                        fools trick of yours, you should have known better, when<lb/>
                        he fell before you in the battle, than to think that <del rend="strikethrough">a coward</del><add place="above">he</add><lb/>
                        would ever have forgiven his defeat. Why did you let him<lb/>
                        live to plot <del rend="strikethrough"><!--something of--></del> revenge as a reward for your <del rend="strikethrough">very</del>worst<lb/>
                        with clemency;<lb/>
                        Leoni smiled in <!--unsure--><lb/>
                        I knew him then and I know him now, he said<lb/>
                        Let him plot against .. me .. <!--note here--> if he will &#x2013; think you I care<lb/>
                        for his <del rend="strikethrough">coward wrath</del> meanly devised revenge or coward and<lb/>
                        impotent wrath. Garcio is to me as the wave that dashes <!--???--><lb/>
                        its week spray on the forehead of yonder __ and away colding<lb/>
                        cry.<lb/>
                        Nevertheless Leoni, if he were to catch you near his castle<lb/>
                        without your followers, I fancy our next charge <del rend="strikethrough">at him</del><lb/>
                        would <!-- cannot read what is struckthrough here except headed? by you--> be without a leader<lb/>
                        You had better stay here out of the <!--unsure--> or take<lb/>
                        us with you &#x2013; I&#x02BC;ll follow you to the castle with an<lb/>
                        utmost possible pleasure <del rend="strikethrough">and when he&#x02BC;s down here</del><lb/>
                        providing you don&#x02BC;t sound <del rend="strikethrough">us</del> retreat as you so <!--unsure--><lb/>
                        did once we wereabout to give the rascals a<lb/>
                        ___ how they <del rend="strikethrough">hacked the</del><add place="above">stayed to attach the</add> band of Leoni&#x2014;<add place="above">some of them would</add> you were possessed<lb/>
                        that day Leoni, mad, quite mad.<lb/>
                        have remembered it as long as their heads stood on their shoulders<lb/>
                        <add place="above">You must not follow me</add> Not yet, said Leoni, you <del rend="strikethrough">may have seen</del> must remain here<lb/><pb/>
                        this evening at least but keep your <!--unsure--> headed, and<lb/>
                        stray not. I may have need <add place="above">of</add>you this night.<lb/>
                        Its hightime I know, muttered Amalfiero, to have need<lb/>
                        of us, we might as well be <!--unsure--> or <!--unsure--><lb/>
                        at once as ___ here like moon called all night, not a<lb/>
                        blow to the stretch nor a shot find. Well, if he will go<lb/>
                        he <del rend="strikethrough">will</del> must, I suppose he&#x02BC;ll be freed of this in time<lb/>
                        or <del rend="strikethrough">somebody</del> Garcio will teach him the independence of <!--unsure--><lb/>
                        contemplation. And with a low disoriented kind of growl<lb/>
                        Amalfiero crouched, sulked behind a fallen column looked to the primming<lb/>
                        of his cartine, <!--italian rolling papers?--> turned his sword belt round the that the belt might<lb/>
                        be near his hand, and so the rest of the band <del rend="strikethrough">were</del> had soon<lb/>
                        disappeared into curious places of concealment. and Leoni leaping<lb/>
                        down <!--not sure what it says above--> from the rocks, <del rend="strikethrough">with a light idly found</del> moved swiftly <!--not sure if it says swiftly--><lb/>
                        along the seashore towards the castle of &#x2013;<lb/>
                        And <add place="above">a change came over/and it grew</add> his countenance <del rend="striketrough">was</del> wild and a gladness rested on it<lb/>
                        and the haughtiness of his life faded away<lb/>

                        * * * * *

                        Giulietta sat in her chamber, in the eastern tower of the<lb/>
                        castle of.<gap reason="omission" unit="chars" quantity="6"/><!--Conditional note: It appears as though Ruskin at this given point in time had not officially chosen the name "Castel Alto," thus the reasoning for the large space here. It looks like he intended to come back to this and write a name.--> The evening was sinking down<lb/>
                        when the shores of the deep sea <del rend="strikethrough">And Giulietta&#x02BC;s eye rested</del><lb/>
                        and the evening star <del rend="strikethrough">as it</del> rose up out of the deep and<lb/>
                        climbed slowly up into the darkening sky, and far through<lb/>
                        the deep blue air gleamed its melancholy ray. and show paley on the quivering countenance of the moving wakes<lb/>
                        And Giulietta&#x02BC;s large dark eye rested <add place="above">sadly</add> on the star, and what
                        were Giuliettas thoughts and now. Fast waned the daylight away<lb/>
                        and the glow of the sky that was shed over it by the departing<lb/>
                        sun became cold, and the shadow of the perceding starlight<lb/>
                        became visible on the chequered floor and <add place="above">covered</add> walls <del rend="strikethrough">and</del><lb/>
                        <!--something is deleted here but cannot tell what it is--> of the chamber. And the <del rend="strikethrough">subjects beneath</del> night<lb/><pb/>
                        came glowered down upon the sea,<lb/>
                        and the star climbed higher and higher and as it <!--strikethrough here, cannot read it--> <add place="above">touched</add><lb/>
                        the summit of <del rend="strikethrough">a distant</del><add place="above">the</add> mountain the night breeze came <!--cannot read-->
                        over the deep. and as it <!--strikethrough--> died away <del rend="strikethrough">a</del><add place="above">the</add> voice was heard<lb/>
                        ringing below the <del rend="strikethrough">sea</del> castle. And Giulietta drew near the<lb/>
                        window and listened, and the sounds <add place="below" rend="underline">came</add><add place="above">rose</add> softly of when<lb/>
                        the wings of the night wind and <del rend="strikethrough">go</del> the moon and the<lb/>
                        <del rend="strikethrough">start</del><!--strikethrough above unclear-->looked down, and saw a blush passed over Giuliettas<lb/>
                        lovely cheek <del rend="strikethrough">for the voice was Francescos</del> and thus it sang. the voice<lb/>
                        <lg><l>There was a tower within my heart</l><lb/>
                            <l>The tower was <del rend="strikethrough">high and</del>strong and high</l><lb/>
                            <l>But oh, its walls they fell before</l>
                            <l>The glance of thy bright eye</l>
                            <l>A throne of love writhing the tower</l>
                            <l> A loftly throne, was seen</l>
                            <l> And there shore sittest on the throne</l>
                            <l>Indistinguishable <gap reason="omission" unit="chars" quantity="2"></gap>queen</l></lg>
                    </p>
                    
                </div>
<div>
                <head type="subhead">2.</head>
                <lg><l>Fall high upon the Apennine</l>
                    <l>Is set my mountain tower</l>
                    <l>And there with gems and marble fears<!--?--></l>
                    <l>I&#x02BC;ve decked a lady&#x02BC;s bower</l>
                    <l>The lady, a bower is fair to see</l>
                    <l>Now lady&#x02BC;s there I&#x02BC;ve ween</l>
                    <l>Oh maiden, went away with me</l>
                    <l>And thou salt be its queen</l></lg>
                    </div>
<div>
                    <head type="subhead">3.</head>
                    <lg><l>And far among the mountains blue</l>
                        <l>I have a healthy bond</l>
                        <l>My heart is bold, my band is true</l><pb/>
                        <l>They wait for my command</l>
                        <l>Their hands are strong their hearts are free</l> 
                        <l>Their swords are bright and keen</l>
                        <l>Oh maiden, wend away with me</l>
                        <l>And thou shalt be their queen</l></lg>
</div>
<div>
<p>
                    And the voice <del rend="strikethrough">faded away</del> died, and the tears passed<lb/>
                    <del rend="strikethrough">away</del> drearily into the stillness of the night<lb/>
                <del rend="strikethrough">And the song cased, and the tones passed away into<lb/>
                    the stillness of the night;</del>
                Giulietta opened a secret door<lb/>
                and descended, and Francesco saw her come forth into<lb/>
                the night in her beauty; robed in a robe of lights<lb/>
    &#x201C;What meant thy song to night, Francesco?&#x201D; said the maiden<lb/>
    &#x201C;What can a farewell to thee mean, Giulietta, but  misery?&#x201D;<lb/>
                And why farewell, said Giulietta, and she looked engineeringly <!--unsure--><lb/>
                at her lover, and there was <add place="above">an</add> agony passing over his <del rend="strikethrough">high forehead,</del><add place="above">countenance</add> and
                the damp <add place="above">deathlike</add> dew hung upon his forehead.<gap reason="omission" unit="chars" quantity="2"></gap> Why farewell he<lb/>
                repeated, ay. why farewell between thee and me, <del rend="strikethrough">After</del>cannot<lb/>
                shall not be<lb/>
    <add place="above">Why this agony, Francesco</add> Whither wouldn&#x02BC;t thou go. <del rend="strikethrough">Francesco</del>said Giulietta,<lb/>
                Ask the withered by that is torn quivering from its bough<lb/> <!--??-->
                and drifted at the will of the wretched wind &#x2013;ask the meteor<lb/>
                that is hurled regularly <!--??--> down <add place="above">among</add>the stars. ask the spring<lb/>
                of the ream when the tempest whirls it along the shore<lb/><pb/>
                where they would go for <!--worn and illegible--> and the autumn leaf<lb/>
                and vain as the ocean spray, and desolating and feared as<lb/>
                the sufference of the ___ of the night, shall I be Guilietta,<lb/>
                This is the madness Francesco, replied the maiden, where you<lb/>
                wait we part, or if not, how cant thou hast intended<lb/>
                I love knowest me not Giulietta &#x2013; <!--not sure if this is right--> I am not noble I am<lb/>
                not brave<lb/>
                Mock me not &#x2013; <del rend="strikethrough">thou not,</del> <!--there is a symbol here i am not sure how to represent--> Francesco said the maiden&#x2013;<lb/>
                I could be, I will be, Giulietta we will not part&#x2013;
                fly with me &#x2013; the night is down on the mountains my<lb/>
                mind <!--?--> is war&#x2013; ere the day downs we shall be for hence<lb/>
                in royalty, in honour, ay if thou will in power.<lb/>
                Thy bend, repeated <del rend="strikethrough">the maiden</del><add place="above">Giulietta</add> Fly with the will when<lb/>
                What art thou <add place="above">what mean you,</add> Francesco.
                I know not maiden, said Francesco <del rend="strikethrough">and be taught of I</del><lb/>
                I have not been what <del rend="strikethrough">not</del> I seem to be &#x2013; yet <!--unsure-->
                make me to. With thee I am Francesco&#x2013; without thee<lb/>
                I am a walking misery. the curse of others, <del rend="strikethrough">said</del>a <!--unsure--> curse<lb/>
                <del rend="strikethrough">of my own heart</del>an <add place="above">embodied</add> fear of reckless madness<lb/>
                the pestilence, the scourge, the deeper curse of my<lb/>
                own heart &#x2013; in one word, without thee, I am<lb/>
                Leoni.<lb/>
    And the word struck through to the maiden&#x02BC;s heart<lb/>
                with a coldness as of death, the cry she <!--something is struck through here cannot read--><add place="above">would have uttered</add>died<lb/>
                upon her lips, and she fainted in the arms of her lover<lb/>
                Oh how beautiful was the fear upon Giuliettas face on the day<lb/>
                in the lifeless __ __ as the snow that hid beneath the<lb/>
                moon upon the high Alpennine and the turn on <del rend="strikethrough">a</del><add place="above">her</add> countenance<lb/>
                was as the terror of troubled slumber<lb/>
                Then the hectic flush passed over her cheek, and she woke<lb/>
                from the partial death with a deep <add place="above">as of one in</add>gasp of pain and her dark<lb/>
                eye gleamed with a vague horror And she 
                her hand over her ___ brow. and lo &#x2013; it was as the ___<lb/>
                closed that ___ over the <del rend="strikethrough"><!--cannot read this--></del> brightness<lb/>
                of the midmight mood <gap></gap> Francesco. Francesco&#x2013; she said there<lb/> <!--there is text here that seems so fall off the page-->
                <del rend="strikethrough">is dead, dead she said</del>
    &#x201C;Francesco, Francesco!&#x201D; she said , &#x201C;thou toldest me
    something , - it was terrible , tell it me again . Fran&#x2010;
                        cesco ! -thou art not Francesco ,&#x201D; and she paused for a
                        moment . &#x201C;I know now ,&#x201D; she said ; &#x201C;I remember
                        well , very well , Francesco is dead , and thou — thou
                        art not , thou canst not , thou shalt not be Leoni , - the
                        bandit Leoni , - my brother&#x02BC;s enemy . O , Francesco !
                        say thou mockest me !&#x201D;
                        &#x201C;I was once Leoni ,&#x201D; he replied ; - &#x201C;thy brother&#x02BC;s
                        enemy never , or Garcio had not now lived . Could I
                        be the enemy of your brother , Giulietta ?&#x201D;
                        And Giulietta felt that it was Francesco , and not
                        Leoni who spoke , and she paused in deep agony .
                        
                        * * * * *
                        
                        Great was the tumult in the castle of <gap reason="omission" /><lb/>
                            an old peasant <del type= "strikethrough">(who had large gathering sticks amid the thickets <lb/>
                                or the seashoreat the foot of the castle.)</del> had come to Garcio<lb/>
                            saying<lb/>that he seen two figures (one of <add place="above">them</add><lb/>
                            <del type="strikethrough">which></del>was a maiden of exceeding beauty,)<lb/>
                            passing down westward <del type="strikethrough">towards</del><lb/>
                            on the <add place="above">sea</add>shore, at <add place= "above">the Lord of the Castle</add><lb/>
                            <del type="strikethrough">they had followed him</del>; he had seen them pass<lb/>
                            undeserved, the countenance of the other he said was<lb/>
                            one which he knew well, one which once seen was easily forgotten,hat of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName>,Leoni the bandit. Then <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName> <lb/>
                            for him only he feared. <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName> was wild with rage <add place="above">&#x0026; he</add> called his followers together, and the clash<lb/>
                            of arms was loud in the hall&#x2014;and then from the gate<lb/>
                            issused a troop of <del type="strikethrough">around used</del> warriors and their swords gleamed<lb/>
                            coldly in the <add place="above">star</add><del type="strikethrough">moon</del>light and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName> spurned on his <lb/>
                            bloody warhorse in the war&#x2013; and his countenance was pale<lb/>
                            with <del type="strikethrough">the</del> wrath, and he dashed madly forward along <lb/>
                            the winding shore<lb/>
                            
                            But one of the maidens of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName>, when she heard<lb/>
    the peasant&#x02BC;s tale, went and sought for <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName>, in her <del type="strikethrough">chamber</del><add place="above">father&#x02BC;s hall</add>, <lb/>
    and she was not there, and in her <del type="strikethrough">father&#x02BC;s</del> chamber and-<lb/><fw type="pageNum" place="top right">99</fw>
                            and she not there, and she descended by the secret staircase, <lb/>
                            and she saw footsteps in the dew on the grassy ground.<lb/>
    Then she returned weeping, &#x2013; and she came to the <del type="strikethough">the old man he&#x02BC;s</del><lb/>
                            father of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> &#x2010;and told him that <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">LEONI</persName>the bandit<lb/>
                            had carried <add place="above">her</add>away <del type="strikethrough">Giulietta</del><gap reason= "omission" /><lb/>And the old man was weak,<lb/>
                            and very feeble&#x2013; and he could not grieveand he bowed<lb/>
                            his head gently upon his breast and died<lb/>
                And the spirit went forth with a complaining, and <lb/>
                passed moaning on the night wind in search of those whom it loved&#x2010;<lb/>
                loved&#x2014;<gap reason= "omission"/> And it <add place="above">went</add><del type="strikethrough">fled</del> forth like a wrath of sea mist along the shore<lb/>
                and came and looked over the head of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> as she fled with<lb/>
                with <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName>, and as the spirit came near with her she rememembered her father  <lb/>
                and how he had said that the sea would not rise to him &#x2014;<lb/>
                And she stopped in great misery, exclaiming&#x2013; oh my father,my father<lb/>
                surely I have murdered thee  my father&#x2010;Then she heard through<lb/>
                her weeping the<lb/>noise of a soft sigh beside her&#x2010; and she startled<lb/>
                and looked round&#x2010;it was with&#x2010;like the voice of the wind among the <del type="strikethrough"> birds </del> <lb/>
                <name type="botanical" corresp="#LAUREL">laurel</name> leaves, neither like the mummers of the little waves upon the shore <lb/>
                <del type="strikethrough">And she said to <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName></del><lb/>
                Heardest thou nothing? <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName>, said to <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName>Leoni.<lb/>
                Nothing, Giulietta he replied. Nay, now  that I listen, methinks<lb/>
                I hear a sound, far away, like the tramp of steeds along the<lb/>
                sand. <gap reason= "omission"/> And Giulietta listened, and she was filled with great<lb/>
                fear.<gap reason= "omission"/> Oh fly, Leoni! she said, it is Garcio! fly and leave me<lb/>
                here.<lb/>
                But <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName> raised her in his arms, and bare her softly forward,<lb/>
                and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> overcame her fantasies and struggled onward,and they fled.<lb/>
                And now the rocks were seen rising high from the sea shore, and<lb/>
                the columns of the ruined temple were seen afore their summit, and<lb/>
    <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName> knew that his band was near.<add place="above">Oh on</add>&#x201C;one effort more Giuletta<lb/>
                he exclaimed. <gap reason= "omission"/> and we are safe. And now the tramp <fw type="pageNum" place="bottom left">99</fw><lb/>
                of the galloping horses came nearer and nearer, and the voices<lb/>
                of men were heard urging them on. Louder and louder became<lb/>
                the sound, and <del type="strikethrough">Leoni</del><persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> made one last struggle forward<lb/>
                and, they gained the rocks  ,they stood beneath the ruined<lb/>
                temple. <gap reason= "omission"/> Anselmo&#x2013; Anselmo&#x2013; cried Leoni aloud<lb/>
                <ref type="gloss_textual" target="filename_glosses.php#LACKOFQUOTATION"/>Anselmo Anselmo cried <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName> aloud<lb/>
                and he was answered, by a shout from the cliffs,<lb/>
                and the bandits leaped from their concealment; but ere<lb/>
                they gained the shore, the foremost horseman of the<lb/>
                opposite troop dashed like lightning into view &#x2014; it<lb/>
                was Garcio&#x2014; a shout of triumph burst from his lips<lb/>
                when he saw <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName>&#x2014;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> saw him level his,<lb/>   
                carbine&#x2014; with a shriek of agony, she threw herself<lb/>
                threw herself before <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName>, and fell dead into his arms and the <add place="above">dying</add> sigh<lb/>   
                that came from her lips sounded like&#x2013; <persName type="fictional" corresp="#FRANCESCO">Francesco</persName><lb/>   
                The band of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName> heard the shot, and were around<lb/>
                him <add place="above">in</add> an instant: and lo their leader was standing<lb/>   
                beside the body of a maiden and the calm upon his countenance <lb/>   
                was dreadful and there was a smile upon his lips like the <lb/>   
                grooming of the dog bowed of a withered skull and there<lb/>   
                was a stillness in his eye, and on her features but &#x2013; it was as<lb/>   
                the stillness of the volcano before it bursts forth into desolation<lb/>
                And his troops stood round him in a fearful silence&#x2013;<lb/>   
                <del type="strikethrough">Then/<del><add place="above">They was absolute still</add>like a whirlwind over the quietness of deeprooted waters,<lb/>   
                came <del type="strikethrough">a/<del><add place="above">the</add> the madness over the soul of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName>&#x2014; and he looked<lb/>   
                and saw that his band was beside him <del type="strikethrough">and he said/<del>
                his band was beside him <del type="strikethrough">and he said/<del>Stand by me, this night he said, and revenge <del type="strikethrough">yours</del> the loss of your leader<lb/>   
                <del type="strikethrough">And</del>Then he shouted his warshout aloud, and the bandits&#x2014;<lb/>   
                swelled the sound with eager voices, and <add place="above"> as </add> the followers of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName><lb/>   
                replied Leoni ashed at them like a thunderbolt&#x2014;<lb/>
                    Then loudly into the quietness of the leader rose the roar of <fw type="pageNum" place="bottom right">100</fw><lb/> of the battle, and the echoes rolled heavily over the sea.<gap reason= "omission"/> On came the<lb/>
                    bandit like the torando in its frower, and the bouncer of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName>low<lb/>   
                    backward theivery, but he cheered them again to the outset and the<lb/>   
                    tumult bellowed along the shore.<del type="strikethrough">as the</del> and the shots rang loud and<lb/>   
                    there from among the volumes of smoke lit by the.<del type="strikethrough">amis</del> death<lb/>   
                    flashes that curled its heavy and sulphurous mass into the <lb/>   
                    choked <del type="strikethrough">they</del>leaver&#x2014; <gap reason= "omission"/> Like the light that trembled along<lb/>   
                    <add place="above"> ruffed </add> waters of the ocean with <del type="strikethrough">its</del>its<add place="above"> a </add> shores and sparkles, gleamed<lb/>   
                    the <del type="strikethrough">sales</del> flashing sales amid the darkness of the war&#x2013; but <lb/>   
                    the dash of the warfront and the roar of the fire was not mingled <lb/>   
                    with any voice&#x2013; for the combatants could not shout in <lb/>   
                    the madness of the struggle, and the wounded fell in silence<lb/>   
                    and gashed out their <add place="above"> undignified</add> souls without a grover&#x2014; <lb/>   
                    
                    <del type="strikethrough">With the wickerate wrath of an <add place="above"> the </add> avenging first of the victim <lb/>   
                        frustating its murder, did</del>&#x0026; Leoni burst his path through<lb/>   
                    the <del type="strikethrough">the </del> mass of battle, and his <add place="above"> his bloodshot eye </add>  <del type="strikethrough">watched the </del>was on<lb/>   
                    on the crest of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName> as it rose <add place="above"> and fell </add> on the bellowy burst of<lb/>   
                    the war, and whether it were foe or friend whom he <lb/>   
                    met in his madness, he dashed the combatants aside in death,<lb/>   
                    and dove his way onward toward that <del type="strikethrough">high plunge of his</del><lb/>   
                    <del type="strikethrough">enemy</del> And with the implacable wrath of an avenging <lb/>   
                    spirit when the dark ghost of the victim walks the earth<lb/>   
                    in pursuit of its madness, <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName><del type="strikethrough">follow </del> sought<lb/>   
                    his single foe &#x2014; And the followers of <del type="strikethrough">Leoni </del><add place="above"> <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName></add> shrunk<lb/>   
                    back ever from his glance, and, as he broke <del type="strikethrough">into the </del><lb/>   
                    although the fore front of their battle, some turned <del type="strikethrough">their backs</del><lb/>   
                    and fled, and the rest hung back in disorder and dismay.<lb/>   
                    
                    Then the bandits drew backward out of the rest of the battle <lb/>   
                    like the dark reflux of a mighty bellow&#x2014; before it breaks upon<lb/>   
                    the shore, they joused for a moment, a murmer <del type="strikethrough">as came rite </del><fw type="pageNum" place="bottom left">100</fw>
                    
                    from their ranks, louder and louder became the voice, and then<lb/>   
                    and then with a shout that startled the very start thy broke down <lb/>   
                    upon thier heistating opponnets. <lb/>   
                    
                    And the shock was as the shock of an ocean, and irristable,<lb/>   
                    and the ranks of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName> were overwhelmed <add place="above"> and broken </add> in an instant,<lb/>   
                    and wild was the tumult as they were driven backwards <lb/>   
                    and struck down.  Then <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName> saw <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName> come upon with<lb/>   
                    the swoop of an eagle, and his eye quailed and his <lb/>   
                    limb quivered, before the despair of his <del type="strikethrough">off </del>foe&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    Wretch cried Leoni, lovest thou life? &#x2014;Oh, would<lb/>   
                    that I could make thy life to thee, what thou hast<lb/>   
                    made it to me,&#x2013; and thou shouldst live&#x2013; <lb/>   
                    I spared thee once, for her sake, &#x2013;thou hast well<lb/>   
                    rewarded me &#x2014; thy sister strikes thee &#x2013; <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName>&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    And he smote him dead. <lb/>   
                    
                    And the voice of battle drifted away towards the <lb/>   
                    the castle of <gap reason= "omission"/>,<ref type="gloss_contextual" target="filename_glosses.php#CASTLEOF"/> and the shouts of the victorious <lb/>   
                    bandits were heard echoing along the cliffs. But <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName> 
                    was no longer at their head ; in their victory they were <lb/>   
                    no longer at their head ; in their victory they were<lb/>   
                    without a leader, &#x2014;they remembered that he had commanded <lb/>   
                    them  to revenge his loss, and few , very few , of the followers of<lb/>   
                    <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName>, escaped the slaughter of that night&#x2014;and the flowers<lb/>   
                    soon <del type="strikethrough">were ready from </del> <add place="above"> wrapt thousands round </add>the towers of the castle and <del type="strikethrough">wraft it <lb/>   
                        round </del> and thou ready for once the darkness of the ocean. <lb/>   
                    And The bandits met by the <add place= "above">horrid</add> light of the ruthering fire<lb/>   
                    and sought for <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName> among the dead, and they found<lb/>   
                    the body of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GARCIO">Garcio</persName> &#x2014; and the sword of their leader lying beside<lb/>   
                    it&#x2013; but him they found not, and they retired<add place="above"> well </add>, under cover<lb/>   
                    of the night, to their fastness among the mountains. <fw type="pageNum" place="bottom right">101</fw><lb/>   
                    
                    Oh calmly, <add place="above"> brightly </add> beautifully the monring rose up out of the eastern <lb/>   
                    sea &#x2013;and widely spread the rosy<del type="strikethrough">glory </del> <add place="above"> dawn</add> over the deep&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    Gloriously the radiance stole, up into the high heaven &#x2014;<lb/>   
                    and the white clouds waved their light wings in the<lb/>   
                    deepness of its infinite blue, and looked out eastward<lb/>   
                    rejoicing, as they met the morning breeze that sprang upward <lb/>   
                    from its repose, in the <del type="strikethrough">olive </del>grove of silver olives&#x2010;<lb/>   
                    and it breathed on the gale clouds and <del type="strikethrough">it </del><add place="above"> they </add>fussed silently on<lb/>   
                    their path to meet the sun.<lb/>   
                    
                    And the sun lifted hishead majestically out of the sea, and <lb/>   
                    looked forth when the world   and the mists rolled away <lb/>   
                    before <del type="strikethrough">the </del> his glance, from its surface, and the waters<lb/>   
                    walked in light and the waves tussled onward, singing, with<lb/>   
                    sweet low voices, and the sun laid along the surges<lb/>   
                    a long golden path even unto the shore.<lb/>   
                    
                    And the mountains saw his glory an that morning <add place="above"> was </add> unconscious of the desolation<lb/>   
                    of the night, there was no sadness in the brillance of the door<lb/>   
                    and <add place="above"> that shown on the ruins of the castle </add> the voices of the winds and waters was gay, and the<lb/>   
                    surges that had dashed away the blood from the shore through the <lb/>   
                    night <add place="above"> now </add> broke clear and white on the unstained pebbles <lb/>   
                    And the columns of the ruined temple on the <del type="strikethrough">shore </del> <add place="above"> rocks </add> stood <lb/>   
                    tall in the heaven, and broadly and darkly against the gleaming<lb/>   
                    sky rose the tall trouts and spreading foliage of the ancient <lb/>   
                    trees. <gap reason= "omission"/> A figure was leaning against the rocks in<lb/>   
                    the sea shore, and war and haggered was <del type="strikethrough">the</del> its countenance<lb/>   
                    as if it had been withered away by the drowning fire that<lb/>   
                    flickered in the eye. <gap reason= "omission"/> Few, very few could have<lb/>   
                    recognised, in the  weary face and and withered form, the leaving <fw type="pageNum" place="bottom left">101</fw> <lb/>   
                    of the haughty and fiery <persName type="fictional" corresp="#LEONI">Leoni</persName> and the fishermen of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#POZZ">Pozzuolo</persName><lb/>   
                    affirm, that, for years of ten after that terrible night, the same<lb/>   
                    figure was seen wandering among the rocks upon the shore<lb/>   
                    with sleepless eye and weary limbs, and <del type="strikethrough">with its lacking </del> walking <lb/>   
                    among the crack as if seeking something he knew not what<lb/>   
                    with the restlessness of madness passing bitter <del type="strikethrough">old </del> and thriller at <lb/>   
                    old tunes whether the night winds were surging <add place="above"> sadly </add><lb/>   
                    or the starks gleaming tearfully, or the moon breaking <lb/>   
                    brightly, or the sun sitting silenting over the resting place <lb/>   
                    of the Bandits bride
                    
                    And where were <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> thoughts. She was<lb/>   
                    <del type="strikethrough">listening </del>waiting for a voice, that rose every evening<lb/>   
                    as the star disappered behind the summit of a distant<lb/>   
                    peaked mountain from the myrtle grove beneath the castles.<lb/>   
                    <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> hardley knew how the very sweet was to<lb/>   
                    her ear for it was the voices of all who loved her with<lb/>   
                    more than common love&#x2013; even with a love like that<lb/>   
                    of spirit. They had first met when <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> was young<lb/>   
                    very young, and <persName type="fictional" corresp="#FRANCESCO">Francesco</persName>&#x2014; a youth just verging <lb/>   
                    into manhood &#x2014; From their love she had been like <lb/>   
                    a halo of glory in the life of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#FRANCESCO">Francesco</persName>&#x2013; <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> knew <lb/>   
                    it &#x2010;she could not help loving <del type="strikethrough">our</del>him whose thoughts,<lb/>   
                    whose hopes, whose being were incented in her only&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    <del type="strikethrough">she thought of his she came upon his spirit <add place="above">soul </add><lb/>   
                        like the morning on the dark mountains &#x2013;<persName type="fictional" corresp="#FRANCESCO">Francesco</persName> <lb/>   
                        thought not how black would be the midnight<lb/>   
                        if that sun should ever set </del><lb/>   
                    
                    The thought of her came over his soul like the <lb/>  
                    morning on dark moutains &#x2014; when absent from <lb/>  
                    her. <persName type="fictional" corresp="#FRANCESCO">Francesco</persName> had two lines, and one was cold and dead <lb/>  <fw type="pageNum" place="bottom right">102</fw>
                    and <add place="above"> dark &#x0026; </add> cheerless, but the other was <del type="strikethrough">visionary></del><add place="above">the dreamy </add> life <add place="above">of the mind</add> beautiful<lb/>  
                    exceedingly, full of light and loveliness, for the vision of <lb/>  
                    her was there<del type="strikethrough">always</del><lb/>  
                    
                    Her father knew not of the love for his child. <persName type="fictional" corresp="#FRANCESCO">Francesco</persName><lb/>   
                    had been <add place="above"> her</add> only <del type="strikethrough">at interval</del> for meoments by stelath<lb/>   
                    pleading to <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> saw anicent feud of thier families<lb/>   
                    as an excuse for maintaining the <add place="above"> his love in</add> secret<lb/>   
                    Several times in the infuse or the dancer at the castle   <lb/>   
                    of &#x2010; a knight had useful of more graceful form <lb/>   
                    and nobles braving &#x2014; more knew him&#x2014; unless there was<lb/>   
                    recongition in the brightness of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta&#x02BC;s</persName>eye&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    Several times when  <add place="above"> she </add> did gone forth with his father<lb/>   
                    <add place="above"> &#x0026; a</add> of filthy knights the ranks had been thrown <lb/>   
                    into confusion as it by the supernatural individual <lb/>   
                    <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta</persName> only knew how &#x0026;several times when<lb/>   
                    the unusal was singing in the ball had come forward<lb/>   
                    of laughter glance and lotter brow and all bent forward <lb/>   
                    to <del type="strikethrough">hiss </del><add place="above">listened to </add>  his  <del type="strikethrough">strain but like </del>strain but the lay of love, charming all<lb/>   
                    was intended only for one&#x2014;<fw type="pageNum" place="bottom left">102</fw><lb/>   
                    
                    The song ceased for a moment,<add place="above">and </add> then again the profound <lb/>   
                    night breeze became vocal&#x2013; but <add place="above">now </add>the sounds were low and sad&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    and full of<add place="above">melancholy</add><del type="strikethrough">wildly</del> on <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GUILETTA">Guiletta&#x02BC;s</persName> ear&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    
                    Now broad and brillant hid the light <lb/>   
                    Of <del type="strikethrough">moon and </del> stars on flood and fell<lb/>   
                    But in my breath is a starless night<lb/>   
                    For I have come to say farewell&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    How glad, how swift was want to be <lb/>   
                    The step that love me back to thee<lb/>   
                    Now coldy rooms upon my heart<lb/>   
                    The mutuiny that is but to part&#x2014;<lb/>   
                    2. 
                    I do not ask a star, but while <lb/>   
                    I begin where I must not stay<lb/>   
                    Oh, but give me but a taunting smile <lb/>   
                    To light me on my lonely way<lb/>   
                    To shine a brillant leaving star <lb/>   
                    To my reverant glance afar&#x2013;<lb/>   
                    Through midnight which can have no morrow<lb/>   
                    Or the deep silent surge or sorrow <lb/>   
                    3.
                    <del type="strikethrough">The</del> ardent fire within me flashes&#x2013;<lb/>   
                    And though my heart counseled may be<lb/>   
                    There is a Phoenix in its ashes &#x2014;<lb/>   
                    Oh how I love the love of thee<lb/>   
                    Although my hope <del type="strikethrough">be chill</del> and my joy be chill<lb/>   
                    That constant flower will flicker still<lb/>   
                    And round my broken heart will play<lb/>   
                    With mocking melancholy ray<lb/>

                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>