<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;Title of Work&#x201d;</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in <hi rend="italic">Title of Printed Work</hi> (Date)</title>
                <!--The xml:ids for author and editor below should include the first, middle, and last initials of the author and the editor, respectively.-->
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#APW">Author of Printed Work</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#EPW">Editor of Printed Work</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#CR">Chalines Rosario</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Poems of John Ruskin</title>
                        <title type="sub">Volume I: Poems Written in Boyhood, 1826-1835</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1891">1891</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">xxiii</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Simple Prose. Delete this <div/> if not used.-->
            <div type="prose">
                <head type="title">Sermon XVIII</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter">The 6th. 7th. and 8th Commandments.</head>
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296810_Recto_01"/>
                    <p>13. 14. &#x0026; 15 verses. of 20 Chapter. of <title type="scripture" corresp="#EXODUS">Exodus</title>.
                    <lb/>I have already directed your attention
                    <lb/>to the first five of the ten commandments,
                    <lb/>we must now devote some of out time
                    <lb/>to the examination of the 6th, a precept
                    <lb/>which although it forbids what all do
                    <lb/>not consider crime, yet was decidadly ne
                    <lb/>cessary to regulate the conduct of that de&#x2010;
                    <lb/>praved people to whom <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</persName> addressed
                    <lb/>it. A variety of views have been taken
                    <lb/>of it, and many doubts raised concern&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ing it, but the commandment, is deci
                    <lb/>ded, all would be unhinged, if it were 
                    <lb/>not, it is doubtful in its application
                    <lb/>to one case only, namely to self defence.
                    <lb/>But here are not yet more difficulties. for the
                    <lb/>inquiry is suggested, shall we except in the
                    <lb/>case of national as well as in that of per
                    <lb/>sonal defence, and if we do so, the pre
                    <lb/>cept becomes exceedingly limited. as it is dif&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ficult to distinguish between purely defensive
                    <lb/>or partly offensive war. Indeed it is easy to
                    <lb/>satisfy ourselves that we are acting on pe
                    <lb/>rsonal self defence, when we are not so,
                    <lb/>and much more, much easier, to persuade
                    <lb/>ourselves and decieve ourselves, as 
                    <lb/>to defensive war.If therefore, under our 
                    <lb/>economy, we except atall, we are immed
                    <lb/>iately involved in difficulties. But, with the 
                    <lb/>Jews, this was provided for. There were
                    <lb/>cities of refuge for the person who had
                    <lb/>killed in self defence, and their battles.
                    <lb/>were always under oracular direction. But
                    <lb/>as exceptions in certain cases have been made
                    <lb/>under such direction, we now make such
                    <lb/>exceptions generally, on the principle that
                    <lb/>what is right in one case, cannot be
                    <lb/>wrong in another. But the case is not
                    <lb/>parallel, as it would be if <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</persName> were spe
                    <lb/>cifically to guide everything at present
                    <lb/>and to place himself at the head of all
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296810_Verso_01"/>
                    <lb/>our affairs, We cannot take advantage
                    <lb/>of these exceptions, for they were made under
                    <lb/>peculiar auspices, and in peculiar circum&#2010;
                    <lb/>stances, we know not whether in our case,
                    <lb/>they would be admitted, we ought to think
                    <lb/>that as they are contrary to this com&#x2010;
                    <lb/>mandment they would not be so, our 
                    <lb/>business is to obey the commandment
                    <lb/>just as it is given us, and not to look
                    <lb/>our for exceptions.</p> 
                    <p>But it may be said that it would
                    <lb/>be impossible to preserve any people, if 
                    <lb/>they were not to act on the general pri
                    <lb/>nciples of nations, or of self defence (unless
                    <lb/>they were defended by miracles, which
                    <lb/>do not belong to the present economy
                    <lb/>of the earth. Now we have seen that
                    <lb/>we must not refer to the Jews as an
                    <lb/>example, we must take the laws in a
                    <lb/>general sense as they were addressed to 
                    <lb/>the whole of mankind, except where 
                    <lb/>the deity himself has made exceptions 
                    <lb/>We must remember that whatever laws
                    <lb/>were addresed to <persName corresp="#NOAH">Noah</persName>, when he came
                    <lb/>out of the ark, which were not after
                    <lb/>wards abrogated, were addressed to the 
                    <lb/>father the future father of all mankind
                    <lb/>and were therefore, as well as the code
                    <lb/>of commandments delivered on <placeName corresp="#SINAI">Sinai</placeName>
                    <lb/>to be rules for the future conduct of all
                    <lb/>mankind. Now, in the sixth verse of 
                    <lb/>the 9th chapter of <title type="scripture" corresp="#GENESIS">Genesis</title>, we find the word.
                    <lb/>Whoso sheddith mans blood, by man
                    <lb/>shall his blood be shed. This is decis&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ive, the highest possible penalty is attach
                    <lb/>ed to murder under any circumstances.
                    <lb/>This authority dissipates all difficul&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ties that can be started, for all such
                    <lb/>difficulties are founded on the supposi&#x2010;
                    <lb/>tion that we may take the management
                    <lb/>of affairs into our own hands.&#x2014;With
                    <lb/>regard to the principle of defensive was
                    <lb/>it is still less doubtful. I might notice
                    <lb/>the example presented us in the 14 chapter.
                    <lb/>of <title type="scripture" corresp="#ZACHARIAH">Zachariah</title>, in which there is a com&#x2014;
                    <lb/>bination of many nations against 
                    <lb/>the church of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, yet there is no appear
                    <lb/>ance of resistance on the side of the church
                    <lb/>it stands still, and is indolent in the
                    <lb/>midst of this mighty preparation, while
                    <lb/><persName type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</persName> himself appears on its side. he <del rend="strikethrough">in</del>
                    <lb/>brings a tumult among the people,
                    <lb/>and the church of <persName type="fictional" corresp="GOD">God</persName> dwells safe&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ly in <placeName corresp="#JERUSALEM">Jerusalem</placeName>.</p> 
                    <p>We have next to consider that this pre
                    <lb/>cept may be violated without killing,
                    <lb/>and this is referred to by the now tes&#x2010;
                    <lb/>tament, &#x201C;if any man hate his brother
                    <lb/>he is a murderer and this is almost
                    <lb/>worse, at least with regard to the 
                    <lb/>state of the criminal, than actual murder
                    <lb/>For in the first case, there is a general cry 
                    <lb/>against him, all at one pronounce him 
                    <lb/>guilty, he is clearly so before <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</persName> &#x0026; man
                    <lb/>and <!-- [there(?)] --> is an opportunity for reflecting
                    <lb/>afforded him, by his crime being thus
                    <lb/>brought before him. but it is not so when
                    <lb/>the murder is committed in the heart, 
                    <del rend="strikethrough">The reu</del> The criminal then can reason 
                    <lb/>away his sin, he says to himself my 
                    <lb/>aversion is not to this individual, but to
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296810_Verso_02"/>
                    <lb/>his faults. the crime is thus not seen 
                    <lb/>in its working, and there is no general 
                    <lb/>cry against him to convince his mind &#x0026;
                    <lb/>bring the crime home to him, and it there
                    <lb/>fore requires constant watching, and never
                    <lb/>failing care, lest when we first allow our
                    <lb/>selves even to perceive the faults of an indiv
                    <lb/>idual, we be found sowing such seeds of 
                    <lb/>enmity in our hearts, as may afterwards
                    <lb/>spring up and flourish against him &#x0026; let
                    <lb/>us so escape from the grasping of this dread
                    <lb/>ful commandment, that after having es&#x2010;
                    <lb/>caped all earthly tribunals, we may not,
                    <lb/>be arrainged for our secret sins before the 
                    <lb/>bar of the almighty,</p>
                    <p>In verse 14 we have another precept of
                    <lb/>the same general application, unconfined
                    <lb/>to any economy. although so frequently
                    <lb/>disregarded. I speak not of publick law
                    <lb/>which prohibits its violation, but of pri&#x2010;
                    <lb/>vate history. here also the crime may
                    <lb/>be committe in the heart. <title type="scripture" corresp="#MATTHEW">Matthew</title> 5 
                    <lb/>Now it may be asked, if the more pres
                    <lb/>sing of the interdict would, here, prevent
                    <lb/>the crime. It would not. To speak to
                    <lb/>the river of wickedness, and tell it You are
                    <lb/>not to do this, or you are not to do that.&#x2015;
                    <lb/>would be like endeavouring to shut up the 
                    <lb/>tempest. No, the only way is to exert some
                    <lb/>hallowing influence. for the passions given
                    <lb/>were intended to work, and to work pow
                    <lb/>erfully, and our inquiry must be, not
                    <lb/>whether they are to be indulged, but in
                    <lb/>what way they are to be indulged. We,
                    <lb/>are thus not endeavouring to annihi
                    <lb/>late, or paralyse, but to direct. We must
                    <lb/>then hold up to view the great things of <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</persName>
                    <lb/>the pure, the chaste, hallowed &#x0026; <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>
                    <lb/>himself, an object sufficiently command
                    <lb/>ing to egross and interest all the affecti
                    <lb/>ons, and this is in fact the only mode of 
                    <lb/>escape from committing crime in the heart.
                    <lb/>In the 15 verse we find a prohibition of the 
                    <lb/>appropriation of property, without the 
                    <lb/>consent of the individual possessing it. Now
                    <lb/>stealing in the plain and ordinary accep
                    <lb/>tation of the term, is a crime from which 
                    <lb/>all our senses recoil at once, but they do
                    <lb/>not so, from the possession of property by 
                    <lb/>unfair means by any. even the slightest
                    <lb/>deviation from fair and honest principles
                    <lb/>which is equally an act of theft. In a com
                    <lb/>mercial country like ours, how many se
                    <lb/>cret violations of this commandment might 
                    <lb/>be discoverabl. and indeed wihtout con&#x2010;
                    <lb/>stant application to <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</persName>. it is very difficult
                    <lb/>to watch over all our actions with such con
                    <lb/>stant care as may enable us to prevent the
                    <lb/>slightest&#x2014;deviaton from a strict observa
                    <lb/>tion of this important commandment</p>
                    <p>The 9 and 10 commandments, are of
                    <lb/>too much importance to permit us to
                    <lb/>enter a present upon their examination
                    <lb/>but I shall make a few general observation 
                    <lb/>which have been sugested to me by the con
                    <lb/>sideration of these precepts. I would first
                    <lb/>of all endeavour to impress upon you the
                    <lb/>vast importance of trusting in <persName type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</persName>. We are
                    <lb/>so clearly brought in guilt by every com
                    <lb/>mandment, there is no chance of escape. 
                    <lb/>no excuse, that we can offer for our con
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296810_Recto_02"/>
                    <lb/>violation of these commandments, But if 
                    <lb/>we can fulfil this important duty, our
                    <lb/>despair is no quickened by the examina
                    <lb/>tion of our hearts. we read not our own con
                    <lb/>demnation in the code of commandments 
                    <lb/>and although we know that neither by re
                    <lb/>formation nor repentance we can escape
                    <lb/>from them, yet we are able to regard them
                    <lb/>as the requirements of a kind and generous
                    <lb/>Father. and the way to fulfil which has been
                    <lb/>pointed out by him.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>