<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;Title of Work&#x201d;</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in <hi rend="italic">Title of Printed Work</hi> (Date)</title>
                <!--The xml:ids for author and editor below should include the first, middle, and last initials of the author and the editor, respectively.-->
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#APW">Author of Printed Work</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#EPW">Editor of Printed Work</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#SEM">Sarah Elizabeth Montelepre</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Poems of John Ruskin</title>
                        <title type="sub">Volume I: Poems Written in Boyhood, 1826-1835</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1891">1891</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">xxiii</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Simple Prose. Delete this <div/> if not used.-->
            <div type="witness" subtype="sermon">
                <head type="title">Sermon V</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <pb facs="296805v_0026"/>
                    <head type="chapter">The character of Abraham</head>
                    <p>1st verse XXIV.  And <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> was old
                    <lb/>and well stricken, in years, and the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> 
                    <lb/>had blessed <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> in all things.  I 
                    <lb/>have read these verses, in order to make 
                    <lb/>some observations on the history, char
                    <lb/>acter, and religion of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, as an 
                    <lb/>illustration of the faith and obedience, of 
                    <lb/>which he sets us so striking an example.
                    <lb/>Now I should premise that although we 
                    <lb/>often consider religion, generally, as a cr
                    <lb/>eed of outward institutions, and although 
                    <lb/>it is fitting so to do, yet it is also ne
                    <lb/>cessary, that we should consider it, as 
                    <lb/>embodied in some of the principal
                    <lb/>characters which are held forth, for our 
                    <lb/>imitation, in the holy <title type="scripture" corresp="#BIBLE">scripture</title>s.  For
                    <lb/>religion, as drawn by the pen of in
                    <lb/>spiration, is entirely perfect, both in 
                    <lb/>its injunctions, and in its ordinan&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ces, but as it appears in character, 
                    <lb/>it is imperfect sometimes distorted, its 
                    <lb/>injunctions are forgotten, and its ordi&#x2010;
                    <lb/>nances are not observed, which is entire
                    <lb/>ly caused by the imperfection of man, 
                    <lb/>not of religion.  Yet, it will be profita
                    <lb/>ble for us to observe how far, and how 
                    <lb/>perfectly, religion can be embodied, in 
                    <lb/>the character of any human creature 
                    <lb/>and thus, and thus only we shall be a
                    <lb/>ble to feel, and to lament the great&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ness of our own coming short.  
                    <lb/>Without therefore, yielding one title, of 
                    <lb/>the influence, and perfect excellency of 
                    <lb/>religion, we wish to see how far that 
                    <lb/>influence extends itself, over the life,
                    <lb/>the actions, and the character, of this 
                    <lb/>great patriarch.  Now, the history of</p>
                    <pb facs="296805v_0027"/>
                    <lb/><p><persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, is not that, of a young and 
                    <lb/>inexperienced convert, it is not of the first 
                    <lb/>enthusiasm, and budding of religion, but of
                    <lb/>the steady and undeviating piety of an ag
                    <lb/>ed, and venerable man, of one who has 
                    <lb/>been much tried. and whose trials having
                    <lb/>been passed through with glory, and with 
                    <lb/>honour, have only caused him to come
                    <lb/>forth like refined gold from the furnace 
                    <lb/>he was old, and stricken in age, and the 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> had blessed him in all things.</p>
                    <lb/><p>We shall now proceed to consider the var
                    <lb/>ious points of the history of the patriarch
                    <lb/>and the example, which they present us 
                    <lb/>with.  The conduct of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> through
                    <lb/>out the whole of his life, is, in the first 
                    <lb/>place, a most striking illustration of faith 
                    <lb/>and this faith was realized in his every 
                    <lb/>action. and indeed, in the very first action
                    <lb/>of which any mention is made.  He was 
                    <lb/>told to leave his house, his family, his coun
                    <lb/>try, but for what compensation?  He is not
                    <lb/>told where is his residence to be.  He is not 
                    <lb/>told.  What is the use of the sacrifice.  He is 
                    <lb/>not told.  The place in which he had been 
                    <lb/>brought up, where his affections must have
                    <lb/>been centred, and with which recollections
                    <lb/>most dear to him must have associa&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ted, must be left in order to go to an un
                    <lb/>known land, of which nothing whatever
                    <lb/>is told <del rend="strikethrough">us</del> him.  Now, had <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, in
                    <lb/>stead of exercising faith required evidence 
                    <lb/>farther evidence than the voice of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, it is
                    <lb/>possible, that on account of this hesitati
                    <lb/>on, he might have been disinherited,  The 
                    <lb/>only evidence which he had, or which he 
                    <lb/>asked for, was, the certainty that <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>
                    <lb/>had spoken, and all, except this, was en
                    <lb/>tirely unsatisfactory.  Oh, that we could
                    <lb/>be contended to do thus, to believe the 
                    <lb/>promises of <title type="scripture" corresp="#BIBLE">Scripture</title>, without prying in
                    <lb/>to the future and to receive the word of
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, as sufficient testimony.  But, it
                    <lb/>may be asked, if we receive the testimony 
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> in any other way than that, in 
                    <lb/>which it was accepted by <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, and
                    <lb/>before I answer this question, I would,
                    <lb/>observe how exceedingly different are the
                    <lb/>circumstances in which we are placed, from
                    <lb/>those in which we have found <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> 
                    <lb/>exercising his faith <del rend="strikethrough">so</del> in such an unqual
                    <lb/>ified, and unhesitating manner.  We have
                    <pb facs="296805v_0028"/>
                    <lb/>seen these promises fulfilled, which had only
                    <lb/>been made to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, we have seen the
                    <lb/>birth of that <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">redeemer</persName>, on whom it was 
                    <lb/>faith only which enabled <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> to be
                    <lb/>lieve, and during a lengthened series of 
                    <lb/>ages, we have seen the christian church
                    <lb/>passing through <del rend="strikethrough">?</del> severe and numberless 
                    <lb/>trials and passing through them with vic
                    <lb/>tory, and triumph, We stand on ground in
                    <lb/>finitely superior to that on which <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>stood, and under these circumstances,&#x2014; I
                    <lb/>would answer, that I very much doubt, 
                    <lb/>if we atall accept the word, in the man
                    <lb/>ner in which it was accepted by <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName><!--"ham" on next line-->,
                    <lb/>If the word of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> were, indeed, 
                    <lb/>thus received, should we not be inclined to 
                    <lb/>enquire more closely and  more constantly
                    <lb/>into the <title type="scripture" corresp="#BIBLE">Scripture</title>s, into that which is 
                    <lb/>the very ground of our faith.  I think, that
                    <lb/>if we did receive the word thus unqualifi
                    <lb/>edly, without <del rend="strikethough">dis</del> endeavoring to under
                    <lb/>stand those parts which the <persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName>
                    <lb/>hath placed above our comprehension, there
                    <lb/>would be more unity of action, and prac
                    <lb/>tical effect, in the whole of the Christian 
                    <lb/>system, I consider, that the petty, and in
                    <lb/>dubitably occasioned by that spirit of <del rend="strikethrough">u</del>
                    <lb/>unbelief, or at <del rend="strikethrough">at</del> least of receiving the 
                    <lb/><title type="scripture" corresp="#BIBLE">bible</title> only with commutations and reser
                    <lb/>vations, to bring down its inscrutable, 
                    <lb/>mysteries to the levell of our feeble com
                    <lb/>prehensions, instead of accepting the tes&#x2010;
                    <lb/>timony at <!--line?--> once, of risking all when the 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> hath spoken, and the <persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName> hath 
                    <lb/>commanded us.  It was no light thing
                    <lb/>nor one that in any <del rend="strikethrough">ther</del> other case would
                    <lb/>have been entered upon without long &#x0026; 
                    <lb/>mature consideration, that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> should 
                    <lb/>leave his family and his friends, his home 
                    <lb/>and his country to go into a strange, and 
                    <lb/>unknown land, whose inhabitants, if it
                    <lb/>had other inhabitants than the wild beasts 
                    <lb/>of the field, knew nothing of the <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> whom
                    <lb/>he worshipped and obeyed, It had been 
                    <lb/>long, ere <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> in such a circumstance
                    <lb/>as this, had followed the advice of the wi
                    <lb/>sest or the holiest of mortals, and it had
                    <lb/>then been after much doubt and deep de
                    <lb/>liberation.  But when he heard the voice
                    <pb facs="296805v_0029"/>
                    <lb/>of the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName>, he complied at once, and his com
                    <lb/>pliance was unhesitating and unqualified.
                    <lb/><!--?-->I should question the wisdom of man, if it
                    <lb/>led me into trouble or perplexity, but if the
                    <lb/>commands of the <persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName> appeared to
                    <lb/>bring me into either, yet I feel myself en
                    <lb/>tirely safe, under his guidance, and am will
                    <lb/>ing to sacrifice any thing, and every thing
                    <lb/>if the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> commands me so to do.</p>
                    <lb/><p>Again, <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> was promised by <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> 
                    <lb/>that he should have a son, and that in 
                    <lb/>him should his seed be called, and thus, 
                    <lb/>all the promises which <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> ever made
                    <lb/>to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, that his should be made a 
                    <lb/>great nation, that his name should be 
                    <lb/>made great &#x0026;, are entirely centred upon
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName>.  And yet, in apparent contra&#x2010;
                    <lb/>diction to the whole of this, another com
                    <lb/>mandment is given to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, to sac
                    <lb/>rifice <persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName>. to take away that life
                    <lb/>on which the fulfilment of all the promis
                    <lb/>es depended. and besides all this, it was,
                    <lb/>apparently in contradiction to the for<del rend="strikethrough">m</del>
                    <lb/>mer commands of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>., for human sac
                    <lb/>rifice had been expressly forbidden.  Now
                    <lb/>under these circumstances and in our way 
                    <lb/>of receiving the word of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, these opp
                    <lb/>posing points would have, very likely des
                    <lb/>troyed our faith we should have doubt
                    <lb/>ed, and reasoned, &#x0026; deliberated and hesita
                    <lb/>ted and most likely rejected,  But, we 
                    <lb/>see that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> does not reason
                    <lb/>atall upon the circumstance, he knows
                    <lb/>not, and he does not endeavour to ascer
                    <lb/>tain, how his expectations justly found
                    <lb/>ed on the promises, were to be realized
                    <lb/>but he knows that he is a creature with
                    <lb/>his creator, and his motto which he kept 
                    <lb/>continually in view was, Shall not the 
                    <lb/>judge of all the earth do right, he does
                    <lb/>not take upon him to reconcile opposing 
                    <lb/>circumstances, he does not suffer his affec
                    <lb/>tions, or aught else to interfere with his
                    <lb/>obedience, and <del rend="strikethrough">t</del> we find him about to
                    <lb/>sacrifice <persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName>.  But the trial of his
                    <lb/>faith is sufficient. he is arrested by an
                    <lb/>angel, and a ram, provided as a more ac
                    <lb/>ceptable sacrifice to the <persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName>, is 
                    <lb/>offered up in the stead of <persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName>.  But it
                    <lb/>may again be objected, why was his faith 
                    <lb/>thus tried, was it merely to increase that
                    <lb/>faith, was it only to improve his charac
                    <lb/>ter, Certainly not.  It was to afford
                    <pb facs="296805v_0030"/>
                    <lb/>a farther example and illustration, of faith
                    <lb/>to the descendants of the patriarch, who was 
                    <lb/>to be the father of the faithful.  Let us
                    <lb/>now again direct the attention of those who
                    <lb/>are wanting in faith to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>. and ask
                    <lb/>them if they yet think, that their ac
                    <lb/>ceptation of the word of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> is equally free,
                    <lb/>and unlimited, with that of the patriarch
                    <lb/>I should, next consider the circumstan
                    <lb/>ces of the life of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, as a most re
                    <lb/>markable illustration of the power of 
                    <lb/>Prayer. 2, and 22 to 33 verse XVIII We here
                    <lb/>find <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> and <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, in immediate 
                    <lb/>and visible contact.  Three men appear
                    <lb/>ed unto <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> in the plain of <placeName corresp="#MAMRE">Mamre</placeName><!--"re" on next line-->
                    <lb/>, as he sat in his tent door in the heat 
                    <lb/>of the day.  One of these was <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> him Se
                    <lb/>self, the other two were angels, We may 
                    <lb/>ask how <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> was present to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, &#x0026; 
                    <lb/>I would answer, in the same manner
                    <lb/>as he appeared to <persName corresp="#MOSES">Moses</persName> in the fiery bush,
                    <lb/>or to the Israelites, in the pillar of cloud 
                    <lb/>That is, he chose some body, in this in
                    <lb/>stance he appeared in the form of him 
                    <lb/>whom he created in his own image, to in
                    <lb/>dicate, or signify his especial presence; al
                    <lb/>though this body, whether it were cloud
                    <lb/>or fire, or flesh, could not, strictly speak
                    <lb/>ing be called <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, Now, after the
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> had made himself known unto
                    <lb/><!--"A" on previous line--><persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> we find that he entered into
                    <lb/>conversation with him, the creature was
                    <lb/>thus placed in intimate communion with
                    <lb/>the <persName corresp="#GOD">Creator</persName>, and I do not know anything
                    <lb/>throughout the whole range of sacred
                    <lb/>writings that is so strikingly illustra
                    <lb/>tive of the power of prayer, as the result 
                    <lb/>of this conversation.  We see <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>in perfect self possession, yet remember
                    <lb/>ing that he is but dust and ashes, calm
                    <lb/>ly offering up, in the spirit of benevolence
                    <lb/>his prayers for <placeName corresp="#SODOM">Sodom</placeName>, and presenting
                    <lb/>his reasons to the <persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName> for inter
                    <lb/>rupting his purpose, &#x0026; <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> every one of these
                    <lb/>supplications, we find to be answered in 
                    <lb/>the affirmative.  Here then, we have 
                    <lb/>an example of the feelings with which
                    <lb/>we constantly and invariable should pray  
                    <lb/>This prayer rests upon faith, and we may
                    <lb/>be sure that prayers which are not
                    <lb/>so grounded, will not be accepted.
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Recto_1"/>
                    <lb/>And, in our own case, if we can believe, the
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Redeemer</persName> has died, and has obtained for us
                    <lb/>salvation, we may then with all boldness
                    <lb/>appear before <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, yet with diffidence, know
                    <lb/>ing our own depravity yet assured that our
                    <lb/>prayers will be granted.  For <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> looks not
                    <lb/>for certain forms of worship or for cer
                    <lb/>tain turns of expression, but for the feeling
                    <lb/>the faith, the love, the faith, which should,
                    <lb/>instigate the prayer, the love, which sho
                    <lb/>uld direct the prayer, the feeling, which
                    <lb/>should animate the prayer, and be assur
                    <lb/>ed, that the prayer of the patriarch, was
                    <lb/>entirely in keeping with all these.  <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> 
                    <lb/>premises, that he is but dust and ashes,
                    <lb/>here was his humility, he asked nothing
                    <lb/>for himself, he entirely forgot his own 
                    <lb/>case in his anxiety for the preservati
                    <lb/>on of even the wickedest of the men of 
                    <lb/><placeName corresp="#SODOM">Sodom</placeName>, for he was not so anxious for
                    <lb/>the safety of the few righteous men who
                    <lb/>might exist in <placeName corresp="#SODOM">Sodom</placeName>, as that their
                    <lb/>presence might preserve the unrighteous 
                    <lb/>from destruction, he reduces the sup
                    <lb/>posed number of these men to the
                    <lb/>very lowest limit which even his
                    <lb/>benevolence could suggest, or permit 
                    <lb/>and yet the mercy of the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> is unlim
                    <lb/>ited.  here was <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>s love and
                    <lb/>benevolence toward his fellow crea
                    <lb/>tures, and he also says. &#x201C;That be far 
                    <lb/>from thee to do after this manner
                    <lb/>to slay the righteous with the wicked
                    <lb/>and that the righteous should be as
                    <lb/>the wicked, that be far from thee!_ 
                    <lb/>Shall not the judge of all the earth do 
                    <lb/>right,?__ Here was his accordance in 
                    <lb/>and certainty of, the divine justice, 
                    <lb/>and being grounded and supported <!--by?-->
                    <lb/>this justice, his prayer was accepted.
                    <lb/>In the 3rd, and last place, I would
                    <lb/>wish to consider the circumstances,
                    <lb/>attendant upon the life of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>as an illustration of the <del rend="strikethrough">pe</del> general.
                    <lb/>weakness of human nature,.  Relig
                    <lb/>ion, as we before observed, is perfect,
                    <lb/>and spotless in itself, but we never
                    <lb/>find it so in the history of man, be
                    <lb/>cause the evil of his nature is constant
                    <lb/>ly resisting the operation of religion
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Verso_1"/>
                    <lb/>Now had <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> been entirely per
                    <lb/>fect, it might be said that we had 
                    <lb/>found religion embodied purely em
                    <lb/>bodied in his character, in contradic
                    <lb/>tion to all other experience. But he was
                    <lb/>not perfect, he deviated from the path
                    <lb/>of religion in many circumstances and
                    <lb/>those not unimportant ones, When he
                    <lb/>went into <placeName corresp="#EGYPT">Egypt</placeName>, he denied that 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#SARAH">Sarah</persName><!--"Sa" on previous line--> was his wife in order to avoid
                    <lb/>an imaginary injury, it might be said
                    <lb/>he told the truth when he said she 
                    <lb/>was his sister, but not the whole truth 
                    <lb/><del rend="strikethrough">and</del> the deception was as great as if 
                    <lb/>it had been a positive falsehood, and 
                    <lb/>the wickedness in him, was, therefore 
                    <lb/>also equal.  When we consider, that
                    <lb/>this was the same man who would un
                    <lb/>hesitatingly have sacrificed his son at 
                    <lb/>the command of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, is it not a won
                    <lb/>derful illustration of the words of st <persName corresp="#STPAUL">Paul</persName>
                    <lb/>&#x201C;the spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh 
                    <lb/>is weak.  Now it may be asked, why 
                    <lb/>the failings of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> are told us,
                    <lb/>and there are two reasons, First, it was
                    <lb/>to bring evidence, of the truth of the nar
                    <lb/>rative, For had <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> been held
                    <lb/>up to us, as perfect religion embodied, 
                    <lb/>as faultless, had the history of his faith
                    <lb/>his love his justice, alone been given to
                    <lb/>us, this handle would be at once have
                    <lb/>been seized upon by infidelity, and the
                    <lb/>accuracy of the whole narrative would 
                    <lb/>have been questioned, if not its truth
                    <lb/>as being in entire contradiction to the
                    <lb/>maxims inculcated by the <title type="scripture" corresp="#BIBLE">Scripture</title>s 
                    <lb/>and confirmed by experience.  And sec
                    <lb/>ondly, that the conduct of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> 
                    <lb/>might be constantly held up to all
                    <lb/>posterity, as an example, which not on
                    <lb/>ly ought to imitated, but which
                    <lb/>in some degree, might be so.  For
                    <lb/>we again repeat, that if we had not
                    <lb/>been informed of the failings of the
                    <lb/>patriarch, and he had been held up
                    <lb/>to us entirely perfect, we should have
                    <lb/>affirmed that the model was beyond 
                    <lb/>our imitation, and that either the man
                    <lb/>who attained to such a high degree of
                    <lb/>perfection. must have been gifted with
                    <lb/>powers <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> much superior to ours,&#x2014;or 
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Recto2"/>
                    <lb/>else, must have been placed in totally 
                    <lb/>different situations, and which were 
                    <lb/>much more favourable.  Thus, hav
                    <lb/>ing no hope of success, we should have
                    <lb/>been deterred from making the ef
                    <lb/>fort, and the whole benefit of the exam
                    <lb/>ple presented to us by <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, would 
                    <lb/>have been entirely lost, But when we 
                    <lb/>see how great the failings were, even 
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, we can consider him, as 
                    <lb/>going before us in a path, in which 
                    <lb/>by the grace of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, we may follow.
                    <lb/>him, and as are, whom we are able 
                    <lb/>to imitate, inasmuch as even he, was 
                    <lb/>not perfect.  Still these failings, it 
                    <lb/>must be remarked, were only inciden
                    <lb/>tal, they were not of frequent occurr
                    <lb/>ence, and his habit his general ha
                    <lb/>bit, was to rise above them, And, al
                    <lb/>though he was a man of like passions 
                    <lb/>with ourselves, yet there may have. 
                    <lb/>been other causes, which can also ac
                    <lb/>count for his so utterly forgetting
                    <lb/>himself.  There is, there can be, no 
                    <lb/>doubt. that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> had one, gen
                    <lb/>eral rule, by which to guide himself
                    <lb/>in all difficulties, this was, to ask. if 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> had spoken, if so, <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> instantly to 
                    <lb/>obey, without even so much as reason
                    <lb/>ing upon the subject, and it was 
                    <lb/>only when he forgot himself, and 
                    <lb/>deviated from this general rule, or line 
                    <lb/>of conduct, that he was drawn into
                    <lb/>into any failing like that which we
                    <lb/>have been considering.  It is neither 
                    <lb/>said that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> was comman
                    <lb/>ded to go into <placeName corresp="#EGYPT">Egypt</placeName>. nor that he
                    <lb/>asked <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> whether it were fitting so 
                    <lb/>to do, No, we are told that he fear
                    <lb/>ed for his flocks, and for his herds, be
                    <lb/>cause of the famine that prevailed, 
                    <lb/>through the land, it was entirely a 
                    <lb/>selfish consideration, which induced him
                    <lb/>to go down into <placeName corresp="#EGYPT">Egypt</placeName>, and therefore, 
                    <lb/>not being under the protection of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>
                    <lb/>he was first encompassed by danger, &#x0026; 
                    <lb/>then induced to commit crime, in order, 
                    <lb/>to escape.  We may learn from this, that
                    <lb/>it is necessary constantly to adhere to our
                    <lb/>fundamental<!--y--> principles, if we deviate from
                    <lb/>those but a very little, we are gone
                    <pb facs="Ruskin_MA_3451_296806_Verso_2"/>
                    <lb/>There is another remarkable failing of 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, which remains to be noticed
                    <lb/>his taking <persName corresp="#HAGAR">Hagar</persName> to be his wife, It is true 
                    <lb/>that <persName corresp="#ISHMAEL">Ishmael</persName>, the son of <persName corresp="#HAGAR">Hagar</persName> was under 
                    <lb/>divine protection but it was not by him 
                    <lb/>that the promises were to be fulfilled.  The
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> had expressly said, In <persName corresp="#ISAAC">Isaac</persName> shall 
                    <lb/>thy seed be called, and it was not by
                    <lb/>his command, that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> took 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#HAGAR">Hagar</persName><!--"Ha" on previous line-->. and the after circumstances as
                    <lb/>might have been expected, ended evilly 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#SARAH">Sarah</persName> believed imperfectly, that is, she
                    <lb/>believed that the promises would be ful
                    <lb/>filled, but she could not trust the man
                    <lb/>ner of it to the <persName corresp="#GOD">Almighty</persName>, and as this 
                    <lb/>manner was above her comprehension
                    <lb/>she endeavoured to fulfill<del rend="strikethrough">ed</del>, them, in 
                    <lb/>her own way, and it was the part of 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> to have resisted her.  But we
                    <lb/>see, that here again he forgot himself 
                    <lb/>and yielded, therefore, let us hencefor
                    <lb/>ward look up to him, as a man of 
                    <lb/>like passions with ourselves, let us com
                    <lb/>pare our history and our circumstan
                    <lb/>ces with his, and let us endeavour, if
                    <lb/>it be possible, to follow in the path in 
                    <lb/>which he has preceded us, but, with stron
                    <lb/>ger faith, purer love, and holier devotion.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>