<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">&#x201c;Title of Work&#x201d;</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in <hi rend="italic">Title of Printed Work</hi> (Date)</title>
                <!--The xml:ids for author and editor below should include the first, middle, and last initials of the author and the editor, respectively.-->
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#APW">Author of Printed Work</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#EPW">Editor of Printed Work</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#SEM">Sarah Elizabeth Montelepre</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Poems of John Ruskin</title>
                        <title type="sub">Volume I: Poems Written in Boyhood, 1826-1835</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1891">1891</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">xxiii</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Simple Prose. Delete this <div/> if not used.-->
            <div type="witness" subtype="sermon">
                <head type="title">Sermon 3</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <pb facs="296805v_0011"/>
                    <head type="chapter">The state of the world after the flood.</head>
                    <p>We are now to direct our attention, to a 
                    <lb/>few of the principle events, which immed&#x2010;
                    <lb/>iately followed the deluge. 20, of VIII, to end.
                    <lb/>The very first intimation, which<!--HGV omits "which"--> we have 
                    <lb/>of altars being built unto the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName>, is in 
                    <lb/>this passage, and we find, that it was 
                    <lb/>the very first action of <persName corresp="#NOAH">Noah</persName>, after he came
                    <lb/>out of the ark.  But although this is the 
                    <lb/>very first positive intimation, which we 
                    <lb/>have, of altars being built unto the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> 
                    <lb/><del rend="strikethrough">i</del>there is no ground to believe that the 
                    <lb/>descendants of <persName corresp="#SETH">Seth</persName>, built no altars.  Nay 
                    <lb/>we have great reason to believe that al&#x2010;
                    <lb/>tars were used, as we are told that they 
                    <lb/>offered sacrifices.  We may infer, from
                    <lb/>this, the first action of <persName corresp="#NOAH">Noah</persName>, two things,
                    <lb/>his gratitude, and his obedience.  His<!--HGV reads "This"--> grat&#x2010;
                    <lb/>itude at once led him to build the altar,
                    <lb/>his obedience to the previous ordinances 
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> made him bring the animals to be
                    <lb/>sacrificed thereon.  He might well indeed 
                    <lb/>be grateful, for the merciful preservation
                    <lb/>which had been extended to him.  And we 
                    <lb/>thus find that <persName corresp="#NOAH">Noah</persName>s very first action
                    <lb/>symbolized the atonement of <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>.
                    <lb/>We now find the acceptance of <persName corresp="#NOAH">Noah</persName>s offe
                    <lb/>ring announced to us.  We are told.  The 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> smelled a sweet savour, and the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> 
                    <lb/>said in his heart.  I will not again
                    <lb/>curse the ground any more for mans sake
                    <lb/>for the imagination of mans heart is 
                    <lb/>evil continually.  The reason here is re&#x2010;
                    <lb/>markable[.]  The heart of man is so 
                    <pb facs="296805v_0012"/>
                    <lb/>entirely evil from his youth, so utterly deprav
                    <lb/>ed and corrupted, that no expression whate
                    <lb/>ver of divine vengeance, would ever restrain 
                    <lb/>it, and it would be entirely useless continual
                    <lb/>ly to destroy the race of mankind.  But then 
                    <lb/>it may be objected, why did the flood come 
                    <lb/>at all[.]  Why was this terrible judgement 
                    <lb/>executed against mankind, if it was not 
                    <lb/>to have the least effect upon them.  It is 
                    <lb/>remarkable, that the same <del rend="strikethrough">event</del>reason s
                    <lb/>should<!--<"reason s should"...DCH: Is that 's' supposed to be there all by itself like that?--> be given, both for causing the flood
                    <lb/>and afterwards witholding a repetition of 
                    <lb/>it.  Now the deluge was not a trial of
                    <lb/>men,<!--HGV reads "man"--> to see whether any judgement or pun
                    <lb/>ishment would have any effect in causing
                    <lb/>their amendment, it was not an experim
                    <lb/>ment<!--'m' doubled with line break--> of which <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> did not know the result
                    <lb/>but it was to show, the utter hopelessness 
                    <lb/>of reclaiming the children of men, in any 
                    <lb/>other manner, than by their being born a
                    <lb/>again<!--'a' doubed with line break--> in <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName>.  There was therefore good 
                    <lb/>reason, both for causing the deluge, and for 
                    <lb/>preventing its repetition.  The next circum
                    <lb/>stance which is to be noticed, is the grant 
                    <lb/>of animal food which <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> made to man 
                    <lb/>at this period.  There was no grant be
                    <lb/>fore made to man, of any thing for food 
                    <lb/>but the products of the vegetable kingdom  
                    <lb/>Still we have reason to suppose that animal 
                    <lb/>food was used before the flood, for all <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>s 
                    <lb/>ordinances were utterly neglected and despised
                    <lb/>by the sons of <persName corresp="#CAIN">Cain</persName>[,] but we may infer<del rend="strikethrough">e</del>,
                    <lb/>from the grant now made of animal food,
                    <lb/>that the sons of <persName corresp="#SETH">Seth</persName>, or at least, <persName corresp="#NOAH">Noah</persName>, &#x0026; 
                    <lb/>his family, abstained from it and held the 
                    <lb/>divine command in veneration.  But, it may 
                    <lb/>be asked, why was that granted now, which
                    <lb/>was denied before.  It should be remembered
                    <lb/>that the vegetable kingdom must have 
                    <lb/>been partially destroyed, or at least mater
                    <lb/>ially injured, by the operation of the flood, 
                    <lb/>and for some time, vegetables must have 
                    <lb/>been entirely inadequate, for the sustenance 
                    <lb/>of mankind.  Therefore the means of his sup
                    <lb/>port are now enlarged, but at the same 
                    <lb/>time, all cruelty, which might have been 
                    <pb facs="296805v_0013"/>
                    <lb/>consequent upon the introduction of animal 
                    <lb/>food, was forbidden by the following precept
                    <lb/>Verse 4.9.<!--footnote 1: "Check whether 4.9 or 4.4. HGV reads 9."--> flesh with the life thereof which is 
                    <lb/>the blood thereof, shall ye not eat  The next
                    <lb/>circumstance to which our attention is to be 
                    <lb/>directed, is the enforcement of capital pun
                    <lb/>ishment  Whoso sheddeth mans blood, by man<!--HGV reads "such"-->
                    <lb/>shall his blood be shed, and the reason assig&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ned, is the dignity of man, &#x201C;for in the image 
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName><del rend="strikethrough">e</del> made he him, but this punishment 
                    <lb/>was entirely confided to murder.  Some say 
                    <lb/>that this law, was confined to the economy 
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#MOSES">Moses</persName>, but it is, I think, not so.  It was 
                    <lb/>given as the law of the new world, and 
                    <lb/>was intended to go down to the latest
                    <lb/>generations  <persName corresp="#NOAH">Noah</persName> is here the father of the 
                    <lb/>world, and this is the foundation of the 
                    <lb/>criminal law, throughout all the after&#x2010;
                    <lb/>world.  This severe law against murder was 
                    <lb/>rend{e}<!--?-->red necessary by the state of violence 
                    <lb/>which we are told prevailed before the
                    <lb/>flood and in which it is probable that mur
                    <lb/>der was no uncommon circumstance[,] and 
                    <lb/>no ordinance atall less severe than the one 
                    <lb/>under consideration, would have had the 
                    <lb/>least effect in its prevention.</p>
                    <lb/><p>We now pass on, to the token which is 
                    <lb/>given by <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, of the faithfulness of the 
                    <lb/>covenant which he made, not to des&#x2010;
                    <lb/>troy mankind again.  It has been said 
                    <lb/>that as physical nature is such, as, with
                    <lb/>out the intervention of any miracle, to 
                    <lb/>produce the rainbow, by the refraction of 
                    <lb/>the suns rays in the drops of falling rain, 
                    <lb/>the bow must either not have been a to&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ken to mankind, given at this time, or 
                    <lb/>else, that there could have been no 
                    <lb/>rain upon the<!--HGV omits "the"--> earth before the flood.
                    <lb/>For this last hypothesis, we have, on the 
                    <lb/>contrary, ample<!--HGV reads "awful"--> reason to believe that
                    <lb/>there was rain.  5 and 6[,] of II  But there 
                    <lb/>went up a mist from the earth and wa
                    <lb/>tered the whole face of the ground, for 
                    <lb/>the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName> had not yet caused it to rain
                    <lb/>upon the earth from which we may in
                    <lb/>fer, that rain followed immediately[,] &#x0026;
                    <lb/>for the first, this is no proof that the 
                    <lb/>rainbow was not a token given by <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, 
                    <pb facs="296805v_0014"/>
                    <lb/>We should rather say that <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName><!--<<g>>od; cap over lc--> selected an 
                    <lb/>object well known, and of frequent recur&#x2010;
                    <lb/>rence in the common course of nature 
                    <lb/>as a token which would constantly be in 
                    <lb/>view, of the faithfulness of his covenant[,] &#x0026; 
                    <lb/>which was quite sufficient.  After this, 
                    <lb/>we find the whole human race, having 
                    <lb/>collected themselves into one community[,] a
                    <lb/>bout to enter into a scheme of pride and 
                    <lb/>wickedness, which clearly shows how soon
                    <lb/>the depravity incident to man had ag
                    <lb/>ain taken root<!--HGV reads "roots"--> among the progeny of
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#NOAH">Noah</persName>.  This is the first public step of 
                    <lb/>any consequence in which they general
                    <lb/>ly concurred; and this is one, which di
                    <lb/>rectly sets forth their<!--HGV reads "this"--> spirit of pride  
                    <lb/>We read, that they found a plain in 
                    <lb/>the land of <placeName corresp="#SHINAR">Shinar</placeName>, and they said [one] to<!--HGV reads "to one"--> 
                    <lb/>another, Go to, let us build a city and 
                    <lb/>tower<!--HGV reads "a tower"--> whose top may reach unto heaven 
                    <lb/>and they had brick for stone, and slime 
                    <lb/>had they for mortar.  Now<!--"<[...?]> Now"-->, this tower
                    <lb/>was certainly not built for the purpose 
                    <lb/>of affording them an asylum from a 
                    <lb/>second deluge, which they  might have 
                    <lb/>supposed to be impending, for we read
                    <lb/>that the tower was built in a plain, &#x0026; 
                    <lb/>it is certain, that the very highest e&#x2010;
                    <lb/>minences would have been selected for 
                    <lb/>its foundation, had it been intended for 
                    <lb/>this purpose, for no tower that they 
                    <lb/>could build, would ever have attained 
                    <lb/>the elevation of the circumjacent moun
                    <lb/>tains,<!--"circumjacentmoun" run together at line break--> and again, it could not be to 
                    <lb/>prevent their threaten&#x02BC;d dispersion through 
                    <lb/>the earth, for that was inevitable, as 
                    <lb/>such numbers could never dwell togeth
                    <lb/>er, as well on the account of scarcity of 
                    <lb/>food, as for various other causes.  No, it 
                    <lb/>was to make them a name, to raise 
                    <lb/>a mon[u]ment to themselves, before their 
                    <lb/>necessary dispersion.  They built no al
                    <lb/>tars to their <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, to testify their
                    <pb facs="296805v_0015"/>
                    <lb/>gratitude to him, they brought no sac
                    <lb/>rifices, to testify their expectation of the 
                    <lb/>coming of a Saviour.  No&#x2014; every motive, 
                    <lb/>was lost<!--HGV reads "cast"--> in one which was pride, and that 
                    <lb/>in its most extravagant form.  They a{p}
                    <lb/>pear to have forgotten the existence of a 
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, and th[is] was a mere monument 
                    <lb/>to themselves, which they intended to 
                    <lb/>make them a name, that is,<!--"thatis"--> to per
                    <lb/>petuate their memory and fame to the 
                    <lb/>latest posterity showing how far sin,
                    <lb/>had, at this period, again found its 
                    <lb/>way among men.  But this undertak
                    <lb/>ing, which was begun to perpetuate their 
                    <lb/>fame, did only in the end perpetuate thier 
                    <lb/>shame for <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> caused it to be given up, <del rend="strikethrough">and</del>
                    <lb/>their dispersion was effected so much the soon
                    <lb/>er, and in order to effect it the more com
                    <lb/>pletely, <persName corresp="#GOD">GOD</persName> caused the confusion of tongues,
                    <lb/>which, besides scattering them abroad in
                    <lb/>to all countries, was in itself a severe
                    <lb/>punishment, and remains so to the pres
                    <lb/>ent day.  For, even now, infinite evil and 
                    <lb/>difficulty arises from the variety of langua
                    <lb/>ges spoken in different parts of the globe[.]  
                    <lb/>Much time is wasted, and much talent 
                    <lb/>is lost or dissipated by many students, be
                    <lb/>fore this unavoidable difficulty can be 
                    <lb/>overcome[.]  And if we consider, what the 
                    <lb/>time thus wasted, and the talent thus 
                    <lb/>lost, might have effected, had they been 
                    <lb/>applied to any useful or beneficial purpose, 
                    <lb/>we cannot but acknowledge, that the con
                    <lb/>fusion of tongues, was, and is, a very se
                    <lb/>vere punishment.</p>
                    <lb/><p>Yet, as we uniformly find it,<!--HGV omits "it"--> this judgment 
                    <lb/>is mingled with mercy.  Supposing, 
                    <lb/>that the children of men<!--HGV reads "man"--> had concluded
                    <lb/>their impious undertaking, and had built
                    <lb/>their city, and their tower.  The necessity 
                    <lb/>that they should separate, would, very 
                    <lb/>soon, have become pressing[.]  And would 
                    <lb/>not dreadful contests have taken place 
                    <lb/>among a multitude so hardened, &#x0026; 
                    <lb/>who had entirely forgotten, or despised 
                    <lb/>the commandments and ordinances of <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>{'s}
                    <lb/>contests, as to who should quit the part,
                    <lb/>the very<!--"thevery"--> small part, of the world already
                    <lb/>known, and go out among the bri
                    <lb/>ars, and thorns of the wilderness, far 
                    <lb/>from all inhabited, or cultivated reg&#x2010;{ions}<!--speculative: "reg-" divided at end of recto but never completed--> 
                    <pb facs="296805v_0016"/>
                    <lb/>to build themselves new cities, or find new
                    <lb/>pastures[.]  There would have been such com
                    <lb/>bats for the regions already known, as would 
                    <lb/>almost have exterminated the race of man 
                    <lb/>as effectually as did the deluge[.]<!--semicolon followed by period-->  All this 
                    <lb/>violence and bloodshed however, is preven
                    <lb/>ted by the confusion of tongues, which scat
                    <lb/>tered them at once, saving them and pun
                    <lb/>ishing them at the same time[.]</p>
                    <lb/><p>In spite of this however, we find, after 
                    <lb/>their dispersion, the viol{e}nce which preceded
                    <lb/>the flood again commencing[.]  It is said
                    <lb/>that <persName corresp="#NIMROD">Nimrod</persName> was a mighty hunter before 
                    <lb/>the <persName corresp="#GOD">Lord</persName>.  Now at this period, when ani&#x2010;
                    <lb/>mals multiplied more than men,<!--HGV reads "man"--> it became 
                    <lb/>of very great consequence, that the more 
                    <lb/>powerful of them, at least, should be des
                    <lb/>troyed.  In consequence, he who excelled in 
                    <lb/>this department would obtain a leadership 
                    <lb/>and authority over his fellow, which after&#x2010;
                    <lb/>wards readily he turned to his own aggran
                    <lb/>dizement.  The hunting of <persName corresp="#NIMROD">Nimrod</persName>, is, on 
                    <lb/>this account, celibrated, and we can have 
                    <lb/>no doubt, that he afterwards took advan
                    <lb/>tage of <del rend="strikethrough">this</del> the authority[,] thus obtained,
                    <lb/>to raise himself to the power and dignity<!--HGV reads "divinity"--> 
                    <lb/>of a monarch, or a tyrant.  I am not speak
                    <lb/>ing just now against monarchy  That is 
                    <lb/>an institution which I consider to have been 
                    <lb/>ordained by <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName>, and which therefore should 
                    <lb/>be honoured by men, and only evil in its 
                    <lb/>origin.  Again[,] it may be supposed, that 
                    <lb/>any individual, who, after the dispersion, first
                    <lb/>led to the building of towns, or the establish
                    <lb/>ment of Colonies, would in the first case,
                    <lb/>be looked up to with respect, or even vene&#x2010;
                    <lb/>ration, which would increase, until, after 
                    <lb/>his death, he might be ranked as a minor 
                    <lb/>divinity[.]  The number of these divinities would 
                    <lb/>be gradually increased, and their actions 
                    <lb/>would, in the course of time, be exaggera
                    <lb/>ted by tradition, till the true, and only <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> 
                    <lb/>would be entirely lost, and this was the o
                    <lb/>rigin of idolatry.  This was the state of 
                    <lb/>abandonment, and idolatry into which the 
                    <lb/>earth was plunged, at the period of the cal
                    <lb/>ling of <del rend="strikethrough">Noah</del> <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName></p>
                    <lb/><p>We shall now proceed to draw a few in
                    <lb/>ferences, from the circumstances, which 
                    <pb facs="296805v_0017"/>
                    <lb/>we have seen to day to have been those 
                    <lb/>of the world immediately after the flood  
                    <lb/>I would first notice the desperate and in
                    <lb/>curable wickedness of the human heart; I
                    <lb/>have often spoken of this before, and I speak
                    <lb/>of it again, both because examples of is<!--it?-->
                    <lb/>are constantly introduced throughout the
                    <lb/>whole of the sacred writings, and because it
                    <lb/><!--"and because it" repeated--> is a circumstance which can
                    <lb/><hi rend="underline">not be</hi> too often impressed on the mind of
                    <lb/>every one.  We see, that as soon as any
                    <lb/>individual made himself useful to his fel
                    <lb/>low creatures in any one department he
                    <lb/>employed those powers which he had thus
                    <lb/>obtained, to aggrandize himself<!--"f" written over "v"-->, in short
                    <lb/>to subjugate, and tyrannize over that
                    <lb/>people, for whose benefit he had previous
                    <lb/>ly been labouring.  Again, does not
                    <lb/>the entire absence of religion, from the
                    <lb/>multitude in the plain of <placeName corresp="#SHINAR">Shinar</placeName>, offer
                    <lb/>another remarkable example, of this dread
                    <lb/>ful depravity[.]  Every thing was lost in
                    <lb/>their selfish ness, in their vain glory; in
                    <lb/>their pride; <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> was altogether forgotten
                    <lb/>and mankind gave a loose rein to their
                    <lb/>passions, ending in their own confusion.</p>
                    <lb/><p>Again, we should learn from this, the
                    <lb/>amazing importance of humility.  The fame
                    <lb/>of the builders of <placeName corresp="#BABEL">Babel</placeName>, has, through their
                    <lb/>pride, been perpetuated, but not in the
                    <lb/>manner that they wished, to their glory
                    <lb/>and their honour, but to their abasement
                    <lb/>and degradation.  Had they been found
                    <lb/>worshipping <persName corresp="#GOD">God</persName> with humility, had they
                    <lb/>built altars, and brought sacrifices, it
                    <lb/>had then been an everlasting monument
                    <lb/>to their glory, and posterity would have
                    <lb/>looked back upon their humility, with res
                    <lb/>peck, and veneration.  But it was not
                    <lb/>so, and their confusion is now an everl&#x2010;<!--"l" doubled with line break-->
                    <lb/>lasting memorial of that truth, that pride
                    <lb/>cometh before a fall, and of the impor&#x2010;
                    <lb/>tance, the momentous importance, <del rend="strikethrough">of our</del>
                    <lb/>which I would endeavour to impress upon 
                    <lb/>the minds of all present, of <del rend="stikethrough">the</del> one of the
                    <lb/>very first of the graces, <del rend="strikethrough">simplicit</del> hum
                    <lb/>ility[,] which christain grace can only be 
                    <pb facs="296805v_0018"/>
                    <lb/>obtained, and preserved, by going to the cross 
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#JESUSCHRIST">Christ</persName><!--"C" written over "c"-->, and there, when we find the Redeem
                    <lb/>er laying down his life, because man was found 
                    <lb/>so fearfully and astonishingly depraved, that
                    <lb/>nothing else would save him, we shall no long
                    <lb/>er trust, in our powers to obtain<!--HGV reads "attain"--> salvation
                    <lb/>through our own righteousness, and shall dis
                    <lb/>cover, and acknowledge, that we have noth
                    <lb/>ing whatsoever, whereof to glory&#x0026;&#x2014;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>