<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="webpage">
        <fileDesc xml:id="legal">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Legal</title>
                <title type="sub">Webpage</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName corresp="#CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2015-03-25">March 25, 2015</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Webpage Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>https://erm.selu.edu/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="webpage">
                <head type="title">Conditions of Use</head>
                    <div type="section">
                    <head type="section"><hi rend="italic">Early Ruskin Manuscripts, 1826&#x2013;1842</hi></head>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Early Ruskin Manuscripts, 1826&#x2013;1842</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>) is produced at Southeastern Louisiana University 
                            with the support of the Department of English.</p>
                        <p>All commentary in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>, including apparatuses, glosses, notes, transcripts, and other editorial
                            treatments of the manuscripts is &#x00A9; by David C. Hanson. If quoting from <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>, please
                            identify the title of the work or commentary quoted, the date that you accessed <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi>, and the
                            following credit line and url: <hi rend="italic">The Early Ruskin Manuscripts, 1826&#x2013;1842</hi>. Ed. David C.
                            Hanson, 2016&#x2013;. &#x3008;https://erm.selu.edu/&#x3009;.</p>
                        <p>Materials in the site are made available under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) license. 
                          The license is available <ref type="external" target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/legalcode">here</ref>. 
                            The license can also be found at the root of the GitHub repository <ref type="external" target="https://github.com/GarthKiepper/Ruskin">here</ref>.</p>
                        <p>The originals of the manuscripts facsimiled in <hi rend="italic">ERM</hi> are divided among several collections. 
                            For any given work or manuscript, permission to exhibit a
                            facsimile and/or transcribe text from a manuscript will be found credited to the relevant collection in the Apparatus Pages for both works and manuscripts (specifically, in
                            the section of a given apparatus describing &#x201C;Manuscripts&#x201D;), and in Notes Pages at the end of a note. 
                            Permission to use a facsimile of a manuscript should be sought from the institution that holds the manuscript.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Andron Scriptor Web</head>
                        <p>The Andron Scriptor Web font used by this project is a special edition of Andreas St&#x00F6;tzner’s Andron Font Project,
                            financed by the Norwegian Research Council and the University of Bergen. It has been issued to support scholarly editing
                            in medieval philological studies and is provided free of charge. The creator and the provider of the font, Andreas
                            St&#x00F6;tzner and the Medieval Unicode Font Initiative (MUFI), have to be credited in colophons of works which utilize
                            the font. Any alteration to the font, including its contents, disposition, glyph shapes, and/or name, is a violation of
                            international copyright law and therefore strictly prohibited. If enhancements and/or improvements to the font are
                            desired, these should be forwarded to MUFI for consideration in future updates of the font. Andron is a trademark of
                            Andreas St&#x00F6;tzner, and its design is &#x00A9; by Andreas St&#x00F6;tzner, all rights reserved.</p>
                    </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>