<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <fileDesc xml:id="chamouni_prose_msxi">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Chamouni" [essay]</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from a Transcription of the MS XI Fair Copy</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#JR">John Ruskin</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2017-12-31">31 December 2017</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country type="nation">United States of America</country>
                        <region type="state">Connecticut</region>
                        <settlement type="city">New Haven</settlement>
                        <institution>Yale University</institution>
                        <repository>Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</repository>
                        <collection>MS Vault Ruskin</collection>
                        <msName>MS XI</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <locus facs="1229925.jpg 1229926.jpg 1229927.jpg 1229928.jpg"></locus>
                            <note>For a discussion of foliation, see <ref type="apparatus" target="tite_of_apparatus.php#MAJORMS">"Title of Work": Manuscripts</ref>.</note>
                            <filiation><!--Entry needed here.--></filiation>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <!--If additional entries are made below, the hands count must be increased.-->
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote corresp="#HANDUNIDENTIFIED" scribe="UNIDENTIFIED">
                                <p>Unidentified hand.</p>
                            </handNote>
                            <handNote corresp="#HANDJJR" scribe="JJR">
                                <p>John James Ruskin's hand.</p>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="witness" subtype="essay">
                <pb facs="1229925"/>
                <head type="title"><handShift new="#HANDUNIDENTIFIED" script="cursive" medium="ink"/><placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI"><hi rend="underline">Chamouni</hi></placeName><ref type="gloss" target="chamouni_prose_glosses_textual.php#HANDGLOSS"/></head>
                <p>And this is our last excursion on <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Swiss</placeName> ground thought I scanning<lb/> 
                    the provoking clouds that ever rolled massively among the regions of<lb/> 
                    eternal snow, though far above the blue mountains that encircle their<lb/> 
                    mighty monarch.<ref type="gloss" target="chamouni_glosses_contextual.php#MCLIFFYDIADEMGLOSS"/> I have always a sort of kindred feeling for these<lb/> 
                    beautiful blue hills they ever look half <placeName corresp="#ENGLAND">English</placeName>, and I love them for it.<lb/> 
                    They may not be so wonderful, so majestic, so mighty, or so beautiful<lb/>
                    but they are more like home, sweet home, &#x0026; it is pleasant very pleasant<lb/> 
                    to meet a friend in a foreign land. We are going to <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>. C&#x02BC;est<lb/>
                    vrai, but it seems exceeding strange. Before we left home, I had<lb/>
                    read of <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, heard of <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, &#x0026; seen some few drawings<lb/> 
                    of <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, but never so much as dreamed of going to <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>,<lb/> 
                    it seemed so uncome&#x2010;at&#x2010;able, and for the <geogName corresp="#MONTBLANC">Mont Blanc</geogName>, it seemed<lb/> 
                    in another world, in fairy&#x2010;land, and of course had a magic <add place="above"><space quantity="57" unit="chars"/>halo</add> thrown<lb/> 
                    round it, an (aetherialness,) that can never be joined with reality<lb/> 
                    That halo comes again on looking back. And this is our last excursion<lb/> 
                    on <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Swiss</placeName> ground thought I, the last, &#x0026; the wildest, &#x0026; the sweetest, because,<lb/> 
                    because, perhaps it <del rend="strikethrough">was</del><add place="above"><space quantity="22" unit="chars"/>is</add> the last. The day was exceedingly favourable<lb/>
                    for the scenery of the lower mountains, not for the <geogName corresp="#ALPS">Alps</geogName>, they were<lb/> 
                    reserved for other times. The noon verged gradually from burning<lb/> 
                    shineshine,<ref type="gloss" target="chamouni_poem_glosses_textual.php#SHINESHINEGLOSS"/> to thick thundery clouds, that rolled rapidly over the murky<lb/> 
                    heaven, as we entered a solitary mountain recess, a cliffy defile, leading<lb/> 
                    from the valley of <placeName corresp="#MAGLAND">Maglan</placeName>, to that of <placeName corresp="#SALLANCHES">Salenches</placeName>.<ref type="gloss" target="chamouni_glosses_contextual.php#MAGLANTOSALLANCHESGLOSS"/> Down they burst with<lb/> 
                    a fierce rattling turmoil &#x0026; headlong flash flash flashing, and the<lb/> 
                    bridleless clouds careered along the crags at such a wild rate, that their<lb/>
                    <pb facs="1229926"/>
                    own speed broke them into scattered <del rend="strikethrough">disorder</del><add place="above"><space quantity="38" unit="chars"/>confusion</add>, that the blue sky shone 
                    calmly through their openings, and the labouring sun struggled<lb/> 
                    strangely, now gleaming waterily on the red ribbed skeleton crags, now<lb/> 
                    mingling with the quiver of <add place="above"><space quantity="28" unit="chars"/>the</add> lightning, now again plunged into the<lb/> 
                    swift rack of the thunder clouds that seemed sweeping round the<lb/> 
                    mountain summits like lashed ocean waves round a labouring<lb/>  
                    vessel. The <geogName corresp="#ARVE">Arve</geogName> swelled on the instant and his turbid waves<lb/> 
                    tore madly down, trees, stones, rocks, all tost along the channel, by<lb/> 
                    the arrowy force of that resistless river, ever mighty but now<lb/> 
                    fearful. As the sun verged towards the horizon, the clouds swept 
                    partially away, the hills, the cliffs, the mountains the rocks, and the<lb/> 
                    blue vaulted sky glowed with his last rays for a moment, he sunk<lb/> 
                    &#x0026; the night came, his darkness made yet more visible by the thunder<lb/> 
                    gloom of the storm.<lb/></p> 
                
                <p>Voila les aiguilles quoth our char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc driver. If any person<lb/> 
                    in the whole world is totally insensible to pain, knocks, aches, &#x0026; bruises,<lb/> 
                    it must be a <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Swiss</placeName> char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc driver. The <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Swiss</placeName> char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc is<lb/> 
                    a vehicle expressly built for the purpose of passing over those roads,<lb/>
                    which no other species of conveyance can pass over twelve yards<lb/> 
                    of without immediate demolition<g type="terminal-comma">,</g><ref type="gloss" target="chamouni_poem_glosses_textual.php#TERMINALCOMMA"/> It is a sort of large side<lb/> 
                    saddle, capable of containing, if well packed three &#x201C;pauvres<lb/> 
                    miserables&#x201D;, with a back &#x0026; roof to it, &#x0026; a board to put the feet on,<lb/> 
                    with a leather to keep you in, all which are of a most ancient<lb/> 
                    &#x0026; venerable description, this is fixed totally without springs or<lb/>
                    any thing of the kind, as far as I could see, upon four wheels, et<lb/> 
                    voil&#x00E0; un char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc. With this kind of vehicle upon roads, which<lb/> 
                    always resemble, &#x0026; are often carried through the beds of tumbling<lb/>
                    <pb facs="1229927"/>
                    mountain torrents.<ref type="gloss" target="chamouni_poem_glosses_textual.php#FULLSTOP"/> Any one may easily imagine the sort of<lb/>
                    pleasurable penance to which he is subjected who submits to be<lb/>
                    driven from <placeName corresp="#SALLANCHES">Salenches</placeName> up to <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName> in a char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc.<lb/></p>
                
                <p>Voila les aiguilles quoth our char&#x2010;&#x00E0;&#x2010;banc driver.<ref type="gloss" target="chamouni_glosses_contextual.php#VOILAGLOSS"/> How I started<lb/> 
                    I believe I was dreaming of home at the time, it is odd you<lb/>
                    always think it would be very pleasant, to be where you are not<lb/> 
                    it can&#x02BC;t be helped but it is very provoking, the charms of a<lb/> 
                    place always increase in geometrical ratio as you get farther<lb/>
                    from it, &#x0026; therefore &#x02BC;tis a rich pleasure to look back on any thing<lb/> 
                    though it has a dash of regret. It is singular that almost all<lb/> 
                    pleasure is past, or coming. Well I looked up, &#x0026; lo! seven thousand<lb/>
                    feet above me soared the needles of <geogName corresp="#MONTBLANC">Mont Blanc</geogName>, splintered, &#x0026;<lb/>
                    crashed, &#x0026; shivered, the marks of the tempest for three score<lb/> 
                    centuries, yet they are here, shooting up, red, bare, scarcely even<lb/> 
                    lichened, entirely inaccessible, snowless, the very snow cannot cling<lb/> 
                    to the down plunging sheerness of these terrific flanks, that rise<lb/>
                    pre&#x2010;eminently dizzying &#x0026; beetling above the sea of wreathed snow<lb/>
                    that rolled its long surging waves over the summits of the lower<lb/>
                    &#x0026; less precipitous mountains. Then came the stretching gloominess<lb/> 
                    of the pine forests jagging darkly upon the ridge of every crag<lb/>
                    strangely contrasted with the cold blueness of the peaky glaciers<lb/> 
                    that filled the huge ravines between the hills descending like<lb/> 
                    the bursting billows of a chafed ocean&#x2010;tide from the desolate dominion<lb/> 
                    of the snow &#x0026; curling forward till they lay on the green fields of<lb/> 
                    <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName>, which stretched away one unbroken line of luxuriance<lb/> 
                    till bounded by the lonely desertness of the <placeName corresp="#COLDEBALME">Col de Balme</placeName>.<ref type="gloss" target="filename_glosses.php#COLDEBALMEGLOSS"/><lb/>
                    There is not another scene like <placeName corresp="#CHAMOUNI">Chamouni</placeName> throughout all <placeName corresp="#SWITZERLAND">Switzerland</placeName>.<lb/>
                    <pb facs="1229928"/>
                    In no other spot, that I have seen is the rich luxuriance<lb/> 
                    of the cultivated valley, the flashing splendour of the eternal<lb/>
                    snow, the impending magnificence of the bare spiry crag &#x0026;<lb/> 
                    the strange cold rigidity of the surgy glaciers, so dreadfully<lb/> 
                    &#x0026; beautifully combined. There is silence unbroken, no thunder<lb/> 
                    of the Avalanche comes crashing from the recesses of the hills<lb/> 
                    there is no voice from the chasmy glacier, no murmur from the<lb/> 
                    thousand mountain streams, you are in solitude, a strange<lb/>
                    unearthly solitude, but you feel as if the air were full of<lb/>
                    Spirits.<lb/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="date">
                <dateline><space unit="chars" quantity="42"/><handShift new="#HANDJJR" script="cursive" medium="ink"/><persName type="pen_name" corresp="#JR">J.R.</persName><lb/>
                    <space unit="chars" quantity="33"/>fragment from a Journal<lb/>
                    <space unit="chars" quantity="56"/>1833.<ref type="gloss" target="chamouni_prose_glosses_textual.php#DATELINEGLOSS"/></dateline>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>