<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Charles Goodspeed</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For XML:ID, enter your intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-25">October 25, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title"><persName corresp="#CG">Charles E. Goodspeed</persName> (<date notBefore="1867" notAfter="1950">1867&#x2013;1950</date>)</head>
                <p>Charles Eliot Goodspeed was significant both as a personal collector of Ruskin and as a seller to other Ruskin collectors, 
                    operating from his shop in Boston, first opened in 1898 (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WHITEHILLGOODSPEED"><persName corresp="WMWHITEHILL">Whitehill</persName>, "Charles Eliot Goodspeed"</ref>, 261). 
                    In his memoir, Yankee Bookseller (1937), Goodspeed dates his Ruskin collecting from his youth in the 1880s, 
                    giving two reasons for "the spell of Ruskin". First, his books occupied, "if not the highest, at least high rank in modern English literature", 
                    for "although his style is criticised", he "is conceded to be a great prose writer". Second, for collectors, Ruskin's books presented outstanding 
                    "examples of book-making", excelling "principally in illustration" (pp. 263, 264). 
                    In the 1939 edition of <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#LEHMANNHAUPTBOOKINAMERICA">Lehmann&#x2010;Haupt, <title type="book" corresp="#LEHMANNHAUPTBOOKINAMERICA"><hi rend="italic">The Book in America</hi></title></ref>, 
                    Goodspeed is characterized as a disciple of Ruskin, and moved by many interests shared with the Stone and Kimball generation (p. 254), 
                    referring to the small art&#x2010;nouveau publishers of the 1890s, such as Stone &#x0026; Kimball in Chicago and 
                    Copeland &#x0026; Day in Boston, which had in common their determination to publish only works of literary quality and 
                    to bring out their selections in an attractive and distinctive format (p. 211). From the founding of his bookselling business 
                    through the early 1930s, Goodspeed realized these art-book ambitions in small publishing projects of his own, 
                    printed by the Merrymount Press (Mahoney, "C. E. Goodspeed and Company", 180).</p>
                <p>As a bookseller, Goodspeed describes himself as having served a steady--albeit, he wrote, a "fading"--New England market for Ruskin, 
                    which he attributed to the influence of Charles Eliot Norton, and which he believed himself to have cornered, 
                    having "bought more . . . [Ruskin first editions] abroad than any other American dealer". He "found no competition" 
                    in scouring London particularly for first editions of lesser-known Ruskin titles--the many books and pamphlets beyond 
                    "the nine-volume set comprising Modern Painters, The Seven Lamps of Architecture, and The Stones of Venice" 
                    that "was always on the shelves of the larger booksellers" (Yankee Bookseller, 262-63). 
                    Part of Goodspeed's interest in the later Ruskin was owing to the "minute attention" that the author gave to all aspects 
                    of book-making in such publications as "Praeterita, Deucalion, Proserpina, and the other books issued in parts" 
                    (Yankee Bookseller, 264). The spell of these volumes for Goodspeed was not confined to their bibliographical appeal, however, 
                    since, as Whitehill remarks about the bookseller's retirement years, he collected minerals and tended to rare, wild plant species 
                    in his woodland garden ("Charles Eliot Goodspeed", 361).</p>
                <p>As a Boston bookseller, Goodspeed was well positioned to acquire Ruskin rarities from the sale of Francesca Alexander's estate, 
                    as well as from the library of the son of Charles Eliot Norton.<!-- NAME NEEDED -->. 
                    Fellow American Ruskin collectors whom Goodspeed mentions as his customers include Caleb B. Tillinghast and John G. Winant. 
                    He knew R. B. Adam only by reputation (Yankee Bookseller, 265, 262, 265).</p>
                <p>As a Ruskin collector, Goodspeed was important as representing stateside the 
                    <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="collecting_of_modern_authors_note.html">Collecting of Modern Authors in the Late Nineteenth and Early Twentieth Centuries</ref>, 
                    characterized by a commitment to comprehensiveness in collecting an author's first editions and to preserving firsts in their original condition. 
                    In Yankee Bookseller, he comments on his "mistake" as a young collector of having his fledgling Ruskin collection uniformly rebound, 
                    a collection that he disposed of and then rebuilt on "the primary rule that pamphlet issues of all kinds, if intended for sale to collectors, 
                    must be preserved in their original form" (pp. 261-62). Eventually, his comprehensive collection reached five hundred volumes 
                    of first editions along with "all the authorized editions of Ruskin and his biographies", which he donated to Wellesley College, 
                    "in consideration of Ruskin's interest in the education of girls and from the fact that both of [his] daughters were graduated" from that institution (p. 265).</p>
                <p>Goodspeed was important also as a Ruskin manuscript collector, playing a highly competitive role in the sales of 1930-32. A key figure for ERM, he took a particular interest in the early manuscripts 
                    available in these sales, drawn to them probably owing to their relation to Ruskin's authobiography. "It is for the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>," 
                    he wrote of his many Ruskin acquisitions, "that I have most regard. 
                    I had bought it when published in periodical form, looking forward to each succeeding number with a keener interest than the modern reader would have for the weekly installment of a story by Agatha Christie 
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Evening Post</hi>. . . . I cannot imagine a temptation sufficent to make me part with Ruskin's portrait of Rose La Touche 
                    and his manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>" (269).</p>
                <p><!-- SOLD KING AND FORS LOTS FROM 1931 (YB 267); SEE 267-68 FOR EARLY MSS, HOW DESCRIBED --> 
                    Prosperpina and Deucalion, at a time when few took an interest in these late works. 
                He even bid for Ruskin's mineral collection. . . .</p>
                <p>After publishing his memoir of book dealing and collecting in 1937 and retiring to Shirley, Massachusetts, his house burned in 1941 
                    (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WHITEHILLGOODSPEED"><persName corresp="WMWHITEHILL">Whitehill</persName>, "Charles Eliot Goodspeed"</ref>, 361, 363). 
                    Portions of his personal library were destroyed and others damaged. . . . [Donations to Yale.]</p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>