<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">London Docks</title>
                <title type="sub">Notes</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal><persName>David C. Hanson</persName></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For xml:id, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName xml:id="CWB">Charles W. Borchers, IV</persName>
                    <resp>contributing encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2010-10-27">October 27, 2010</date>
                    <!--The notes version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Notes Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University</name></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond, LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>erm@humanitiesonline.selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="note">
                <head type="title">London Docks</head>
                <p>In &#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol. 1, Mama remarks to Lucy that Papa has &#x201C;got to go to
                    town and then into the city and then to the docks&#x201D; (chap. 1), and Ruskin later
                    includes an illustration, &#x201C;Harry’s Dock,&#x201D; [Plate] &#x201C;8,&#x201D; [&#x201C;Harry and Lucy,&#x201D; Vol.
                    1] <!--Correction needed here?-->. By the mid&#x2010;1820s, new docks had been recently completed or were under
                    construction to help move the enormous increase in trade. Shortly prior to these
                    developments, Thomas Pennant described Blackwall and Wapping as miles of
                    streets, &#x201C;inhabited by multitudes of seafaring men, alternate occupants of sea
                    and land: their floating tenements . . . before them. In fact, the whole river,
                    from the bridge, for a vast way, is covered with a double forest of masts, with
                    a narrow avenue in mid-channel&#x201D; (Pennant, <hi rend="italic">History of
                        London</hi> 2:56). Since the later eighteenth century, congestion on the
                    river had became unbearable, permitting huge losses to thievery. Consequently,
                    the engineering feat of the new docks was considered among the great
                    testimonials to England’s commercial might (Margetson, <hi rend="italic">Regency
                        London</hi> 21). </p>
                <p>The West India and East India docks, which handled trade to and from those
                    regions, the Surrey dock system, and the London Dock at Wapping were all built
                    within the first decade of the nineteenth century. As Ruskin was writing his
                    &#x201C;Harry and Lucy&#x201D; volumes, the St. Katherine Dock was under construction near the
                    Tower, with the warehouses built directly on the water. It opened in 1828
                    (Broodbank, <hi rend="italic">Port of London</hi>, 1:155, 161). </p>
                <p>John James Ruskin presumably did his business primarily at the London Dock in
                    Wapping, since for a time it held a monopoly on tobacco, rice, wine and brandy,
                    other than the Indies trade. Built on twenty acres, it opened in 1805
                    (Broodbank, <hi rend="italic">Port of London</hi>, 1:114, 117, 140). A plate in
                    Broodbank (1:113 opp.) shows an inlet from the river opening to a large, square
                    basin, where ships could dock side by side. The basin was surrounded by large
                    warehouses. </p>
                <p>The appearance of warehouses was determined by &#x201C;requirements of structural
                    stability and fire protection,&#x201D; and remained consistent from the Great Fire of
                    the seventeenth century through the twentieth century. Materials were brick,
                    timber for floors, and tiles or slate for roofs, although cast iron was used for
                    columns and reinforcements from the early 1800s. Of interest for the Ruskin
                    firm, for wine and spirits at the London docks &#x201C;an important feature . . . was
                    the vaults . . . beneath quay level.&#x201D; These were wide barrel vaults resting on
                    stone or cast&#x2010;iron columns (Tucker, &#x201C;Warehouses in Dockland&#x201D; 22, 24, 26). </p>
                <p>Transport from the city to the docks was at first by omnibus. River steamers were
                    in service by the mid&#x2010;1830s; and soon thereafter, rail lines, among the first in
                    the kingdom, ran to Greenwich and Blackwall (Pearsall, &#x201C;Dockland Transport&#x201D;
                    145&#x2013;46). For John James, the trip would not have been far from the premises of
                    Ruskin, Telford, and Domecq, which were housed in Billiter Street (see City of
                    London).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>