<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../common/ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="witness">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK and its WITNESS, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi".
            The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_msi.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_witness">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Electronic Text Generated from the Printed Witness in <hi rend="italic">Title of Printed Work</hi> (Date)</title>
                <!--The xml:ids for author and editor below should include the first, middle, and last initials of the author and the editor, respectively.-->
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#APW">Author of Printed Work</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#EPW">Editor of Printed Work</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The transcript version for all first passes is 1.0.-->
                    <title>Transcript Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <!--Example entries have been provided for The Poems of John Ruskin (1891). Actual entries may vary.-->
                        <editor>
                            <persName>W. G. Collingwood</persName>
                        </editor>
                        <title type="main">The Poems of John Ruskin</title>
                        <title type="sub">Volume I: Poems Written in Boyhood, 1826-1835</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="edition">4<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Allen</publisher>
                            <date when="1891">1891</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">xxiii</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Simple Prose. Delete this <div/> if not used.-->
            <div type="prose">
                <head type="title">Title of Prose Piece</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter">Title of Chapter</head>
                    <p>Body paragraph.</p>
                    <pb facs="296805v_0018"/>
                    <p>1st to 3rd verse. XII. We must fix our attention
                    <lb/>to day, in the first place, upon the various dis
                    <lb/>pensations, which have been, both before, and af
                    <lb/>ter the flood, held forth to man, as the means
                    <lb/>of his salvation. The first of these dispensa
                    <lb/>tions, was that before the fall, which was en
                    <lb/>tire perfection in the creature, and power to
                    <lb/>obtain his own salavation, in consequence
                    <lb/>of which, a proportionate demand was made
                    <lb/>upon him, of perfect obedience, by his <name type="fictional" corresp="#CREATOR">Creator</name>.
                    <lb/>But this perfection was lost, and the
                    <lb/>power of obtaining salvation by that dispen
                    <lb/>sation, was at an end. Then there came a
                    <lb/>change, but it is to be observed, that it
                    <lb/>was only a change of the creature, not of
                    <lb/>the <name type="fictional" corresp="#CREATOR">Creator</name>, <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> made the same demands
                    <lb/>upon man, but another mode was ordain
                    <lb/>ed to him, of fulfilling them; The <name type="fictional" corresp="#CREATOR">Creator</name>
                    <lb/>was, and is, the same, under every
                    <lb/>change and every dispensation and these
                    <lb/>various changes were only different modes
                    <lb/>of showing his glory, his justice, and his
                    <lb/>soverignty, Now, we must bear in mind
                    <lb/>that the dispensation after was quite uni
                    <lb/>versal in its character, the promise of sal
                    <lb/>vation was equally extended to all the hu
                    <lb/>man race, it shut out none, and there
                    <lb/>was no benefit given to one individual,
                    <lb/>which was not attainable by all, it was
                    <lb/>universal in efficacy, although it was not
                    <lb/>so in facts, and it would also have been
                    <lb/>on account of sin.</p>
                    <p>But this universality is now lost, in the
                    <lb/>administration to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>. A particular
                    <lb/>nation is selected descending from a single
                    <lb/>individual; But we should observe, that al
                    <pb facs="296805v_0019"/>
                    <lb/>though, this particular administration, is
                    <lb/>limited, the former one is still continued
                    <lb/>and still extending its benefits to all men,
                    <lb/>it is an addition, not  limitation, it is
                    <lb/>introduced into the former economy, with
                    <lb/>out destroying it. And we have several
                    <lb/>proofs of this. For under what dispensa
                    <lb/>tion can we suppose what <persName corresp="#MELCHISEDEK">Melchisedek</persName> was
                    <lb/>a high preist, Certainly under the first, and
                    <lb/>not under the Abrahamic We may now
                    <lb/>enter into the particulars of the calling of
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>. 31st verse, 11. It may be as
                    <lb/>ked, how <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, as it is here told us
                    <lb/>departed, with his family, from <placeName corresp="#UR">Ur of Chaldees</placeName>,
                    <lb/>apparently before he was called by
                    <lb/><name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>. But, I think it is evident that <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>
                    <lb/>had appeared to him before he left <persName corresp="#HUR">Hur</persName> and
                    <lb/>arrived in <placeName corresp="#HARAN">Haran</placeName>. For, there is no doubt
                    <lb/>that the beginning of the twelfth chapter
                    <lb/>goes back to events which had happened
                    <lb/>previously to his departure from <placeName corresp="#UR">Ur</placeName>.
                    <lb/>Let us look at the seventh chapter of <title type="Scripture">Acts</title>,
                    <lb/>and the 2nd verse. <persName corresp="#STEPHEN">Stephen</persName> says, "The <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>
                    <lb/>of Glory appeared unto our father <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>when he was in <placeName corresp="#MESOPOTAMIA">Mesopotamia</placeName>, before he dwelt
                    <lb/>in <placeName corresp="#HARAN">Charran</placeName>, which is <placeName corresp="#HARAN">Haran</placeName> , according
                    <lb/>to the Greek pronunciation" and said un
                    <lb/>to him Get thee out of thy country,
                    <lb/>and from thy kindered and come into the land
                    <lb/>which I shall show thee For taking the
                    <lb/>order of the words in <title type="book" corresp="#BIBLE">Genesis</title>, we should i 
                    <lb/>magine, that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> was called after
                    <lb/>he had dwelt in <placeName corresp="#HARAN">Haran</placeName>, or <placeName corresp="#HARAN">Charran</placeName>, but we
                    <lb/>may be sure, that <persName corresp="#STEPHEN">Stephen</persName> and <persName corresp="#MOSES">Moses</persName> were
                    <lb/>in perfect unison, and that, as <persName corresp="#MOSES">Moses</persName> says
                    <lb/>"the <persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> had said to Abram," the seeming <!-- is he referring to Abraham here?-->
                    <lb/>contradiction is only from the transposi
                    <lb/>tion of the words</p>
                    <p>We may next consider the situation of
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> and his family his religious views
                    <lb/>, and condition, before he was called, in or
                    <lb/>der to preserve the worship of the True <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>,
                    <lb/>who was, at this period, almost entirely
                    <lb/>forgotten, amid the depravity and idolatry
                    <lb/>so generally prevailing, prevailing so com
                    <lb/>pletely indeed, that we have authority
                    <lb/>for supposing that there were idols, even
                    <pb facs="296805_0020"/>
                    <lb/>even in <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abrahams</persName> own family; Now, if
                    <lb/>this state of things had continued for a very
                    <lb/>small time longer, the earth would have been
                    <lb/>left without one single testimony of even the
                    <lb/>existence of the true <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>. It was therefor nec
                    <lb/>essary, immediately to bring <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> away
                    <lb/>from his house, and from his kindered, and to
                    <lb/>wean him from the worship of the Idols, which
                    <lb/>were placed even in his own house. For, we
                    <lb/>read in the twenty fourth chapter of <persName corresp="#JOSHUA">Joshua</persName>, and
                    <lb/>the second verse, "Your fathers dwelt on the other
                    <lb/>side of the flood in old time, (that is, on the other
                    <lb/>side of the river <geogName corresp="#EUPHRATES">Euphrates</geogName>; which was called the
                    <lb/>flood, because it was the largest river then
                    <lb/>known; and not meaning the deluge) even <persName corresp="#TERAH">Terah</persName>,
                    <lb/>the father of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> and the father of
                    <lb/>Nahor, and they served other <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">Gods</name>," it is distinct
                    <lb/>ly stated that they were Idolaters, and al
                    <lb/>though it does not positively affirm, that
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> himself was a worshipper of idols
                    <lb/>, yet, I think we may suppose him to have
                    <lb/>been so, before he was called of <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>, and his
                    <lb/>future blessings announced to him.</p>
                    <p>In these blessings, there are a few particulars
                    <lb/>which may be severally noticed. There is,
                    <lb/>first, a simple promise made to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>that the <persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> will shew him a land, there
                    <lb/>is nothing more, there is no imitation
                    <lb/>given as to its character, its name, or its po
                    <lb/>sition, it is not said whether it shall be
                    <lb/>barren, or fruitful, large, or small, desert
                    <lb/>or inhabited. He is left to exercise his
                    <lb/>faith, he must leave his house, his coun
                    <lb/>try, his kindred, and he must trust all
                    <lb/>his interests in the hands of his <name type="fictional" corresp="#CREATOR">Creator</name>.
                    <lb/>This however, he does, and what without a
                    <lb/>moments hesitation, as the <persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> had spo
                    <lb/>ken unto him, and his instant and willing
                    <lb/>compliance presents us with an example
                    <lb/>of what our conduct ought invariably
                    <lb/>to be, with regard to the promises of
                    <lb/><name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>. But how much, how con
                    <lb/>stantly we deviate from the rule of con
                    <lb/>duct which the patriarch has, in this
                    <lb/>instance, so strictly observed. How daily,
                    <lb/>how hourly, are we wishing, and even
                    <lb/>stipulating to the <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">Almighty</name> to under 
                    <lb/>stand the entire bearing of everything
                    <lb/>which is written in <title type="book" corresp="#BIBLE">Scripture</title>, <!--How to tag books?-->
                    <pb facs="296805v_0021"/>
                    <lb/>When we ought, without a moments hes
                    <lb/>itation, to trust ourselves, and our con
                    <lb/>cerns wholly to the keeping, and man
                    <lb/>agement, of a true, kind, and a faith
                    <lb/>ful <name type="fictional" corresp="#CREATOR">Creator</name>, we are as suspicious
                    <lb/>as if we were moving in the country
                    <lb/>of an artful, and vigilant enemy, and
                    <lb/>where an ambush was laid for us in every
                    <lb/>thicket. How different how exceedingly
                    <lb/>different, was the spirit of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>. He
                    <lb/>knew only, but he knew that certainly
                    <lb/>that <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> had spoken, and that the
                    <lb/>path which he had to follow, was in
                    <lb/>stant and unhesitating confidence, &#x0026;
                    <lb/>he therefore waits for nothing more. If
                    <lb/>we were to follow his example, and, ha
                    <lb/>ving seen some of the promises clearly
                    <lb/>and completely fulfilled, will believe
                    <lb/>that those which are yet obscure to us,
                    <lb/>shall, in time, be discovered to be e
                    <lb/>qually true we shall then be able to
                    <lb/>travel on fearlessly, with such a
                    <lb/>degree of firmness as will enable us,
                    <lb/>trusting in the faith of our <name type="fictional" corresp="#CREATOR">Creator</name>, to
                    <lb/>relieve our minds from all worldly f
                    <lb/>ears and troubles. Let us remember, that
                    <lb/>very few promises indeed had been made
                    <lb/>to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, in comparison of the num
                    <lb/>ber which have been delivered to us, and,
                    <lb/>that, of those few, none had been hither
                    <lb/>to fulfilled, that he saw those prophe
                    <lb/>cies only under an obscure and dawn
                    <lb/>ing light, which are seen by us under
                    <lb/>a full blaze of noontide splendour, and let
                    <lb/>us then who rise so far above in the
                    <lb/>degree of explicitness belonging  to those
                    <lb/>prophecies which we are required and co
                    <lb/>mmanded to trust to, not fall far be
                    <lb/>low him in either the greatness, or 
                    <lb/>the readiness of our faith.</p>
                    <p>The next article of this promise, is, that
                    <lb/>the <persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> will make of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> a great
                    <lb/>nation, showing, what we have men
                    <lb/>tioned before, that the Abrahamic dis
                    <lb/>pensation was limited to a peculiar
                    <lb/>nation, the descendants of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, al
                    <lb/>though it shut out no one from
                    <lb/>the previous administrations.
                    <pb facs="296805v_0022"/>
                    <lb/>There is the same want of perspicuity in
                    <lb/>this promise <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> is not told when
                    <lb/>or where, or how, or under what circum
                    <lb/>stances the <persName corresp="#LORD">Lord</persName> will make him a great
                    <lb/>nation, and <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abrahams</persName> faith is again put
                    <lb/>to the test, but it fails not The verse
                    <lb/>goes on I will bless thee. Now, we should
                    <lb/>remark here, that to be made a great
                    <lb/>nation alone might, or might not be a
                    <lb/>blessing, most probably might on the
                    <lb/>contrary prove a curse, for wealth, power,
                    <lb/>glory, any, or all of the good things of this
                    <lb/>world, only can prove blessings, when they
                    <lb/>are accomplished by the blessing of the <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">Almighty</name>,
                    <lb/> and it is therefore, this blessing,
                    <lb/>which constitutes what is really good
                    <lb/>or desireable, in every thing. We might
                    <lb/>suppose kingdoms and rulers and nations
                    <lb/>to be submitted to <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, or forces,
                    <lb/>and wealth and power, and dominion, to
                    <lb/>be given unto him, but if we suppose
                    <lb/>him alone possessed of infinitely
                    <lb/>more than all these, and beyond the
                    <lb/>power of man to injure him, while on the
                    <lb/>other hand, though he might be endowed
                    <lb/>with every good thing which earth
                    <lb/>could bestow upon him, if we suppose
                    <lb/>him void of divine grace, we suppose
                    <lb/>him unblest, with every blessing, and un
                    <lb/>happy with every happiness, while the pow
                    <lb/>er in which lay his pride, or the domin
                    <lb/>ion in which lay his power, might, in
                    <lb/>the end, only prove preludes to his fear
                    <lb/>ful and irrrevocable overthrow. It is
                    <lb/>only when the blessing of <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> rests
                    <lb/>upon a man, that we can imagine
                    <lb/>him happy, or upon a nation, that
                    <lb/>we can imagine it great.</p>
                    <p>Again, it is promised to him, that his
                    <lb/>name shall be made great. Now, we
                    <lb/>are not to infer from this, that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>desired a great name. On the contra
                    <lb/>ry had he desired it, it would most probably
                    <lb/>not have been granted him, because, we
                    <lb/> may be sure, that this was not to min
                    <lb/>ister to his pride, but to support his
                    <pb facs="296805v_0023"/>
                    <lb/>weakness. It was to encourage him in his
                    <lb/>humble simplicity, and in order that he might
                    <lb/>not yield to any despondency, which, other
                    <lb/>wise, might have overcome him, when he
                    <lb/>found himself in a strange land, where the
                    <lb/><name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> whom he served was not known, and far
                    <lb/>from his own his own country, his kin
                    <lb/>dred, his friends, and his family. The pro
                    <lb/>mise to make his name great, was to
                    <lb/>encourage his diffidence, and not to sup
                    <lb/>port his ambition.</p>
                    <p>The next promise, is, that he shall be
                    <lb/>a blessing. This is a very great, and im
                    <lb/>portant addition, to the former promise,
                    <lb/>that he should be blessed. For, had this
                    <lb/>only been granted him, his enjoyment
                    <lb/>would have been personal only, he would
                    <lb/>have stood alone, and his happiness would
                    <lb/>have been greatly cloyed, by seeing the
                    <lb/>misery, the vice, the violence, and the dep
                    <lb/>ravity with which he was surrounded.
                    <lb/>We cannot suppose one, who has attained
                    <lb/>a tall rock, in the middle of a tempes
                    <lb/>tuous ocean, and who sees his fellow&#x2010;be
                    <lb/>ings perishing around him to be hap
                    <lb/>py, although we may suppose him thank
                    <lb/>ful, and we cannot suppose, that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>would have been supremely happy,
                    <lb/>although blest with all the good that
                    <lb/>earth or heaven could give, had that
                    <lb/>blessing been only personal: But, was it
                    <lb/>not a great encouragement to him, when
                    <lb/>he knew, that wherever he went, his pre
                    <lb/>sence should scatter blessings on every
                    <lb/>one around, that mirth should fol
                    <lb/>low his footsteps, and gladness accom
                    <lb/>pany his presence. This would se
                    <lb/>cure the blessings of all around him, en
                    <lb/>vy would not detract him, and malice
                    <lb/>would not injure him, his benevolence
                    <lb/>would be gratified, and his selfishness
                    <lb/>forgotten, or subdued. Now, it may
                    <lb/>be asked, if this circumstance, that <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>should be a blessing to all, was
                    <lb/>not inconsistent with, or contradic
                    <lb/>tory to, the limitation, the peculiar
                    <lb/>limitation, of the Abrahamic dipsen
                    <lb/>sation. We would answer No. For
                    <pb facs="296805v_0024"/>
                    <lb/>although, on account of the peculiar cir
                    <lb/>cumstances in which the patriarch was
                    <lb/>placed, he might be forced so far, to en
                    <lb/>ter into correspondence with the idolaters
                    <lb/>by whom he was surrounded, and although
                    <lb/>this correspondence might, in some de
                    <lb/>gree bring a blessing upon them, although
                    <lb/>he might, enter into traffic with them
                    <lb/>and buy and sell, (as we see from the 9th
                    <lb/>and following verses of the XXIII Chapter
                    <lb/>that he bought a cave, from <placeName corresp="#EPHRON">Ephron</placeName>, of
                    <lb/>the children, of <persName corresp="#HETH">Heth</persName>, for four hundreds
                    <lb/>shekels of silver) yet we cannot suppos
                    <lb/>that he was intimate with them. <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>
                    <lb/> had pointed out to him the path which
                    <lb/>he was to follow, and that was one of
                    <lb/>entire seclusion and seperation, from
                    <lb/>the rest of mankind, and it was his
                    <lb/>bounden duty, under all circumstances
                    <lb/>to stand aloof from all the worshippers
                    <lb/>of other <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">Gods</name>, and to adhere to this se
                    <lb/>vere rule so strictly, as even to with
                    <lb/>draw himself from his own family, &#x0026;
                    <lb/>friends, when these went after unknown
                    <lb/>gods, in short, all, that the smallest de
                    <lb/>gree would interpose between him, and
                    <lb/>the <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> whose servant he had been
                    <lb/>appointed, must be entirely set aside.
                    <lb/>And, let me say, that this should
                    <lb/>be our line of conduct at the present
                    <lb/>day, we should stand aloof from every
                    <lb/>thing that, would seperate us, and our
                    <lb/>heavenly <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">Father</name>. We must not enter
                    <lb/>more into correspondence with world
                    <lb/>ly men more than is absolutely neces
                    <lb/>sary, we must set the world and the
                    <lb/>things of the world aside, or we shall
                    <lb/>share in their ruin. Lot did not ad
                    <lb/>here strictly to this rul, but entered in
                    <lb/>to an alliance with the people of <placeName corresp="#SODOM">Sodom</placeName>
                    <lb/>and <placeName corresp="#GOMORRAH">Gomorrah</placeName>, and although he himself
                    <lb/>by a timely flight was enabled to es
                    <lb/>cape, yet we know, that one individ
                    <lb/>ual of his family, who left the city
                    <lb/>of the idolaters with delay, and regret,
                    <lb/>was overtaken by the same destruction
                    <lb/>Let this, my friends be a warning to
                    <lb/>us, and let us remember, that the less
                    <pb facs="296805v_0025"/>
                    <lb/>we have to do with the things of this
                    <lb/>world, the better we are preparing for anoth
                    <lb/>er.</p>
                    <p>Again, the verse goes on, to say that <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>
                    <lb/>not only will bless the friends of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/>but will set himself against his enemies
                    <lb/>Still, we observe that is exactly the line of
                    <lb/>enemies of his people may perhaps triumph
                    <lb/>on the earth, but their triumph will be
                    <lb/>but of short duration, and <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name> will, in
                    <lb/>the latter end, bring them to a fearful
                    <lb/>account, for in all these things, we are
                    <lb/>more than conquerors. Even on the ear
                    <lb/>th, when he hath flourished for a little
                    <lb/>time like a flower of the field, and spread
                    <lb/>out his branches, like a green olive tree,
                    <lb/>by the rivers of waters, yet but a little
                    <lb/>while, and he passeth away, and the
                    <lb/>place thereof shall know it no more
                    <lb/>We have an example of this, in the battle
                    <lb/>of kings, in which we are told that
                    <lb/><persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, with three hundred and eigh
                    <lb/>teen men, defeated the forces of the five
                    <lb/>combined kings.
                    <lb/>We now come to the last, but the prin
                    <lb/>cipal part of this blessing, I say the prin
                    <lb/>cipal, because in this part, the dispen
                    <lb/>sation, which before was confined to
                    <lb/>one peculiar nation, is here extended
                    <lb/>to all the nations of the earth, "and in
                    <lb/>thee shall all families of the earth, be
                    <lb/>blessed. This part of the covenant, with
                    <lb/>out doubt, refers to <persName corresp="#LORD">Christ</persName>, who, being
                    <lb/>one ofthe descendants of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, yet
                    <lb/>extends the Abrahamic dispensation,
                    <lb/>through his death, to the Jew, and the
                    <lb/>Gentile, to the bond and the free, to all,
                    <lb/>who will believe on him. Such were
                    <lb/>the various circumstances of the Abra
                    <lb/>hamic dispensation. And now, my
                    <lb/>friends let me repeat, for I cannot
                    <lb/>too often impress it upon you, how very
                    <lb/>striking an instance, of the blessed pow
                    <lb/>er of faith, we have in the conduct
                    <lb/>of <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>, on this occasion, <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName>
                    <lb/> believed, and was steady in that
                    <lb/>believe, under a very obscure vision on
                    <lb/>ly of the glory of the <persName corresp="#LORD">Son of man</persName>
                    <lb/>The gospel is delivered to us, under cir
                    <lb/>cumstances exceedingly different, we have
                    <lb/>line upon line, and precept upon precept.
                    <pb facs="296805v_0026"/>
                    <lb/>The redeemer has appeared, and the bless
                    <lb/>ing has been accomplished, and yet
                    <lb/>we still find thousands disbelieving
                    <lb/>this grand salvation Let me tell you
                    <lb/>that the rejection of the <title type="book" corresp="#BIBLE">Gospel</title>, or its
                    <lb/>neglect is a fearful and perilous crime. Let
                    <lb/>us not be found guilty of either. Let
                    <lb/>us receive it as <persName corresp="#ABRAHAM">Abraham</persName> did, and
                    <lb/>cast off every thing that can come be
                    <lb/>tween us and <name type="fictional" corresp="#GOD">God</name>, and may we be
                    <lb/>found, in the latter days among those
                    <lb/>families, who shall actually enjoy these
                    <lb/>most precious, and imperishable blessings.</p>
                    
                    
                   
                    
                    
                    
                    
                  
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                   
                </div>      
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>