<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="ruskin.rnc" type="compact"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ruskin.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="apparatus">
        <!--The xml:id for <fileDesc/> should include the title (or an abbreviated title) of the subject WORK followed by "apparatus", for example,
            "the_steam_engine_apparatus". The xml:id also corresponds with its XML file's name, for example, "the_steam_engine_apparatus.xml".-->
        <fileDesc xml:id="title_of_work_apparatus">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Title of Work"</title>
                <title type="sub">Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName corresp="#DCH">David C. Hanson</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <!--For corresp, enter your first, middle, and last intials.-->
                    <persName corresp="#YNH">Your Name Here</persName>
                    <resp>contributing transcription/encoding/review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Southeastern Louisiana University</sponsor>
                <funder>American Philosophical Society, Beinecke Library, Bibliographical Society of America,
                    Blossman Foundation, Huntington Library, Louisiana Board of Regents, National Endowment for
                    the Humanities, NINES, Pierpont Morgan Library, South Central Modern Language Association,
                    and Southeastern Louisiana University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">
                    <!--DATE WHEN should reflect the date that this electronic text was finalized for publication to the Web.-->
                    <date when="2011-08-01">August 1, 2011</date>
                    <!--The apparatus version for all first passes is 1.0. Where a version number is followed by "(TC)", the file has been TextCrawled.-->
                    <title>Apparatus Version 1.0</title>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor><name type="institution">Southeastern Louisiana University Department of English</name></distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Southeastern Louisiana University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SLU 10861</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Hammond LA 70402</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ruskinproject@selu.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright David C. Hanson.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digitally, prepared by David C. Hanson.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <head type="title">&#x201C;Title of Work&#x201D;</head>
                <!--An apparatus may contain all or only some of the following sections.-->
                <div type="section" xml:id="TITLE">
                    <head type="section">Title</head>
                    
                    <div type="prose"><!-- No electronic transcript marked up heretofore; this is from published text; compare carefully against Ms -->  
                        <p>perambulating&#x2014;Oh, woe to the walker who is 
                            compelled to drag himself up their steeps, those tiresome paved steeps,<pb/>
                            those hard, unyielding, provokingly smooth flagstones, or to go thundering 
                            down, his rapidity increasing every instant, when he is once in for it 
                            lurching tremendously like a ship in a swell, jerk, jerk, jerking&#x2014;<emph>Oh, facilis 
                                descensus Averni, sed sed;</emph>&#x2014;Ay, there's the rub. The H&#x00F4;tel de Bellevue 
                            at <placeName corresp="#BRUSSELS">Brussels</placeName> ought to have a <emph>belle vue</emph> for you might as well scale the crags 
                            of <placeName corresp="#GIBRALTAR">Gibraltar</placeName> as storm the heights of the H&#x00F4;tel de Bellevue; whence, for all 
                            the boast of its title, I never could discover more <emph>belle vue</emph> than a dusty 
                            square, some formal houses, and a few murky park trees. </p>
                        
                        <p>We left <placeName corresp="#BRUSSELS">Brussels</placeName> on Wednesday morning for <placeName corresp="#WATERLOO">Waterloo</placeName>; the sun beamed 
                            sweetly among the long trunks of the aged trees of the forest of Soigny; 
                            and their damp bark glistened dewily,&#x2014;as it rose up taller and taller, 
                            branching off into the bending boughs, and slender spray, with the delicate 
                            foliage scattered through: here every leaf defined separately and clearly 
                            as you looked up to the broad sky; there in light, spready masses, par- 
                            tially concealing the long tapery trunks which retired back, farther and 
                            still farther, yet distinctly grouped, and those groups separated by the 
                            gleamy stream of yellow sunshine, which shone full on the sides of the 
                            swelling green grassy banks, then broken by the intervening hollows, 
                            then climbing again up the dewy moss and white trunks. It was exceed- 
                            ing beautiful; I could have fancied the glister of the bright bayonets 
                            changing, like starlight on a wavy ocean, among the retiring foliage of 
                            those ancient trees&#x2014;I forgot how many long years had past by since 
                            that eventful day. </p>
                        
                        <p>This is the field of <placeName corresp="#WATERLOO">Waterloo</placeName>. The round hills of green pasture lay 
                            unbroken before me, without a single tree, except where, fax to the right, 
                            the rich forest country commenced again, breaking away in rounded 
                            masses, till lost in the blue of the faint horizon. All is peace now. 
                            Englishmen may feel proud on the field of Waterloo&#x2014;perhaps I did; but 
                            there is something mingled with it&#x2014;Poor <persName corresp="#NBE">Napoleon</persName>! The grass is very 
                            green on the field of <placeName corresp="#WATERLOO">Waterloo</placeName>&#x2014;it has grown from the dust of our bravest. 
                            Oh, tread on it softly!  </p>
                    
                    <p>FOR BLACK FOREST <hi rend="superscript">2</hi> ["<emph>Kehl</emph>, line 2, is my conjecture; the word in the original is illegible. The poem 
                        must refer to the day's journey descrihed in <emph>Pr&#x00E6;terita</emph>, i. ch. vi. § 130: 'Earliest 
                        morning saw us trotting over the bridge of boats to Kehl, and in the eastern light I 
                        well remember watching the Black Forest hills enlarge and rise as we crossed the 
                        plain of the <geogName corresp="#RHINE">Rhine</geogName>.'"&#x2014;<emph>Editor's Note</emph>, <date when="1891">1891</date>.] </p>
                    
                    <p><hi rend="superscript">1</hi> [Here the MS. (viii.) adds one line: "Towards the south horizon"&#x2014;similar to the 
                        last line of the passage on <placeName corresp="#CADENABBIA">Cadenabbia</placeName>.] </p>     
                    
                    <lg type="stanza" n="17">
                        <l>While, gaunt as gorge of hunted boar,</l>
                        <l>Dark yawns the foaming pass before,</l>
                        <l>Where the tormented waters rage,</l>
                        <l>Like demons in their Stygian cage,</l>
                        <l>In giddy eddies whirling round</l>
                        <l>With a sullen choking sound;</l>
                        <l>Or flinging far the scattering spray,</l>
                        <l>O&#x02019;er the peaked rocks that bar his way.</l>
                        <l>&#x02014;No marvel that the spell-bound Rhine,</l>
                        <l>Like giant overcome with wine,</l>
                        <l>Should <hi rend="italic">here</hi> relax his angry frown,</l>
                        <l>And, soothed to slumber, lay him down</l>
                        <l>Amid the vine-clad banks, that lave</l>
                        <l>Their tresses in his placid wave.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note
                            xml:id="xmlidneeded34" n="34" resp="#DH" place="botwin">Notation
                            Needed</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    
                    <p>In forming the persona <persName type="pen_name" corresp="#JR">J.R.</persName>, Ruskin was influenced not only by literary and artistic sources, 
                        but also by living poets and artists 
                        whom he was fortunate to meet or correspond with during his conceptualization and composition of the "Account." These contacts became especially important 
                        as Ruskin was "brought forward" as a professional contributor to 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="friendships_offering_note.html"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref> 
                        (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#HANSONRUSKIN1830S">Hanson, &#x201C;Ruskin in the 1830s&#x201D;</ref>). 
                        Two of these men present a striking contrast with one another&#x2014;<ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="rogers_samuel_note.html">Samuel Rogers (1763&#x2013;1855)</ref> and 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="hogg_james_note.html">James Hogg (ca. 1770&#x2013;1835)</ref>. Ruskin also had some contact at this time with 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="loudon_j_c_note.html">John Claudius Loudon (1783&#x2013;1843)</ref>.</p>
                    <p>The personae of Hogg and Rogers each exhibited multiple and even contradictory sides, and the Ruskins must have been selective 
                        about what aspects of these public figures they hoped to cultivate in the patronage of their precocious son. 
                        Respecting Hogg, the Ruskins thought of him in his role as the Ettrick Shepherd, who was romantically imagined as having received his call to poetry 
                        when he was shepherd in Ettrick Forest in the <geogName corresp="#SCOTTISHBORDERS">Scottish Borders</geogName>, 
                        and who still resided in georgic retirement on his farm in the Yarrow Valley. 
                        The Ruskins would have played down Hogg's colorful and risqu&#x00E9; character in the &#x201C;Noctes Ambrosianae&#x201D; 
                        in <hi rend="italic">Blackwood&#x02BC;s Edinburgh Magazine</hi>. This side of Hogg appealed to the Bront&#x00EB; siblings, 
                        who imitated the bravado and swagger of these dialogues in their own collaborative and competitive writing, 
                        but Ruskin's parents would hardly have considered such a persona as an appropriate model 
                        for Ruskin's solitary and decorous authorship.</p>
                    <p>When the Ruskins first met Hogg personally in 1832, he was undertaking his first visit to the metropolis of London, 
                        where was lionized by London society. Hogg's introduction to the Ruskins came by way of the community of expatriate Scottish literati in London 
                        who surrounded the publishing firms of John Murray and Smith, Elder. The latter, in particular, as the publisher of 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="friendships_offering_note.html"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></ref>, 
                        served as the hub for these connections: Hogg as a contributor to the annual; 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="pringle_thomas_note.html">Thomas Pringle (1789&#x2013;1834)</ref>, 
                        as editor, and longtime friend of Hogg; and even Ruskin's cousin, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_charles_note.html">Charles Thomas Richardson (1811&#x2013;34)</ref>, as a shopboy with the firm, 
                        who was the first to present Ruskin with a copy of <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi> (probably the <date when="1829">1829</date> 
                        or <date when="1830">1830</date> volume, both of which contained contributions by Hogg).</p>
                    <p>Rogers, in sharp contrast with Hogg, was the urbane "man of taste," whose townhouse in St. James Square 
                        was a showplace of exquisitely curated Regency neoclassicism, and the scene of his famous breakfasts in which Rogers acted the part of social arbiter 
                        of the current London artistic and literary scene. In his most positive light, Rogers might have appeared to the Ruskins as a splendid embodiment 
                        of John James's tastes and aspirations. A former associate of Byron, and a habitu&#x00E9; of at least the byways of fame, 
                        Rogers had earned a sound reputation for his topographical poem, <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>, 
                        which may have paled in comparison to the popular glare of <hi rend="italic">Childe Harold&#x02BC;s Pilgrimage</hi>, 
                        but which was respectably and approachably neoclassical--regular in its versification, and grounded in the tradition of the 
                        Grand Tour to Italy. Rogers was also, like John James, a successful businessman, having made his fortune in banking; 
                        and even though he lavished extravagant sums on artists, engravers, and printers in order to satisfy his perfectionism in crafting editions of his poetry, 
                        Rogers recouped his huge investment in his illustrated edition of <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> and profited handsomely by its unprecedented sales. 
                        The unattractive side of Rogers was his notoriously acid wit and his worldliness at a time when middle-class Evangelical earnestness 
                        was turning the tide on the influence of Regency "men of taste."</p>
                    <p>The two writers also differed profoundly in taste. Rogers was so committed to his neoclassicism that <persName corresp="#JMWT">Turner</persName> 
                        reined in his apocalyptic manner typical of his other works of the period in favor of a style that would harmonize with Rogers's restraint, 
                        by using less dramatic perspective in his vignette designs for <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#HOLCOMBCLASSICALTURNER">Holcomb, &#x201C;Neglected Classical Phase of Turner&#x02BC;s Art&#x201D;</ref>). 
                        The artist whom Hogg most admired and hoped to secure as illustrator for his grandest gift book, a deluxe edition of <hi rend="italic">The Queen's Wake</hi>, 
                        was <persName corresp="#JMARTIST">John Martin</persName> (<date notBefore="1789" notAfter="1854">1789&#x2010;1854</date>)--the artist who, 
                        ever far from restraining the apocalyptic, made his career by exploiting such subjects for their most histrionic theatricality and scale 
                        (All too typically for the hapless author, and despite generous subscription donations 
                        by John James Ruskin and others, Hogg's deluxe edition was never produced owing to disruptions in trade caused by Reform agitation in 1832; 
                        see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#OHALLORANILLUSTRATIONS">O&#x02BC;Halloran, &#x201C;Illustrations to <hi rend="italic">The Queen&#x02BC;s Wake</hi>&#x201D;</ref>, c&#x2010;civ.)</p>
                    <p>Of the two relationships, the Ruskins' contact with Hogg is the best documented 
                        (see <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="hogg_james_note.html">James Hogg (ca. 1770&#x2013;1835)</ref>). 
                        Their apparent preference for the Ettrick Shepherd's advice about Ruskin's future as a poet, when the youth was laboring over the 
                        <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_msix.html">MS IX fair copy of the "Account"</ref>, may be no accident. 
                        Compared to Rogers, Hogg may have seemed hapless in his fortunes: his London venture ended in him foolishly mislaying his trust in an under-financed publisher, 
                        who went bankrupt and squandered the opportunity to produce a collected edition worthy of the author, whereas Rogers boasted the means to encase his writing 
                        in increasing splendor. (In 1834, when John James wrote to Hogg about John's "promise of very considerable talent," 
                        Rogers followed up the success of his 1830 <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> with an edition of his collected <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>, 
                        likewise illustrated by Turner, Stothard, and others, which the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi> declared to be a "volume which, 
                        for true elegance and pictorial fancy, is unequalled, in an age remarkable for its love of splendid books" 
                        [<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#GARDENMEMORIALS">Garden, ed., <hi rend="italic">Memorials of James Hogg</hi></ref>, 274; 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#PIGGOTTTURNERSVIGNETTES">Piggott, <hi rend="italic">Turner&#x02BC;s Vignettes</hi></ref>, 39].) 
                        Nonetheless, when writing to Hogg, John James sounds pointed in addressing Hogg as a man &#x201C;of talent and of heart,&#x201D; 
                        as compared with &#x201C;the world at large,&#x201D; which lacks &#x201C;comprehen[sion] . . . patience . . . feeling . . . delicacy,&#x201D; 
                        suggesting that he trusted the humble Scottish "shepherd" over the urbane man of taste 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#GARDENMEMORIALS">Garden, ed., <hi rend="italic">Memorials of James Hogg</hi></ref>, 274).</p>
                    <p>Despite John James's sentiments, both Rogers's successes and Hogg's disappointments were endemic to a period of transition between publishing in the age of 
                        <persName corresp="#WS">Scott</persName> and the more entrepreneurial and innovative, yet also volatile and confusing print culture 
                        in the age of <persName corresp="#CJHD">Dickens</persName>. In a time when critical discourse commonly bemoaned the decline of poetry in unpropitious circumstances 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#BRISTOWVICTORIANPOETINTRO">Bristow, &#x201C;Introduction,&#x201D; <hi rend="italic">Victorian Poet</hi></ref>, 4-5), 
                        both Rogers and Hogg appreciated how poetry could gain new life from its relation with the visual arts--a 
                        relation that was rooted in tradition reaching back to the humanist dialogue or <hi rend="italic">paragone</hi> between the sister arts, 
                        yet that was also undergoing renewal and transformation by mass-market print technologies. Both men shrewdly exploited the changes in print technology 
                        that created new venues and audiences for literature and art, such as the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="annuals_note.html">annuals and other illustrated books</ref> 
                        (on Hogg's enterprising approach to these venues during an otherwise depressed period in literary publishing, see 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#CURRIEINTROHOGGANNUALS">Currie, introduction to Hogg, <hi rend="italic">Contributions to Annuals and Gift&#x2010;Books</hi></ref>, xix-xxxii; 
                        and for his appreciation of the fine arts--particularly modern painting, for its connection with literature and its accessibility to ordinary people--see 
                        <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#HUGHESHOGGARTANNUALS">Hughes, &#x201C;Hogg, Art, and the Annuals&#x201D;</ref>).</p>
                    <p>The sole anecdote to survive concerning Ruskin's audience with Rogers can be read in terms of commonalities shared by these mentors 
                        in the literary and artistic culture of the 1830s. We have no contemporary documentation of Ruskin's introduction to Rogers under Pringle's wing, 
                        other than evidence of Pringle's regular entr&#x00E9;e to St. James Place 
                        (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#VIGNEPRINGLE">Vigne, <hi rend="italic">Thomas Pringle</hi></ref>, 192). 
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s later story about his supposed contretemps of "congratulating . . . [Rogers] with enthusiasm 
                        on the beauty of the engravings by which his poems were illustrated," indicating that the youth knew &#x201C;more of the vignettes 
                        [in <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>] than the verses,&#x201D; and the chiding of Pringle "that, in future, 
                        when . . . in the company of distinguished men, . . . [he] should listen more attentively to their conversation" 
                        evokes a bygone era that valued polite conversation and dilettantish colleccting 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 34:96, 35:93). 
                        Yet, while Ruskin fits the anecdote into what he now regarded as his fatuous beginnings as a poet, his misplaced complements to the illustrator 
                        proves him to have been a boy of his decade, who had so carefully studied the visual culture represented by Rogers's <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> 
                        as well as by Prout's <hi rend="italic">Facsimiles</hi>. (While we do not know when Ruskin's introduction to Rogers occurred, 
                        it is a reasonable guess that Pringle secured an audience on the strength of the youth's precocious achievement in the 
                        <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_msix.xml">MS IX fair copy of the &#x201C;Account&#x201D;</ref>.)</p>
                    <p>In the mentoring of <persName type="pen_name" corresp="#JR">J.R.</persName>, perhaps the most important qualification is indicated by a word dropped in the only 
                        mention of a publication by John to survive in the family correspondence of 1834. In a verse letter to his father dated <date when="1834-03-10">10 March 1834</date>, 
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> mentions--not Pringle and <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi>--but 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="loudon_j_c_note.html">John Claudius Loudon (1783&#x2013;1843)</ref>, the editor 
                        of botanical, landscaping, and other natural history publications. A key is that Ruskin regarded Loudon as a "friend" of the family: 
                        &#x201C;To <persName corresp="#JCL">Mr Loudon</persName>, as a friend, / By way of some communication, / Some kind of little lucubration / On any sort of observation, 
                        / Among the <geogName corresp="#ALPS">Alps</geogName>, you know, / On Micaslate, or any slates, / Granite, and gold, or toads and snakes, / I think that I shall make a show&#x201D; 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography#RFL">Burd, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 285). 
                        Ruskin was alluding to his geological notes--dated March 1834, but published later that yea--in Loudon's 
                        <hi rend="italic">Magazine of Natural History</hi>, 
                        <ref type="apparatus" target="enquiries_on_the_causes_of_the_colour_of_the_water_of_the_rhine_apparatus.html">"Enquiries on the Causes of the Colour of the Water of the Rhine"</ref>, and 
                        <ref type="apparatus" target="facts_and_considerations_on_the_strata_of_mont_blanc_apparatus.html">"Facts and Considerations on the Strata of Mont Blanc, and on Some Instances of Twisted Strata Observable in Switzerland"</ref>. 
                        One is struck by the apparent anomaly that the one forthcoming publication to merit Ruskin's attention--if he was as yet apprised of his other firsts for this year, 
                        the poetry commissions for <hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi>--were these geological observations, and later in life Ruskin would find it convenient 
                        to stress his keenness of factual observation at the expense of his poetic effusion. Again, however, one can perceive commonalities. 
                        <persName corresp="#JCL">Loudon</persName>, like <persName corresp="#TP">Pringle</persName> and Hogg, was a Scot--a member of the extended "family" 
                        of Scottish literati in <placeName corresp="#LONDON">London</placeName> who surrounded the boy wonder, many of whom visited 
                        <placeName corresp="#HERNE">Herne Hill</placeName> in the <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date>. Loudon's publications also depended on the thriving visual culture 
                        of illustrated books and magazines during the period, and they were perhaps not too distant from the poetry anthologies in their communal appraoch, 
                        inviting amateurs to contribute to forums such as the 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="magazine_of_natural_history_note.html"><hi rend="italic">Magazine of Natural History</hi></ref> 
                        and trade &#x201C;lucubrations&#x201D; that did not necessarily depend on professional status.</p>
                    
                    
                    
                    <p> words words words<ref type="gloss" target="name_of_witness_gloss#NAMEOFGLOSS"><hi rend="superscript">NOTE No.</hi></ref>
                    
                    Note No.
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>Signs of havoc caused by the July Revolution in <placeName corresp="#FRANCE">France</placeName> and the <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgian</placeName> Revolution of <date when="1830">1830</date> were still being marked six years later by
                        <persName corresp="#JM">Murray&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers on the Continent</hi>;
                        and decades later, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> would
                        contrast <persName corresp="#SP">Prout&#x02BC;s</persName> quietude of
                        manner with the state of medieval <placeName corresp="#FRANCE">French</placeName> architecture &#x201C;such as her vestiges
                        remained after all the wreck of revolution and recoil of war had passed
                        over them&#x201D; (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 14:395). In the boyhood
                        &#x201C;Account,&#x201D; although composed much closer in time to these
                        events, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> shows little
                        consciousness of recent political history. </p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> does comment in the
                        &#x201C;Account&#x201D; on national identities, seeing <placeName corresp="#CALAIS">Calais</placeName> as &#x201C;an introduction to
                        <placeName corresp="#FRANCE">France</placeName>, and to the
                        <placeName corresp="#FRANCE">French</placeName>,&#x201D; but the
                        narrator moralizes in non&#x2010;specific terms. On the road between
                        <placeName corresp="#CALAIS">Calais</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#BRUSSELS">Brussels</placeName>, climbing to the top of
                        <placeName corresp="#CASSEL">Mont Cassel</placeName>, the narrator
                        points out the &#x201C;fifteen battle&#x2010;fields&#x201D; visible from
                        the eminence that tell &#x201C;a fearful tale of the ready ire of
                        nations, yet looking as green and peaceful as if they had never been
                        watered with blood.&#x201D; Nothing is said about such signs of recent
                        conflict as the destruction of the ancient Abbey of <placeName corresp="#STBERTIN">St. Bertin</placeName> at <placeName corresp="#STOMER">St. Omer</placeName>; rather, while the narrator,
                        passing <placeName corresp="#STOMER">St. Omer</placeName>, sneers at the
                        &#x201C;serpent folds&#x201D; of &#x201C;Romes religion&#x201D;
                        supposedly lurking beneath a religious procession, the <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">English</placeName> anti&#x2010;Catholic
                        sentiment associated with that place was as old as the Gunpowder
                        Plot&#x2014;the Jesuit College at <placeName corresp="#STOMER">St.
                            Omer</placeName> having been implicated in that history. </p>
                    <p>Similarly out of touch is the poem&#x02BC;s passage through <placeName corresp="#FRANCE">France</placeName> to <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgium</placeName> and the neglect of any
                        commentary on the <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgian</placeName>
                        character. The <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgian</placeName>
                        Revolution of <date when="1830">1830</date> had established the Kingdom
                        of <placeName corresp="#Belgium">Belgium</placeName> as a state separate
                        from the United Kingdom of the
                        Netherlands<!--TPD: Should United Kingdom, Netherlands, and Europe be added into the crib and tagged, or are they too vague?-->.
                        <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">English attitudes</placeName> to the
                        new kingdom&#x2014;as <persName corresp="#PF">Pieter
                            Fran&#x00E7;ois</persName> finds, examining such popular sources as
                        travel guidebooks&#x2014;were initially divided along party lines, with
                        Whigs approving the Catholic revolutionaries and Tories supporting the
                        Protestant Dutch kingdom (<persName corresp="#JM">Murray&#x02BC;s</persName> 1836 <hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book</hi> remained staunchly Tory). Over the course of
                        the <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date>, however,
                        <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">British</placeName> opinion unified
                        around a myth of <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgium</placeName> as a
                        &#x201C;little <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">Britain</placeName>&#x201D;
                        that shared a royal connection in <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgium&#x02BC;s</placeName>
                        <persName corresp="#LGCF">King Leopold I</persName>, and that supposedly
                        had copied its neighbor&#x02BC;s constitutionalism and rising
                        industrialization, and that even harbored, the <placeName corresp="#ENGLISH">English</placeName> convinced themselves, a
                        &#x201C;hidden&#x201D; protestantism beneath the nation&#x02BC;s
                        Catholic national identity (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#FRANCOISBELGIUM">Fran&#x00E7;ois,
                            &#x201C;British Views on Belgium&#x201D;</ref>, 663&#x2013;64). Yet <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> impressions of <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgium</placeName>, as given in the
                        &#x201C;Account,&#x201D; do not reflect the partisan Tory views that
                        <persName corresp="#JM">Murray&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book</hi> would advise to tourists,
                        condemning the <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgians</placeName> for
                        lacking the &#x201C;heroic patriotism&#x201D; and
                        &#x201C;high&#x2010;minded courage and ceaseless perseverence&#x201D; of
                        their Protestant Dutch neighbors and for possessing &#x201C;a coarseness
                        of manners&#x201D; and &#x201C;debasement of the national
                        character&#x201D; (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#MURRAYSHANDBOOKCONTINENT1836"><hi rend="italic">Hand&#x2010;book for Travellers on the
                            Continent</hi></ref>, 78). Nor do any of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> remarks appear to share in the myth of
                        the <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">Englishness</placeName> of the
                        <persName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgian</persName> character. </p>
                    
                    <p>USE FOR GERMANY AND THE ALPS===========Other works acquired by the family both return in <date notBefore="1833-09-22" notAfter="1833-12-21">autumn 1833</date>, and during <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> ongoing
                        composition of the &#x201C;Account&#x201D; in <date when="1834">1834</date>, <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName>
                        continued to acquire travel publications typical of this eclectic,
                        transitional period. There were travel accounts written in the immediate
                        post&#x2010;<placeName corresp="#WATERLOO">Waterloo</placeName>
                        period by <persName corresp="#VFRC">Vicomte Fran&#x00E7;ois Ren&#x00E9;
                            de Chateaubriand</persName> (<date when="1768">1768</date>&#x2013;<date when="1848">1848</date>) and by <persName corresp="#WSR">William Stewart Rose</persName> (<date when="1775">1775</date>&#x2013;<date when="1843">1843</date>), an associate of
                        <persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName> and <persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>.<note><persName corresp="#JJR">John
                            James&#x02BC;s</persName> account book does not identify the
                            titles of these works, but <persName corresp="#VAB">Van Akin
                                Burd</persName> suggests <persName corresp="#VFRC">Chateaubriand&#x02BC;s</persName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Souvenirs d&#x020BC;Italie, d&#x020BC;Angleterre,
                                et d&#x020BC;Am&#x00E9;rique</hi> (<date when="1815">1815</date>) and <persName corresp="#WSR">Rose&#x02BC;s</persName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Letters from the North of Italy</hi> (<date when="1819">1819</date>).</note> There was also a &#x201C;P.
                        Rhine&#x201D; (perhaps <hi rend="italic">Pilgrims of the Rhine</hi>, a
                        decidedly eclectic work by <persName corresp="#EBL">Edward
                            Bulwer&#x2010;Lytton</persName> [<date when="1803">1803</date>&#x2013;<date when="1873">73</date>], published in this
                        year). For his birthday in <date when="1834-02-08">February 1834</date>,
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> received two works on
                        Alpine travel: one, a work by <persName corresp="#HBS">Horace&#x2010;B&#x00E9;n&#x00E9;dict de Saussure</persName> (<date when="1740">1740</date>&#x2013;<date when="1799">99</date>), whose
                        writings combined travel narrative with scientific observation of the
                        <geogName corresp="#ALPS">Alps</geogName>; the other, <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of the Passes of the Alps</hi> by
                        <persName corresp="#WBI">William Brockedon</persName> (<date when="1787">1787</date>&#x2013;<date when="1854">1854</date>), who
                        combined his talents as both an artist and scientist with travel writing
                        and illustration. <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> wrote to his
                        father that <persName corresp="#WBI">Brockedon&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        engravings in the <hi rend="italic">Illustrations</hi> carried him
                        &#x201C;again over the summits of the higher <geogName corresp="#ALPS">Alps</geogName>, over the winding paths of <placeName corresp="#SPLUGEN">Splugen</placeName><!--TPD: Is it alright to forgo the U-umlaut in this instance?-->,
                        and the glaciered crest of the <placeName corresp="#SIMPLON">Simplon</placeName>, and the summmer snows of the <placeName corresp="#STBERNARD">St Bernard</placeName>, and the lovely plains
                        of gentle <placeName corresp="#ITALY">Italy</placeName>&#x201D; (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography#RFL">Burd, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ruskin Family Letters</hi></ref>, 278; and see 286
                        n. 1 for <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        <date when="1833">1833</date>&#x2013;<date when="1834">34</date> lists
                        of book purchases). </p>
                    
                    <p> or the much larger, full&#x2010;page
                        lithographs by <persName corresp="#SP">Prout</persName> for the <hi rend="italic">Facsimiles</hi>&#x2014;but more commonly he invented
                        the scene but realized his idea stylistically in the manner of <persName corresp="#SP">Prout</persName> or 
                        <persName corresp="#JMWT">Turner</persName> or <persName corresp="#TSP">Stothard</persName>.</p>
                    
                    <p><persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>
                        advances his &#x201C;Account&#x201D; from a travelogue poem in the
                        eighteenth&#x2010;century topographical tradition, to a work reflecting
                        the material culture of ekphrastic, topographical, and
                        travel&#x2010;related publishing in the <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date>.</p>
                    
                    <p>Starting either with the section for &#x201C;St. Goar&#x201D; or with
                        that for &#x201C;Heidelberg&#x201D; (the Library Edition&#x02BC;s
                        documentation confuses the issue, as explained below), even a single
                        drawing is presently lacking; and the fair copy of the text ends a short
                        way into the prose for &#x201C;Heidelberg&#x201D;&#x2014;so at this
                        point in <ref type="apparatus" subtype="mss" target="msix_apparatus.html">MS IX</ref>, the fair&#x2010;copy
                        project clearly had broken down, and it is unlikely that
                        once&#x2010;existing drawings have been removed. COULD BE ARGUED THAT TRIO OF SECTIONS AND HEIDELBERG A KIND OF GRAND FINALE</p>
                    
                    <p>Walton's take on Ruskin's early art education as reflected in the "Account" is based on Ruskin's comic assessment in <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi> of his abilities 
                        in “copying” engraved illustrations with such “great,” and “to most people now incredible, exactness,” 
                        his obsessiveness not only prevented the project from completion, but also feminized his formation of self. Gifted with “so little original faculty,” 
                        he lagged behind his cousin, 
                        <ref type="note" subtype="biographical" target="richardson_mary_note.html">Mary Richardson (<date notBefore="1815" notAfter="1849">1815&#x2013;49</date>)</ref>, 
                        in “free-hand copying,” so that, far from developing a viable persona, he ventured outside Herne Hill only to be “treated [like] a girl” when he attended day school 
                        (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref> 35: 81, 74-75, 77, 83).</p>
                    
                    <p> Nord&#x2010;Pas&#x2010;de&#x2010;Calais and <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgium</placeName>. These are among the northern Continental sites
                        that <persName corresp="#SP">Prout</persName> brought to <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">British</placeName> attention in the <date notBefore="1820" notAfter="1829">1820s</date> and <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date>. (<persName corresp="#SP">Prout&#x02BC;s</persName> even more far&#x2010;flung destinations
                        in Eastern Europe, such as <placeName corresp="#PRAGUE">Prague</placeName>, which he depicted in the <hi rend="italic">Facsimiles</hi> and exhibited in watercolors at the Old Water
                        Colour Society, found little success with the public.)</p>
                    
                    <p><persName corresp="#SP">Prout&#x02BC;s</persName> role in this transition
                        in taste remains an emphasis even in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> later writing about the artist. Despite
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> changing purposes
                        over the years, his writing on <persName corresp="#SP">Prout</persName>
                        always refers back to the artist&#x02BC;s discovery of northern Europe
                        as a distinctive accomplishment in these earlier decades. For example,
                        in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        <date when="1849">1849</date> article on <persName corresp="#SP">Prout</persName> for the <hi rend="italic">Art Journal</hi>, he
                        does characterize the artist&#x02BC;s first tour of northern Europe in
                        terms of conversion and destiny, a preoccupation of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> in the <date notBefore="1840" notAfter="1849">1840s</date>: &#x201C;the
                        painter&#x02BC;s vocation . . . fixed from that hour,&#x201D; the
                        &#x201C;first effect upon his mind was irrepressible enthusiasm, with a
                        strong feeling of a new&#x2010;born attachment to Art, in a new world
                        [in northern Europe] of exceeding interest.&#x201D; While in keeping
                        with the concerns of <hi rend="italic">The Seven Lamps of
                            Architecture</hi> as well as of <hi rend="italic">The Stones of
                                Venice</hi>&#x2014;situating <persName corresp="#SP">Prout&#x02BC;s</persName> personal discovery of vocation within a
                        larger cultural history framed by a critique of misguided modernist
                        feeling (<date corresp="#SP">Prout</date> becoming &#x201C;the
                        interpreter of a great period of the world&#x02BC;s history, of that in
                        which age and neglect had cast the interest of ruin over the noblest
                        ecclesiastical structures of Europe, and in which there had been born at
                        their feet a generation . . . which understood not their meaning&#x201D;
                        and which would destroy those structures, in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> view, by way of
                        &#x201C;resoration&#x201D; [<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 12:311, 314])&#x2014;the core of the <date when="1849">1849</date> argument is built around his youthful
                        experience of <persName corresp="#SP">Prout&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        discovery of <placeName corresp="#FLANDERS">Flanders</placeName>. </p>
                    <p>Likewise, in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        <date when="1879">1879</date>&#x2013;<date when="1880">80</date>
                        <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on <persName corresp="#SP">Prout</persName>
                        prepared to accompany his loan of drawings for exhibition at the Fine
                        Art Society, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        experience of <persName corresp="#SP">Prout</persName> in the <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date> remains preserved in
                        yet a later purpose, which is now to hearken autobiographically to his
                        youth spent with his father in regular attendance at the Old Water
                        Colour Society. There, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>
                        alleges, <persName corresp="#SP">Prout&#x02BC;s</persName> discovery of
                        northern Europe earned the artist &#x201C;by common and tacit
                        consent&#x201D; the &#x201C;privilege . . . to introduce foreign
                        elements of romance and amazement into this&#x2014;perhaps slightly
                        fenny&#x2014;atmosphere of English common sense&#x201D; that was typical
                        of the homelier subjects of other artists (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 14:390). This later characterization from
                        <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin&#x02BC;s</persName> last decade of
                        writing comes closest to <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>&#x02BC;s
                        presentation of the role of <persName corresp="#SP">Prout&#x02BC;s</persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Facsimiles</hi> as prompting the family&#x02BC;s
                        &#x201C;amazed&#x201D; sudden departure for this romantic travel
                        starting in northern <placeName corresp="#FRANCE">France</placeName> and
                        <placeName corresp="#BELGIUM">Belgium</placeName> (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.html#JRWORKSLE">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, 39:79). Like the <date when="1849">1849</date> essay, however, the <date when="1879">1879</date>&#x2013;<date when="1880">80</date>
                        <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> retain the youthful experience of wonder
                        and exotic discovery outside the traditional Grand Tour, which <persName corresp="#SP">Prout&#x02BC;s</persName> lithographs opened up for
                        <placeName corresp="#BRITAIN">British</placeName> viewers in the
                        <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date>. </p>
                    
                <p>SHOULD BE USED UP:
                    
                    If this second stint of draft related to the "Account" in MS VIII suggests as well as in the preceding stint, which contains only draft "Account" 
                        (see <ref type="apparatus" target="msviii_apparatus.html#LISTB1">MS VIII: Contents, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.1</ref>), 
                        Ruskin focused largely on poetry and prose chronicling the lower Rhine journey, the crossing of the Alps, and the Italy and Switzerland tour--writing 
                        that he fell short of incorporating into the <ref type="apparatus" target="msix_apparatus.html">MS IX</ref> fair copy 
                        beyond a partial account of Heidelberg, which stops in mid-sentence. 
                        On evidence explained in Composition and Publication, Ruskin commenced the first of these two stints around the date of his 
                        <date when="1834-02-08">8 February 1834 birthday</date>. The entirety of the draft of the "Account" in MS VIII, therefore, 
                        substantial in volume and substance as that draft is, can be narrowed to between February and April. 
                        Since, near the end of the second stint, Ruskin was composing poetry on Ehrenbreitstein and Heidelberg, 
                        we can conjecture also that his fair copying in MS IX was keeping pace with his draft, and that he abandoned both aspects of the project at the same time, 
                        although it is possible that he continued to fair-copy after the time of any extant draft.</p>
                        <p>Judging by the sequence of prose and poetry &#x201C;Account&#x201D; sections contained in MS VIII, one can glimpse <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> 
                            as farther behind in fair-copying when starting this draft in MS VIII than when he ended, the two aspects of the project gradually converging before he broke off 
                            the "Account" to take up "Saltzburg." 
                            Near the beginning of the draft, he composed the prose sections for &#x201C;Andernacht&#x201D; and for &#x201C;St. Goathr,&#x201D; (the prose sections 
                            corresponding to the two poems selected for publication as &#x201C;Fragments from a Metrical Journal&#x201D; 
                            in Friendship's Offering, although the occurrence of the prose does not necessarily provide a clue as to when he composed or revised the poems for the annual). 
                            In <ref type="apparatus" target="msix_apparatus.html">MS IX</ref>, the prose sections on &#x201C;Andernacht&#x201D; and &#x201C;St. Goar&#x201D; 
                            fall approximately two&#x2010;thirds of the way into the work as fair&#x2010;copied. 
                            Ruskin cannot have carried the fair copy so far in early February, however, 
                            since mixed with the Rhine, Alpine, and Italian related writing in this first MS VIII stint is 
                            prose (but not the corresponding poems) describing the Belgian and earlier Rhine stages--prose 
                            on &#x201C;The Meuse,&#x201D; Cologne, and &#x201C;Brussels,&#x201D; in that order. 
                            In <ref type="apparatus" target="msix_apparatus.html">MS IX</ref>, these prose pieces 
                            fall roughly one&#x2010;third of the way into the fair copy, so it appears that in February Ruskin was catching up the composite-genre fair copy 
                            by drafting prose to complement poems on the Belgian tour that he had already composed (in MS IA, g.1). 
                            Assuming that Ruskin already had MS IX underway, the fair copy at this point would have contained the poems, prose, and perhaps drawings 
                            on Calais, Cassel, and Lille. Over the next three months, while continuing to compose writing related to crossing the Alps and beyond, 
                            Ruskin appears to have brought the fair copy in pace with ongoing, intermittent draft relating to the <geogName corresp="#RHINE">Rhine</geogName>. 
                            Of this draft, the only <hi rend="italic">poems</hi> are those on 
                            <ref type="witness" target="ehrenbreitstein_poem_msviii.html">&#x201C;Ehrenbreitstein&#x201D;</ref> 
                            and <ref type="witness" target="heidelberg_poem_msviii.html">&#x201C;Heidelberg&#x201D;</ref>, 
                            which fall within approximately the last quarter of the &#x201C;Account&#x201D; so far as fair-copied.</p>
                        <p>As already mentioned, the all-verse version of the "Account" represented by MS IA, g.1, could date from as early as the 1833 tour itself, 
                            but that manuscript can date no later than the MS IX fair copy (which incorporates textual revisions in the MS IA version) of the opening three sections, 
                            on Calais, Cassel, and Lille, which must have been underway by the first half of February when Ruskin composed the prose section on Brussels in MS VIII. 
                            Since the other "Account" manuscript bound in MS IA--the folded sheet, g.2--contains draft of prose for "Calais" 
                            along with draft of the poems for &#x201C;Andernacht&#x201D; and &#x201C;St. Goar&#x201D; (as well as sample representing Italy, the poem on "Milan Cathedral"), 
                            one can interpret this manuscript as representing a transition from the all-verse to the composite versions of the "Account," 
                            starting with the prose added to the project's opening poem--"Calais," which John James and John composed jointly, on evidence of the draft in MS IA, g.1. 
                            The draft in g.2 of the poems on &#x201C;Andernacht&#x201D; and &#x201C;St. Goar&#x201D; correspond to the versions of those poems as fair-copied in MS IX, 
                            and not as revised for Friendship's Offering; and since draft of the prose sections on those two sites fall so close to the start of the MS VIII draft, 
                            one might hazard that Ruskin's reconception of the genre of the work, along with the start of its fair-copy realization in MS IX, occurred not long before the onset of the 
                            MS VIII "Account" draft in February 1834--perhaps in December 1833, as a New Year's suprise for John James--but 
                            no firm evidence establishes when or how the transition came about.</p>
                        
                        
                            <head type="subsection">Editorial Approaches to the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title></head>
                            <p>As traced in <ref type="internal" target="#PUB">Publication</ref>, the publishing history of the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title> 
                                might be viewed as a gradual recovery and conjectural reconstruction of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s final intentions for 
                                his elaborately composite&#x2010;genre, albeit uncompleted <title type="manuscript" corresp="#MSIX">MS IX</title> fair&#x2010;copy version. To see the editorial history 
                                in this teleological light assumes, however, that each of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s editors projected a similar ideal text. 
                                While all of these editors--Pringle, Harrison and Ruskin's father, Collingwood, and Cook and Wedderburn--did presumably have access to sufficient evidence 
                                of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s largest ambitions for the project&#x2014;his composite&#x2010;genre version&#x2014;their respective treatments 
                                suggest differing views about a preferred ideal text. The differences were partly dependent on the varying constraints of the publication venues. 
                                <title type="anthology" corresp="#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></title>, as a 
                                <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="annuals_note.php">literary and artistic annual</ref>, was meant to anthologize only brief lyric poems or tales, 
                                whereas the <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="library_edition_note.php">Library Edition</ref> aimed at unprecedented completeness in collecting 
                                <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s works. More fundamental than these contraints, however, was a question of what constituted an ideal or appropriate <hi rend="italic">public</hi> 
                                text of the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title>.</p>
                            <p>Initially, in terms of authorial intention and audience, and therefore of perceived ideal text, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and his editors worked at cross purposes.
                                In the study of modern manuscripts, Donald Reiman has argued for the importance of distinguishing between a manuscript&#x02BC;s status as 
                                <hi rend="italic">public</hi>, <hi rend="italic">private</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">confidential</hi>&#x2014;a distinction that depends, &#x201C;not [on] its degree of 
                                [rhetorical or aesthetic] artfulness or the level of personal intimacy between the writer and its readers but the nature and extent of the writer&#x02BC;s intended audience. 
                                A manuscript is <hi rend="italic">private</hi> if its author intended it to be read only by one person or a specific small group of people whose identity he knew in advance; 
                                <hi rend="italic">confidential</hi> if it was intended for a predefined but larger audience who may&#x2014;or may not&#x2014;be personally known to or interested in the author; 
                                and <hi rend="italic">public</hi> only if it was written to be published or circulated for perusal by a widespread, unspecified audience, including such abstractions 
                                as the nation, the reading public, and posterity&#x201D; 
                                (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REIMANMODERNMANUSCRIPTS">Reiman, <hi rend="italic">The Study of Modern Manuscripts</hi></ref>, 65). 
                                In the case of the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title>, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s audience was private, in that he expected his productions to be read primarily by his family, but also confidential, 
                                in that his parents shared his work with friends whose identity he could not predict. For example, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> could not have predicted that samples of his verse 
                                composed (probably) for the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title> would be read by the eminent writer, <persName corresp="#JH">James Hogg</persName>, but <persName corresp="#JJR">John James</persName> took care in his letter prefacing the sample for <persName corresp="#JH">Hogg</persName> 
                                to establish confidentiality: &#x201C;Touching my son, there are many to whom I would never name him or his pursuits; but to men of talent and of heart I find I can say 
                                many things that I dare not tell the world at large. It cannot comprehend; it has not patience, nor feeling, nor delicacy&#x201D; 
                                (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#GARDENMEMORIALS">Garden, ed., <hi rend="italic">Memorials of James Hogg</hi></ref>, 274). 
                                In writing the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title>, <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> establishes the potential confidentiality of such an audience, not by any prefatory claims on the &#x201C;heart&#x201D; of the reader, 
                                but by <hi rend="italic">imitating</hi> public status in a document whose immediate audience is private, his family; that is, 
                                in the <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_msix.php">MS IX fair&#x2010;copy version</ref>, 
                                <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> imitates the materiality of illustrated travel publications of the <date notBefore="1830" notAfter="1839">1830s</date>, the steel&#x2010;engraved 
                                <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="annuals_note.php">Annuals and Other Illustrated Books</ref>, 
                                thereby rendering this version perhaps more confidential than the 
                                <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_msia_g1.php">MS IA, <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.1, version</ref>, 
                                which was a private collaboration with his father.</p>
                            <p>In editing poems from the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title> as <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_fo.php">&#x201C;Fragments from a Metrical Journal&#x201D;</ref>, 
                                <persName corresp="#TP">Pringle</persName> replaced <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s imitation with the actual conditions and rhetoric of a public production, while creating an illusion of the original work 
                                as less confidential than private in Reiman&#x02BC;s terms. A &#x201C;journal&#x201D; belonging to &#x201C;J.R.&#x201D; seems mysteriously private 
                                in keeping with the nineteenth&#x2010;century cult of the personal, which, as Reiman remarks, led to a fashion for collecting autograph manuscripts 
                                (<ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#REIMANMODERNMANUSCRIPTS">Reiman, <hi rend="italic">The Study of Modern Manuscripts</hi></ref>, 18&#x2013;28). 
                                Thus the editor or editors&#x2014;the extent of <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s involvement in entitling or revising these poems is unknown&#x2014;widen the supposed gap between public and private. 
                                On the one hand, in <date when="1834">1834</date> the general readers of 
                                <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING1835"><title type="anthology" corresp="#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering; and Winter&#x02BC;s Wreath . . . for MDCCCXXXV</hi></title></ref>, 
                                might have connected the title, <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_fo.php">&#x201C;Fragments from a Metrical Journal&#x201D;</ref>, 
                                with <persName corresp="#GGB">Byron</persName>&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Childe Harold&#x02BC;s Pilgrimage</hi>; however, on the other hand, the text discourages a sense of the author as an &#x201C;I,&#x201D; 
                                having eliminated the prose pieces that affect an easy, confidentially personal tone, while revising the MS IX versions of 
                                <ref type="witness" target="andernacht_poem_msix.php">&#x201C;Andernacht&#x201D;</ref> and 
                                <ref type="witness" target="st_goar_poem_msix.php">&#x201C;St. Goar&#x201D;</ref> to achieve a sharper, more objective study in topographical contrast 
                                in their published versions. What <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> had produced as a confidential, imitatively &#x201C;public&#x201D; manuscript in the 
                                <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_msix.php">MS IX fair copy</ref> recedes&#x2014;or seems to recede&#x2014;into the privileged knowledge of the editor.</p>
                            <p>This sense of the editor as holding insider&#x02BC;s knowledge was enhanced by the publication of 
                                <ref type="witness" target="ehrenbreitstein_poem_msix.php">&#x201C;Ehrenbreitstein&#x201D;</ref>  
                                as <ref type="witness" target="ehrenbreitstein_poem_1850.php">&#x201C;Ehrenbreitstein: Fragment from a Metrical Journal&#x201D;</ref>  
                                in the privately printed and distributed <ref type="note" target="poems_1850_note.php"><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1850)</ref>. 
                                For many recipients of that volume, the title must have suggested merely that the editors were adding another &#x201C;fragment&#x201D; 
                                to the <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_fo.php">&#x201C;Fragments from a Metrical Journal&#x201D;</ref> 
                                that had so far been made public&#x2014;if, indeed, the title meant even that much, 
                                given that the volume did not reprint the two poems that had formed the original &#x201C;Fragments,&#x201D; 
                                published sixteen years earlier. For readers to perceive this publication as more than just a compounding of fragments&#x2014;rather, 
                                as a sophisticated reinstatement of a missing middle poem that, 
                                in <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_msix.php">MS IX fair copy</ref>, 
                                had bridged the two poems, which were later separated and published as a more severely contrasting pair in 
                                <title type="anthology" corresp="#FRIENDSHIPSOFFERING"><hi rend="italic">Friendship&#x02BC;s Offering</hi></title>&#x2014;would 
                                have required a perceptive critical reading of the three fragments considered as a unit, 
                                a reading that would in turn have relied on a comprehensive knowledge of the textual history of the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title>. 
                                Besides <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself, perhaps only <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> and <persName corresp="#WHH">W. H. Harrison</persName> possessed that privileged and knowledgable perspective. 
                                Since this edition was printed for private circulation, the editors were in a position to share their privileged knowledge with readers. 
                                Still, for many of the original recipients of the volume (as well as for the collectors who acquired copies later), 
                                <ref type="witness" target="ehrenbreitstein_poem_1850.php">&#x201C;Ehrenbreitstein: Fragment from a Metrical Journal&#x201D;</ref> 
                                would not have been perceived less as opening up an ideal text of the hitherto unknown portions of a &#x201C;metrical journal,&#x201D; 
                                than as testifying to a private and privileged story about the former omission of this &#x201C;fragment.&#x201D; As <persName corresp="#JJR">John James Ruskin</persName> wrote to <persName corresp="#WHH">Harrison</persName>, 
                                clarifying his intention regarding the audience of the <date when="1850">1850</date> collection, &#x201C;the Book although apparently so is not intended to be anonymous 
                                in a Single Instance [i.e., of selections included in the anthology]. It is only <hi rend="underline">denied</hi> the public&#x201D; 
                                (Durham, <date when="1850-03-24">24 March 1850</date> [MSL 003/004/096], in <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#MSL003-004">Letters from John James Ruskin to W. H. Harrison, 1838&#x2013;1853</ref>).</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#WGC">W. G. Collingwood</persName> situated himself in this tradition of the privileged editor, by virtue of his decision to restrict his <date when="1891">1891</date> edition to poetry, 
                                reserving an edition of early prose for a separate volume (see <ref type="note" subtype="bibliographical" target="poems_1850_note.php">Ruskin, <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> [1850]</ref>). 
                                Now, the audience for the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title> was again public, but inflected by the culture of rare book collecting, which created a new audience of eager and competitive consumers 
                                for rare copies of the <date when="1850">1850</date> <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> by &#x201C;J.R.&#x201C; Thus, in one sense, <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>&#x02BC;s version maintains the tradition 
                                of allowing public access to only fragments from a private horde&#x2014;so private that not even <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> himself, much less the collector privileged by mere cash 
                                to own the <date when="1850">1850</date> <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>, was &#x201C;aware of the amount of material [for the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title>] existing in rough copies at the back of . . . [<persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s] book&#x2010;shelves&#x201D; 
                                (see <ref type="internal" target="#PUBLICATION1891">Publication: 1891</ref>). In another sense, <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> could re&#x2010;frame the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title> as a public work, 
                                available to an anonymous audience, since <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> had told its story in <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>. <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> signals this orientation by quoting long, contextualizing passages 
                                from the autobiography at the head of the poem and in his notes; and his his version of the text, which expands the verse selections to cover the full scope of the <date when="1833">1833</date> tour, 
                                serves as a poetic, documentary gloss on <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s prose autobiographical narration of the master&#x02BC;s first significant experience of Continental landscape and towns. 
                                Yet, if <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> relies on the autobiography to authorize his version of a public text, 
                                his all&#x2010;verse version can claim only faulty authority relative to the manuscript &#x201C;material . . . at the back of . . . [<persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s] book&#x2010;shelves,&#x201D; 
                                for this version is not the young <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s composite&#x2010;genre <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title>. Ironically, 
                                the manuscript that would have supplied some authorization for such a version&#x2014;the all&#x2010;verse, and perhaps more private collaboration between <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName> and his father, 
                                <ref type="witness" target="account_of_a_tour_on_the_continent_msia_g1.php">MS IA, <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.1</ref>&#x2014;was unknown to <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>&#x02BC;s version therefore was a step toward an ideal text of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s original intentions for the <title type="composite" corresp="#JRACCOUNTTOUR">&#x201C;Account&#x201D;</title> only in a limited sense. 
                                As if jealous even of the public dimension that he afforded the work by constructing it as a tour poem illustrative of <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>, 
                                <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName> substituted a new narrative in his <date when="1894">1894</date> biography, 
                                <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#WGCLIFEOFJR1893"><hi rend="italic">Life and Work of John Ruskin</hi></ref>, 
                                suggesting that <persName corresp="#JR">John</persName>&#x02BC;s motives in making the work were furtive and separate from his father&#x02BC;s interests, 
                                a closely held harbinger of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s mature mission in <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters</hi> 
                                (see <ref type="bibliography" target="bibliography.php#HANSONRUSKIN1830S">Hanson, &#x201C;Ruskin in the 1830s&#x201D;</ref>). 
                                This conception is almost the opposite of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s intention in his youth, which was to imitate a public work of his own time&#x2014;an 
                                imitation of <persName corresp="#SR">Rogers</persName>&#x02BC;s <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>, as acknowledged in <hi rend="italic">Praeterita</hi>&#x2014;and which 
                                was meant to be confidentially shared with readers who qualified as &#x201C;men of talent and of heart.&#x201D; 
                                Thus, <persName corresp="#WGC">Collingwood</persName>&#x02BC;s version was a step toward restoration of <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s original youthful project only in the sense that it provided an expanded framework, 
                                which <persName corresp="#ETC">Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName> could dramatically fill out with the poems&#x02BC; missing complementary prose pieces, and with (at least) one reproduction of a hand&#x2010;illustrated page, along with footnotes describing 
                                the remaining drawings and where in the work they are placed. The Library Edition&#x02BC;s version is the first genuine attempt at representing <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s work 
                                as originally conceptualized. At the same time, <persName corresp="#ETC">Cook</persName> and <persName corresp="#AW">Wedderburn</persName> inherited the agendas of their predecessors, and they too inevitably framed the work also 
                                as supplemental material illustrating <persName corresp="#JR">Ruskin</persName>&#x02BC;s autobiography.</p>
                        
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>